<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-23A</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Records Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Limiting Pardons for Serious Crimes Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Records</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2010</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>5</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2010</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-6-14">99560</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal> to extend the ineligibility periods for certain applications for a pardon. It also enables the National Parole Board to consider additional factors when deciding whether to grant a pardon for certain offences.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Limiting Pardons for Serious Crimes Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-47</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL RECORDS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 22, s. 4(1); 2000, c. 1, s. 1(F)</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Restrictions on application for pardon</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>A person is ineligible to apply for a pardon until the following period has elapsed after the expiration according to law of any sentence, including a sentence of imprisonment, a period of probation and the payment of any fine, imposed for an offence:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>10 years, in the case of a serious personal injury offence within the meaning of section 752 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, including manslaughter, for which the applicant was sentenced to imprisonment for a period of two years or more or an offence referred to in Schedule 1 that was prosecuted by indictment, or five years in the case of any other offence prosecuted by indictment, an offence referred to in Schedule 1 that is punishable on summary conviction or an offence that is a service offence within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> for which the offender was punished by a fine of more than two thousand dollars, detention for more than six months, dismissal from Her Majesty’s service, imprisonment for more than six months or a punishment that is greater than imprisonment for less than two years in the scale of punishments set out in subsection 139(1) of that Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>three years, in the case of an offence, other than one referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), that is punishable on summary conviction or that is a service offence within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 22, s. 4(1)</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>Section 4.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Pardon</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board may grant a pardon for an offence if the Board is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant, during the applicable period referred to in section 4, has been of good conduct and has not been convicted of an offence under an Act of Parliament; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an offence referred to in paragraph 4(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), granting the pardon at that time would provide a measurable benefit to the applicant, would sustain his or her rehabilitation in society as a law-abiding citizen and would not bring the administration of justice into disrepute.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Onus on applicant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the case of an offence referred to in paragraph 4(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the applicant has the onus of satisfying the Board that the pardon would provide a measurable benefit to the applicant and would sustain his or her rehabilitation in society as a law-abiding citizen.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In determining whether granting the pardon would bring the administration of justice into disrepute, the Board may consider</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the nature, gravity and duration of the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the circumstances surrounding the commission of the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>information relating to the applicant’s criminal history and, in the case of a service offence within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, to any service offence history of the applicant that is relevant to the application; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any factor that is prescribed by regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 22, s. 4(1); 2000, c. 1, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsections 4.2(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Inquiries</MarginalNote><Label>4.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of an application for a pardon, the Board</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall cause inquiries to be made to ascertain the applicant’s conduct since the date of the conviction; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may, in the case of an offence referred to in paragraph 4(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), cause inquiries to be made with respect to any factors that it may consider in determining whether granting the pardon would bring the administration of justice into disrepute.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Entitlement to make representations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Board proposes to refuse to grant a pardon, it shall notify in writing the applicant of its proposal and advise the applicant that he or she is entitled to make, or have made on his or her behalf, any representations to the Board that he or she believes relevant either in writing or, with the Board’s authorization, orally at a hearing held for that purpose.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is evidence of the fact that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Board, after making inquiries, was satisfied that the applicant for the pardon was of good conduct, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the conviction in respect of which the pardon is granted should no longer reflect adversely on the applicant’s character; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 1, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 6.3(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notation of records</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall make, in the automated criminal conviction records retrieval system maintained by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, a notation enabling a member of a police force or other authorized body to determine whether there is a record of an individual’s conviction for an offence listed in Schedule 2 in respect of which a pardon has been granted.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 1, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 6.3(9) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend Schedule 1 or 2 by adding or deleting a reference to an offence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.1</Label><Text>Subparagraph 7.2(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(iii) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a service offence referred to in paragraph 4(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>); or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Section 9.1 of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing factors for the purposes of paragraph 4.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.1</Label><Text>In the English version of the Act, the words “granted or issued” are replaced by the word “granted” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition “pardon” in subsection 2(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 6(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 6.4;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 7;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 7.1(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of section 7.2 before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 8.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.2</Label><Text>In section 2.1 of the English version of the Act, the words “grant or issue” are replaced by the word “grant”.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.3</Label><Text>In the French version of the Act, the words “octroyée ou délivrée” are replaced by the word “octroyée” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition “réhabilitation” in subsection 2(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraph 7.2(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.4</Label><Text>In section 6.4 of the French version of the Act, the words “octroyé ou délivré” are replaced by the word “octroyé”.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.5</Label><Text>In section 2.1 of the French version of the Act, the expression “d’octroi, de délivrance” is replaced by the expression “d’octroi”.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is renumbered as Schedule 2.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding, before Schedule 2, the Schedule 1 set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>New applications for pardons</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>Subject to section <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal>, an application for a pardon under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal> in respect of an offence that is referred to in paragraph 4(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of that Act, as it read immediately before the day on which this Act comes into force, and that is committed before that day shall be dealt with and disposed of in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by this Act.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Pending applications — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>An application for a pardon under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal> that is made before the day on which this Act comes into force shall be dealt with and disposed of in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal>, as it read when the Board received the application, if the application</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is made after the period referred to in paragraph 4(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of that Act, as it read immediately before the day on which this Act comes into force, has elapsed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is not finally disposed of on the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Paragraph></Section></Body><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 4 and subsection 6.3(9))</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Offences</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 151 (sexual interference with a person under 16),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 152 (invitation to a person under 16 to sexual touching),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 153 (sexual exploitation of a person 16 or more but under 18),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsection 160(3) (bestiality in the presence of a person under 16 or inciting a person under 16 to commit bestiality),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>section 163.1 (child pornography),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>section 170 (parent or guardian procuring sexual activity),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>section 171 (householder permitting sexual activity),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>section 172 (corrupting children),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>section 172.1 (luring a child),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(x)</Label><Text>subsection 173(2) (exposure),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>subsection 212(2) (living on avails of prostitution of a person under 18),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xii)</Label><Text>subsection 212(2.1) (aggravated offence — living on avails of prostitution of a person under 18),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xiii)</Label><Text>subsection 212(4) (obtain, or attempt to obtain, sexual services of a person under 18),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xiv)</Label><Text>paragraph 273.3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) (removal of child under 16 from Canada for purposes of listed offences),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xv)</Label><Text>paragraph 273.3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) (removal of child 16 or more but under 18 from Canada for purpose of listed offence),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xvi)</Label><Text>paragraph 273.3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) (removal of child under 18 from Canada for purposes of listed offences),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xvii)</Label><Text>paragraph 348(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) with respect to breaking and entering a place with intent to commit in that place an indictable offence listed in any of subparagraphs (i) to (xvi), and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xviii)</Label><Text>paragraph 348(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) with respect to breaking and entering a place and committing in that place an indictable offence listed in any of subparagraphs (i) to (xvi);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1970, c. C-34, as that Act read before January 1, 1988:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 166 (parent or guardian procuring defilement), and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 167 (householder permitting defilement);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that are referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and that are punishable under section 130 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that are referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and that are punishable under section 120 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1970, c. N-4; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>of attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Offences</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>involving a child under the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code:</XRefExternal></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 153.1 (sexual exploitation of a person with a disability),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 155 (incest),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 162 (voyeurism),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>paragraph 163(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) (obscene materials),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>paragraph 163(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) (obscene materials),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>section 168 (mailing obscene matter),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>subsection 173(1) (indecent acts),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>section 271 (sexual assault),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>subsection 272(1) and paragraph 272(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) (sexual assault with firearm),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(x)</Label><Text>subsection 272(1) and paragraph 272(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) (sexual assault other than with firearm),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>section 273 (aggravated sexual assault),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xii)</Label><Text>paragraph 348(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) with respect to breaking and entering a place with intent to commit in that place an indictable offence listed in any of subparagraphs (i) to (xi), and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(xiii)</Label><Text>paragraph 348(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) with respect to breaking and entering a place and committing in that place an indictable offence listed in any of subparagraphs (i) to (xi);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>involving a child under the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1970, c. C-34, as that Act read before January 1, 1988:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 153 (sexual intercourse with stepdaughter, etc., or female employee), and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 157 (gross indecency);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>involving a child under the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1970, c. C-34, as that Act read before January 4, 1983:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 144 (rape),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 145 (attempt to commit rape),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 149 (indecent assault on female),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>section 156 (indecent assault on male),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>section 245 (common assault), and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>subsection 246(1) (assault with intent to commit an indictable offence);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that are referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and that are punishable under section 130 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that are referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and that are punishable under section 120 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1970, c. N-4; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>of attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Offences</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1970, c. C-34, as that Act read before January 1, 1988:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 146(1) (sexual intercourse with a female under 14),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 146(2) (sexual intercourse with a female 14 or more but under 16), and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 151 (seduction of a female 16 or more but under 18);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that are referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and that are punishable under section 120 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1970, c. N-4; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>of attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision></Provision></Schedule></Schedule></Bill>