<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" date-time="2008-12-18 15:25:06" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-268</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (minimum sentence for offences involving trafficking of persons under the age of eighteen years)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (minimum sentence for offences involving trafficking of persons under the age of eighteen years)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code (minimum sentence for offences involving trafficking of persons under the age of eighteen years)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2010</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>3</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2010</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2008-12-18">402053</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to include a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of five years for offences involving trafficking of persons under the age of eighteen years.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xlvii.1):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xlvii.11)</Label><Text>section 279.011 (trafficking of a person under the age of eighteen years),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 279.01:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Trafficking of a person under the age of eighteen years</MarginalNote><Label>279.011</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who recruits, transports, transfers, receives, holds, conceals or harbours a person under the age of eighteen years, or exercises control, direction or influence over the movements of a person under the age of eighteen years, for the purpose of exploiting them or facilitating their exploitation is guilty of an indictable offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of six years if they kidnap, commit an aggravated assault or aggravated sexual assault against, or cause death to, the victim during the commission of the offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to imprisonment for a term of not more than fourteen years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of five years, in any other case.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consent</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No consent to the activity that forms the subject-matter of a charge under subsection (1) is valid.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Sections 279.02 and 279.03 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Material benefit</MarginalNote><Label>279.02</Label><Text>Every person who receives a financial or other material benefit, knowing that it results from the commission of an offence under subsection 279.01(1) or 279.011(1), is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than ten years.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Withholding or destroying documents</MarginalNote><Label>279.03</Label><Text>Every person who, for the purpose of committing or facilitating an offence under subsection 279.01(1) or 279.011(1), conceals, removes, withholds or destroys any travel document that belongs to another person or any document that establishes or purports to establish another person’s identity or immigration status is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years, whether or not the document is of Canadian origin or is authentic.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 486(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons to be stated</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an accused is charged with an offence under section 151, 152, 153, 153.1, 155 or 159, subsection 160(2) or (3) or section 163.1, 171, 172, 172.1, 173, 212, 271, 272, 273, 279.01, 279.011, 279.02 or 279.03 and the prosecutor or the accused applies for an order under subsection (1), the judge or justice shall, if no such order is made, state, by reference to the circumstances of the case, the reason for not making an order.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 486.4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an offence under section 151, 152, 153, 153.1, 155, 159, 160, 162, 163.1, 170, 171, 172, 172.1, 173, 210, 211, 212, 213, 271, 272, 273, 279.01, 279.011, 279.02, 279.03, 346 or 347,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>primary designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 487.04 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (vii.1):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(vii.11)</Label><Text>section 279.011 (trafficking of a person under the age of eighteen years),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (vii.1):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(vii.11)</Label><Text>section 279.011 (trafficking of a person under the age of eighteen years),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 752 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xx):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xx.1)</Label><Text>section 279.011 (trafficking of a person under the age of eighteen years),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>