<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-24</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the First Nations Commercial and Industrial Development Act and another Act in consequence thereof</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">First Nations Certainty of Land Title Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>First Nations Commercial and Industrial Development</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2010</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>6</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2010</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-5-5">90546</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Commercial and Industrial Development Act</XRefExternal> to expand the existing regulation-making powers in order to establish a system for the registration of reserve lands for first nations that desire it.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Certainty of Land Title Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 53</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">FIRST NATIONS COMMERCIAL AND INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Commercial and Industrial Development Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>provincial body</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>organisme provincial</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial body</DefinedTermEn> means a body established by the laws of a province.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>provincial official</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fonctionnaire provincial</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial official</DefinedTermEn> means a minister of the Crown in right of a province, a person employed by a province or a person appointed to, or employed by, a provincial body.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Subsection 3(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the arbitration of disputes arising under the regulations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">s</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the disposition or destruction of documents, regardless of medium, that are created or submitted under the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 4:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations — land registration</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the establishment and operation of a system for the registration of interests and rights in reserve lands described in the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content of regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under subsection (1) may, despite any other Act of Parliament,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establish priorities or, in Quebec, rankings among interests or rights that have been registered;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establish a fund to compensate for losses in relation to interests or rights that have been registered or that should have been registered;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for purposes of registration, deem Her Majesty’s or a first nation’s interest or rights in the reserve lands to constitute fee simple title to or, in Quebec, ownership of the lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>deem valid any surrender or designation of the reserve lands made or purported to be made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> despite an assertion to the contrary by any person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>confirm the legal capacity of a first nation to hold, transfer and register interests and rights in the reserve lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorize Her Majesty, without any new surrender or designation of reserve lands under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> by a first nation, to grant fee simple title to those lands to Herself or to the first nation or, in Quebec, confer ownership of those lands on Herself or on the first nation, for a purpose authorized under a surrender or designation made under that Act prior to the grant or conferral;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorize the Minister, for the purposes of registration, to certify that Her Majesty or any other person has an interest or right in the reserve lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>entitle the holders of registrable interests and rights in the reserve lands to apply for registration;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the registration, at the request of the Minister or a first nation, of registrable interests and rights of any person that existed at the time of the initial registration of the fee simple title or ownership or other interests or rights of Her Majesty or the first nation in the reserve lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the substitution by the Minister or a first nation, as the case may be, of registrable interests and rights in the reserve lands for non-registrable ones;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the extinguishment of any interests and rights that are not registered;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the manner of calculating the compensation, if any, to be paid by a first nation for any substitution or extinguishment referred to in paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>), and limit the time for claiming such compensation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>exclude the reserve lands from the application of sections 19, 21 and 55 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interests and rights not affected</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A grant or conferral under paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) does not affect Her Majesty’s title to the reserve lands, or a first nation’s interest or rights in the reserve lands, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The regulations may incorporate by reference any laws of the province, as amended from time to time, with any adaptations that the Governor in Council considers necessary.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 5 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Conditions for making regulations</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Regulations may not be made under section 3 or 4.1 in respect of reserve lands of a first nation unless</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Dispute resolution</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An agreement referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) may provide for the arbitration, in accordance with the laws of the province, of disputes arising from the interpretation or application of that agreement, in which case the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Commercial Arbitration Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the dispute.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to the amendment or repeal of regulations made under section 3 or 4.1.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Sections 7 to 9 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Conflict with first nation laws or by-laws</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>Regulations made under section 3 or 4.1 prevail over any laws or by-laws made by a first nation to the extent of any conflict or inconsistency between them, unless those regulations provide otherwise.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OTHER ACTS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to any instruments made by a provincial official or body under authority of a provincial law incorporated by reference in regulations made under section 3 or 4.1.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A provincial official or body that exercises a power or performs a duty under regulations made under section 3 or 4.1 is not a federal board, commission or other tribunal for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review or appeal in provincial courts</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided by regulations made under section 3 or 4.1, where a power or duty is conferred or imposed by a provincial law that is incorporated by reference in the regulations, its exercise or performance pursuant to the regulations is subject to review by, or appeal to, the courts of the province in the same manner and to the same extent as if the provincial law applied of its own force.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>The portion of section 11 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Acts and omissions</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>In respect of any act or omission occurring in the exercise of a power or the performance of a duty under regulations made under section 3 or 4.1,</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Registration, substitution or extinguishment</MarginalNote><Label>12.1</Label><Text>No civil proceeding may be brought against Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province, a federal or provincial official or body or a person acting on behalf of any of them, in relation to the registration of the title or ownership of Her Majesty or a first nation, or of any registrable interest or right referred to in paragraph 4.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>), or in relation to the substitution or extinguishment of any interest or right in reserve lands pursuant to regulations made under section 4.1.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. L-6</MarginalNote><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENT TO THE CANADA LANDS SURVEYS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 24(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Lands Surveys Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>surrendered lands or a reserve, as those expressions are defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>, other than reserve lands described in regulations made under section 4.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Commercial and Industrial Development Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>