<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-70</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting countering foreign interference</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Countering Foreign Interference Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Countering Foreign Interference Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>16</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2024</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber>91205</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act respecting countering foreign interference</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>update provisions respecting the collection, retention, querying and exploitation of datatsets;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>clarify the scope of section 16 of that Act;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>update provisions respecting the disclosure of information by the Canadian Security Intelligence Service;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>provide for preservation orders and production orders as well as warrants to obtain information, records, documents or things through a single attempt;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>expand the circumstances in which a warrant to remove a thing from the place where it was installed may be issued; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>require a parliamentary review of that Act every five years.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also makes a consequential amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Intelligence Commissioner Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 2 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, create the following offences:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>committing an indictable offence at the direction of, for the benefit of, or in association with a foreign entity;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>knowingly engaging in surreptitious or deceptive conduct at the direction of, for the benefit of or in association with a foreign entity for a purpose prejudicial to the safety or interests of the State or being reckless as to whether the conduct is likely to harm Canadian interests; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>engaging in surreptitious or deceptive conduct, at the direction of or in association with a foreign entity, with the intent to influence, among other things, the exercise of a democratic right in Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends that Act to remove as an element of the offence of inducing or attempting to induce — at the direction of, for the benefit of or in association with a foreign entity or terrorist group — by intimidation, threat or violence, a person to do anything or cause anything to be done, that the thing be done for the purpose of harming Canadian interests when the person who is alleged to have committed the offence or the victim has a link to Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to, among other things, broaden the scope of the sabotage offence to include certain acts done in relation to essential infrastructures and ensure that certain provisions respecting the interception of “private communications” as defined in that Act apply to certain offences in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Finally, it makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 3 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> and makes consequential amendments to other Acts to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>create a general scheme to deal with information relating to international relations, national defence or national security in the course of proceedings that are in the Federal Court or the Federal Court of Appeal and that are in respect of any decision of a federal board, commission or other tribunal;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>permit the appointment of a special counsel for the purposes of protecting the interests of a non-governmental party to those proceedings in respect of such information; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>allow a person charged with an offence to appeal a decision, made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> with respect to the disclosure of certain information in relation to criminal proceedings, only after the person has been convicted of the offence, unless there are exceptional circumstances justifying an earlier appeal.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also adds references to international relations, national defence and national security in a provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that relates to the protection of information, as well as references to international relations and national defence in certain provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> that equally relate to the protection of information.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 4 enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal> which, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provides for the appointment of an individual to be known as the Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>requires certain persons to provide the Commissioner with certain information if they enter into arrangements with foreign principals under which they undertake to carry out certain activities in relation to political or governmental processes in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>requires the Commissioner to establish and maintain a publicly accessible registry that contains information about those arrangements;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>provides the Commissioner with tools to administer and enforce that Act; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Countering Foreign Interference Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The heading before section 2 of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Définitions et interprétation</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Canadian</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>dataset</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>exploitation</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>query</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Forms</MarginalNote><Label>2.1</Label><Text>If this Act requires that a form be used, the form may incorporate any variations that the circumstances require.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with Deputy Minister — warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Director or any employee who is designated by the Minister for the purpose of applying for a warrant under section 21, 21.1, 22.21 or 23 shall consult the Deputy Minister before applying for the warrant or, if applicable, the renewal of the warrant.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2.1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with Deputy Minister — production order</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>The Director or any employee who is designated by the Minister for the purpose of applying for a production order under section 20.4 shall consult the Deputy Minister before applying for the order.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 10 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Oaths</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The Director and every employee shall, before commencing the duties of office, take an oath of allegiance and the oaths set out in Schedule 1.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 11.01:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Datasets</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Section 11.01 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Canadian</DefinedTermEn> in respect of a person, means a Canadian citizen, a <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> or a corporation incorporated or continued under the laws of Canada or a province. (<DefinedTermFr>Canadien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>dataset</DefinedTermEn> means a collection of information that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is characterized by a common subject matter;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is stored as an electronic record;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>contains <DefinitionRef>personal information</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>is relevant to the performance of the Service’s duties and functions under any of sections 12 to 16 but cannot be collected or retained under any of those sections. (<DefinedTermFr>ensemble de données</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>exploitation</DefinedTermEn> means a computational analysis or series of computational analyses that is performed on one or more collections of information for the purpose of obtaining intelligence that would not otherwise be apparent. (<DefinedTermFr>exploitation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>query</DefinedTermEn> means a specific search or series of specific searches, with respect to a person or entity, that is performed on one or more collections of information for the purpose of obtaining intelligence. (<DefinedTermFr>interrogation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 11.02 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Subsections 11.03(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Classes — Canadian datasets</MarginalNote><Label>11.03</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall, by order, determine classes of Canadian datasets for which collection is authorized.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Criteria</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may determine that a class of Canadian datasets is authorized to be collected if the Minister concludes that the querying or exploitation of datasets in the class could lead to results that are relevant to the performance of the Service’s duties and functions under section 12, 12.1, 15 or 16.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum period</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) is valid for a period of not more than two years.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Section 11.05 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Collection of datasets</MarginalNote><Label>11.05</Label><Text>The Service may collect a dataset only if it reasonably believes that the dataset</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is a publicly available dataset;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>belongs to an approved class; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>predominantly relates to non-Canadians who are outside Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Collection under section 12, 15 or 16</MarginalNote><Label>11.051</Label><Text>If the Service concludes that information that was collected under section 12, 15 or 16 constitutes a dataset or could be used to constitute a dataset, that information is deemed to have been collected as a dataset under section 11.05 on the day on which the Service reached that conclusion.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Collection outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>11.052</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after collecting a dataset under section 11.05 outside Canada, the Service shall either destroy the dataset or provide it to a designated employee for the purposes of section 11.07.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed collection date</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A dataset that is provided to a designated employee under subsection (1) is, for the purposes of section 11.07, deemed to have been collected on the day on which it is provided to the designated employee.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Collection in execution of warrant or production order</MarginalNote><Label>11.053</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Service concludes that information that was incidentally collected in the execution of a warrant issued under section 21 or 22.21 or a production order issued under section 20.4 constitutes a dataset or could be used to constitute a dataset, that information is deemed to have been collected as a dataset under section 11.05 on the day on which the Service reached that conclusion.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The terms and conditions of the warrant or production order continue to apply to the dataset.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deemed collection date</MarginalNote><Label>11.054</Label><Text>If a dataset is deemed to have been collected on more than one day under section 11.051, 11.052 or 11.053 or subsection 11.1(3), the dataset is deemed, for the purposes of section 11.07, to have been collected on the latest of those days.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 11.06 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Director may delegate the designation power set out in subsection (1) to an employee.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.06(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the designation of an employee under subsection (1) is not a <DefinitionRef>statutory instrument</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 11.07(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Evaluation period — datasets</MarginalNote><Label>11.07</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Service collects a dataset under section 11.05, a designated employee shall, as soon as feasible but no later than the 180th day after the day on which the dataset was collected, evaluate the dataset and confirm if it</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.07(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>If a dataset that is confirmed to be a foreign dataset includes information that relates to individuals within Canada or Canadians and the Service decides to treat it as a Canadian dataset, that dataset is deemed to be a Canadian dataset.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evaluation — class</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the case of a Canadian dataset, a designated employee shall evaluate the dataset and confirm whether it belonged to an approved class on the day on which it was collected and, if it did not, the designated employee shall take the measures set out in section 11.08.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 11.07 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Comparison</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>A designated employee may, for the purpose of determining whether it is necessary to make an application for a judicial authorization under subsection 11.13(1) or a request for an authorization under subsection 11.17(1), compare the dataset to other datasets that have been collected by the Service under this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.07(6)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>delete <DefinitionRef>personal information</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, that in the opinion of the Service is not relevant to the performance of its duties and functions and may be deleted without affecting the integrity of the dataset; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 11.08(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Dataset not within class</MarginalNote><Label>11.08</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a designated employee confirms that the dataset did not belong to an approved class on the day on which it was collected, the Service shall, without delay,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.08(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period — suspension</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Service makes a request to the Minister under paragraph (1)(b), the 180-day period referred to in subsection 11.07(1) is suspended for the period that begins on the day on which a designated employee confirms that the dataset did not belong to an approved class on the day on which it was collected and ends on the day on which the Commissioner approves, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Intelligence Commissioner Act</XRefExternal>, the determination of the Minister in respect of a new class to which the dataset belongs.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 11.09(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>End of evaluation period — Canadian datasets</MarginalNote><Label>11.09</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a designated employee confirms that a dataset is a Canadian dataset or if a dataset is deemed to be a Canadian dataset under subsection 11.07(1.1), the Service shall make an application for judicial authorization under section 11.13 as soon as feasible but no later than the 180th day referred to in subsection 11.07(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>End of evaluation period — foreign datasets</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the designated employee confirms that a dataset is a foreign dataset, the Service shall ensure that the dataset is brought to the attention of the Minister or the designated person, as soon as feasible but no later than the 180th day referred to in subsection 11.07(1), so as to enable the Minister or designated person to make a determination to authorize its retention under section 11.17.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.09(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>À l’expiration du délai de cent quatre-vingts jours, si le Service n’a pas agi conformément aux paragraphes (1) ou (2), il est tenu de détruire l’ensemble de données recueilli.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Continuing obligations of Service</MarginalNote><Label>11.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Service shall take reasonable measures to ensure that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any information in respect of which there is a reasonable expectation of privacy that relates to the physical or mental health of an individual is deleted from a Canadian dataset or a foreign dataset;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any information that is subject to solicitor-client privilege or the professional secrecy of advocates and notaries is deleted from a Canadian dataset; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any information that by its nature or attributes relates to a Canadian or a person in Canada is removed from a foreign dataset.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.1(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not apply to information that is being retained under subsection 11.21(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A dataset collected under paragraph (2)(b) is deemed to have been collected under section 11.05 on the day on which the information that constitutes the dataset was removed from the foreign dataset.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>Section 11.11 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Service may disclose a publicly available dataset and, if it does so, section 19 does not apply to the disclosure.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.12(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the approved class to which the Canadian dataset belongs or to which it belonged on the day on which it was collected; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.13(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the retention of the dataset that is the subject of the application is likely to assist the Service in the performance of its duties and functions under section 12, 12.1, 15 or 16; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.13(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>the manner in which the Service intends to disclose the dataset;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Subsection 11.14(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure of dataset</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The judicial authorization shall also establish any terms and conditions that the judge considers necessary respecting the disclosure of the dataset by the Service.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Section 19 does not apply to the disclosure of the dataset.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum period</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The judicial authorization is valid for a period of not more than five years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>Subsections 11.15(3) to (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction — absence of new application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Service does not request the Minister’s approval under section 11.12 to make a new application for a judicial authorization to retain a Canadian dataset before the period of the judicial authorization given in respect of that dataset expires, the Service shall destroy the dataset within 30 days after the expiry of that period.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>New application — approval not obtained</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>If the Service requests but does not obtain the Minister’s approval under section 11.12 to make a new application for a judicial authorization for a Canadian dataset in respect of which the period of the judicial authorization has not expired, the Service shall destroy the dataset within 30 days after the later of the day on which the request was rejected by the Minister and the day on which the period of the judicial authorization expires.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>New application — approval obtained</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Service requests and obtains the Minister’s approval under section 11.12 to make a new application for a judicial authorization for a Canadian dataset in respect of which the period of the judicial authorization has not expired, the Service may, subject to subsection (5), retain the dataset until a decision is made in respect of the new application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the period of a judicial authorization expires, in the circumstances under subsection (3.1) or (4), the Service shall neither query nor exploit the dataset until and unless a new authorization has been issued for the dataset.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.17(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that the retention of the dataset is likely to assist the Service in the performance of its duties and functions under section 12, 12.1, 15 or 16; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.17(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure of dataset</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The authorization shall also establish any terms and conditions that the Minister or designated person considers necessary respecting the disclosure of the dataset by the Service.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>Section 19 does not apply to the disclosure of the dataset.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum period of authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The authorization is valid for a period of not more than 10 years from the date on which the Commissioner approves it under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Intelligence Commissioner Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>Subsections 11.2(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Dataset subject to judicial authorization — section 12, 12.1 or 15</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A designated employee may, to the extent that it is strictly necessary, query or exploit a Canadian dataset that is subject to a judicial authorization issued under section 11.13 to assist the Service in the performance of its duties and functions under section 12, 12.1 or 15.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Dataset subject to approved authorization — section 12, 12.1 or 15</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A designated employee may, to the extent that it is strictly necessary, query or exploit a foreign dataset that is the subject of an authorization under section 11.17 that has been approved by the Commissioner under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Intelligence Commissioner Act</XRefExternal>, to assist the Service in the performance of its duties and functions under section 12, 12.1 or 15.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.21(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the retention is strictly necessary to assist the Service in the performance of its duties and functions under section 12.1 or 15; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 11.22(1) of the Act before subparagraph (b)(ii) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Query or exploitation in exigent circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>11.22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Director may authorize a designated employee to query or exploit a Canadian dataset that is not the subject of a valid judicial authorization issued under section 11.13 or a foreign dataset that is not the subject of a valid authorization under section 11.17 that has been approved by the Commissioner under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Intelligence Commissioner Act</XRefExternal>, if the Director concludes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that the dataset was collected by the Service under section 11.05; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that there are exigent circumstances that require a query or exploitation of the dataset</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to acquire intelligence for the purpose of preserving the life or safety of any individual, or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 11.22(2)(b) and (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a description of the dataset to be queried or exploited; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the grounds on which the Director concludes that the query or exploitation is likely to produce the intelligence referred to in subparagraph (1)(b)(i) or (ii).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 11.22(2.1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retention</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Service may retain the results of a query or exploitation performed under subsection (1) if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>Paragraphs 11.24(3)(b) and (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>limit access to those datasets to designated employees and take reasonable measures to ensure that any information that they obtained, or to which they had access, is only communicated for the purpose of performing the Service’s duties and functions under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>establish record keeping requirements for those datasets with respect to the rationale for their collection and retention, the details of each query and exploitation, the results of those queries and exploitations, and if the results were retained for the purpose of performing the Service’s duties and functions under section 12, 12.1, 15 or 16; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.25(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the case of a query or exploitation performed on the basis of exigent circumstances under section 11.22, give the Review Agency a copy of the Director’s authorization under that section and indicate the results of the query or exploitation and any actions taken after obtaining those results.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 11.25:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Threats to the Security of Canada</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Security Assessments and Advice</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 15:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Assistance and Cooperation</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Section 16 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information or intelligence outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The assistance provided under subsection (1) may include the collection, from within Canada, of information or intelligence that is located outside Canada if the assistance is directed at a person or thing in Canada or at an individual who was in Canada and is temporarily outside Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 17:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Identity of Employees and Human Sources</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 18.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Disclosure of Information</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 19(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>where the information may be used in the investigation or prosecution of an alleged contravention of any law of Canada or a province, to any person having jurisdiction to investigate the alleged contravention and to the Attorney General of Canada and the Attorney General of the province in which proceedings in respect of the alleged contravention may be taken;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 19(2)(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>where, in the opinion of the Minister, disclosure of the information to any person or entity is essential in the public interest and that interest clearly outweighs any invasion of privacy that could result from the disclosure, to that person or entity.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 19 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorized disclosure — building resiliency against threats</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of building resiliency against threats to the security of Canada, the Service may also disclose information referred to in subsection (1) to any person or entity if all of the following conditions are met:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the information has already been provided to a federal department or agency that performs duties and functions to which the information is relevant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the information does not contain any <DefinitionRef>personal information</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, of a Canadian citizen, a <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> or any individual in Canada, other than personal information of the individual to whom the information is disclosed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the information does not contain the name of a corporation incorporated or continued under the laws of Canada or a province or the name of a Canadian entity, other than the name of the corporation or entity to which the information is disclosed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 19:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Protection of Employees and Justification</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>Paragraph 20.1(8)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the employee would be justified in committing or directing another person to commit an act or omission that would otherwise constitute an offence.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 21:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Preservation order</MarginalNote><Label>20.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Director or any employee who is designated by the Director for the purpose may make an application to a judge for a preservation order under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Making of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other law but subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal>, the judge may order a person or entity to preserve any information, record or document — regardless of medium or form — or thing that is in their possession or control when they receive the order, if the judge is satisfied by information on oath in Form 1 of Schedule 2 that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there are reasonable grounds to suspect that the information, record, document or thing is in the person or entity’s possession or control and will assist the Service to investigate, within or outside Canada, a threat to the security of Canada or to perform its duties and functions under section 16;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the order is necessary to prevent the loss or destruction or ensure the preservation of the information, record, document or thing; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Director or an employee who is designated by the Director for the purpose intends to apply or has applied for a production order under section 20.4 or a warrant under section 21 or 22.21 to obtain the information, record, document or thing or, under section 23, to remove a thing.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form 2</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The order is to be made in Form 2 of Schedule 2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Preservation outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The order may be made in respect of information, records, documents or things located outside Canada, with any modifications that the circumstances require.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Measures</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The judge may include in the order any measure that they consider necessary in the public interest, including to ensure the confidentiality of the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expiry of order</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The order expires 90 days after the day on which it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notification of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Director shall notify the Minister that an application for an order has been made under this section as soon as feasible after the application is made.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Production order</MarginalNote><Label>20.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Director or an employee who is designated by the Minister for the purpose may, after having obtained the Minister’s approval, make an application to a judge for a production order under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Making of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other law but subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal>, the judge may order a person or entity to produce any information, record or document — regardless of medium or form — that is in their possession or control when they receive the order if the judge is satisfied by information on oath in Form 3 of Schedule 2 that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the information, record or document is in the person or entity’s possession or control and will assist the Service to investigate, within or outside Canada, a threat to the security of Canada or to perform its duties and functions under section 16.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form 4</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The order is to be made in Form 4 of Schedule 2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Production outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The order may be made in respect of information, records or documents located outside Canada, with any modifications that the circumstances require.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Measures</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The judge may include in the order any measure that they consider necessary in the public interest, including to ensure the confidentiality of the order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Revocation or variation of production order</MarginalNote><Label>20.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before they produce any information, record or document that they are required to produce under an order made under section 20.4, a person or entity may apply in writing to a judge to revoke or vary the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice required</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The person or entity may make the application only if they give notice of their intention to do so to a judge and to an employee in Form 5 of Schedule 2 within 14 days after the day on which the order is served.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No obligation to produce</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The person or entity is not required to produce the information, record or document until a final decision is made with respect to the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Revocation or variation of order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The judge may revoke or vary the order if satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>it is unreasonable in the circumstances to require the applicant to produce the information, record or document; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>production of the information, record or document would disclose information that is privileged or otherwise protected from disclosure by law.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Clarification — voluntary preservation or production</MarginalNote><Label>20.6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Service may request that a person or entity voluntarily preserve any information, record, document or thing, or voluntarily produce any information, record or document to the Service, without needing to obtain a preservation or production order so long as the person or entity is not prohibited by law from preserving or producing the information, record, document or thing, as the case may be, and the Service may collect it under section 12 or 16.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification — other collection authorities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the fact that a preservation order or production order may be made under section 20.3 or 20.4 does not affect the Service’s authority to collect any information, record, document or thing under any other provision of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No civil or criminal liability</MarginalNote><Label>20.7</Label><Text>No criminal or civil proceedings lie against a person who voluntarily preserves any information, record, document or thing, or voluntarily produces any information, record or document, following a request from the Service in the circumstances described in subsection 20.6(1), or against a person acting on behalf of an entity that receives such a request.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Destruction of preserved elements — preservation order</MarginalNote><Label>20.8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person or entity that is subject to a preservation order made under section 20.3 shall destroy the information, record, document or thing that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving the information, record, document or thing under that section as soon as feasible after the order expires, unless they are subject to a new preservation order, a production order made under section 20.4 or a warrant issued under section 21, 22.21 or 23 with respect to the information, record, document or thing, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of preserved elements — production order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person or entity that is subject to a production order made under section 20.4 with respect to any information, record or document that they preserved under a preservation order made under section 20.3 shall destroy the information, record or document that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving the information, record or document under that section as soon as feasible after the earlier of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the day on which the production order is revoked; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which the information, record or document, or document prepared for the purpose of preserving the information, record or document, is produced under the production order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of preserved elements — warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (1) and (2), a person or entity that preserved any information, record, document or thing under a preservation order made under section 20.3 shall destroy the information, record, document or thing that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving the information, record, document or thing under that section when the information, record, document or thing, or document prepared for the purpose of preserving the information, record, document or thing, is obtained under a warrant issued under section 21 or 22.21 or when a thing is removed in accordance with a warrant issued under section 23.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 21(1.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 21(2)(d.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 21(2)(h) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>any previous application made under subsection (1) or 22.21(1) in relation to a person who is identified in the affidavit in accordance with paragraph (d), the date on which each such application was made, the name of the judge to whom it was made and the judge’s decision on it.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 21(3.01) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section 21 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3.1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information or intelligence outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(3.2)</Label><Text>Without regard to any other law, including that of any foreign state, and to assist the Service in the performance of its duties and function under section 16, a judge may, in a warrant issued under subsection (3), authorize the collection, from within Canada, of information or intelligence that is located outside Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Paragraph 21(4)(d.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsection 21(4.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 22.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application for warrant to obtain information, record, document or thing</MarginalNote><Label>22.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Director or any employee who is designated by the Minister for the purpose believes, on reasonable grounds, that a warrant under this section is required to enable the Service to obtain any information, record or document — regardless of medium or form — or thing that will assist the Service to investigate, within or outside Canada, a threat to the security of Canada or to perform its duties and functions under section 16, the Director or employee may, after having obtained the Minister’s approval, make an application in accordance with subsection (2) to a judge for a warrant under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Matters to be specified in application for warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application to a judge under subsection (1) shall be made in writing and be accompanied by an affidavit of the applicant deposing to the following matters:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the facts relied on to justify the belief, on reasonable grounds, that a warrant under this section is required to enable the Service to obtain any information, record or document — regardless of medium or form — or thing that will assist the Service to investigate, within or outside Canada, a threat to the security of Canada or to perform its duties and functions under section 16;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the type of information, record, document or thing proposed to be obtained;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the powers referred to in paragraphs (3)(a) to (c) proposed to be exercised;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the identity of the person, if known, who has possession of the information, record, document or thing proposed to be obtained;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the persons or classes of persons to whom the warrant is proposed to be directed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a general description of the place where the warrant is proposed to be executed, if a general description of that place can be given;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the period, not exceeding 120 days, for which the warrant is requested to be in force; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>any previous application made under subsection (1) or 21(1) in relation to a person who is identified in the affidavit in accordance with paragraph (d), the date on which each such application was made, the name of the judge to whom it was made and the judge’s decision on it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Issuance of warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite any other law but subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal>, if the judge to whom an application under subsection (1) is made is satisfied of the matters referred to in paragraph (2)(a) set out in the affidavit accompanying the application, the judge may issue a warrant authorizing the persons to whom it is directed to obtain, through a single attempt, any information, record or document — regardless of medium or form — or thing and, for that purpose,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to enter any place or open or obtain access to any thing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to search for, remove or return, or examine, take extracts from or make copies of or record in any other manner the information, record, document or thing; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to install, maintain or remove any thing.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Activities outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Without regard to any other law, including that of any foreign state, a judge may, in a warrant issued under subsection (3), authorize activities outside Canada to enable the Service to investigate a threat to the security of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Obtaining information, records or documents from within Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Without regard to any other law, including that of any foreign state, and to assist the Service in the performance of its duties and functions under section 16, a judge may, in a warrant issued under subsection (3), authorize the Service to obtain, from within Canada, any information, record or document — regardless of medium or form — that is located outside Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Matters to be specified in warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>There shall be specified in a warrant issued under subsection (3)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the type of information, record, document or thing authorized to be obtained and the powers referred to in paragraphs (3)(a) to (c) authorized to be exercised for that purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the identity of the person, if known, who has possession of the information, record, document or thing to be obtained;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the persons or classes of persons to whom the warrant is directed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a general description of the place where the warrant may be executed, if a general description of that place can be given;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the period for which the warrant is in force in accordance with subsection (7); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any terms and conditions that the judge considers advisable in the public interest.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>A warrant issued under subsection (3) ceases to have effect on the earlier of the end of a period of up to 120 days that begins on the day on which the warrant is issued and the day on which the information, record, document or thing is obtained.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification — other warrants</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the fact that a warrant may be issued under this section does not affect a judge’s authority to issue a warrant under section 21 nor the validity of such a warrant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>Subsection 22.3(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Assistance order</MarginalNote><Label>22.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A judge may order any person to provide assistance if the person’s assistance may reasonably be considered to be required to give effect to a warrant issued under section 21, 21.1, 22.21 or 23.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>Section 23 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant authorizing removal</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Director or any employee who is designated by the Minister for the purpose believes, on reasonable grounds, that a warrant under this section is required to enable the Service to remove any thing from any place where it was installed in the performance of the Service’s duties and functions under section 12 or 16 or in accordance with a warrant issued under section 21, 21.1 or 22.21, the Director or employee may make an application in accordance with subsection (2) to a judge for a warrant under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Matters to be specified in application for warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application to a judge under subsection (1) shall be made in writing and be accompanied by an affidavit of the applicant deposing to the following matters:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a general description of the thing to be removed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the facts relied on to justify the belief, on reasonable grounds, that the thing is in the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the powers referred to in paragraphs (3)(a) to (c) proposed to be exercised;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the identity of the person, if known, who possesses the thing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the persons or classes of persons to whom the warrant is proposed to be directed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a general description of the place where the warrant is proposed to be executed, if a general description of that place can be given; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the period for which the warrant is requested to be in force.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Issuance of warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite any other law but subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal>, if the judge to whom an application under subsection (1) is made is satisfied of the matters referred to in paragraph (2)(b) set out in the affidavit accompanying the application, the judge may issue a warrant authorizing the persons to whom it is directed to remove any thing from any place where it was installed and, for that purpose,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to enter any place or open or obtain access to any other thing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to search for the thing; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to install, maintain, remove, return or examine any other thing.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Matters to be specified in warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>There shall be specified in a warrant issued under subsection (3)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a general description of the thing authorized to be removed and the powers referred to in paragraphs (3)(a) to (c) authorized to be exercised for that purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the identify of the person, if known, who possesses the thing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the persons or classes of persons to whom the warrant is directed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a general description of the place where the warrant may be executed, if a general description of that place can be given;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the period for which the warrant is in force; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the terms and conditions that the judge considers advisable in the public interest.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41.1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 24 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant to have effect notwithstanding other laws</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>Despite any other law, a warrant issued under section 21, 22.21 or 23</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 24(a) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (i) and by replacing subparagraph (ii) with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>in the case of a warrant issued under section 22.21, to exercise the powers specified in the warrant for the purpose of obtaining information, records, documents or things of the type specified in the warrant, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a warrant issued under section 23, to exercise the powers specified in the warrant for the purpose of removing the thing specified in the warrant; and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Text>Section 27 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Making and hearing of applications</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application for a judicial authorization under section 11.13, an application under section 20.3 for a preservation order, an application under section 20.4 for a production order, an application under section 21, 21.1, 22.21 or 23 for a warrant, an application under section 22 or 22.1 for the renewal of a warrant or an application for an order under section 22.3 shall be made <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> and heard in private in accordance with regulations made under section 28.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hearing of applications — section 20.5</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application under section 20.5 for the revocation or variation of a production order may be heard in private in accordance with regulations made under section 28.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 28(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing the form of judicial authorizations that may be issued under section 11.13 and of warrants that may be issued under section 21, 21.1, 22.21 or 23;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>governing the practice and procedure of, and security requirements applicable to, hearings of applications for judicial authorization under section 11.13, for warrants that may be issued under section 21, 21.1, 22.21 or 23, for renewals of those warrants and for orders that may be made under section 20.3, 20.4 or 22.3;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 28 of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b.1) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.2)</Label><Text>governing the practice and procedure of, and security requirements applicable to, hearings of applications for the revocation or variation of a production order under section 20.5; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 28:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Parliamentary Review</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Five-year review</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after the fifth anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force and after each subsequent fifth anniversary, a review of this Act and of its administration and operation is to be undertaken by a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is numbered as Schedule 1.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding, after Schedule 1, the Schedule 2 set out in Schedule 1 to this Act.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47</Label><Text>The English version of the Act is amended by replacing “he or she” with “the judge” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 11.13(1) before paragraph (a); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subsection 12.1(3.3).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13, s. 50</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Consequential Amendment to the Intelligence Commissioner Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Text>Section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Intelligence Commissioner Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Query or exploitation of dataset in exigent circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>The Commissioner must review whether the conclusions — made under subsection 11.22(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal> and on the basis of which a query or exploitation of a dataset in exigent circumstances was authorized — are reasonable.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>Measures to Counter Foreign Interference</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 1</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. O-5; 2001, c. 41, s. 25</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Security of Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>49</Label><Text>The long title of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="en"><LongTitle>An Act respecting foreign interference and the security of information</LongTitle></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50</Label><Text>Section 1 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="en"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Alternative Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Alternative title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>person permanently bound to secrecy</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 8(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a current or former member or employee of a department, division, branch or office of the federal public administration, or any of its parts, set out in Schedule 1;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (f) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>special operational information</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 8(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e.1)</Label><Text>the military vulnerabilities or advantages of the Canadian Forces, including the operational or technical vulnerabilities and advantages of any ally or adversary;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the means that the Government of Canada used, uses or intends to use, or is capable of using, to protect or exploit any information or intelligence referred to in any of paragraphs (a) to (e.1), including, but not limited to, encryption and cryptographic systems, and any vulnerabilities or limitations of those means; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>person permanently bound to secrecy</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 8(1) of the Act is amended by deleting “or” at the end of paragraph (a.2) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.3)</Label><Text>a current or former officer or non-commissioned member of a Canadian Forces unit or other element, or any of its parts, set out in Schedule 2 or a current or former officer or non-commissioned member who occupies or occupied a position in the Canadian Forces set out in that Schedule;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.4)</Label><Text>a person who is or was appointed, attached, assigned or seconded to a Canadian Forces unit or other element, or any of its parts, set out in Schedule 2 or to a position in the Canadian Forces set out in that Schedule; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Text>Section 9 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Amending Schedule 1</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend Schedule 1 by adding or deleting the name of any current or former department, division, branch or office of the federal public administration, or any of its parts, that, in the opinion of the Governor in Council, has or had a mandate that is primarily related to security and intelligence matters, or by modifying any name set out in the schedule.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Amending Schedule 2</MarginalNote><Label>9.1</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend Schedule 2 by adding, deleting or modifying</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name of any current or former Canadian Forces unit or other element, or any of its parts, that, in the opinion of the Governor in Council, has or had a mandate that is primarily related to matters of security and intelligence or of national defence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a reference to any current or former position in the Canadian Forces, the powers, duties and functions of which are or were, in the opinion of the Governor in Council, primarily related to matters of security and intelligence or of national defence.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>53</Label><Text>Section 20 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Foreign-influenced or Terrorist-influenced Intimidation, Threats or Violence</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Intimidation, threats or violence</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who, at the direction of, for the benefit of or in association with, a foreign entity or a terrorist group, induces or attempts to induce, by intimidation, threat or violence, any person to do anything or to cause anything to be done.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extraterritorial application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 26(1), a person who commits an act referred to in subsection (1) while outside Canada is deemed to have committed it in Canada if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the victim is in Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the victim is outside Canada and</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the person or the victim or both are</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>a Canadian citizen,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>a person who is ordinarily resident in Canada,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(C)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(D)</Label><Text>a person who owes allegiance to His Majesty in right of Canada, or</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(E)</Label><Text>a person who is locally engaged and who performs their functions in a Canadian mission outside Canada, or</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is a person described in any of clauses (i)(A) to (E), the intimidation, threat or violence is in relation to the victim’s child, relative or <DefinitionRef>intimate partner</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, and the child, relative or partner is in or outside Canada.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, imposed on a person for an offence under subsection (1) is to be served consecutively to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any other sentence imposed on the person, other than one of life imprisonment, for an offence arising out of the same event or series of events; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, to which the person is subject at the time the sentence is imposed on the person for an offence under subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application — subsections 26(2) to (4)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If a person is deemed under this section to have committed an act referred to in subsection (1) in Canada, subsections 26(2) to (4) apply, with any adaptations that may be necessary, to any proceedings in respect of an offence under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>victim</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, in this section, <DefinedTermEn>victim</DefinedTermEn> means the person who the person who commits, or is alleged to have committed, the offence under subsection (1) induces or attempts to induce, or is alleged to have induced or attempted to induce, to do anything or to cause anything to be done.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Intimidation, threats or violence outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>20.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who, while outside Canada, at the direction of, for the benefit of or in association with, a foreign entity or a terrorist group, induces or attempts to induce, by intimidation, threat or violence, any person outside Canada to do anything or to cause anything to be done</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that is for the purpose of increasing the capacity of a foreign entity or a terrorist group to harm Canadian interests; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is reasonably likely to harm Canadian interests.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If any of the facts referred to in paragraph 20(2)(b) apply to either the person who is alleged to have committed an act referred to in subsection (1) or the victim, the person who is alleged to have committed the act is to be prosecuted under subsection 20(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, imposed on a person for an offence under subsection (1) is to be served consecutively to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any other sentence imposed on the person, other than one of life imprisonment, for an offence arising out of the same event or series of events; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, to which the person is subject at the time the sentence is imposed on the person for an offence under subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application — subsections 26(2) to (4)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsections 26(2) to (4) apply, with any adaptations that may be necessary, to any proceedings in respect of an offence under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>victim</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, in this section, <DefinedTermEn>victim</DefinedTermEn> means the person who the person who commits, or is alleged to have committed, the offence under subsection (1) induces or attempts to induce, or is alleged to have induced or attempted to induce, to do anything or to cause anything to be done.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Indictable Offence Committed for a Foreign Entity</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Committing indictable offence for foreign entity</MarginalNote><Label>20.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an indictable offence under this or any other Act of Parliament at the direction of, for the benefit of or in association with, a foreign entity is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, imposed on a person for an offence under subsection (1) is to be served consecutively to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any other sentence imposed on the person, other than one of life imprisonment, for an offence arising out of the same event or series of events; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, to which the person is subject at the time the sentence is imposed on the person for an offence under subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Conduct or Omission for a Foreign Entity</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Engaging in surreptitious or deceptive conduct</MarginalNote><Label>20.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an indictable offence who, at the direction of, for the benefit of or in association with, a foreign entity, knowingly engages in surreptitious or deceptive conduct or omits, surreptitiously or with the intent to deceive, to do anything if the person’s conduct or omission is for a purpose prejudicial to the safety or interests of the State or the person is reckless as to whether their conduct or omission is likely to harm Canadian interests.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) is liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, imposed on a person for an offence under subsection (1) is to be served consecutively to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any other sentence imposed on the person, other than one of life imprisonment, for an offence arising out of the same event or series of events; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, to which the person is subject at the time the sentence is imposed on the person for an offence under subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Political Interference for a Foreign Entity</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Influencing political or governmental process</MarginalNote><Label>20.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an indictable offence who, at the direction of, or in association with, a foreign entity, engages in surreptitious or deceptive conduct with the intent to influence a political or governmental process, educational governance, the performance of a duty in relation to such a process or such governance or the exercise of a democratic right in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) is liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, imposed on a person for an offence under subsection (1) is to be served consecutively to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any other sentence imposed on the person, other than one of life imprisonment, for an offence arising out of the same event or series of events; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other sentence, other than one of life imprisonment, to which the person is subject at the time the sentence is imposed on the person for an offence under subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>educational governance</DefinedTermEn> means the governance of a school board or primary or secondary school, college, university or other institution of higher learning or training institution in Canada. (<DefinedTermFr>gouvernance scolaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>political or governmental process</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any proceeding of a legislative body;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the development of a legislative proposal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the development or amendment of any policy or program;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the making of a decision by a public office holder or government body, including the awarding of a contract;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the holding of an election or referendum; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the nomination of a candidate or the development of an electoral platform by a political party. (<DefinedTermFr>processus politique ou gouvernemental</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>public office holder</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following individuals:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any officer or employee of His Majesty in right of Canada and includes</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a member of the Senate or the House of Commons and any person on the staff of such a member,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a person who is appointed to any office or body by or with the approval of the Governor in Council or a minister of the Crown, other than a judge receiving a salary under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal> or the lieutenant governor of a province,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>an officer, director or employee of any <DefinitionRef>federal board, commission or other tribunal</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>a member of the Canadian Forces, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>a member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>members of the legislature of a province or persons on the staff of such members;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>employees of the government of a province;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>members of a council or other statutory body charged with the administration of the civil or municipal affairs of a city, town, municipality or district, persons on the staff of such members or officers or employees of a city, town, municipality or district;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>members of the council of a <DefinitionRef>band</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>, or of the council of an Indian band established by an Act of Parliament, persons on their staff or employees of such a council;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>members of an aboriginal government or institution that exercises jurisdiction or authority under a self-government agreement, or under self-government provisions contained in a land claims agreement, given effect by or under an Act of Parliament, persons on the staff of those members or employees of that government or institution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>an officer or employee of an entity that represents the interests of First Nations, the Inuit or the Métis. (<DefinedTermFr>titulaire d’une charge publique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>This section applies to any of the following political or governmental processes in Canada:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>federal political or governmental processes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provincial or territorial political or governmental processes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>municipal political or governmental processes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the political or governmental processes of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any other entity that represents the interests of First Nations, the Inuit or the Métis.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>54</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 22(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Preparatory acts</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who, for the purpose of committing an offence under this Act, other than under subsection 13(1) or 18(1), does anything that is directed towards or done in preparation of the commission of the offence, including</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 22(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>55</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is numbered as Schedule 1.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>56</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding, after Schedule 1, the Schedule 2 set out in Schedule 2 to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Terminology Changes</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>” — Acts</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>” is replaced by a reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 38.13(1), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsections 38.131(8) to (10);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subparagraph 5(5)(f)(iii), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraphs 22(4)(g) and (h);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subparagraphs 51(2)(a)(ii) and (b)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Conflict of Interest Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph (j) of the definition <DefinitionRef>offence</DefinitionRef> in section 183,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 486.5(2.1)(d), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the portion of paragraph (c.1) of the definition <DefinitionRef>primary designated offence</DefinitionRef> in section 487.04 before subparagraph (i);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>section 7.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subparagraph 2(1)(a)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>paragraph 183.6(3)(d) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>subsection 20(6) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Patent Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraphs (d) and (e) of the definition <DefinitionRef>privileged information</DefinitionRef> in subsection 45.4(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 45.45(1)(b), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 45.5(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Visiting Forces Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the portion of section 20 before paragraph (a), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 21;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Public Sector Labour Relations Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 238.09(2), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 238.29(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Servants Disclosure Protection Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 17, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 49(1)(c); and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 12(1), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 16(1)(a).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Other references — Acts</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, every reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>” in any provision of an Act of Parliament, other than a provision referred to in subsection (1), is to be read as a reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>” — Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>” is replaced by a reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>section 24 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Military Rules of Evidence</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Grosse Isle, P.Q., Prohibited Place Order</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Exempt Personal Information Bank Order, No. 13 (RCMP)</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Exempt Personal Information Bank Order, No. 14 (CSIS)</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Exempt Personal Information Bank Order, No. 25 (RCMP)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Other references — Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, every reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>” in any provision of a <DefinitionRef>regulation</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>, made under an Act of Parliament, other than a provision referred to in subsection (3), is to be read as a reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>National Defence Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>58</Label><Text>Paragraph 183.6(3)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an offence punishable under section 130 that is an offence under subsection 16(1) or (2), 17(1), 19(1), 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1), 20.4(1) or 22(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>National Security Act, 2017</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>59</Label><Text>Paragraph 82(1)(d) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security Act, 2017</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 2</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>60</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 52(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Sabotage</MarginalNote><Label>52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years or is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction who does a prohibited act with the intent to endanger</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 52 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, no person commits an offence under subsection (1) if they do a prohibited act while participating in advocacy, protest or dissent but they do not intend to cause any of the harms referred to in paragraphs (1)(a) and (b).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>61</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 52:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Sabotage — essential infrastructure</MarginalNote><Label>52.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years or is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction who interferes with access to an essential infrastructure or causes an essential infrastructure to be lost, inoperable, unsafe or unfit for use with the intent to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>endanger the safety, security or defence of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>endanger the safety or security of the naval, army or air forces of any state other than Canada that are lawfully present in Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>cause a serious risk to the health or safety of the public or any segment of the public.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>essential infrastructure</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>essential infrastructure</DefinedTermEn> means a facility or system, whether public or private, completed or under construction, that provides or distributes — or is intended to provide or distribute — services that are essential to the health, safety, security or economic well-being of persons in Canada, including the following:</Text><Definition><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>transportation infrastructure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>information and communication technology infrastructure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>water and wastewater management infrastructure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>energy and utilities infrastructure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>health services infrastructure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>food supply and food services infrastructure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>government operations infrastructure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>financial infrastructure; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>any other infrastructure prescribed by regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Saving — stop work</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person commits an offence under subsection (1) by reason only that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>they stop work as a result of the failure of their employer and themselves to agree on any matter relating to their employment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>they stop work as a result of the failure of their employer and a bargaining agent acting on their behalf to agree on any matter relating to their employment; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>they stop work as a result of their taking part in a combination of workers or employees for their own reasonable protection as workers or employees.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Saving — obtaining or communicating information</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No person commits an offence under subsection (1) by reason only that they attend at or near or approach a dwelling-house or place for the purpose only of obtaining or communicating information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, no person commits an offence under subsection (1) if they interfere with access to an essential infrastructure or cause an essential infrastructure to be lost, inoperable, unsafe or unfit for use while participating in advocacy, protest or dissent but they do not intend to cause any of the harms referred to in paragraphs (1)(a) to (c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations prescribing any infrastructure for the purpose of paragraph (i) of the definition <DefinitionRef>essential infrastructure</DefinitionRef> in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Sabotage — device</MarginalNote><Label>52.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who makes, possesses, sells or distributes a device intending that it be used or knowing that it will be used, in whole or in part, to carry out an offence under subsection 52(1) or 52.1(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>device</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, <DefinedTermEn>device</DefinedTermEn> includes a <DefinitionRef>computer program</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 342.1(2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Attorney General’s consent</MarginalNote><Label>52.3</Label><Text>No proceeding for an offence under subsection 52(1), 52.1(1) or 52.2(1) shall be instituted without the Attorney General’s consent.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>62</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>offence</DefinitionRef> in section 183 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (a)(iii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii.01)</Label><Text>section 52.1 (sabotage — essential infrastructure),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii.02)</Label><Text>section 52.2 (sabotage — device),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>63</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 185(1.1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence under section 52, 52.1, 52.2, 467.11, 467.111, 467.12 or 467.13;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 185(1.1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>64</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 186(1.1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence under section 52, 52.1, 52.2, 467.11, 467.111, 467.12 or 467.13;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 186(1.1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>65</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 186.1(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence under section 52, 52.1, 52.2, 467.11, 467.111, 467.12 or 467.13;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 186.1 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>66</Label><Text>Paragraph 196(5)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence under section 52, 52.1, 52.2, 467.11, 467.111, 467.12 or 467.13,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>67</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 196.1(5)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an offence under section 52, 52.1, 52.2, 467.11, 467.12 or 467.13;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 196.1(5) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>68</Label><Text>Paragraph 462.48(1.1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an offence against section 52, 52.1, 52.2, 467.11, 467.111, 467.12 or 467.13, or a conspiracy or an attempt to commit, or being an accessory after the fact in relation to, such an offence;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>69</Label><Text>Paragraph 486.5(2.1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 16(1) or (2), 17(1), 19(1), 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1), 20.4(1) or 22(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>70</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (c.1)(ii) of the definition <DefinitionRef>primary designated offence</DefinitionRef> in section 487.04 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 20(1) (intimidation, threats or violence),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii.1)</Label><Text>subsection 20.1(1) (intimidation, threats or violence outside Canada),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii.2)</Label><Text>subsection 20.2(1) (committing indictable offence for foreign entity),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii.3)</Label><Text>subsection 20.3(1) (engaging in surreptitious or deceptive conduct),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii.4)</Label><Text>subsection 20.4(1) (influencing political or governmental process), and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>secondary designated offence</DefinitionRef> in section 487.04 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (c)(i):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.0001)</Label><Text>subsection 52.1(1) (sabotage — essential infrastructure),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.0002)</Label><Text>subsection 52.2(1) (sabotage — device),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>71</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(4.1)(e) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>, or an offence under subsection 21(1) or 22(1) or section 23 of that Act that is committed in relation to an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of that Act,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(4.3)(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>, or an offence under subsection 21(1) or 22(1) or section 23 of that Act that is committed in relation to an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subparagraphs 515(6)(a)(iv) and (v) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>that is an offence under subsection 16(1) or (2), 17(1), 19(1), 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.1(1), 20.3(1), 20.4(1) or 22(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>that is an offence under subsection 21(1) or section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> committed in relation to an offence referred to in subparagraph (iv),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 3</Label><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments and Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2023, c. 32</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>72</Label><Text>On the first day on which both subsection 13.3(1) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend certain Acts and to make certain consequential amendments (firearms)</XRefExternal>, chapter 32 of the Statutes of Canada, 2023, and subsection <XRefInternal>71</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act are in force, paragraph 515(4.1)(e) of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>, or an offence under subsection 21(1) or 22(1) or section 23 of that Act that is committed in relation to an offence under subsection 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) or 20.4(1) of that Act,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2023, c. 32 and Bill C-332</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>73</Label><Text>If a provision of any of the following Acts (in this section referred to as the “other Act”) that amends subsection 515(4.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> comes into force or, in the case of a coordinating amendment, produces its effects on or after the day on which subsection <XRefInternal>71</XRefInternal>(1) comes into force, on the day on which that provision of the other Act comes into force or produces its effects, as the case may be, subsection 515(4.1) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by replacing “<Language xml:lang="fr">d’une infraction visée au paragraphe 20(1) de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur la protection de l’information</XRefExternal>, ou d’une infraction visée aux paragraphes 21(1) ou 22(1) ou à l’article 23 de cette loi commise à l’égard d’une infraction visée au paragraphe 20(1)</Language>” with “<Language xml:lang="fr">d’une infraction visée aux paragraphes 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) ou 20.4(1) de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur l’ingérence étrangère et la protection de l’information</XRefExternal>, ou d’une infraction visée aux paragraphes 21(1) ou 22(1) ou à l’article 23 de cette loi commise à l’égard d’une infraction visée aux paragraphes 20(1), 20.1(1), 20.2(1), 20.3(1) ou 20.4(1)</Language>”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend certain Acts and to make certain consequential amendments (firearms)</XRefExternal>, chapter 32 of the Statutes of Canada, 2023; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (coercive control of intimate partner)</XRefExternal>, if Bill C-332 introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament receives royal assent.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-20</MarginalNote><Label>74</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (5) apply if Bill C-20, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Complaints and Review Commission Act</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 125 of the other Act, then that section 125 is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>125</Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civilian Review and Complaints Commission for the Royal Canadian Mounted Police</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission civile d’examen et de traitement des plaintes relatives à la Gendarmerie royale du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force on the same day as section 125 of the other Act, then that section 125 is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 126 of the other Act, then that section 126 is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>126</Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Public Complaints and Review Commission</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission d’examen et de traitement des plaintes du public</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force on the same day as section 126 of the other Act, then that section 126 is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>60th day after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>75</Label><Text>This Part, other than sections <XRefInternal>72</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>74</XRefInternal>, comes into force on the 60th day after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><TitleText>Measures Relating to the Protection of Information</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 1</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Evidence Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>76</Label><Text>Section 36.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>official</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>36.1</Label><Text>In sections 37 to 38.43, <DefinedTermEn>official</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 118 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>77</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 37.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal to court of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>37.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1.1), an appeal lies from a determination under any of subsections 37(4.1) to (6)</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 37.1(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation — person charged with offence</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A person who is charged with an offence may appeal a determination referred to in subsection (1) that is made in relation to a criminal trial or other criminal proceeding only if they are convicted of the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation period for appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An appeal under this section shall be brought</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal permitted under subsection (1.1), after conviction and within the same period in which the accused may appeal from their conviction or any further time that the court referred to in subsection (1) considers appropriate in the circumstances; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in any other case, within 15 days after the day on which the determination appealed from is made or any further time that the court referred to in subsection (1) considers appropriate in the circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptional circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1.1) and paragraph (2)(a), the court referred to in subsection (1) may, on application by the person charged with the offence, permit the appeal to be brought before conviction if the court is satisfied that there are exceptional circumstances that justify doing so.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>78</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 38:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Provisions of General Application</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>79</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>proceeding</DefinedTermEn> in section 38 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>proceeding</DefinedTermEn> means a proceeding before a court, person or body with jurisdiction to compel the production of information, but does not include a <DefinitionRef>federal proceeding</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section <XRefInternal>38.2</XRefInternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>instance</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>80</Label><Text>Subsection 38.03(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada shall, within 30 days after the day on which they first receive a notice about information under any of subsections 38.01(1) to (4), notify in writing every person who provided notice under section 38.01 about that information of their decision with respect to disclosure of the information.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>81</Label><Text>Section 38.09 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal to Federal Court of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>38.09</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1.1), an order made under any of subsections 38.06(1) to (3) may be appealed to the Federal Court of Appeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation — person charged with offence</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A person who is charged with an offence may appeal an order referred to in subsection (1) that is made in relation to a criminal trial or other criminal proceeding only if they are convicted of the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation period for appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An appeal under this section shall be brought</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal permitted under subsection (1.1), after conviction and within the same period in which the accused may appeal from their conviction or any further time that the Court considers appropriate in the circumstances; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in any other case, within 15 days after the day on which the order is made or any further time that the Court considers appropriate in the circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptional circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1.1) and paragraph (2)(a), the Court may, on application by the person charged with the offence, permit the appeal to be brought before conviction if the Court is satisfied that there are exceptional circumstances that justify doing so.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>82</Label><Text>Paragraph 38.1(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an application for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court of Canada from a judgment made on appeal shall be made within 15 days after the day on which the judgment appealed from is made or within any further time that the Supreme Court of Canada considers appropriate in the circumstances; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>83</Label><Text>Subsection 38.131(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Single judge</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>, for the purposes of the application, the Federal Court of Appeal consists of a single judge of that Court.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>84</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 38.17:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Secure Administrative Review Proceedings</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>38.2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and in sections <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>38.45</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal proceeding</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an application for judicial review or an appeal in the Federal Court of a decision of a <DefinitionRef>federal board, commission or other tribunal</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an appeal in the Federal Court of Appeal from a decision of the Federal Court in a proceeding referred to in paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an application for judicial review or an appeal in the Federal Court of Appeal of a decision of a federal board, commission or other tribunal referred to in paragraph (a); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a proceeding referred to in section 6 or 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charities Registration (Security Information) Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedDefinition><Text>It does not include any proceeding in the Federal Court or the Federal Court of Appeal that is in respect of a matter under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and does not include a proceeding in which information may be disclosed to either of those courts for a purpose listed in the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>instance fédérale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></ContinuedDefinition></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in relation to a federal proceeding in the Federal Court of Appeal, not fewer than three judges of that court, each of whom is either the Chief Justice or a judge designated by the Chief Justice to conduct hearings under section <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>, sitting together in an uneven number; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to a federal proceeding in the Federal Court, the Chief Justice of that court or a judge designated by the Chief Justice to conduct hearings under section <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>juge</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>non-governmental party</DefinedTermEn> means a party to a federal proceeding who is neither the Attorney General of Canada nor represented by the Attorney General of Canada. (<DefinedTermFr>partie non gouvernementale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>participant</DefinedTermEn> means a person who, in connection with a federal proceeding, is required to disclose, or expects to disclose or cause the disclosure of, information. (<DefinedTermFr>participant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>potentially injurious information</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 38. (<DefinedTermFr>renseignements potentiellement préjudiciables</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>sensitive information</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 38. (<DefinedTermFr>renseignements sensibles</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>special counsel</DefinedTermEn> means a person appointed as a special counsel under section <XRefInternal>38.34</XRefInternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>conseiller juridique spécial</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to Attorney General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>38.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every participant who, in connection with a federal proceeding, is required to disclose, or expects to disclose or cause the disclosure of, information that the participant believes is sensitive information or potentially injurious information must, as soon as possible, notify the Attorney General of Canada in writing of the possibility of the disclosure, and of the nature, date and place of the federal proceeding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>During federal proceeding</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every participant who believes that sensitive information or potentially injurious information is about to be disclosed, whether by the participant or another person, in the course of a federal proceeding must raise the matter with the person presiding at the federal proceeding and notify the Attorney General of Canada in writing of the matter as soon as possible, whether or not notice has been given under subsection (1). In such circumstances, the person presiding at the federal proceeding must ensure that the information is not disclosed other than in accordance with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of disclosure from official</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An official, other than a participant, who believes that sensitive information or potentially injurious information may be disclosed in connection with a federal proceeding may notify the Attorney General of Canada in writing of the possibility of the disclosure, and of the nature, date and place of the federal proceeding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>During federal proceeding</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An official, other than a participant, who believes that sensitive information or potentially injurious information is about to be disclosed in the course of a federal proceeding may raise the matter with the person presiding at the federal proceeding. If the official raises the matter, they must notify the Attorney General of Canada in writing of the matter as soon as possible, whether or not notice has been given under subsection (3), and the person presiding at the federal proceeding must ensure that the information is not disclosed other than in accordance with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>This section does not apply when</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the information is disclosed by a person to their lawyer in connection with a federal proceeding, if the information is relevant to that proceeding;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the information is disclosed to enable the Attorney General of Canada, special counsel, a judge, or a court hearing an appeal from an order of the judge, to exercise their powers and perform their duties and functions under this section and sections <XRefInternal>38.22</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>38.41</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>38.43</XRefInternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>disclosure of the information is authorized by the government institution in which or for which the information was produced or, if the information was not produced in or for a government institution, the government institution in which it was first received.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) do not apply to a participant if a government institution referred to in paragraph (5)(c) advises the participant that it is not necessary, in order to prevent disclosure of the information referred to in that paragraph, to give notice to the Attorney General of Canada under subsection (1) or to raise the matter under subsection (2) with the person presiding at the federal proceeding.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>38.22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(5), it is prohibited for a person to disclose in connection with a federal proceeding</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>information about which notice is given under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(1) to (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the fact that notice is given to the Attorney General of Canada under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(1) to (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the fact that a motion is made under section <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal> or that an appeal of an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) in connection with the motion is instituted; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the fact that an agreement is entered into under section <XRefInternal>38.24</XRefInternal> or subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(6).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Disclosure of the information or the facts referred to in subsection (1) is not prohibited if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Attorney General of Canada authorizes the disclosure in writing under section <XRefInternal>38.23</XRefInternal> or by agreement under section <XRefInternal>38.24</XRefInternal> or subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(6); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a judge authorizes the disclosure under subsection <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) or a court hearing an appeal from the order of the judge authorizes the disclosure, and either the time provided to appeal the order or the appeal court’s judgment has expired or no further appeal is available.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization by Attorney General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>38.23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada may, at any time and subject to any conditions that they consider appropriate, authorize the disclosure of all or part of the information and facts the disclosure of which is prohibited under subsection <XRefInternal>38.22</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada must, within 30 days after the day on which they first receive a notice about information under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(1) to (4), notify in writing every person who provided notice under those subsections about that information of their decision with respect to disclosure of the information.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure agreement</MarginalNote><Label>38.24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada and a person who has given notice under subsection <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) and is not required to disclose information but wishes, in connection with a federal proceeding, to disclose any facts referred to in paragraphs <XRefInternal>38.22</XRefInternal>(1)(b) to (d) or information about which the person gave the notice, or to cause that disclosure, may, before the person brings a motion under paragraph <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(2)(c), enter into an agreement that permits the disclosure of part of the facts or information or disclosure of the facts or information subject to conditions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No motion</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an agreement is entered into under subsection (1), the person may not bring a motion under paragraph <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(2)(c) with respect to the information about which they gave notice to the Attorney General of Canada under subsection <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(1) or (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Motion — Attorney General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>38.25</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada may, at any time and under any circumstances during a federal proceeding, bring a motion to a judge for an order with respect to the disclosure of information about which notice was given under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(1) to (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Motion — general</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, with respect to information about which notice was given under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(1) to (4), the Attorney General of Canada does not provide notice of a decision in accordance with subsection <XRefInternal>38.23</XRefInternal>(2) or, other than by an agreement under section <XRefInternal>38.24</XRefInternal>, does not authorize the disclosure of the information or authorizes the disclosure of only part of the information or authorizes the disclosure subject to any conditions,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Attorney General of Canada must bring a motion to a judge for an order with respect to disclosure of the information if a person who gave notice under subsection <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) is a witness;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person, other than a witness, who is required to disclose information in connection with a federal proceeding must bring a motion to a judge for an order with respect to disclosure of the information; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person who is not required to disclose information in connection with a federal proceeding but who wishes to disclose it or to cause its disclosure may bring a motion to a judge for an order with respect to disclosure of the information.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Attorney General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who makes a motion under paragraph (2)(b) or (c) must provide notice of the motion to the Attorney General of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court records</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph (5)(b), a motion under this section is confidential. During the period when a motion is confidential, the Chief Administrator of the Courts Administration Service may, subject to section <XRefInternal>38.31</XRefInternal>, take any measure that they consider appropriate to protect the confidentiality of the motion and the information to which it relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>As soon as they are seized of a motion under this section, the judge</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>must hear the representations of the Attorney General of Canada with respect to making the motion public;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>must, if they decide that the motion should be made public, make an order to that effect;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>must hear the representations of the Attorney General of Canada concerning the identity of all parties or witnesses whose interests may be affected by either the prohibition of disclosure or the conditions to which disclosure is subject and concerning the persons who should be given notice of any hearing of the matter;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>must decide whether it is necessary to hold any hearing of the matter;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>if they decide that a hearing should be held, must</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>determine who should be given notice of the hearing,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>order the Attorney General of Canada to notify those persons, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>determine the content and form of the notice; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>may, if they consider it appropriate in the circumstances, give any person the opportunity to make representations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>After the judge is seized of a motion made under paragraph (2)(c) or, in the case of an appeal from an order of the judge made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) in connection with that motion, before the appeal is disposed of,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Attorney General of Canada and the person who made the motion may enter into an agreement that permits the disclosure of part of the facts referred to in paragraphs <XRefInternal>38.22</XRefInternal>(1)(b) to (d) or part of the information or disclosure of the facts or information subject to conditions; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if an agreement is entered into, the judge’s consideration of the motion or any hearing or appeal must be terminated.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Termination</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (6), after the judge is seized of a motion made under this section — or, in the case of an appeal from an order of the judge made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3), before the appeal is disposed of — and if the Attorney General of Canada authorizes the disclosure of all or part of the information or withdraws conditions to which the disclosure is subject, the judge’s consideration of the motion or any hearing or appeal must be terminated in relation to that information, to the extent of the authorization or the withdrawal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure order</MarginalNote><Label>38.26</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Unless the judge concludes that the disclosure of the information or facts referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>38.22</XRefInternal>(1) would be injurious to international relations or national defence or national security, the judge may, by order, authorize the disclosure of the information or facts.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure — conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the judge concludes that the disclosure of the information or facts would be injurious to international relations or national defence or national security but that the public interest in disclosure outweighs in importance the public interest in non-disclosure, the judge may by order, after considering both the public interest in disclosure and the form of and conditions to disclosure that are most likely to limit any injury to international relations or national defence or national security resulting from disclosure, authorize the disclosure, subject to any conditions that the judge considers appropriate, of all or part of the information or facts, a summary of the information or a written admission of facts relating to the information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order confirming prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the judge does not authorize disclosure under subsection (1) or (2), the judge must, by order, confirm the prohibition of disclosure.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When determination takes effect</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order of the judge that authorizes disclosure does not take effect until the time provided or granted to appeal the order has expired or, if the order is appealed, the time provided or granted to appeal a judgment of an appeal court that confirms the order has expired and no further appeal from a judgment that confirms the order is available.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The judge may receive into evidence anything that, in the opinion of the judge, is reliable and appropriate, even if it would not otherwise be admissible under Canadian law, and may base their decision on that evidence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of order</MarginalNote><Label>38.27</Label><Text>The judge may order the Attorney General of Canada to give notice of an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) to any person who, in the opinion of the judge, should be notified.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal to Federal Court of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>38.28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An order made by a judge of the Federal Court under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) may be appealed to the Federal Court of Appeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation period for appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An appeal must be brought within 15 days after the day on which the order is made or within any further time that the Federal Court of Appeal considers appropriate in the circumstances.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation periods for appeals to Supreme Court of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>38.29</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an application for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court of Canada from an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) by the Federal Court of Appeal, or from a judgment of the Federal Court of Appeal in an appeal of such an order made by the Federal Court, must be made within 15 days after the day on which the order or judgment appealed from is made or within any further time that the Supreme Court of Canada considers appropriate in the circumstances; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if leave to appeal is granted, the appeal must be brought in the manner set out in subsection 60(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Supreme Court Act</XRefExternal> but within the time specified by the Supreme Court of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Special rules — hearing in private</MarginalNote><Label>38.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The judge conducting a hearing under subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(5) or the court hearing an appeal of an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) may make an order that the hearing be held, or the appeal be heard, in private.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special rules — hearing in National Capital Region</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A hearing under subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(5) or an appeal of an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) must, at the request of the Attorney General of Canada, be held or heard, as the case may be, in the National Capital Region, as described in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><Language xml:lang="la">Ex parte</Language> representations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The judge conducting a hearing under subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(5) or the court hearing an appeal of an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) may give any person who makes representations under paragraph <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(5)(f), and must give the Attorney General of Canada, the opportunity to make representations <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><Language xml:lang="la">Ex parte</Language> representations — public hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a hearing under subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(5) is held, or an appeal of an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) is heard, in public, any <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> representations made in that hearing or appeal must be made in private.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Protective order</MarginalNote><Label>38.31</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The judge conducting a hearing under subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(5) or the court hearing an appeal of an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) may make any order that the judge or the court considers appropriate in the circumstances to protect the confidentiality of any information to which the hearing or appeal relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court records</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court records relating to a hearing that is held, or an appeal that is heard, in private or to any <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> representations are confidential. The judge or the court may order that the court records, or any part of them, relating to a private or public hearing or appeal be sealed and kept in a location to which the public has no access.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Judge seized</MarginalNote><Label>38.32</Label><Text>The judge who hears the motion brought under subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) becomes seized of all matters in the federal proceeding.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Undisclosed information — federal proceeding</MarginalNote><Label>38.33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In considering the merits of the federal proceeding, the judge may receive into evidence, and may base their decision on, any information the disclosure of which is prohibited as a result of the application of sections <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Representations and private hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), the judge may — or, if the Attorney General of Canada so requests, the judge must —</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>receive <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> representations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>conduct a hearing in private and in the absence of the non-governmental party and their counsel.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In conducting a hearing under paragraph (2)(b), the judge must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>deal with all matters as informally and expeditiously as the circumstances and considerations of fairness and natural justice permit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>without disclosing the information referred to in subsection (1), ensure that the non-governmental party to the federal proceeding is provided with a summary of the information that enables that party to be reasonably informed of the case; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>at the request of the Attorney General of Canada, hold the hearing in the National Capital Region, as described in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The judge may base any decision on the information referred to in subsection (1) even if a summary of that information has not been provided to the non-governmental party.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Special counsel</MarginalNote><Label>38.34</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The judge, in consideration of the principles of fairness and natural justice, may appoint a special counsel for the purposes of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a motion made under section <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal> and the federal proceeding as a whole; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any appeal of the motion or of the federal proceeding.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>List</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The special counsel may be appointed from the list of persons referred to in subsection 85(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Special counsel’s role</MarginalNote><Label>38.35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A special counsel’s role is to protect the interests of the non-governmental party when information and other evidence is presented, or representations are made in private and in the absence of the non-governmental party and their counsel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Responsibilities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A special counsel may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>make oral and written representations with respect to the information or other evidence that has been filed with the court but has not been disclosed to the non-governmental party and their counsel;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>participate in, and cross-examine witnesses who testify during, any part of the proceeding that is held in private and in the absence of the non-governmental party and their counsel; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>exercise, with the judge’s authorization, any other powers that are necessary to protect the interests of the non-governmental party.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the special counsel is not a party to the federal proceeding and the relationship between the special counsel and the non-governmental party is not that of lawyer and client.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protection of communications with special counsel</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>However, a communication between the non-governmental party or their counsel and the special counsel that, if the relationship were one of lawyer and client, would be subject to solicitor-client privilege or the professional secrecy of advocates is deemed to be subject to that privilege or professional secrecy. For greater certainty, in respect of that communication, the special counsel is not a compellable witness in any proceeding.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>38.36</Label><Text>A special counsel is not personally liable for anything they do or omit to do in good faith under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to provide information</MarginalNote><Label>38.37</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada must, within a period set by the judge, provide the special counsel with a copy of the information or other evidence that has been filed with the court in relation to the federal proceeding, including any information or other evidence that is not disclosed to the non-governmental party and their counsel.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Restrictions on communications — special counsel</MarginalNote><Label>38.38</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>After the information or other evidence is received by the special counsel, the special counsel may, during the remainder of the federal proceeding and any appeal in respect of it, communicate with another person about the federal proceeding or the appeal only with the judge’s or appeal court’s authorization and subject to any conditions that the judge or appeal court considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restrictions on communications — other persons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the special counsel is authorized to communicate with a person, the judge or appeal court may prohibit that person from communicating with anyone else about the federal proceeding or appeal during its remainder or may impose conditions with respect to such a communication during that period.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure and communication prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>38.39</Label><Text>With the exception of communications authorized by a judge or disclosures permitted under section <XRefInternal>38.22</XRefInternal>, it is prohibited for a person to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>disclose information or other evidence that is disclosed to them under section <XRefInternal>38.37</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>38.38</XRefInternal> and that is treated as confidential by the judge; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>communicate with another person about the content of any part of a federal proceeding, or an appeal in respect of it, that is heard in private and in the absence of the non-governmental party and their counsel.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Fairness</MarginalNote><Label>38.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The judge may, if they are of the opinion that they are unable to conduct a fair hearing because the non-governmental party is not reasonably informed of the case, make an order granting an appropriate remedy to the non-governmental party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Potential orders</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The orders that may be made under subsection (1) include, but are not limited to, the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an order allowing or dismissing the federal proceeding; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an order finding against any party on any issue relating to information the disclosure of which is prohibited.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a remedy referred to in subsection (1) must not include the disclosure of information ordered not to be disclosed under subsection <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(3) or <XRefInternal>38.41</XRefInternal>(4).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate of Attorney General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>38.41</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada may personally issue a certificate that prohibits the disclosure of information in connection with a federal proceeding for the purpose of protecting information obtained in confidence from, or in relation to, a <DefinitionRef>foreign entity</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> or for the purpose of protecting national defence or national security. The certificate may only be issued after an order or decision that would result in the disclosure of the information to be subject to the certificate has been made under this or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Service of certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada must cause a copy of the certificate to be served on</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person presiding or designated to preside at the federal proceeding to which the information relates or, if no person is designated, the person who has the authority to designate a person to preside;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>every party to the federal proceeding;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>every person who gives notice under section <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal> in connection with the federal proceeding;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>every person who, in connection with the federal proceeding, may disclose, is required to disclose or may cause the disclosure of the information about which the Attorney General of Canada has received notice under section <XRefInternal>38.21</XRefInternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>every party to a hearing under subsection <XRefInternal>38.25</XRefInternal>(5) or to an appeal of an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) in relation to the information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any court that hears an appeal from an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3) in relation to the information; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any other person who, in the opinion of the Attorney General of Canada, should be served.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Filing of certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada must cause a copy of the certificate to be filed in the registry of the Federal Court of Appeal or the Federal Court, as the case may be, and the registry of any court that hears an appeal from an order made under any of subsections <XRefInternal>38.26</XRefInternal>(1) to (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Attorney General of Canada issues a certificate, then, despite any other provision of this Act, disclosure of the information is prohibited in accordance with the terms of the certificate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Statutory Instruments Act does not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a certificate issued under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada must, without delay after a certificate is issued, cause the certificate to be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The certificate and any matters arising out of it are not subject to review or to be restrained, prohibited, removed, set aside or otherwise dealt with, except in accordance with section <XRefInternal>38.42</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expiry</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The certificate expires 10 years after the day on which it is issued and may be reissued.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for review of certificate</MarginalNote><Label>38.42</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A party to the federal proceeding referred to in section <XRefInternal>38.41</XRefInternal> may apply to the Federal Court of Appeal for an order varying or cancelling a certificate issued under that section on the grounds referred to in subsection (7) or (8), as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Attorney General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The applicant must give notice of the application to the Attorney General of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Single judge</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>judge</DefinitionRef> in section <XRefInternal>38.2</XRefInternal> and section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>, for the purposes of the application, the Federal Court of Appeal consists of a single judge of that Court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Admissible information</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In considering the application, the judge may receive into evidence anything that, in the opinion of the judge, is reliable and appropriate, even if it would not otherwise be admissible under Canadian law, and may base a determination made under any of subsections (7) to (9) on that evidence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special rules and protective order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>38.3</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>38.31</XRefInternal> apply, with any necessary modifications, to an application made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expedited consideration</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The judge must consider the application as soon as reasonably possible, but not later than 10 days after the application is made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Varying certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the judge determines that some of the information subject to the certificate does not relate either to information obtained in confidence from, or in relation to, a foreign entity, or to national defence or national security, the judge must make an order varying the certificate accordingly.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cancelling certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If the judge determines that none of the information subject to the certificate relates to information obtained in confidence from, or in relation to, a foreign entity, or to national defence or national security, the judge must make an order cancelling the certificate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirming certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If the judge determines that all of the information subject to the certificate relates to information obtained in confidence from, or in relation to, a foreign entity, or to national defence or national security, the judge must make an order confirming the certificate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination is final</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, a determination of a judge under any of subsections (7) to (9) is final and is not subject to review or appeal by any court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>If a certificate is varied or cancelled under this section, the Attorney General of Canada must, as soon as possible after the decision of the judge and in a manner that mentions the original publication of the certificate, cause to be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the certificate as varied under subsection (7); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a notice of the cancellation of the certificate under subsection (8).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>foreign entity</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>foreign entity</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Interference and Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>38.43</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary for carrying out the purposes and provisions of sections <XRefInternal>38.2</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>38.42</XRefInternal>, including regulations respecting the notices and certificates.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>38.44</Label><Text>The report referred to in section 38.17 must also set out the operation of section <XRefInternal>38.41</XRefInternal> for the previous year and include the number of certificates issued under that section.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rules</MarginalNote><Label>38.45</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chief Justice of the Federal Court of Appeal and the Chief Justice of the Federal Court may each establish a committee to make rules governing the practice and procedure in relation to the participation of special counsel in federal proceedings before the court over which they preside. The rules are binding despite any rule of practice that would otherwise apply.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Composition of committees</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each committee established is to be composed of the appropriate Chief Justice, the Attorney General of Canada or one or more representatives of the Attorney General of Canada, and one or more members of the bar of any province who have experience in a field of law relevant to federal proceedings. Each Chief Justice may also designate additional members of their committee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chief Justice to preside</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Each Chief Justice, or a member designated by them, is to preside over their committee.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>85</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is amended by replacing the references after the heading “SCHEDULE” with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><OriginatingRef>(Paragraph 38.01(6)(d), subsections 38.01(8) and 38.02(1.1) and section 38.2)</OriginatingRef></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>86</Label><Text>Items 2, 4 and 21 of the schedule to the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>87</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 69.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>69.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a certificate under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> prohibiting the disclosure of information contained in a record is issued before a complaint is filed under this Part in respect of a request for access to that information, this Part does not apply to that information.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 69.1(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate following filing of complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Part, if a certificate under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> prohibiting the disclosure of information contained in a record is issued after the filing of a complaint under this Part in relation to a request for access to that information,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>88</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 83.039(2)(a) to (c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 83.039(2)(e) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 83.039 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 38.2 to 38.45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> apply to the judicial review proceedings referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>89</Label><Text>Paragraphs 83.05(6)(a) and (b) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>90</Label><Text>Section 83.06 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Return of information</MarginalNote><Label>83.06</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 83.05(6), any information that is obtained in confidence from a government, an institution or an agency of a foreign state, from an international organization of states or from an institution or an agency of an international organization of states and that is provided to the judge by the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness shall be returned to counsel representing the Minister and shall not be considered by the judge in making the determination under paragraph 83.05(6)(d), if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge determines that the information is not relevant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the judge determines that the information is relevant but should be summarized in a statement to be provided to the applicant; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Minister withdraws the information.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 38.2 to 38.45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> apply to an application made under subsection 83.05(5).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. H-6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Human Rights Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>91</Label><Text>Paragraph 58(2)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>at any time, an objection to the disclosure is made, or a certificate is issued, in accordance with sections 38 to 38.13 or 38.2 to 38.41 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>92</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 70.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>70.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a certificate under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> prohibiting the disclosure of personal information of a specific individual is issued before a complaint is filed by that individual under this Act in respect of a request for access to that information, the provisions of this Act respecting that individual’s right of access to their personal information do not apply to the information that is subject to the certificate.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 70.1(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate following filing of complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, if a certificate under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> prohibiting the disclosure of personal information of a specific individual is issued in respect of personal information after the filing of a complaint under this Act in relation to a request for access to that information,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 70.1(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information not to be disclosed</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Privacy Commissioner and every person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Privacy Commissioner, in carrying out their functions under this Act, shall not disclose information subject to a certificate issued under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> and shall take every reasonable precaution to avoid the disclosure of that information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limited power of delegation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Privacy Commissioner may not, nor may an Assistant Privacy Commissioner, delegate the investigation of any complaint respecting information subject to a certificate issued under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> except to one of a maximum of four officers or employees of the Commissioner specifically designated by the Commissioner for the purpose of conducting that investigation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>93</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 4.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a certificate under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> prohibiting the disclosure of personal information of a specific individual is issued before a complaint is filed by that individual under this Part in respect of a request for access to that information, the provisions of this Part respecting that individual’s right of access to their personal information do not apply to the information that is subject to the certificate.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 4.1(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate following filing of complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Part, if a certificate under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> prohibiting the disclosure of personal information of a specific individual is issued after the filing of a complaint under this Part in relation to a request for access to that information:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 4.1(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information not to be disclosed</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commissioner and every person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Commissioner, in carrying out their functions under this Part, shall not disclose information subject to a certificate issued under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>, and shall take every reasonable precaution to avoid the disclosure of that information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power to delegate</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may not delegate the investigation of any complaint relating to information subject to a certificate issued under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> except to one of a maximum of four officers or employees of the Commissioner specifically designated by the Commissioner for the purpose of conducting that investigation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 113</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Charities Registration (Security Information) Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>94</Label><Text>Section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Charities Registration (Security Information) Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial consideration</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following provisions govern the determination:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any information or evidence the disclosure of which would be injurious to national security shall be returned to the Ministers and shall not be considered by the judge in determining whether the certificate is reasonable if either</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the judge determines that the information or evidence is not relevant or, if it is relevant, that it should be part of a summary of the information or evidence provided to the applicant or the registered charity, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the matter is withdrawn;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the judge shall provide the applicant or registered charity with an opportunity to be heard; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the judge may receive into evidence anything that, in the opinion of the judge, is reliable and appropriate, even if it is inadmissible in a court of law, and may base the decision on that evidence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 38.2 to 38.45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> apply to the determination.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 20, s. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Secure Air Travel Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>95</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 16(6)(a) to (c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Secure Air Travel Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(6)(f) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 16 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 38.2 to 38.45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> apply to appeals under this section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 36, s. 42</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Prevention of Terrorist Travel Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>96</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 4(4)(a) to (c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prevention of Terrorist Travel Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(4)(f) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 38.2 to 38.45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> apply to appeals under this section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>97</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 6(2)(a) to (c) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 6(2)(e) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 38.2 to 38.45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> apply to judicial review proceedings referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="4"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>SOR/2001-360; SOR/2006-165, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Regulations Implementing the United Nations Resolutions on the Suppression of Terrorism</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>98</Label><Text>Paragraphs 2.2(2)(a) and (b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Regulations Implementing the United Nations Resolutions on the Suppression of Terrorism</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>99</Label><Text>Section 2.3 of the Regulations is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><Label>2.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 2.2, any information that is obtained in confidence from a government, an institution or an agency of a foreign state, from an international organization of states or from an institution or an agency of an international organization of states and that is provided to the judge by the Minister shall be returned to counsel representing the Minister and shall not be considered by the judge in making the determination under paragraph 2.2(2)(d), if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge determines that the information is not relevant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the judge determines that the information is relevant but should be summarized in a statement to be provided to the applicant; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Minister withdraws the information.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 38.2 to 38.45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> apply to an application made under section 2.2.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 2</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>100</Label><Text>Paragraph 487.3(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (iii) and by adding the following after that subparagraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii.1)</Label><Text>be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security, or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 3</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>101</Label><Text>Subsection 77(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Filing of evidence and summary</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When the certificate is referred, the Minister shall file with the Court the information and other evidence that is relevant to the ground of inadmissibility stated in the certificate and on which the certificate is based, as well as a summary of information and other evidence that enables the person named in the certificate to be reasonably informed of the case made by the Minister but that does not include anything that, in the Minister’s opinion, would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person if disclosed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>102</Label><Text>Subsection 79.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>79.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 79, the Minister may, without it being necessary for the judge to certify that a serious question of general importance is involved, appeal, at any stage of the proceeding, any decision made in the proceeding requiring the disclosure of information or other evidence if, in the Minister’s opinion, the disclosure would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>103</Label><Text>Subsection 82.31(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>82.31</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 82.3, the Minister may, without it being necessary for the judge to certify that a serious question of general importance is involved, appeal, at any stage of the proceeding, any decision made in the proceeding requiring the disclosure of information or other evidence if, in the Minister’s opinion, the disclosure would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>104</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 83(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>at any time during a proceeding, the judge may, on the judge’s own motion — and shall, on each request of the Minister — hear information or other evidence in the absence of the public and of the permanent resident or foreign national and their counsel if, in the judge’s opinion, its disclosure could be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 83(1)(d) and (e) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the judge shall ensure the confidentiality of information and other evidence provided by the Minister if, in the judge’s opinion, its disclosure would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>throughout the proceeding, the judge shall ensure that the permanent resident or foreign national is provided with a summary of information and other evidence that enables them to be reasonably informed of the case made by the Minister in the proceeding but that does not include anything that, in the judge’s opinion, would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person if disclosed;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 83(1.2)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the person has knowledge of information or other evidence whose disclosure would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person and, in the circumstances, there is a risk of inadvertent disclosure of that information or other evidence.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>105</Label><Text>Paragraph 85.1(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Minister’s claim that the disclosure of information or other evidence would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>106</Label><Text>Subsection 86.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial review</MarginalNote><Label>86.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, at any stage of the proceeding, apply for judicial review of any decision made in a proceeding referred to in section 86 requiring the disclosure of information or other evidence if, in the Minister’s opinion, the disclosure would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person. The application may be made without an application for leave.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>107</Label><Text>Subsection 87.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>87.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, without it being necessary for the judge to certify that a serious question of general importance is involved, appeal, at any stage of the proceeding, to the Federal Court of Appeal any decision made in a judicial review requiring the disclosure of information or other evidence if, in the Minister’s opinion, the disclosure would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security or endanger the safety of any person.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 4</Label><TitleText>Transitional Provisions, Coordinating Amendments and Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Previously commenced proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>108</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3), any proceeding commenced before the day on which this section comes into force and in respect of which any of the provisions amended or repealed by this Part apply is to be continued in accordance with those provisions as they read immediately before that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Section 37.1 — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 37.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>, as that section read immediately before the day on which this section comes into force, continues to apply in respect of a determination made under any of subsections 37(4.1) to (6) of that Act in relation to a criminal trial or other criminal proceeding if the charge at issue in the trial or other proceeding is laid before that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Section 38.09 — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 38.09 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>, as that section read immediately before the day on which this section comes into force, continues to apply in respect of an order made under any of subsections 38.06(1) to (3) of that Act in relation to a criminal trial or other criminal proceeding if the charge at issue in the trial or other proceeding is laid before that day.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2024, c. 4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>109</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security Review of Investments Modernization Act</XRefExternal> and section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, paragraphs 25.7(1)(a) to (e) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Investment Canada Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-26</MarginalNote><Label>110</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (9) apply if Bill C-26, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting cyber security, amending the Telecommunications Act and making consequential amendments to other Acts</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the first day on which section 2 of the other Act and section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, paragraphs 15.9(1)(a) to (e) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 12 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act, then, on the day on which that section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> comes into force, item 5 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 12 of the other Act, then that section 12 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If section 12 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section 12 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>On the first day on which section 145 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Critical Cyber Systems Protection Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 13 of the other Act, and section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, paragraphs 145(1)(a) to (e) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Critical Cyber Systems Protection Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If section 14 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act, then, on the day on which that section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> comes into force, item 6 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 14 of the other Act, then that section 14 is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If section 14 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section 14 is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-27</MarginalNote><Label>111</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill C-27, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Digital Charter Implementation Act, 2022</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 108 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Consumer Privacy Protection Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 2 of the other Act, and section <XRefInternal>84</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force,</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsection 108(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Consumer Privacy Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>108</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a certificate under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> prohibiting the disclosure of personal information of a specific individual is issued before a complaint is filed by that individual under this Act in respect of a request for access to that information, the provisions of this Act respecting that individual’s right of access to their personal information do not apply to the information that is subject to the certificate.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 108(2) of that Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate following filing of complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, if a certificate under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> prohibiting the disclosure of personal information of a specific individual is issued after the filing of a complaint under this Act in relation to a request for access to that information,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsections 108(3) and (4) of that Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information not to be disclosed</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Commissioner and every person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Commissioner, in exercising their powers and performing their duties and functions under this Act, must not disclose information subject to a certificate issued under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> and must take every reasonable precaution to avoid the disclosure of that information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power to delegate</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must not delegate the investigation or inquiry in respect of any complaint relating to information subject to a certificate issued under section 38.13 or 38.41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> except to one of a maximum of four officers or employees of the Commissioner specifically designated by the Commissioner for the purpose of conducting that investigation or inquiry, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 4 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>93</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>93</XRefInternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 4 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>93</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>93</XRefInternal> is deemed to have come into force before that section 4.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>60th day after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>112</Label><Text>This Part, other than sections <XRefInternal>109</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>111</XRefInternal>, comes into force on the 60th day after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 4</Label><TitleText>Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Enactment of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment</MarginalNote><Label>113</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal> is enacted as follows:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="yes"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act respecting the provision and registration of information in relation to arrangements entered into with foreign states or powers and their proxies under which persons undertake to carry out certain activities in relation to political or governmental processes in Canada</LongTitle><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canada’s national security is increasingly challenged by foreign states or powers and their proxies;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas interference by foreign states or powers and their proxies has a significant impact on Canada’s international relations and foreign policy;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas efforts by foreign states or powers and their proxies to influence, in a non-transparent manner, political and governmental processes at all levels of government in Canada have systemic effects throughout the country and endanger democracy, sovereignty and core Canadian values;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas efforts by foreign states or powers and their proxies to influence, in a non-transparent manner, political and governmental processes at one level of government in Canada may have effects on the political and governmental processes of another level of government;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas some of those efforts have a particularly negative effect on certain communities in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas there is a growing consensus in Canada and among its allies that foreign influence registries are a necessary tool to lessen foreign interference in the affairs of sovereign states;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas it is desirable that information respecting certain foreign influence activities that are carried out in relation to political or governmental processes in Canada be registered in a way that makes it accessible to the public;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas the registration of that information should not impede freedoms that are vital to Canada’s political culture;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>And whereas it is desirable that an independent public office holder administer and enforce requirements respecting the registration of that information;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>arrangement</DefinedTermEn> means an arrangement under which a person undertakes to carry out, under the direction of or in association with a foreign principal, any of the following activities in relation to a political or governmental process in Canada:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>communicating with a public office holder;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>communicating or disseminating or causing to be communicated or disseminated by any means, including social media, information that is related to the political or governmental process;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>distributing money or items of value or providing a service or the use of a facility. (<DefinedTermFr>arrangement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner appointed under subsection 9(1). (<DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign principal</DefinedTermEn> means a <DefinitionRef>foreign economic entity</DefinitionRef>, a <DefinitionRef>foreign entity</DefinitionRef>, a <DefinitionRef>foreign power</DefinitionRef> or a <DefinitionRef>foreign state</DefinitionRef>, as those expressions are defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>commettant étranger</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> includes a corporation, a trust, a joint venture, a partnership, a fund, an unincorporated association or organization and any other legal entity. (<DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>political or governmental process</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any proceeding of a legislative body;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the development of a legislative proposal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the development or amendment of any policy or program;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the making of a decision by a public office holder or government body, including the awarding of a contract;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the holding of an election or referendum; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the nomination of a candidate or the development of an electoral platform by a political party. (<DefinedTermFr>processus politique ou gouvernemental</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>public office holder</DefinedTermEn> means an individual included in a class of individuals specified in the regulations and, unless they are excluded by the regulations, any of the following individuals:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>public office holder</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lobbying Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an individual referred to in any of paragraphs 4(1)(a) to (c) of that Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an individual referred to in paragraph 4(1)(d) or (d.1) of that Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an officer or employee of an entity referred to in subparagraph 4(c)(ii) of this Act. (<DefinedTermFr>titulaire d’une charge publique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to ensure that persons who, under an arrangement, carry out activities in relation to a political or governmental process in Canada do so in a transparent manner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to deter foreign principals from making efforts to influence political or governmental processes in Canada in a non-transparent manner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to raise public awareness of efforts by foreign principals to influence political or governmental processes in Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>to strengthen national security.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>This Act applies to arrangements relating to any of the following political or governmental processes:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>federal political or governmental processes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provincial, territorial, or municipal political or governmental processes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the political or governmental processes of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any other entity that represents the interests of First Nations, the Inuit or the Métis.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Provision of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to provide information</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who enters into an arrangement with a foreign principal must, within 14 days after the day on which they enter into the arrangement, provide the Commissioner with the information specified in the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to update information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The person must, in accordance with the regulations, also provide the Commissioner with updates on any information they have provided under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Non-application — persons</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 5 does not apply to any of the following persons:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a foreign national who holds a passport that contains a valid diplomatic, consular, official or special representative acceptance issued by the Chief of Protocol for the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an employee of a foreign principal who is acting openly in the employee’s official capacity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person who is included in a class of persons specified in the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application — arrangements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 5 does not apply to any of the following arrangements:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an arrangement to which His Majesty in right of Canada is a party;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an arrangement that is included in a class of arrangements specified in the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — false or misleading information</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>A person must not knowingly provide any false or misleading information to the Commissioner or to any person acting on the Commissioner’s behalf or under the Commissioner’s direction.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Registry</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Duties of Commisioner</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must establish and maintain a registry that contains information provided under section 5 that is included in a class of information specified in the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accessible to public</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The registry must be accessible to the public.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council is to appoint an individual to be known as the Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner, to be responsible for the administration and enforcement of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The appointment is to be made after</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>consultation with</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Leader of the Government in the Senate or Government Representative in the Senate and the Leader of the Opposition in the Senate,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Leader or Facilitator of every other recognized party or parliamentary group in the Senate,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the Leader of the Opposition in the House of Commons, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the leader in the House of Commons of each party having at least 12 members in that House; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>approval of the appointment by resolution of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure of office and removal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, the Commissioner holds office during good behaviour for a term of up to seven years, but may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council at any time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reappointment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner is eligible to be reappointed for one additional term of up to seven years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interim appointment</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Commissioner, or if that office is vacant, the Governor in Council may appoint an individual to hold that office in the interim for a term of up to six months, and that individual is to, while holding office, be paid the remuneration and expenses that may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner is to be paid the remuneration that is fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Travel and living expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner is entitled to be paid, in accordance with Treasury Board directives, reasonable travel and living expenses incurred in the exercise of their powers and the performance of their duties and functions under this Act while absent from their ordinary place of work.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarifications</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Commissioner is an employee for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and is employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deputy Commissioners and staff</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Deputy Commissioners and officers and employees that are necessary to enable the Commissioner to exercise their powers and perform their duties and functions under this Act are to be appointed in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions of Deputy Commissioners</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Deputy Commissioners are to exercise the powers, and perform the duties and functions, that the Commissioner may assign to them.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Technical assistance</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The Commissioner may engage on a temporary basis the services of persons having technical or specialized knowledge of any matter relating to the Commissioner’s work to advise and assist the Commissioner in the exercise of their powers and performance of their duties and functions and, with the approval of the Treasury Board, may fix and pay the remuneration and expenses of those persons.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Advisory opinions and interpretation bulletins</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may issue advisory opinions and interpretation bulletins with respect to the enforcement, interpretation or application of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarifications</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The advisory opinions and interpretation bulletins are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> and are not binding.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>No civil or criminal proceeding lies against the Commissioner, or any person acting on their behalf or under their direction, in respect of anything that is done or omitted to be done in good faith in the course of the exercise or performance, or purported exercise or performance, of any power, duty or function of the Commissioner under this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Confidentiality</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation on disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>With the exception of information in the registry made accessible to the public under section 8, the Commissioner, and any person acting on the Commissioner’s behalf or under the Commissioner’s direction, may not disclose any information that comes to their knowledge in the performance of their duties and functions under this Act, unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the disclosure is, in the opinion of the Commissioner, necessary for the purpose of conducting an investigation under section 16;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the information is disclosed in the course of proceedings for a violation under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the information is disclosed in the course of a prosecution for an offence under section 131 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> (perjury) in respect of a statement made to the Commissioner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the Commissioner believes on reasonable grounds that the disclosure may assist a law enforcement agency in the investigation of an offence under this or any other Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province or territory;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the disclosure is authorized under the regulations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the disclosure is otherwise permitted, authorized or required by law.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Investigations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Power to investigate</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may conduct an investigation for the purpose of ensuring compliance with subsection 5(1) or (2) or section 7.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers on investigation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In conducting an investigation, the Commissioner may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the same manner and to the same extent as a superior court of record,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>summon and enforce the attendance of persons before the Commissioner and compel them to give oral or written evidence on oath or solemn affirmation, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>compel persons to produce any documents or other things that the Commissioner considers relevant for the investigation;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>administer oaths and solemn affirmations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>receive and accept information, whether or not it would be admissible as evidence in a court of law.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Evidence in other proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>Evidence given by a person in an investigation and evidence of the existence of an investigation are inadmissible against the person in a court or in any other proceeding, other than in a proceeding for a violation under this Act or in a prosecution of the person for an offence under section 131 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> (perjury) in respect of a statement made to the Commissioner.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Administrative Monetary Penalties</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Violation and liability</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text> A person who contravenes subsection 5(1) or (2) or section 7 commits a violation and is liable to an administrative monetary penalty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The purpose of an administrative monetary penalty is to promote compliance with this Act and not to punish.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Violation or offence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an act or omission may be proceeded with as a violation or as an offence, proceeding with it in one manner precludes proceeding with it in the other.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of violation</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may issue a notice of violation to a person if the Commissioner has reasonable grounds to believe that the person has committed a violation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The notice of violation must set out</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person’s name;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the violation at issue;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the amount of the administrative monetary penalty to which the person is liable;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the person’s right, within 30 days after the day on which the notice is served or within any longer period that the Commissioner may specify, to pay the penalty or to make representations to the Commissioner with respect to the violation and the penalty, and the manner for doing so; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the fact that, if the person does not pay the penalty or make representations in accordance with the notice, the person will be deemed to have committed the violation and the Commissioner may impose a penalty in respect of it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of penalty</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the person pays the penalty in accordance with the notice of violation, they are deemed to have committed the violation and proceedings in respect of it are ended.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision — commission of violation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the person makes representations in accordance with the notice, the Commissioner must decide, on a balance of probabilities, whether the person committed the violation and, if so, may impose the penalty set out in the notice, a lesser penalty or no penalty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Failure to pay or make representations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who neither pays the penalty nor makes representations in accordance with the notice is deemed to have committed the violation and the Commissioner may impose the penalty set out in the notice, a lesser penalty or no penalty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must cause notice of any decision made under subsection (2) or (3) to be served on the person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must make public the nature of a violation, the name of the person who committed it and the amount of the penalty imposed, if any.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In doing so, the Commissioner may include the reasons for their decision, including the relevant facts, analysis and considerations that formed part of it.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the administrative monetary penalties scheme, including regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount, or range of amounts, of the administrative monetary penalties that may be imposed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the factors to be taken into account in relation to the imposition of an administrative monetary penalty;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>compliance agreements; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the individuals or classes of individuals who may exercise or perform any of the Commissioner’s powers, duties or functions in relation to the scheme, including the designation of such individuals or classes of individuals by the Commissioner.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Contravention — subsection 5(1) or (2) or section 7</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence if they contravene subsection 5(1) or (2) or section 7.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Due diligence defence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person is not to be found guilty of an offence under subsection (1), other than for a contravention of section 7, if they establish that they exercised due diligence to prevent the commission of the offence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Obstruction</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence if they knowingly obstruct the Commissioner, or any person acting on the Commissioner’s behalf or under the Commissioner’s direction, in the conduct of any of the Commissioner’s powers, duties and functions under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Punishment — sections 23 and 24</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under section 23 or 24 is liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $5 million or to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years less a day, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Judicial Review</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Rules</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following rules apply to judicial review proceedings in respect of decisions made by the Commissioner under this Act:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge must provide the applicant and the Commissioner with an opportunity to be heard;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the judge determines that evidence or other information provided by the Commissioner is not relevant or if the Commissioner withdraws evidence or other information, the judge must not base their decision on that evidence or other information and must return it to the Commissioner; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the judge must ensure the confidentiality of all evidence and other information that the Commissioner withdraws.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protection of information on appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies to any appeal of a decision made by a judge in relation to the judicial review proceedings referred to in this section and to any further appeal, with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>judge</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn> means the Chief Justice of the Federal Court or a judge of that Court designated by the Chief Justice.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>specifying classes of individuals for the purposes the definition <DefinitionRef>public office holder</DefinitionRef> in section 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>excluding classes of individuals from that definition;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>specifying the information to be provided for the purposes of section 5;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>respecting the updating of information for the purposes of subsection 5(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>specifying classes of persons for the purposes of paragraph 6(1)(c) and classes of arrangements for the purposes of paragraph 6(2)(b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>specifying the classes of information to be contained in the registry referred to in section 8;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>respecting the retention and disposal by the Commissioner of information contained in the registry referred to in section 8;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>authorizing <DefinitionRef>government institutions</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, or entities specified in the regulations to disclose information to the Commissioner and any other individual referred to in subsection 11(1) for the purposes specified in the regulations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>respecting the disclosure of information for the purposes of paragraph 15(e).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner must, within six months after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the Minister an annual report on the Commissioner’s activities during that year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which the House is sitting after the day on which the Minister receives it.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Special reports</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may, at any time, submit a special report to the Minister on any matter that is within the scope of the Commissioner’s powers, duties and functions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the special report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which the House is sitting after the day on which the Minister receives it.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In preparing an annual or special report, the Commissioner must consult with the deputy heads concerned to ensure that it does not contain information whose disclosure would be injurious to international relations, national defence or national security.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>deputy head</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>deputy head</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review of Act</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>During the first year after a general election, a comprehensive review of this Act and its operation must be undertaken by the committee of the Senate or of the House of Commons that is designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee must, within one year after the review is undertaken — or within any further period that the Senate or the House of Commons, as the case may be, authorizes — submit to the appropriate House a report on the review that includes a statement of any changes that the committee recommends.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Response</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>The Minister must, no later than 120 days after the day on which the report referred to in subsection 31(2) is submitted, cause to be tabled in each House of Parliament a response that addresses each of the changes recommended in the report.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Existing arrangements — federal processes</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Text>If, before the day on which paragraph 4(a) comes into force, a person has entered into an arrangement with a foreign principal in relation to a process referred to in that paragraph and the arrangement is in force on that day, then subsection 5(1) applies to the person but the required information must be provided within 60 days after that day.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Existing arrangements — provincial, territorial or municipal processes</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Text>If, before the day on which paragraph 4(b) comes into force, a person has entered into an arrangement with a foreign principal in relation to a process referred to in that paragraph and the arrangement is in force on that day, then subsection 5(1) applies to the person but the required information must be provided within 60 days after that day.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Existing arrangements — Indigenous processes</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Text>If, before the day on which paragraph 4(c) comes into force, a person has entered into an arrangement with a foreign principal in relation to a process referred to in that paragraph and the arrangement is in force on that day, then subsection 5(1) applies to the person but the required information must be provided within 60 days after that day.</Text></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-36</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Service Superannuation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>114</Label><Text>Part II of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn> Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commissaire à la transparence en matière d’influence étrangère</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>115</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>department</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Committee of Parliamentarians Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>department</DefinedTermEn> means, except in subsection 25(2), a department named in Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, a division or branch of the federal public administration — other than a review body or the office of the Intelligence Commissioner — set out in column I of Schedule I.1 to that Act, a corporation named in Schedule II to that Act, a <DefinitionRef>parent Crown corporation</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 83(1) of that Act, the Canadian Forces or the Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner appointed under subsection 9(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>ministère</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>appropriate Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (c.1), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (d) and by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>with respect to the Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner appointed under subsection 9(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre compétent</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 13, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>116</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>department</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Security and Intelligence Review Agency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>department</DefinedTermEn> means, other than in subsection 42(2), a department named in Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, a division or branch of the federal public administration — other than a review body and the office of the Intelligence Commissioner — set out in column I of Schedule I.1 to that Act, a corporation named in Schedule II to that Act, a <DefinitionRef>parent Crown corporation</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 83(1) of that Act, the Canadian Forces or the Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner appointed under subsection 9(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>ministère</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>appropriate Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (d), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (e) and by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>with respect to the Foreign Influence Transparency Commissioner appointed under subsection 9(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre compétent</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>117</Label><Subsection type="CIF"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3), this Part comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (b) of the definition <DefinitionRef>public office holder</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>113</XRefInternal>, and paragraph 4(b) of that Act come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council, but that day must not be before the day referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (c) and (d) of the definition <DefinitionRef>public office holder</DefinitionRef> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>113</XRefInternal>, and paragraph 4(c) of that Act come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council, but that day must not be before the day referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no" type="amending"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><Label>SCHEDULE 1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 46)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><AmendedText><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 20.3(2))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Application to Obtain a Preservation Order</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="right-align" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">(Court File No.)</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>FEDERAL COURT</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>IN THE MATTER OF an application by (<Emphasis style="italic">Name</Emphasis>) for a preservation order under section (<Emphasis style="italic">12 or 16</Emphasis>) and subsection 20.3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1985, c. C-23</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND IN THE MATTER OF (<Emphasis style="italic">Subject</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" hyphenation="no" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This is the information of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of Director or designated employee</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc"/> (“the applicant”).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The applicant says that they have reasonable grounds to suspect that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record, document or thing</Emphasis>) is in the possession or control of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person or entity</Emphasis>) and will assist the Canadian Security Intelligence Service to investigate, within or outside Canada, a threat to the security of Canada or to perform its duties and functions under section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The applicant says that the order is necessary to prevent the loss or destruction or ensure the preservation of the information, record, document or thing.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The applicant also says that the Director or a designated employee of the Service intends to apply or has applied for a production order under section 20.4 of that Act or a warrant under section 21 or 22.21 of that Act to obtain the (<Emphasis style="italic">information, record, document or thing</Emphasis>) or under section 23 of that Act to remove a thing.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The reasonable grounds are:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The applicant therefore requests that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person or entity</Emphasis>) be ordered to preserve the (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record, document or thing</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they receive the order for 90 days after the day on which the order is made.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sworn before me on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of applicant</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of commissioner for taking oaths</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 2</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 20.3(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Preservation Order</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="right-align" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">(Court File No.)</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>FEDERAL COURT</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>IN THE MATTER OF an application by (<Emphasis style="italic">Name</Emphasis>) for a preservation order under section (<Emphasis style="italic">12 or 16</Emphasis>) and subsection 20.3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1985, c. C-23</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND IN THE MATTER OF (<Emphasis style="italic">Subject</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person or entity</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc"/>:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas I am satisfied by information on oath of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of Director or designated employee</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc"/>,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record, document or thing</Emphasis>) is in your possession or control and will assist the Canadian Security Intelligence Service to investigate, within or outside Canada, a threat to the security of Canada or to perform its duties and functions under section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that the order is necessary to prevent the loss or destruction or ensure the preservation of the information, record, document or thing; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that the Director or a designated employee of the Service intends to apply or has applied for a production order under section 20.4 of that Act or a warrant under section 21 or 22.21 of that Act to obtain the (<Emphasis style="italic">information, record, document or thing</Emphasis>) or under section 23 of that Act to remove a thing.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, you are required to preserve the (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record, document or thing</Emphasis>) that is in your possession or control when you receive this order until (<Emphasis style="italic">insert date</Emphasis>) unless, before that date, the (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record, document or thing</Emphasis>) is obtained under a production order made under section 20.4 of that Act or a warrant issued under section 21 or 22.21 of that Act or a thing is removed in accordance with a warrant issued under 23 of that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You are required to destroy the (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record, document or thing</Emphasis>) that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business, (<Emphasis style="italic">and, if applicable,</Emphasis> and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving the information, record, document or thing) in accordance with section 20.8 of that Act. If you contravene that provision without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of judge</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 3</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 20.4(2))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Application to Obtain a Production Order</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="right-align" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">(Court File No.)</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>FEDERAL COURT</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>IN THE MATTER OF an application by (<Emphasis style="italic">Name</Emphasis>) for a production order under section (<Emphasis style="italic">12 or 16</Emphasis>) and subsection 20.4(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1985, c. C-23</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND IN THE MATTER OF (<Emphasis style="italic">Subject</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" hyphenation="no" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This is the information of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of Director or designated employee</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc"/> (“the applicant”).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The applicant says that they have reasonable grounds to believe that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record or document</Emphasis>) is in the possession or control of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person or entity</Emphasis>) and that it will assist the Canadian Security Intelligence Service to investigate, within or outside Canada, a threat to the security of Canada or to perform its duties and functions under section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The applicant says that they have obtained the approval of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness to make this application.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The reasonable grounds are:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The applicant therefore requests that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person or entity</Emphasis>) be ordered to produce (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record or document</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they receive the order.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sworn before me on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of applicant</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of commissioner for taking oaths</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 4</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 20.4(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Production Order</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="right-align" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">(Court File No.)</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>FEDERAL COURT</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>IN THE MATTER OF an application by (<Emphasis style="italic">Name</Emphasis>) for a production order under section (<Emphasis style="italic">12 or 16</Emphasis>) and subsection 20.4(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1985, c. C-23</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND IN THE MATTER OF (<Emphasis style="italic">Subject</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person or entity</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc"/>:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas I am satisfied by information on oath of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of Director or designated employee</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc"/>, that there are reasonable grounds to believe that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record or document</Emphasis>) is in your possession or control and that it will assist the Canadian Security Intelligence Service to investigate, within or outside Canada, a threat to the security of Canada or to perform its duties and functions under section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, you are ordered to produce (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record or document</Emphasis>) that is in your possession or control when you receive this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the information, record or document</Emphasis>) must be produced to the Director or an employee of the Service in accordance with that person’s instructions, within (<Emphasis style="italic">time</Emphasis>) and in (<Emphasis style="italic">form</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You have the right to apply to revoke or vary this order in accordance with section 20.5 of that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of judge</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 20.5(2))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Notice — Application for Revocation or Variation of a Production Order</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="right-align" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">(Court File No. — to match Production Order)</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>FEDERAL COURT</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>IN THE MATTER OF an application by (<Emphasis style="italic">Name</Emphasis>) for the revocation or variation of a production order under section 20.5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.C. 1985, c. C-23</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>NOTICE</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This is a notice that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person or entity named in the order</Emphasis>) (“the applicant”) intends to apply to the Federal Court for the revocation or variation of the production order made on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>) and served on the applicant on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>A copy of this notice has been provided to an employee of the Canadian Security Intelligence Service on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The applicant intends to file the application for revocation or variation on or before (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), the date by which the applicant must comply with the production order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of applicant</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></FormGroup></Schedule></AmendedText></Schedule><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no" type="amending"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section <XRefInternal>56</XRefInternal>)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><AmendedText><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 8(1) and section 9.1)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading></Schedule></AmendedText></Schedule></Bill><?Pub *0000276828?>