<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" date-time="2021-02-11 07:36:44" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-244</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2-3 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023-2024</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Copyright Act (diagnosis, maintenance and repair)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Copyright Act (diagnosis, maintenance and repair)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Copyright Act (diagnosis, maintenance and repair)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>7</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>26</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2024</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-02-11">441129</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Copyright Act</XRefExternal> in order to allow the circumvention of a technological protection measure if the circumvention is solely for the purpose of the diagnosis, maintenance or repair of certain types of products.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-42</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Copyright Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>circumvent</DefinitionRef> in section 41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Copyright Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in respect of a technological protection measure within the meaning of paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>technological protection measure</DefinitionRef>, to descramble a scrambled work or computer program, or decrypt an encrypted work or computer program or to otherwise avoid, bypass, remove, deactivate or impair the technological protection measure, unless it is done with the authority of the copyright owner; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinitionRef>technological protection measure</DefinitionRef> in section 41 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>controls access to a work, including a computer program, to a performer’s performance fixed in a sound recording or to a sound recording and whose use is authorized by the copyright owner;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 41.12:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Diagnosis, maintenance and repair</MarginalNote><Label>41.121</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 41.1(1)(a) does not apply to a person who circumvents a technological protection measure for the sole purpose of maintaining or repairing a product, including any related diagnosing, if the work, performer’s performance fixed in a sound recording or sound recording to which the technological protection measure controls access forms a part of the product.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsection (1) applies to a person who circumvents a technological protection measure in the circumstances referred to in that subsection for another person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person acting in the circumstances referred to in subsection (1) is not entitled to benefit from the exception under that subsection if the person does an act that constitutes an infringement of copyright.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>