<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-48</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><?Pub Caret1?><Year-s>59-60</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010-2011</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and to make consequential amendments to the National Defence Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Protecting Canadians by Ending Sentence Discounts for Multiple Murders Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2011</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>5</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2011</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-10-4">90541</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> with respect to the parole inadmissibility period for offenders convicted of multiple murders. It also makes consequential amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Protecting Canadians by Ending Sentence Discounts for Multiple Murders Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 675 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2.2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal against s. 745.51(1) order</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>A person against whom an order under subsection 745.51(1) has been made may appeal to the court of appeal against the order.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Section 676 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal against decision not to make s. 745.51(1) order</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Attorney General or counsel instructed by the Attorney General for the purpose may appeal to the court of appeal against the decision of the court not to make an order under subsection 745.51(1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 745.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Recommendation by jury — multiple murders</MarginalNote><Label>745.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a jury finds an accused guilty of murder and that accused has previously been convicted of murder, the judge presiding at the trial shall, before discharging the jury, put to them the following question:</Text><Oath>You have found the accused guilty of murder. The law requires that I now pronounce a sentence of imprisonment for life against the accused. Do you wish to make any recommendation with respect to the period without eligibility for parole to be served for this murder consecutively to the period without eligibility for parole imposed for the previous murder? You are not required to make any recommendation, but if you do, your recommendation will be considered by me when I make my determination.</Oath></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies to an offender who is convicted of murders committed on a day after the day on which this section comes into force and for which the offender is sentenced under this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Crimes Against Humanity and War Crimes Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 745.5:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Ineligibility for parole — multiple murders</MarginalNote><Label>745.51</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the time of the sentencing under section 745 of an offender who is convicted of murder and who has already been convicted of one or more other murders, the judge who presided at the trial of the offender or, if that judge is unable to do so, any judge of the same court may, having regard to the character of the offender, the nature of the offence and the circumstances surrounding its commission, and the recommendation, if any, made pursuant to section 745.21, by order, decide that the periods without eligibility for parole for each murder conviction are to be served consecutively.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The judge shall give, either orally or in writing, reasons for the decision to make or not to make an order under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) apply to an offender who is convicted of murders committed on a day after the day on which this section comes into force and for which the offender is sentenced under this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Crimes Against Humanity and War Crimes Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. N-5</MarginalNote><TitleText>NATIONAL DEFENCE ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 35, s. 36</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Paragraph 140.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a reference in sections 745.2 to 745.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to a jury is deemed to be a reference to the panel of a General Court Martial; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Section 149 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Concurrent punishment</MarginalNote><Label>149.</Label><Text>Where a person is under a sentence imposed by a service tribunal that includes a punishment involving incarceration and another service tribunal subsequently passes a new sentence that also includes a punishment involving incarceration, both punishments of incarceration shall, subject to section 745.51 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, after the date of the pronouncement of the new sentence, run concurrently but the punishment higher in the scale of punishments shall be served first.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Section 230 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the decision to make an order under subsection 745.51(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Section 230.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the decision not to make an order under subsection 745.51(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-41</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill C-41, introduced in the 3rd session of the 40th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Military Justice in the Defence of Canada Act</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 68 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Paragraph 226.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a reference in sections 745.2 to 745.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to a jury shall be read as a reference to the panel of a General Court Martial; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 68 of the other Act, then, on the day on which that section 68 comes into force, paragraph 226.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a reference in sections 745.2 to 745.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to a jury shall be read as a reference to the panel of a General Court Martial; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 68 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> is deemed to have come into force before that section 68 and subsection (3) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>This Act, other than section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal>, comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>