<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-30</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59-60</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010-2011</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official"><?Pub Caret?>Response to the Supreme Court of Canada Decision in R. v. Shoker Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2011</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>7</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2011</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-5-28">90535</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to allow a court to require that an offender or defendant provide a sample of a bodily substance on the demand of peace officers, probation officers, supervisors or designated persons, or at regular intervals, in order to enforce compliance with a prohibition on consuming drugs or alcohol imposed in a probation order, a conditional sentence order or a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 of that Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ALTERNATIVE TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Alternative title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Response to the Supreme Court of Canada Decision in R. v. Shoker Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 729:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Proof of certificate of analyst — bodily substance</MarginalNote><Label>729.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In a prosecution for failure to comply with a condition in a probation order that the accused not consume drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance, or in a hearing to determine whether the offender breached such a condition of a conditional sentence order, a certificate purporting to be signed by an analyst that states that the analyst has analyzed a sample of a bodily substance and that states the result of the analysis is admissible in evidence and, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, is proof of the statements contained in the certificate without proof of the signature or official character of the person who appears to have signed the certificate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>analyst</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>analyst</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 254(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of intention to produce certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No certificate shall be admitted in evidence unless the party intending to produce it has, before the trial or hearing, as the case may be, given reasonable notice and a copy of the certificate to the party against whom it is to be produced.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requiring attendance of analyst</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The party against whom a certificate of an analyst is produced may, with leave of the court, require the attendance of the analyst for cross-examination.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 22, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 732.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>abstain from the consumption of drugs except in accordance with a medical prescription, of alcohol or of any other intoxicating substance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation on the demand of a peace officer, a probation officer or someone designated under subsection (9) to make a demand, at the place and time and on the day specified by the person making the demand, if that person has reasonable grounds to believe that the offender has breached a condition of the order that requires them to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation at regular intervals that are specified by a probation officer in a notice in Form 51 served on the offender, if a condition of the order requires the offender to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 732.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice — samples at regular intervals</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The notice referred to in paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.2</Emphasis>) must specify the places and times at which and the days on which the offender must provide samples of a bodily substance under a condition described in that paragraph. The first sample may not be taken earlier than 24 hours after the offender is served with the notice, and subsequent samples must be taken at regular intervals of at least seven days.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designations and specifications</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraphs (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c.2</Emphasis>) and subject to the regulations, the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory shall, with respect to the province or territory,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may take samples of bodily substances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the places or classes of places at which the samples are to be taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be analyzed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be stored, handled and destroyed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the records of the results of the analysis of the samples are to be protected and destroyed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may destroy the samples; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may destroy the records of the results of the analysis of the samples.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further designations</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>For the purpose of paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) and subject to the regulations, the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory may, with respect to the province or territory, designate persons or classes of persons to make a demand for a sample of a bodily substance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Samples of bodily substances referred to in paragraphs (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c.2</Emphasis>) may not be taken, analyzed, stored, handled or destroyed, and the records of the results of the analysis of the samples may not be protected or destroyed, except in accordance with the designations and specifications made under subsection (8).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of samples</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory, or a person authorized by the Attorney General or minister, shall cause all samples of bodily substances provided under a probation order to be destroyed within the periods prescribed by regulation unless the samples are reasonably expected to be used as evidence in a proceeding for an offence under section 733.1.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing bodily substances for the purposes of paragraphs (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c.2</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the designations and specifications referred to in subsections (8) and (9);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the periods within which samples of bodily substances are to be destroyed under subsection (11); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting any other matters relating to the samples of bodily substances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 732.1:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition on use of bodily substance</MarginalNote><Label>732.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall use a bodily substance provided under a probation order except for the purpose of determining whether an offender is complying with a condition of the order that they abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition on use or disclosure of result</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), no person shall use, disclose or allow the disclosure of the results of the analysis of a bodily substance provided under a probation order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The results of the analysis of a bodily substance provided under a probation order may be disclosed to the offender to whom they relate, and may also be used or disclosed in the course of an investigation of, or in a proceeding for, an offence under section 733.1 or, if the results are made anonymous, for statistical or other research purposes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (1) or (2) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 22, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 742.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>abstain from the consumption of drugs except in accordance with a medical prescription, of alcohol or of any other intoxicating substance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation on the demand of a peace officer, the supervisor or someone designated under subsection (7) to make a demand, at the place and time and on the day specified by the person making the demand, if that person has reasonable grounds to suspect that the offender has breached a condition of the order that requires them to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation at regular intervals that are specified by the supervisor in a notice in Form 51 served on the offender, if a condition of the order requires the offender to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 742.3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice — samples at regular intervals</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The notice referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>) must specify the places and times at which and the days on which the offender must provide samples of a bodily substance under a condition described in that paragraph. The first sample may not be taken earlier than 24 hours after the offender is served with the notice, and subsequent samples must be taken at regular intervals of at least seven days.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designations and specifications</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>) and subject to the regulations, the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory shall, with respect to the province or territory,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may take samples of bodily substances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the places or classes of places at which the samples are to be taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be analyzed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be stored, handled and destroyed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the records of the results of the analysis of the samples are to be protected and destroyed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may destroy the samples; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may destroy the records of the results of the analysis of the samples.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further designations</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>For the purpose of paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) and subject to the regulations, the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory may, with respect to the province or territory, designate persons or classes of persons to make a demand for a sample of a bodily substance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Samples of bodily substances referred to in paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>) may not be taken, analyzed, stored, handled or destroyed, and the records of the results of the analysis of the samples may not be protected or destroyed, except in accordance with the designations and specifications made under subsection (6).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of samples</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory, or a person authorized by the Attorney General or minister, shall cause all samples of bodily substances provided under a conditional sentence order to be destroyed within the periods prescribed by regulation, unless the samples are reasonably expected to be used as evidence in proceedings under section 742.6.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing bodily substances for the purposes of paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the designations and specifications referred to in subsections (6) and (7);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the periods within which samples of bodily substances are to be destroyed under subsection (9); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting any other matters relating to the samples of bodily substances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 742.3:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition on use of bodily substance</MarginalNote><Label>742.31</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall use a bodily substance provided under a conditional sentence order except for the purpose of determining whether an offender is complying with a condition of the order that they abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition on use or disclosure of result</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), no person shall use, disclose or allow the disclosure of the results of the analysis of a bodily substance provided under a conditional sentence order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The results of the analysis of a bodily substance provided under a conditional sentence order may be disclosed to the offender to whom they relate, and may also be used or disclosed in the course of proceedings under section 742.6 or, if the results are made anonymous, for statistical or other research purposes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (1) or (2) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 44, s. 81(2)</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 810(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Adjudication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the justice or summary conviction court before which the parties appear is satisfied by the evidence adduced that the person on whose behalf the information was laid has reasonable grounds for the fear, the justice or court may order that the defendant enter into a recognizance, with or without sureties, to keep the peace and be of good behaviour for a period of not more than 12 months.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Refusal to enter into recognizance</MarginalNote><Label>(3.01)</Label><Text>The justice or summary conviction court may commit the defendant to prison for a term of not more than 12 months if the defendant fails or refuses to enter into the recognizance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions in recognizance</MarginalNote><Label>(3.02)</Label><Text>The justice or summary conviction court may add any reasonable conditions to the recognizance that the justice or court considers desirable to secure the good conduct of the defendant, including conditions that require the defendant</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to abstain from the consumption of drugs except in accordance with a medical prescription, of alcohol or of any other intoxicating substance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation on the demand of a peace officer, a probation officer or someone designated under paragraph 810.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to make a demand, at the place and time and on the day specified by the person making the demand, if that person has reasonable grounds to believe that the defendant has breached a condition of the recognizance that requires them to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation at regular intervals that are specified, in a notice in Form 51 served on the defendant, by a probation officer or a person designated under paragraph 810.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to specify them, if a condition of the recognizance requires the defendant to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 810(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forms</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A recognizance and a committal to prison in default of recognizance may be in Forms 32 and 23, respectively.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 22, s. 19(1)</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 810.01(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Décision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Le juge devant lequel les parties comparaissent peut, s’il est convaincu par la preuve apportée que les craintes du dénonciateur sont fondées sur des motifs raisonnables, ordonner que le défendeur contracte l’engagement de ne pas troubler l’ordre public et d’avoir une bonne conduite pour une période maximale de douze mois.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 22, s. 19(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 810.01(4.1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions in recognizance</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>The provincial court judge may add any reasonable conditions to the recognizance that the judge considers desirable for preventing the commission of an offence referred to in subsection (1), including conditions that require the defendant</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 810.01(4.1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation on the demand of a peace officer, a probation officer or someone designated under paragraph 810.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to make a demand, at the place and time and on the day specified by the person making the demand, if that person has reasonable grounds to believe that the defendant has breached a condition of the recognizance that requires them to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation at regular intervals that are specified, in a notice in Form 51 served on the defendant, by a probation officer or a person designated under paragraph 810.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to specify them, if a condition of the recognizance requires the defendant to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Subsection 810.1(3.02) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require the defendant to provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation on the demand of a peace officer, a probation officer or someone designated under paragraph 810.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to make a demand, at the place and time and on the day specified by the person making the demand, if that person has reasonable grounds to believe that the defendant has breached a condition of the recognizance that requires them to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require the defendant to provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation at regular intervals that are specified, in a notice in Form 51 served on the defendant, by a probation officer or a person designated under paragraph 810.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to specify them, if a condition of the recognizance requires the defendant to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>Subsection 810.2(4.1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation on the demand of a peace officer, a probation officer or someone designated under paragraph 810.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to make a demand, at the place and time and on the day specified by the person making the demand, if that person has reasonable grounds to believe that the defendant has breached a condition of the recognizance that requires them to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to provide, for the purpose of analysis, a sample of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation at regular intervals that are specified, in a notice in Form 51 served on the defendant, by a probation officer or a person designated under paragraph 810.3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to specify them, if a condition of the recognizance requires the defendant to abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 810.2:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Samples — designations and specifications</MarginalNote><Label>810.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 810, 810.01, 810.1 and 810.2 and subject to the regulations, the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory shall, with respect to the province or territory,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may take samples of bodily substances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the places or classes of places at which the samples are to be taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be analyzed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the samples are to be stored, handled and destroyed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which the records of the results of the analysis of the samples are to be protected and destroyed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may destroy the samples; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate the persons or classes of persons that may destroy the records of the results of the analysis of the samples.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further designations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory may, with respect to the province or territory, designate the persons or classes of persons</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to make a demand for a sample of a bodily substance for the purposes of paragraphs 810(3.02)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), 810.01(4.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>), 810.1(3.02)(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) and 810.2(4.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to specify the regular intervals at which a defendant must provide a sample of a bodily substance for the purposes of paragraphs 810(3.02)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), 810.01(4.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), 810.1(3.02)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) and 810.2(4.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Samples of bodily substances referred to in sections 810, 810.01, 810.1 and 810.2 may not be taken, analyzed, stored, handled or destroyed, and the records of the results of the analysis of the samples may not be protected or destroyed, except in accordance with the designations and specifications made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of samples</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory, or a person authorized by the Attorney General or minister, shall cause all samples of bodily substances provided under a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 to be destroyed within the period prescribed by regulation unless the samples are reasonably expected to be used as evidence in a proceeding for an offence under section 811.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing bodily substances for the purposes of sections 810, 810.01, 810.1 and 810.2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the designations and specifications referred to in subsections (1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the periods within which samples of bodily substances are to be destroyed under subsection (4); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting any other matters relating to the samples of bodily substances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice — samples at regular intervals</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The notice referred to in paragraph 810(3.02)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), 810.01(4.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), 810.1(3.02)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) or 810.2(4.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) must specify the places and times at which and the days on which the defendant must provide samples of a bodily substance under a condition described in that paragraph. The first sample may not be taken earlier than 24 hours after the defendant is served with the notice, and subsequent samples must be taken at regular intervals of at least seven days.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition on use of bodily substance</MarginalNote><Label>810.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall use a bodily substance provided under a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 except for the purpose of determining whether a defendant is complying with a condition in the recognizance that they abstain from the consumption of drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition on use or disclosure of result</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), no person shall use, disclose or allow the disclosure of the results of the analysis of a bodily substance provided under a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The results of the analysis of a bodily substance provided under a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 may be disclosed to the defendant to whom they relate, and may also be used or disclosed in the course of an investigation of, or in a proceeding for, an offence under section 811 or, if the results are made anonymous, for statistical or other research purposes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (1) or (2) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 811:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Proof of certificate of analyst — bodily substance</MarginalNote><Label>811.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In a prosecution for breach of a condition in a recognizance under section 810, 810.01, 810.1 or 810.2 that a defendant not consume drugs, alcohol or any other intoxicating substance, a certificate purporting to be signed by an analyst that states that the analyst has analyzed a sample of a bodily substance and that states the result of the analysis is admissible in evidence and, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, is proof of the statements contained in the certificate without proof of the signature or official character of the person who appears to have signed the certificate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>analyst</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>analyst</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 254(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of intention to produce certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No certificate shall be admitted in evidence unless the party intending to produce it has, before the trial, given reasonable notice and a copy of the certificate to the party against whom it is to be produced.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requiring attendance of analyst</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The party against whom a certificate of an analyst is produced may, with leave of the court, require the attendance of the analyst for cross-examination.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by adding the following after Form 50:</Text><AmendedText><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 51</Label><OriginatingRef>(Paragraphs 732.1(3)(c.2), 742.3(2)(a.2), 810(3.02)(c), 810.01(4.1)(g), 810.1(3.02)(i) and 810,2(4.1)(g))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>NOTICE OF OBLIGATION TO PROVIDE SAMPLES OF BODILY SUBSTANCE</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>To A.B., of ................, (<Emphasis style="italic">occupation</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">address in Canada</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">date of birth</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">gender</Emphasis>):</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Because, on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), you were ordered, under (<Emphasis style="italic">applicable provision</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, to provide samples of a bodily substance prescribed by regulation at regular intervals for the purpose of analysis;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>You are provided with this notice to inform you of your obligations with respect to providing samples.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>1. On (<Emphasis style="italic">specify a day not earlier than 24 hours after the day on which the notice is served</Emphasis>), you must report, at any time from (<Emphasis style="italic">time</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">time</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">address of place at which sample to be taken, as designated by the Attorney General of the province or Minister of Justice of the territory</Emphasis>), to provide a sample of your (<Emphasis style="italic">specify type of bodily substance prescribed by regulation</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>2. Every (<Emphasis style="italic">specify a number not less than seven</Emphasis>) days after you first report to provide a sample, you must report, at any time from (<Emphasis style="italic">time</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">time</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">address of place at which sample to be taken, as designated by the Attorney General of the province or Minister of Justice of the territory</Emphasis>), to provide a sample of your (<Emphasis style="italic">specify type of bodily substance prescribed by regulation</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>3. You have the right to apply to a court to terminate the obligation to provide samples, and the right to appeal any decision of that court.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>4. If you are found to have not complied with your obligation to provide samples as set out in this notice, you may be subject to a fine or imprisonment, or to both (<Emphasis style="italic">or, in the case of a conditional sentence,</Emphasis> you may be subject to proceedings under section 742.6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the consequences of which may include imprisonment).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>5. The results of the analysis of the bodily substances may be used or disclosed in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, including in proceedings against you, the result of which may be that you are subject to a fine or imprisonment, or to both (<Emphasis style="italic">or, in the case of a conditional sentence,</Emphasis> including in proceedings under section 742.6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the consequences of which may include imprisonment).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Served on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place the notice is served</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" topmarginspacing="20"><Text>..................................................</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of probation officer, supervisor or person designated by the Attorney General or Minister of Justice, as the case may be</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>