<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-18</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>60</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2011</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to reorganize the Canadian Wheat Board and to make consequential and related amendments to certain Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Marketing Freedom for Grain Farmers Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canadian Wheat Board</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2011</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>25</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2011</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2011-10-17">90627</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 of this enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> to change the governance structure of the Canadian Wheat Board and to make other changes in preparation for the implementation of Parts 2 and 3. Part 2 replaces the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> with a new Act that continues the Canadian Wheat Board and charges it with the marketing of grain through voluntary pooling. Part 3 provides for the possible continuation of the Board under other federal legislation, while Part 4 provides for its winding up if no such continuation occurs. Finally, Part 5 provides for the repeal of the new Act enacted by Part 2.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marketing Freedom for Grain Farmers Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>OPERATIONS OF THE CANADIAN WHEAT BOARD DURING PRELIMINARY PERIOD</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-24</MarginalNote><TitleText>Amendments to the Canadian Wheat Board Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Subsection 3.01(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Composition of the board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The board consists of five directors, including a chairperson and a president.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 3.02(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Directors</MarginalNote><Label>3.02</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Four directors are appointed by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Minister. The president is appointed by the Governor in Council in accordance with section 3.09.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 3.02(4) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 3.04(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence ou empêchement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>En cas d’absence ou d’empêchement du président du conseil, le conseil peut désigner l’un des administrateurs pour assurer l’intérim.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>Paragraph 3.05(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The heading before section 3.06 and sections 3.06 to 3.08 of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Section 3.12 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed best interests</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Any act taken by a director or officer of the Corporation for the purpose of facilitating the implementation of Part 2 or 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marketing Freedom for Grain Farmers Act</XRefExternal> is deemed to be in the best interests of the Corporation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Section 3.13 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advance of costs</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Corporation may advance moneys to any individual referred to in subsection (1) for the costs, charges and expenses of an action or proceeding referred to in that subsection unless there are reasonable grounds to believe that the individual does not fulfil the conditions set out in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>). The individual must repay the moneys if he or she does not fulfil those conditions.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>Subsection 4(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Status</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Corporation is not an agent of Her Majesty and, despite Part X of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, is not a Crown corporation within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>. The directors, officers, clerks and employees of the Corporation are not part of the federal public administration.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.1</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 18:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>18.1</Label><Text>Despite subsection 18(2), the Corporation may agree to buy or sell grain if the agreement provides for purchase or sale to occur on or after the day on which Part 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marketing Freedom for Grain Farmers Act</XRefExternal> comes into force.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 19(2)</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 33(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i.2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 28(E)</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 45(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 45 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 45(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), a person may agree to sell or buy wheat or wheat products if the agreement provides for the sale or purchase to occur on or after the day on which Part 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marketing Freedom for Grain Farmers Act</XRefExternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Directors</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>Every person holding office as an elected director of the Canadian Wheat Board immediately before the day on which this Part comes into force ceases to hold office on that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Election of directors</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In respect of the pool period during which this Part comes into force, the costs of an election of directors of the Corporation that have been incurred but not deducted before this Part comes into force are to be deducted in accordance with subsection 33(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> as it read on the day before the day on which this Part comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definition</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In subsection (1), <DefinedTermEn>pool period</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>VOLUNTARY POOLING</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Enactment of Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal> is enacted as follows:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act to provide for the constitution and powers of The Canadian Wheat Board responsible for the marketing of grain</LongTitle><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>bank</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>banque</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>bank</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a bank or an authorized foreign bank within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a credit union, caisse populaire or other cooperative credit society that is designated by the Minister on the application of that society as a bank for the purposes of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a company within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal>, or a company, society or provincial company within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal>, that is designated by the Minister on the application of that company, society or provincial company as a bank for the purposes of this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a Province of Alberta Treasury Branch established under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">The Treasury Branches Act</XRefExternal> as enacted by the Legislature of the Province of Alberta.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>board</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>conseil</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>board</DefinedTermEn> means the board of directors of the Corporation.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Corporation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Commission</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Corporation</DefinedTermEn> means The Canadian Wheat Board continued by subsection 4(1).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>elevator</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>silo</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>elevator</DefinedTermEn> means a grain elevator, warehouse or mill that has been declared by Parliament to be a work for the general advantage of Canada.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>pooling point</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>point de mise en commun</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>pooling point</DefinedTermEn> means a place designated under subsection (3).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>producer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>producteur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>producer</DefinedTermEn> means a person actually engaged in the production of grain and any person entitled, as landlord, vendor or mortgagee or hypothecary creditor, to grain produced by a person actually engaged in the production of grain or to any share of that grain.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Words and expressions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless it is otherwise provided in this Act, words and expressions used in this Act have the same meaning as in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Grain Act</XRefExternal>, except that when in any definition of any such word or expression contained in that Act the word “elevator” is used, it has the meaning given to it under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designating pooling points</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by regulation, designate any place in Canada as a pooling point for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>HER MAJESTY</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Binding on Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>This Act is binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>THE CANADIAN WHEAT BOARD</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Continuation of the Corporation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Corporation continued</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Canadian Wheat Board continued by subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> is continued as a corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Headquarters</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The headquarters of the Corporation are in the city of Winnipeg in Manitoba.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Status, Object and Powers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Status</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Corporation is not an agent of Her Majesty and, despite Part X of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, is not a Crown corporation within the meaning of that Act. The directors, officers, clerks and employees of the Corporation are not part of the federal public administration.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Object</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The object of the Corporation is to market grain for the benefit of producers who choose to deal with the Corporation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The Corporation possesses the following powers:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to buy, take delivery of, store, transfer, sell, ship or otherwise dispose of grain;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to enter into contracts or agreements for the purchase, sale, handling, storage, transportation, disposition or insurance of grain;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to the approval of the Minister of Finance, to enter into commercial banking arrangements;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to section 26, to borrow money by any means, including the issuing, reissuing, selling and pledging of bonds, debentures, notes and other evidences of indebtedness of the Corporation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to the approval of the Minister of Finance, to invest moneys of the Corporation in bonds, debentures, notes or other evidences of indebtedness of or guaranteed by</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Government of Canada or the government of any province of Canada,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the government of a foreign country or of any province or state of that country, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a financial institution whether in or outside Canada;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the course of its operations, to enter into and deal with any contracts and transactions that the Corporation considers necessary for risk management purposes, including options, futures contracts, forward contracts and currency, commodity and interest rate swaps;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to issue negotiable certificates in accordance with this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to acquire, hold and dispose of real and personal property or immovables and movables, but the Corporation is not authorized to acquire or dispose of any real property or immovables without the approval of the Governor in Council;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to employ any technical, professional or other officers, clerks or employees that may be necessary for the conduct of its business;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to establish branches or employ agents or mandataries in Canada or elsewhere;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to establish, utilize and employ any marketing agencies or facilities that it considers necessary for the purpose of its operations under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to operate elevators, either directly or by means of agents or mandataries, and, subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Grain Act</XRefExternal>, to pay those agents or mandataries, commissions, storage and other charges, remuneration or compensation as may be agreed on with the approval of the Canadian Grain Commission;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to authorize any officer, clerk or employee of the Corporation or any other person to act on behalf of the Corporation in the conduct of its operations under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to act as agent for or on behalf of any minister or agent of Her Majesty in right of Canada in respect of any operations that it may be directed to carry out by the Governor in Council; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>generally to do any acts and things that may be necessary or incidental to carrying on its operations under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Board of Directors</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Board of directors</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>The board of directors is to direct and manage the business and affairs of the Corporation and is for those purposes vested with all the powers of the Corporation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Composition of the board</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The board consists of five directors, including a chairperson and a president.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Four directors are appointed by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Minister. The president is appointed by the Governor in Council in accordance with section 13.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Term</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The directors, with the exception of the president, hold office for a maximum term of four years, up to a maximum of three terms.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Part-time directors</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Unless the Governor in Council directs otherwise, the directors, with the exception of the president, must perform their functions on a part-time basis.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The directors are paid the remuneration that is fixed by the board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Travel and living expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The directors, with the exception of the president, are entitled to be paid reasonable travel and living expenses incurred by them in the course of their duties under this Act while absent from their ordinary place of residence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The board is to designate one director to be the chairperson and to fix the remuneration of the chairperson.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The chairperson performs the duties conferred on the chairperson by the by-laws, calls and presides at meetings of the board and determines the agenda of those meetings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the chairperson is absent or unable to act, the board may designate one of the directors to act as chairperson.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>By-laws</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>The board may make by-laws respecting the administration and management of the business and affairs of the Corporation, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the convening, frequency and conduct of meetings of the board, the participation of directors in those meetings by telephone or other communication facilities, the quorum at the meetings and the confidentiality of the board’s deliberations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the holding of annual meetings;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the periodic review of the performance of the president by the board;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the manner in which the board may recommend to the Minister the removal of the president;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the establishment of committees of the board and the powers, duties and functions of the committees; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the exercise of the powers set out in section 7.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>President</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The president is appointed by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Minister and holds office during pleasure for the term that the Governor in Council may determine.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may recommend that a person be appointed president only if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister has consulted the board with respect to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the qualifications required of the president, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the person whom the Minister is proposing to recommend; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the board has fixed the remuneration to be paid to the president and has informed the Minister of the remuneration.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The president is paid the remuneration fixed in accordance with paragraph 13(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Travel and living expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The president is entitled to be paid reasonable travel and living expenses incurred during the course of the president’s duties under this Act while absent from the president’s ordinary place of work.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duties</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The president is the chief executive officer of the Corporation and has, on behalf of the board, responsibility for the direction and management of the business and day-to-day operations of the Corporation with authority to act, subject to resolution of the board, in all matters that are not by this Act or the by-laws specifically reserved to be done by the board or the chairperson.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the president is absent or unable to act or the office of president is vacant, the Minister may appoint an interim president. An interim president is not entitled to act for more than 90 days without the approval of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Directors and Officers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Duty of care</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The directors and officers of the Corporation in exercising their powers and performing their duties must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>act honestly and in good faith with a view to the best interests of the Corporation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>exercise the care, diligence and skill that a reasonably prudent person would exercise in comparable circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed best interests</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any act taken by a director or officer of the Corporation for the purpose of facilitating the implementation of Part 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marketing Freedom for Grain Farmers Act</XRefExternal> is deemed to be in the best interests of the Corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to comply</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The directors and officers of the Corporation must comply with the provisions of this Act and the regulations as well as with the by-laws of the Corporation and any directions given to the Corporation under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit of liability</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Directors and officers are not liable under subsection (1) or (3) if they rely in good faith on</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>financial statements of the Corporation represented to them by an officer of the Corporation or in a written report of the auditor of the Corporation as fairly reflecting the financial condition of the Corporation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a report of a lawyer, notary, accountant, engineer, appraiser or other person whose position or profession lends credibility to a statement made by that person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Indemnity</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation may indemnify a present or former director or officer of the Corporation or a person who acts or has acted as a director or officer at the request of the Corporation against all costs, charges and expenses, including an amount paid to settle an action or satisfy a judgment, that are reasonably incurred by them in respect of any civil, criminal or administrative action or proceeding to which they are a party by reason of being or having been such a director, officer or person if they</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>acted honestly and in good faith with a view to the best interests of the Corporation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a criminal or administrative action or proceeding that is enforced by a monetary penalty, had reasonable grounds to believe that their conduct was lawful.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advance of costs</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Corporation may advance moneys to any individual referred to in subsection (1) for the costs, charges and expenses of an action or proceeding referred to in that subsection unless there are reasonable grounds to believe that the individual does not fulfil the conditions set out in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>). The individual must repay the moneys if he or she does not fulfil those conditions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indemnity as of right</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this section, a person referred to in subsection (1) is entitled to indemnity from the Corporation in respect of all costs, charges and expenses reasonably incurred by that person in connection with the defence of any civil, criminal or administrative action or proceeding to which the person is made a party by reason of being or having been a director or officer of the Corporation, if the person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was substantially successful on the merits in their defence of the action or proceeding; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fulfils the conditions set out in paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application to court</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Corporation or a person referred to in subsection (1) may apply to a court for an order approving an indemnity under this section and the court may so order and make any further order it thinks fit.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Contingency fund</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Fund established</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A contingency fund is established to be used by the Corporation</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to carry out any activities set out in the annual corporate plan approved under section 26 or, on the approval of the Minister with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, to carry out any other activity; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to provide for potential losses resulting from the operation of section 30 or 37.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Crediting contingency fund</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), the Corporation may deduct an amount from any amount it receives in the course of its operations under this Act and credit the amount so deducted to the contingency fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Corporation is not authorized to make a deduction referred to in subsection (2) if, as a result of the deduction, a loss would be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contingency fund balance</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the balance at any particular time of the contingency fund need not be positive.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Pricing, Profits and Losses</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Sale and disposal of grain</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation may sell and dispose of grain acquired by it as a result of its operations under this Act for the prices that it considers reasonable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Profits</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Profits realized by the Corporation from its operations in grain under this Act during any crop year, other than from its operations under Part 2, with respect to the disposition of which no provision is made elsewhere in this Act, are to be credited to the contingency fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Losses</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Losses sustained by the Corporation from its operations under Part 2 in relation to any pool period fixed under that Part, during that pool period, for which no other provision is made under this Act, are to be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Investment of Moneys</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of expenses</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation may, at the time of realization, use every profit realized by it on the sale of bonds, debentures, notes or other evidences of indebtedness acquired by it under paragraph 7(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) in payment of expenses incurred by it in its operations or may credit the profit to the contingency fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Losses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every loss sustained by the Corporation on the sale of a bond, debenture, note or other evidence of indebtedness acquired under paragraph 7(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) is, for all purposes, deemed to be an expense incurred by the Corporation in the course of its operations at the time of the sale.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Accounts and Reports</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Obligations of the Corporation</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>keep proper books and accounts of its operations under this Act, showing any particulars that may be requisite for proper accounting in accordance with established accounting practice;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with the approval of the Governor in Council, appoint a firm of chartered accountants for the purpose of auditing accounts and records and certifying reports of the Corporation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>report in writing to the Minister as soon as feasible after the end of each month, as at the close of business on the last day of that month, its purchases and sales of all grain during the month and the quantities of grain then held by it, the contracts to take delivery of grain to which it is then a party, all securities then held by it and the financial result of its operations as at the end of that month;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make any reports and provide any information that the Minister may from time to time require; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in each year, on or before March 31 or any other date that the Governor in Council may fix, report to the Minister in writing, as at the close of business on the last day of the preceding crop year, its purchases and sales of all grain during that crop year, the quantities of grain then owned by it, the contracts to take delivery of grain to which it is then a party, all securities then held by it and the financial result of its operations as at the end of that crop year and any further information that the Minister may require, and the report is to be certified by the auditors of the Corporation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause a copy of each report of the Corporation made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) to be laid before Parliament on any of the first 15 days that either House of Parliament is sitting after the Minister receives it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commercially detrimental information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may exclude from the report any information whose publication, in the opinion of the Minister, would be detrimental to the commercial interests of the Corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Pension Fund and Group Insurance</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Pension fund</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, establish a pension fund for the directors and the officers, clerks and employees employed by the Corporation under this Act and their dependants, including their spouse, common-law partner and children, any other relative of the director, officer, clerk or employee, and any child or other relative of the spouse or common-law partner of the director, officer, clerk or employee. The Corporation may contribute to the pension fund out of funds of the Corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Corporation’s contributions deemed operational expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Contributions to the pension fund made by the Corporation under subsection (1) are deemed to be expenses incurred in connection with its operations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Group insurance plans</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>With the approval of the Governor in Council, the Corporation may enter into a contract with any person for the provision of a group life insurance plan and a group medical-surgical insurance plan for the directors and the officers, clerks and employees employed by the Corporation under this Act and their dependants, including their spouse, common-law partner and children, any other relative of the director, officer, clerk or employee, and any child or other relative of the spouse or common-law partner of the director, officer, clerk or employee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Corporation’s contribution to premiums</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Corporation may contribute a share of the premiums payable under any insurance plan referred to in subsection (1) out of the funds of the Corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Corporation’s contributions deemed operational expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Contributions made by the Corporation under subsection (2) are deemed to be expenses incurred in connection with its operations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>common-law partner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>In subsections 22(1) and 23(1), <DefinedTermEn>common-law partner</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to an individual, means a person who is cohabiting with the individual in a conjugal relationship, having so cohabited for a period of at least one year.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Directions by Governor in Council</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Directions to the Corporation</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, direct the Corporation with respect to the manner in which any of its operations, powers and duties under this Act are to be conducted, exercised or performed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The directors are to cause the directions to be implemented and, in so far as they act in accordance with section 16, they are not accountable for any consequences arising from the implementation of the directions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Best interests</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Compliance by the Corporation with directions is deemed to be in the best interests of the Corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Plans, Borrowings and Guarantees</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Corporate plan</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation must submit annually a corporate plan to the Minister for the approval of the Minister in consultation with the Minister of Finance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Scope and content of corporate plan</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The corporate plan must encompass all the business and activities of the Corporation and must contain any information that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Borrowing plan</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Corporation must submit annually to the Minister of Finance for approval a plan indicating the amount of money that the Corporation intends to borrow in the coming crop year for the purposes of carrying out its corporate plan.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Corporation must not undertake any borrowings described in the borrowing plan approved under subsection (3) unless the Minister of Finance has approved the time and terms of the borrowings, including which borrowings are to be guaranteed by the Minister of Finance on behalf of Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Guarantee of borrowings</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The repayment with interest, if any, of money borrowed by the Corporation is guaranteed by the Minister of Finance on behalf of Her Majesty if the terms approved under subsection (4) indicate that it is to be guaranteed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loans and guarantee of credit sales</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance, on behalf of Her Majesty, may, on any terms that the Governor in Council may approve,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make loans or advances to the Corporation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>guarantee payment with interest of amounts owing to the Corporation in respect of the sale of grain on credit.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>INTERPROVINCIAL AND EXPORT MARKETING OF GRAIN BY THE CORPORATION</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>pool period</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>In this Part, <DefinedTermEn>pool period</DefinedTermEn> means any period or periods, not exceeding one year in the aggregate, that the Corporation may set as a pool period in respect of grain.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Purchase of Grain and Initial Payment</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Grain for interprovincial and export trade</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation may undertake the marketing of grain in interprovincial and export trade and for that purpose may buy grain offered by a producer for sale and delivery to the Corporation at an elevator, in a railway car or at any other place.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements when grain purchased</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Corporation buys grain under subsection (1), it must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay to producers selling and delivering grain to the Corporation a sum certain per tonne basis in storage at a pooling point to be fixed from time to time</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>by the Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, in respect of grain of a base grade, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>by the Corporation, with the approval of the Minister and the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, in respect of each other grade of grain;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) the sum certain payable to producers in respect of grain of any grade is increased during a pool period, pay to the holder of a certificate that is referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) the amount of the increase in respect of each tonne of grain of that grade sold and delivered to the Corporation during the pool period before the day on which the increase becomes effective; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>issue to a producer who sells and delivers grain to the Corporation a certificate indicating the number of tonnes purchased and delivered and the grade of the grain, which certificate entitles the holder to share in the equitable distribution of the surplus, if any, arising from the operations of the Corporation with regard to the grain sold and delivered to the Corporation during the same pool period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sum to have proper price relationship</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Each sum certain fixed by the Corporation under subparagraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) in respect of a grade of grain other than a base grade must be an amount that brings the sum certain for that grade into proper price relationship with the sum certain for the base grade.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Storage and other delivery-related payments</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Corporation may set for any pool period and pay to each producer, under the conditions set by the Corporation, a sum per tonne on account of storage of grain on the producer’s farm, interest costs and other delivery-related amounts. Payment must be made from the account maintained by the Corporation for the pool period during which the grain was delivered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deferred delivery permit</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>On application made to the Corporation by a producer before August 31 in any crop year, the Corporation may, in accordance with any conditions that may be specified in the regulations, issue to the producer a deferred delivery permit to deliver grain that the producer was unable to deliver during the immediately preceding crop year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Option</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Grain delivered and sold in a crop year under a deferred delivery permit issued under subsection (5) may, at the option of the producer,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>be recorded as a delivery and sale by the producer in that crop year; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>be deemed for all purposes to have been delivered and sold during the immediately preceding crop year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Payment of Balance and Interim Payments</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Deductions from receipts</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as the Corporation receives payment in full for all grain sold and delivered to it during a pool period and all credit sales of the grain in respect of which payment is guaranteed under section 26 have been concluded, there is to be deducted, from the aggregate of the total amount so received, the principal so guaranteed and any interest that accrues during that pool period in respect of sales of grain on credit concluded during any pool period, all moneys disbursed by or on behalf of the Corporation by way of payment in respect of that grain and by way of expenses incurred in connection with the operations of the Corporation attributable to that grain, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the remuneration and allowances of the officers, clerks and employees of the Corporation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the remuneration and expenses of the directors of the Corporation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the necessary travel, living and other expenses incurred in the discharge of duties under this Act by the persons referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the estimated expenses of distribution of the balance mentioned in subsection (3), as estimated by the Corporation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional payment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Corporation may, with the approval of the Minister and the concurrence of the Minister of Finance and subject to any terms on which the approval is given, fix and pay in respect of any pool period a sum per tonne to each producer who has sold and delivered grain to the Corporation in a railway car during the pool period, in addition to any payment authorized by section 28.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distribution of balance</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Corporation must, after the end of any pool period, distribute the balance remaining in its account in respect of grain purchased by it during the pool period, after making the deductions from the account provided for in subsection (1) and the payments provided for in subsection (2), among holders of certificates issued by the Corporation under this Part during the pool period, by paying on surrender to it of each certificate, unless the Corporation waives the surrender, to the holder of the certificate, the appropriate sum determined by the Corporation as provided in this Act for each tonne of grain referred to in the certificate according to grade.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interim payments</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), if the Minister, having regard to a report by the Corporation of the effect on its financial position of an interim payment on account of the distribution of the balance referred to in subsection (3), is of the opinion that an interim payment can be made without loss and the Minister of Finance concurs with the Minister’s opinion, the Minister with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance may authorize and direct that payment to be made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expenses — international grain marketing organizations</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Expenses incurred by the Corporation with respect to any international organization for the purposes of marketing grain and the expenses of any director or officer of the Corporation of and incidental to attendance at meetings of that international organization or any committee of that organization are deemed to be expenses incurred in connection with the operations of the Corporation within the meaning of this section, but nothing in this subsection is to be construed as authorizing the payment by the Corporation of any contributions required to be paid by Canada to or in support of that international organization or any committee of that organization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of amounts</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Corporation must, with the approval of the Minister and the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, determine and fix the amounts to which producers are entitled per tonne according to grade under certificates issued under this Part so that each producer receives, in respect of grain sold and delivered to the Corporation during each crop year for the same grade of grain, the same price basis at a pooling point and that each price bears a proper price relationship to the price for each other grade.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Corporation not liable</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>There is no liability on the Corporation in respect of a certificate issued under this Part except as provided in this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Early payment</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation may, in accordance with this section, pay to holders of certificates issued by the Corporation under this Part who apply for such a payment, an amount instead of the amount that would be distributed under paragraph 28(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or section 29.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Possible gains</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any gains of the Corporation that result from the operation of this section are to be credited to the contingency fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Possible losses</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any losses of the Corporation that result from making payments under subsection (1) are to be paid out of the contingency fund.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Quality Characteristics Within Grades</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Action within a grade</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>In taking any action under section 28, 29 or 34 in respect of a grade of grain, the Governor in Council, the Corporation or the Minister with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance may take that action in respect of any grain within that grade that has an inherent quality characteristic that distinguishes it from any other grain within that grade as if the grain having that inherent quality characteristic were grain of a different grade.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Distribution variations within a grade</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>In carrying out any distribution under subsection 29(3), the Corporation may adjust the appropriate sum determined by the Corporation as provided in this Act for each tonne of grain referred to in that subsection according to grade in order to pay a premium or make a discount in respect of any grain within any grade that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has an inherent quality characteristic that distinguishes it from any other grain within that grade; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was delivered to the Corporation at a delivery point that the Canadian Grain Commission has determined to be a point at which the average of the aggregate grain of that grade that was delivered to the point during that pool period had an inherent quality characteristic that distinguished it from any other grain within that grade.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Separate Accounts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Separate accounts</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation must maintain separate accounts with regard to its operations in respect of each type of grain sold and delivered to it during each pool period by producers.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designated grain</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Corporation must maintain a separate account under subsection (1) in respect of grain designated by regulation under subsection 38(1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations and Authorizations Respecting Certificates and Accounts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by regulation,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribe the form of certificates to be issued under section 28;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribe the manner in which the Corporation must adjust its accounts for any pool period in respect of overages, shortages, adjustment of grades, mixing of grain, residual amounts of grain remaining in accounts and other like matters; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribe the conditions for and the manner of negotiating a certificate issued under this Part.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer of grain from preceding pool period</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>The Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, may authorize the Corporation to adjust its accounts at any time by transferring to the then current pool period all grain delivered during a preceding pool period and then remaining unsold, and the Corporation must credit to the accounts for that preceding pool period, and charge against the accounts for the current pool period, the amount that the Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, considers to be a reasonable price for the grain so transferred, and all grain so transferred is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the purposes of the accounts relating to that preceding pool period, deemed to have been sold and paid for in full for that amount; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the accounts relating to the current pool period, to be dealt with as though it had been sold and delivered to the Corporation by producers in the current pool period and purchased by the Corporation for that amount, but no further certificates in respect of that grain are to be issued under paragraph 28(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer of undistributed balances</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>If producers of any grain sold and delivered during a pool period have been for six years or more entitled to receive from the Corporation payments in respect of that grain under certificates issued under this Act or out of an equalization fund, or otherwise, and there is an undistributed balance remaining in the accounts of the Corporation in respect of that grain, the Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, may authorize the Corporation to adjust its accounts</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>by applying the undistributed balance in payment of the expenses of the distribution of the balance mentioned in subsection 29(3) with respect to the same type of grain in any earlier pool period; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>by transferring the remainder of the undistributed balance to the contingency fund.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Other Purchases of Grain</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of the Corporation</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite sections 28 to 36, the Corporation may enter into a contract with a producer or any other person or entity for the purchase and delivery of grain at a price other than the sum certain per tonne for grain as set out in section 28 and on any terms that the Corporation considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a contract entered into under subsection (1) may provide for the pooling of grain on a basis other than that set out in sections 28 to 36.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Possible gains</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any gains of the Corporation that may result from the operation of this section are to be credited to the contingency fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Possible losses</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any losses of the Corporation that may result from the operation of this section are to be paid out of the contingency fund.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designated grain</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by regulation, designate for the purposes of this Part</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any grain within any grade of grain specified in the regulation that has been delivered to the Corporation to be sold by the Corporation to purchasers who, with the consent of the Corporation, have selected and accepted the grain for a use specified in the regulation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>all grain of any grade of grain specified in the regulation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>all grain of any class of grain specified in the regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Two or more grades</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A regulation made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) must specify two or more grades of grain.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A regulation made under subsection (1) comes into force according to the terms of the regulation but not earlier than the beginning of the crop year next following the day on which the regulation is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time when regulation to be made</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A regulation made under subsection (1) must be made not less than five months before the day on which the regulation comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Grade name</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>The grade name of any grain designated by a regulation made under subsection 38(1) is the grade name assigned to that grain under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Grain Act</XRefExternal> with the word “designated” inserted immediately preceding the first word or number of the grade name.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A regulation made under subsection 38(1) must not be repealed at any time other than at the end of a crop year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfer of grain where repeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a regulation made under paragraph 38(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) is repealed, the Governor in Council may authorize the Corporation to transfer all grain of any grade or class specified in the regulation delivered during any pool period and remaining unsold at the time of the repeal of the regulation to the pool period that commences at that time for grain not designated by any regulation made under subsection 38(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Adjustment of accounts</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Corporation transfers grain under authority given under subsection (2), the Corporation must adjust its accounts by crediting to the accounts for each pool period from which the grain is transferred and charging against the accounts for the pool period into which the grain is transferred the amount that the Governor in Council considers to be a reasonable price for the grain so transferred, and all grain so transferred is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the purposes of the accounts for each pool period from which the grain is transferred, deemed to have been sold and paid for in full for that amount; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the accounts for the pool period into which the grain is transferred, to be dealt with as though it had been sold and delivered to the Corporation by producers in that pool period and purchased by the Corporation for that amount, but no further certificates in respect of that grain are to be issued under paragraph 28(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><TitleText>GENERAL</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for any purpose for which regulations may be made under this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Implementation of the North American Free Trade Agreement</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Giving effect to the Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In exercising its powers and performing its duties, the Corporation must give effect to the provisions of the Agreement that pertain to the Corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Treasury Board and the Minister made at the request of the Corporation, make any regulations in relation to the Corporation that the Governor in Council considers necessary for the purpose of implementing any provision of the Agreement that pertains to the Corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In subsections (1) and (2), <DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">North American Free Trade Agreement Implementation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Borrowing by Agents or Mandataries</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Corporation may authorize agents or mandataries to give security</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any other statute or law, the Corporation may authorize any person with whom the Corporation enters or has entered into an agreement relating to the handling or receipt of grain for the Corporation to borrow from any bank on the security of grain delivered to and received by that person and to give security on that grain, in accordance with the bank’s usual requirements, and the bank may take security on that grain under section 427 or 435 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>, and that person is deemed to be the owner of that grain for all those purposes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Default</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In case of default by a person described in subsection (1), the bank must sell or dispose of the grain referred to in that subsection to the Corporation only, and the Corporation must take delivery on the terms of the agreement from the bank in lieu of that person and pay to the bank the Corporation’s fixed carlot prices for any classes and grades of grain delivered at a pooling point or at any other delivery point that may be authorized by the Corporation, together with charges, allowances and costs provided for in the agreement, and the security on that grain ceases and the Corporation to that extent has clear title to that grain, and those payments are to that extent a complete fulfilment of the Corporation’s obligations to that person in respect of that grain as if those payments were made to that person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Corporation may authorize shipping agents or mandataries to give security</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any other statute or law, the Corporation may authorize a person with whom the Corporation enters into an agreement relating to the forwarding or selling of grain to borrow from any bank on the security of grain received by that person from the Corporation and to give security on that grain in accordance with the bank’s usual requirements, and the bank may take security on that grain under section 427 or 435 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>, and that person is deemed to be the owner of that grain for all those purposes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Default</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In case of default by a person described in subsection (1), the bank must sell or dispose of the grain referred to in that subsection to the Corporation only, and the Corporation must take delivery from the bank in lieu of that person and pay to the bank the Corporation’s price for that grain as fixed at the time of the making of the advance by the bank, delivered at a pooling point or at any other delivery point that may be authorized by the Corporation, together with charges, allowances and costs of transporting that grain to the delivery point, and the security on that grain ceases and the Corporation has a clear title to that grain.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Declaration</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Declaration for the general advantage of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Text>Without restricting the generality of any declaration in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Grain Act</XRefExternal> that any elevator is a work for the general advantage of Canada, every flour mill, feed mill, feed warehouse and seed cleaning mill is a work for the general advantage of Canada.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Shipping grain</MarginalNote><Label>46.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of shipping grain that has been sold and delivered to the Corporation before the day on which this Act comes into force, the Corporation may, despite anything in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Grain Act</XRefExternal>, but subject to directions contained in any order of the Governor in Council, by order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require that grain to be delivered from an elevator into railway cars or vessels navigating on the Great Lakes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the allocation of railway cars available for the shipment of that grain at any delivery point to any elevator, loading platform or person at the delivery point; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require any person engaged in the business of delivering, receiving, storing, transporting or handling grain to make returns to the Corporation of information relating to that business or any facilities related to that business that are owned, possessed or controlled by that person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Ceasing to have effect</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) ceases to have effect three months after the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Contingency fund</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Text>The balance of the contingency fund established under paragraph 6(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.3</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> immediately before the day on which this Act comes into force is, on that day, credited to the contingency fund established under subsection 18(1).</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Separate account</MarginalNote><Label>48.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The undistributed balance remaining in the separate account referred to in subparagraph 39(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> on the day on which this Act comes into force is, on that day, credited to the contingency fund established under subsection 18(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distribution of the balance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Corporation may use any portion of the undistributed balance credited to the contingency fund under subsection (1) for any purpose that it could have under subsection 39(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> before the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Consequential and Related Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-49</MarginalNote><TitleText>Advance Payments for Crops Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1989, c. 26, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>Section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Advance Payments for Crops Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application of Act</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>This Act applies in respect of crops grown in Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 20</MarginalNote><TitleText>Agricultural Marketing Programs Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 30</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Board</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>permit book</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agricultural Marketing Programs Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2006, c. 3, s. 1(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>administrator</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an organization, other than a lender, that the Minister, taking into account any criteria prescribed by regulation, determines to be an organization that represents producers who produce, in an area, a significant portion of an agricultural product for which advances will be made; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>marketing agency</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and by repealing paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2006, c. 3, ss. 8(1)(E) and (2), 9(E) and 10</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Text>The heading before section 13 and sections 13 to 18 of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2006, c. 3, s. 13</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>Section 24 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Text>Section 33 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>Section 46 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Section 52 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-5</MarginalNote><TitleText>Agricultural Products Cooperative Marketing Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>agricultural product</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agricultural Products Cooperative Marketing Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>grain,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 22</MarginalNote><TitleText>An Act to amend the Canada Grain Act and the Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act and to repeal the Grain Futures Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>Section 17 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Canada Grain Act and the Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act and to repeal the Grain Futures Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. G-10</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Grain Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>lawfully</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Grain Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in accordance with this Act, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>lawfully</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act after subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(iii) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><ContinuedParagraph><Text>deliverable by the owner of the grain, receivable by the public carrier for carriage to the elevator or consignee and receivable by the operator of the elevator or consignee, in accordance with this Act;</Text></ContinuedParagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>actual producer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>producteur-exploitant</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>actual producer</DefinedTermEn> means a person actually engaged in the production of grain;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>producer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>producteur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>producer</DefinedTermEn> means, as well as an actual producer, any person entitled, as landlord, vendor or mortgagee or hypothecary creditor, to the grain produced by an actual producer or to any share of that grain;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 20(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 20(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>douze producteurs-exploitants de grain de l’Ouest;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 20(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any additional persons not exceeding four in number that the Commission considers advisable.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 37 (4th Supp.), s. 23(2)</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 80(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 37 (4th Supp.), s. 23(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 80(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the grain is grain other than grain referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), be the property of the Commission,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 83:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Deductions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Deductions</MarginalNote><Label>83.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any person required to issue a cash purchase ticket under this Act shall deduct from the amount payable under the ticket the prescribed amount per tonne of wheat or barley grown in the Western Division, and shall remit that amount to the prescribed agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Option</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person entitled to a cash purchase ticket may, unless the regulations provide for the payment of refunds, opt out of the payment of deductions under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distribution by agency</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A prescribed agency may use any amount it receives under subsection (1) for the purposes of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>research activities into new and improved grain varieties;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the promotion of the marketing and use of grain grown in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>technical assistance relating to the use of grain grown in Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>covering the administrative costs that it incurs in applying this section.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Power to make regulations</MarginalNote><Label>83.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the amount to be deducted per tonne under section 83.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing an agency to which amounts are to be remitted under section 83.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing exemptions from the deduction under section 83.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>governing the opting out of the payment of deductions or providing for refunds of amounts deducted under section 83.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring a person making a deduction under section 83.1 or the prescribed agency to report on its activities under that section; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting any other matter relating to the administration of section 83.1.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distinctions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under subsection (1) may distinguish on the basis of type, class or grade of grain, or region where the grain was produced.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Ceasing to have effect</MarginalNote><Label>83.3</Label><Text>Sections 83.1 and 83.2 cease to have effect five years after the day on which this section comes into force.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1988, c. 65, s. 125; 1994, c. 45, s. 28(F)</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>Part V.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 22, s. 17</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>Subsection 88(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Inspection</MarginalNote><Label>88.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1.1), an inspector may, at any reasonable time, enter any elevator, any premises of the licensee of an elevator or any premises of a licensed grain dealer in which the inspector has reasonable grounds to believe there is any grain, grain product or screenings owned or possessed by the licensee or any books, records or other documents relating to the operation of the elevator or the business of the grain dealer and may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>examine the premises and any equipment, grain, grain products and screenings found in the premises; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>examine any books, records, bills of lading and other documents that, on reasonable grounds, the inspector believes contain any information relevant to verifying compliance with this Act and make copies of them or take extracts from them.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1988, c. 65, s. 128</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Text>Paragraph 91(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g.1</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1988, c. 65, s. 129</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>Section 105.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1988, c. 65, s. 131(1)</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 107(1.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1988, c. 65, s. 131(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 107(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes any provision of this Act, other than section 72, or of the regulations or any order of the Commission, other than an order for the payment of any money or apportionment of any loss, is guilty of an offence and</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33.</Label><Text>Paragraph 115(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>despite anything in this Act, authorize and direct any minister of the Crown or any agency of the Government of Canada to exercise the powers in respect of the allocation of available railway cars contained in any provision of this Act, other than paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, ss. 32(1)(F) and (2)</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 118(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">g.1</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the acceptance of deliveries of grain in the interests of producers; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-4; 1993, c. 3, s. 2</MarginalNote><TitleText>Farm Products Agencies Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 3, par. 13(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(F)</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>Subsection 16(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Farm Products Agencies Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of agencies</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, establish an agency with powers relating to any farm product or farm products the marketing of which in interprovincial and export trade is not regulated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Dairy Commission Act</XRefExternal> if the Governor in Council is satisfied that a majority of the producers of the farm product or of each of the farm products in Canada is in favour of the establishment of an agency.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. L-10</MarginalNote><TitleText>Livestock Feed Assistance Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 38, s. 24(1)</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Livestock Feed Assistance Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>buy or enter into contracts or agreements for the purchase of feed grain;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-18</MarginalNote><TitleText>Prairie Grain Advance Payments Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prairie Grain Advance Payments Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-8</MarginalNote><TitleText>Seeds Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1988, c. 65, s. 144</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>Section 4.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seeds Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-24</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><?Pub Caret?><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Text>This Part comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><Label>PART 3</Label><TitleText>COMMERCIALIZATION OF THE CANADIAN WHEAT BOARD</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Continuance</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Part and in Parts 4 and 5.</Text><Definition type="transitional"><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>board</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>conseil</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>board</DefinedTermEn> means the board of directors of the Corporation as defined in subection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Corporation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Commission</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Corporation</DefinedTermEn> means the Canadian Wheat Board continued by subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Words and expressions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless it is otherwise provided, words and expressions used in this Part or in Part 4 or 5 have the same meaning as in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Submission to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Corporation must submit an application for continuance under one of the following Acts for the Minister’s approval:</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Cooperatives Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Not-for-profit Corporations Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deadline</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must be submitted to the Minister within four years, or any shorter period specified by the Minister, after the day on which this Part comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Submission to applicable authorities</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Once the application has been approved by the Minister, the Corporation must submit the application to the applicable authorities under the relevant Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Application not invalid</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The application is not invalid solely because the Corporation is incorporated by an Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Text>The Corporation is not entitled to apply for continuance in another jurisdiction.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Simultaneous coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Text>This Part comes into force on the day on which Part 2 comes into force.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Ceasing to Have Effect</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Ceasing to have effect</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Text>This Part ceases to have effect on the day on which Part 4 applies.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><Label>PART 4</Label><TitleText>DISSOLUTION OF THE CANADIAN WHEAT BOARD</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Application of Part</MarginalNote><Label>46.</Label><Text>This Part applies only if the Corporation is not continued under Part 3 within five years, or any shorter period specified by the Governor in Council, after the day on which that Part comes into force.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Final Pool Period</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Final pool period</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, by order, in respect of each grain, designate one or more pool periods set by the Corporation under section 27 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal> as a final pool period for the purposes of winding up the Corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Final payment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Corporation must make all payments due under subsection 29(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal> in respect of the final pool period before winding up the Corporation under section <XRefInternal>48</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Exercising powers</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After the end of the final pool period, the Corporation may exercise its powers under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal> only for the purpose of administering that pool period and winding up the Corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Distribution of Assets</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Distribution of property</MarginalNote><Label>48.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The property of the Corporation is to be applied in satisfaction of its debts and liabilities, and the charges, costs and expenses incurred in winding-up its affairs.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the contingency fund established under subsection 18(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal> forms part of the property of the Corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deadline for claims</MarginalNote><Label>49.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may fix a date by which all claims against the Corporation are to be submitted to the Corporation and must publish a notice of that date in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> at least 60 days before that date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Failure to submit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any claim against the Corporation that is not submitted in accordance with subsection (1) is void.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Winding-up expenses</MarginalNote><Label>50.</Label><Text>All charges, costs and expenses properly incurred in the winding-up of the Corporation, including the remuneration of any liquidator appointed under section <XRefInternal>52</XRefInternal>, are payable out of the assets of the Corporation, in priority to all other claims.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Surplus</MarginalNote><Label>51.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any surplus that remains after the satisfaction of the debts and liabilities of the Corporation and the winding-up charges, costs and expenses belongs to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Unsatisfied debts and liabilities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any debts and liabilities of the Corporation that remain unsatisfied on the day on which the Corporation is dissolved become the debts and liabilities of Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Appointment of Liquidator</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>52.</Label><Text>If the Minister considers it necessary to fully carry out the purpose of this Part, the Minister may appoint a liquidator, who is to hold office during pleasure, to administer the final pool period and wind up the Corporation.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions</MarginalNote><Label>53.</Label><Text>On appointment of a liquidator,</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the president, chairperson and other directors cease to hold their respective offices and the liquidator may exercise all of the powers and perform all the duties and functions of the Corporation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the by-laws made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal> are deemed to be revoked.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Refusal to honour</MarginalNote><Label>54.</Label><Text>The liquidator may refuse to honour any gratuitous contract, or conveyance or contract without consideration or with a merely nominal consideration, respecting either real or personal property or immovables or movables, made by the Corporation before the appointment of the liquidator.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Dissolution Date</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Dissolution</MarginalNote><Label>55.</Label><Text>The Corporation is dissolved on a day fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><Label>PART 5</Label><TitleText>REPEAL OF THE CANADIAN WHEAT BOARD (INTERIM OPERATIONS) ACT</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Application of Part</MarginalNote><Label>56.</Label><Text>This Part applies when the Corporation is continued under Part 3 or dissolved under Part 4.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>57.</Label><Text>Despite sections <XRefInternal>58</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>63</XRefInternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal> continues to apply to the Corporation but only in respect of government records, as defined in that Act, that were under the control of the Corporation on the day before the day on which this Part applies.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2006, c. 9, s. 165</MarginalNote><Label>58.</Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following under the heading “OTHER GOVERNMENT INSTITUTIONS”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Wheat Board</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission canadienne du blé</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. G-10</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Grain Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>59.</Label><Text>Section 55 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Grain Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other works</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Every flour mill, feed mill, feed warehouse and seed cleaning mill is a work for the general advantage of Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 10</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Transportation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 16, s. 9(3)</MarginalNote><Label>60.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>government hopper car</DefinedTermEn> in section 147 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>government hopper car</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>wagon-trémie du gouvernement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>government hopper car</DefinedTermEn> means a hopper car provided to a prescribed railway company by the government of Canada or a province;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-8; 1995, c. 17, s. 45(1)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>61.</Label><Text>Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Wheat Board </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission canadienne du blé</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. M-13; 2000, c. 8, s. 2</MarginalNote><TitleText>Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>62.</Label><Text>Schedule III to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Wheat Board </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission canadienne du blé</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>63.</Label><Text>The schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following under the heading “OTHER GOVERNMENT INSTITUTIONS”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Wheat Board </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Commission canadienne du blé</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>64.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Wheat Board (Interim Operations) Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>