<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-5</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59-60</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010-2011</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Motor Vehicle Safety Act and the Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Ensuring Safe Vehicles Imported from Mexico for Canadians</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Motor Vehicle Safety and Canadian Environmental Protection, 1999</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2011</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>1</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2011</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-4-13">90524</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Motor Vehicle Safety Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</XRefExternal> to allow, subject to certain conditions, the importation of certain used vehicles from Mexico in order for Canada to meet its free trade obligations.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ensuring Safe Vehicles Imported from Mexico for Canadians Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 16</MarginalNote><TitleText>MOTOR VEHICLE SAFETY ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>vehicle</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Motor Vehicle Safety Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>vehicle</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>véhicule</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means any vehicle that belongs to a prescribed class of vehicles.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Subsection 7(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Vehicle from United States or Mexico</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite sections 5 and 6, a vehicle that has been sold at the retail level in the United States, or that is a prescribed vehicle from Mexico, and that fails to satisfy an applicable requirement of those sections may be imported into Canada if the vehicle satisfies the conditions specified in the regulations, if any, and if the person importing the vehicle makes a declaration in the prescribed form and manner that,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within the prescribed period, the vehicle will be made to conform to that requirement and will be inspected in accordance with the regulations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>before the vehicle is presented for licensing under the laws of a province, the vehicle will be certified in accordance with the regulations to so conform by any person who is designated by the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 33</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADIAN ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION ACT, 1999</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 155(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Vehicle from United States or Mexico</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 153 and 154 do not apply in respect of the importation of a vehicle that has been sold at the retail level in the United States, or that is a prescribed vehicle from Mexico, if the vehicle satisfies the conditions specified in the regulations, if any, and if the person importing it makes a declaration in the prescribed form and manner that,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within the prescribed period, the applicable requirements of those sections will be met and, if required by the regulations, the vehicle will be inspected in accordance with them; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>before the vehicle is presented for licensing under the laws of a province or an aboriginal government, the vehicle will be certified, in accordance with the regulations, as conforming to the applicable requirements of those sections.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Subsection 160(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting inspection and certification referred to in subsection 155(2) and, in particular, designating any person who is authorized to inspect or certify vehicles; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><?Pub Caret?><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>