<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-22</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59-60</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010-2011</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the mandatory reporting of Internet child pornography by persons who provide an Internet service</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act respecting the mandatory reporting of Internet child pornography by persons who provide an Internet service</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Mandatory Reporting of Internet Child Pornography by Persons who Provide an Internet Service</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><?Pub Caret1?><Date><YYYY>2011</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>4</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2011</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-5-3">90543</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment imposes reporting duties on persons who provide an Internet service to the public if they are advised of an Internet address where child pornography may be available to the public or if they have reasonable grounds to believe that their Internet service is being or has been used to commit a child pornography offence. This enactment makes it an offence to fail to comply with the reporting duties.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>child pornography</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>pornographie juvénile</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>child pornography</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 163.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>child pornography offence</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>infraction relative à la pornographie juvénile</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>child pornography offence</DefinedTermEn> means an offence under any of the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 163.1(2) (making child pornography);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 163.1(3) (distribution, etc., of child pornography);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 163.1(4) (possession of child pornography); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 163.1(4.1) (accessing child pornography).</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>computer data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données informatiques</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>computer data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, including signs, signals or symbols, that are in a form suitable for processing in a computer system. </Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Internet Service</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>services Internet</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Internet Service</DefinedTermEn> means a service providing Internet access, Internet content hosting or electronic mail.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> means an individual, a corporation, a partnership or an unincorporated association or organization.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Description with cross-reference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The descriptive words in parentheses that follow the reference to a provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in the definition <DefinedTermEn>child pornography offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection (1) do not form part of that definition but are inserted for convenience of reference only.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>DUTIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to report Internet address</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>If a person is advised, in the course of providing an Internet service to the public, of an Internet Protocol address or a Uniform Resource Locator where child pornography may be available to the public, the person must report that address or Uniform Resource Locator to the organization designated by the regulations, as soon as feasible and in accordance with the regulations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to notify police officer</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>If a person who provides an Internet service to the public has reasonable grounds to believe that their Internet service is being or has been used to commit a child pornography offence, the person must notify an officer, constable or other person employed for the preservation and maintenance of the public peace of that fact, as soon as feasible and in accordance with the regulations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Preservation of computer data</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who makes a notification under section 3 must preserve all computer data related to the notification that is in their possession or control for 21 days after the day on which the notification is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of preserved computer data</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The person must destroy the computer data that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving computer data under subsection (1) as soon as feasible after the expiry of the 21-day period, unless the person is required to preserve the computer data by a judicial order made under any other Act of Parliament or the legislature of a province.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>A person must not disclose that they have made a report under section 2 or a notification under section 3, or disclose the contents of a report or notification, if the disclosure could prejudice a criminal investigation, whether or not a criminal investigation has begun.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No seeking out of child pornography</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act requires or authorizes a person to seek out child pornography.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>A civil proceeding cannot be commenced against a person for making a report in good faith under section 2 or for making a notification in good faith under section 3.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Self-incrimination</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in this Act affects any right of a person to be protected against self-incrimination.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provincial or foreign jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>A person who has reported information in compliance with an obligation to report child pornography under the laws of a province or a foreign jurisdiction is deemed to have complied with section 2 of this Act in relation to that information.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OFFENCES AND PUNISHMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>Every person who knowingly contravenes any of sections 2 to 5 is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $1,000,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for a second offence, to a fine of not more than $5,000, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for each subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in all other cases,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $10,000,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for a second offence, to a fine of not more than $50,000, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for each subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $100,000.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>A prosecution for an offence under this Act cannot be commenced more than two years after the time when the act or omission giving rise to the prosecution occurred.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>REGULATIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating an organization for the purpose of section 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the role, functions and activities of the designated organization in relation to information received under this Act, including any security measures to be taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the making of a report under section 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting a notification under section 3;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting security measures to be taken in relation to computer data preserved under section 4; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>generally, for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>