<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-42</BillNumber><Parliament><?Pub Caret1?><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59-60</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010-2011</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Strengthening Aviation Security Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Aeronautics</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2011</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>9</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2011</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-5-28">90557</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> so that the operator of an aircraft that is due to fly over the United States in the course of an international flight may provide information to a competent authority of that country.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Aviation Security Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-2</MarginalNote><TitleText>AERONAUTICS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 4.83(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Foreign states requiring information</MarginalNote><Label>4.83</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act</XRefExternal>, to the extent that that section relates to obligations set out in Schedule 1 to that Act relating to the disclosure of information, and despite subsection 7(3) of that Act, an operator of an aircraft departing from Canada that is due to land in a foreign state or fly over the United States and land outside Canada or of a Canadian aircraft departing from any place outside Canada that is due to land in a foreign state or fly over the United States may, in accordance with the regulations, provide to a competent authority in that foreign state any information that is in the operator’s control relating to persons on board or expected to be on board the aircraft and that is required by the laws of the foreign state.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The operator of an aircraft that is due to fly over, but not land in, the United States must notify all persons who are on board or expected to be on board the aircraft that information relating to them may be provided to a competent authority in the United States in accordance with subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 4.83 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Committee of the House of Commons responsible for transport matters must,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within two years after the day on which this subsection comes into force and every five years thereafter, commence a comprehensive review of the provisions and operation of this section, and complete the review within one year; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within three months after the day on which the review is completed, submit a report to the House of Commons setting out its findings.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>