<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-21</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59-60</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010-2011</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (sentencing for fraud)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official"><?Pub Caret?>Standing up for Victims of White Collar Crime Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code (sentencing for fraud)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2011</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>6</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2011</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-4-30">90534</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide a mandatory minimum sentence of imprisonment for a term of two years for fraud with a value that exceeds one million dollars;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide additional aggravating factors for sentencing;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>create a discretionary prohibition order for offenders convicted of fraud to prevent them from having authority over the money or real property of others;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require consideration of restitution for victims of fraud; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>clarify that the sentencing court may consider community impact statements from a community that has been harmed by the fraud.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Standing up for Victims of White Collar Crime Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 380 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minimum punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>When a person is prosecuted on indictment and convicted of one or more offences referred to in subsection (1), the court that imposes the sentence shall impose a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of two years if the total value of the subject-matter of the offences exceeds one million dollars.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 3, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 380.1(1) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Sentencing — aggravating circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>380.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of section 718.2, where a court imposes a sentence for an offence referred to in section 380, 382, 382.1 or 400, it shall consider the following as aggravating circumstances:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 3, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 380.1(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the magnitude, complexity, duration or degree of planning of the fraud committed was significant;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 380.1(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offence had a significant impact on the victims given their personal circumstances including their age, health and financial situation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 380.1(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offender did not comply with a licensing requirement, or professional standard, that is normally applicable to the activity or conduct that forms the subject-matter of the offence; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offender concealed or destroyed records related to the fraud or to the disbursement of the proceeds of the fraud.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 3, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 380.1(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aggravating circumstance — value of the fraud</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of section 718.2, when a court imposes a sentence for an offence referred to in section 382, 382.1 or 400, it shall also consider as an aggravating circumstance the fact that the value of the fraud committed exceeded one million dollars.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-mitigating factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When a court imposes a sentence for an offence referred to in section 380, 382, 382.1 or 400, it shall not consider as mitigating circumstances the offender’s employment, employment skills or status or reputation in the community if those circumstances were relevant to, contributed to, or were used in the commission of the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Record of proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The court shall cause to be stated in the record the aggravating and mitigating circumstances it took into account when determining the sentence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 380.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition order</MarginalNote><Label>380.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When an offender is convicted, or is discharged on the conditions prescribed in a probation order under section 730, of an offence referred to in subsection 380(1), the court that sentences or discharges the offender, in addition to any other punishment that may be imposed for that offence or any other condition prescribed in the order of discharge, may make, subject to the conditions or exemptions that the court directs, an order prohibiting the offender from seeking, obtaining or continuing any employment, or becoming or being a volunteer in any capacity, that involves having authority over the real property, money or valuable security of another person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The prohibition may be for any period that the court considers appropriate, including any period to which the offender is sentenced to imprisonment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court may vary order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A court that makes an order of prohibition or, if the court is for any reason unable to act, another court of equivalent jurisdiction in the same province, may, on application of the offender or the prosecutor, require the offender to appear before it at any time and, after hearing the parties, that court may vary the conditions prescribed in the order if, in the opinion of the court, the variation is desirable because of changed circumstances.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who is bound by an order of prohibition and who does not comply with the order is guilty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Court to consider restitution order</MarginalNote><Label>380.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When an offender is convicted, or is discharged under section 730, of an offence referred to in subsection 380(1), the court that sentences or discharges the offender, in addition to any other measure imposed on the offender, shall consider making a restitution order under section 738 or 739.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inquiry by court</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As soon as practicable after a finding of guilt and in any event before imposing the sentence, the court shall inquire of the prosecutor if reasonable steps have been taken to provide the victims with an opportunity to indicate whether they are seeking restitution for their losses, the amount of which must be readily ascertainable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Adjournment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On application of the prosecutor or on its own motion, the court may adjourn the proceedings to permit the victims to indicate whether they are seeking restitution or to establish their losses, if the court is satisfied that the adjournment would not interfere with the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form for victims</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Victims may indicate whether they are seeking restitution by completing Form 34.1 in Part XXVIII or a form approved for that purpose by the Lieutenant Governor in Council of the province where the court has jurisdiction or by using any other method approved by the court, and, if they are seeking restitution, shall establish their losses, the amount of which must be readily ascertainable, in the same manner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If a victim seeks restitution and the court decides not to make a restitution order, it shall give reasons for its decision and shall cause those reasons to be stated in the record.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Community impact statement</MarginalNote><Label>380.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, for the purpose of determining the sentence to be imposed on an offender, or whether the offender should be discharged under section 730, in respect of an offence referred to in subsection 380(1), the court may consider a statement made by a person on a community’s behalf describing the harm done to, or losses suffered by, the community arising from the commission of the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The statement must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>be prepared in writing and filed with the court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>identify the community on whose behalf the statement is made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>explain how the statement reflects the community’s views.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copy of statement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The clerk of the court shall provide a copy of the statement, as soon as practicable after a finding of guilt, to the offender or counsel for the offender, and to the prosecutor.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by adding the following after Form 34:</Text><AmendedText><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 34.1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 380.3)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>STATEMENT ON RESTITUTION FOR FRAUD</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of ............,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To the court that is sentencing (<Emphasis style="italic">name the offender</Emphasis>) who was convicted, or was discharged under section 730 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, of an offence referred to in subsection 380(1) of that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>I, (<Emphasis style="italic">name of declarant</Emphasis>), declare that (<Emphasis style="italic">check the appropriate box</Emphasis>):</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>[ ]</Label><Text>(i) I am not seeking restitution for the losses I suffered as a result of the commission of the offence.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="no" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>[ ]</Label><Text>(ii) I am seeking restitution in the amount of $................. for the following losses I suffered as a result of the commission of the offence.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>I declare that I have suffered the following losses as a result of the commission of the offence:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Complete the following table if seeking restitution.</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision><TableGroup bilingual="no" pointsize="10" rowbreak="no" spanlanguages="no" spanmarginalnotecol="no"><table frame="none"><tgroup align="left" cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="41.93pi" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="46.99pi" /><tbody><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Description</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Amount of loss</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" hyphenation="no" justification="left" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">describe each thing of which the declarant was defrauded</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" hyphenation="no" justification="left" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">state, in respect of each thing, the amount of the loss</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>1. ...........................</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>........................</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>2. ...........................</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>........................</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>3. ...........................</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>........................</Text></Provision></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>4. ...........................</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>........................</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>I understand that the amount of my losses must be readily ascertainable by the court. For that purpose, I am responsible for providing the court with all necessary documents, including bills, receipts and estimates, in support of my claim for restitution.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated this ........ day of ............ 20........, at ............. .</Text></Provision><Provision justification="right" language-align="no" list-item="no" topmarginspacing="20"><Text>.......................................</Text><Provision justification="right" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>Signature of declarant</Text></Provision></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>