<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-6</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>59-60</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2010-2011</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and another Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code and another Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2011</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>2</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2011</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-4-19">90516</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> with regard to the right of persons convicted of murder or high treason to be eligible to apply for early parole. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Transfer of Offenders Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><?Pub Caret?><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 745.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is renumbered as subsection 745.01(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply if the offender is convicted of an offence committed on or after the day on which this subsection comes into force.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 34, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 745.6(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application for judicial review</MarginalNote><Label>745.6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) to (2.6), a person may apply, in writing, to the appropriate Chief Justice in the province in which their conviction took place for a reduction in the number of years of imprisonment without eligibility for parole if the person</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 745.6(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>committed the murder or high treason before the day on which this paragraph comes into force;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 745.6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Less than 15 years of sentence served</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>A person who is convicted of murder or high treason and who has served less than 15 years of their sentence on the day on which this subsection comes into force may, within 90 days after the day on which they have served 15 years of their sentence, make an application under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>At least 15 years of sentence served</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>A person who is convicted of murder or high treason and who has served at least 15 years of their sentence on the day on which this subsection comes into force may make an application under subsection (1) within 90 days after</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the end of five years after the day on which the person was the subject of a determination made under subsection 745.61(4) or a determination or conclusion to which subsection 745.63(8) applies; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which this subsection comes into force, if the person has not made an application under subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application of subsection (2.2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2.2) has no effect on a determination or decision made under subsection 745.61(3) or (5) or 745.63(3), (5) or (6) as it read immediately before the day on which this subsection comes into force. A person in respect of whom a time is set under paragraph 745.61(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 745.63(6)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) as it read immediately before that day may make an application under subsection (1) within 90 days after the end of that time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further five-year period if no application made</MarginalNote><Label>(2.4)</Label><Text>If the person does not make an application in accordance with subsection (2.1), (2.2) or (2.3), as the case may be, they may make an application within 90 days after the day on which they have served a further five years of their sentence following the 90-day period referred to in that subsection, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent applications</MarginalNote><Label>(2.5)</Label><Text>A person who makes an application in accordance with subsection (2.1), (2.2) or (2.3), as the case may be, may make another application under subsection (1) within 90 days after</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the end of the time set under paragraph 745.61(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 745.63(6)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), if a time is set under that paragraph; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the end of five years after the day on which the person is the subject of a determination made under subsection 745.61(4) or a determination or conclusion to which subsection 745.63(8) applies, if the person is the subject of such a determination or conclusion.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent applications</MarginalNote><Label>(2.6)</Label><Text>A person who had made an application under subsection (1) as it read immediately before the day on which this subsection comes into force, whose application was finally disposed of on or after that day and who has then made a subsequent application may make a further application in accordance with subsection (2.5), if either paragraph (2.5)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is applicable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2.7)</Label><Text>The 90-day time limits for the making of any application referred to in subsections (2.1) to (2.5) may be extended by the appropriate Chief Justice, or his or her designate, to a maximum of 180 days if the person, due to circumstances beyond their control, is unable to make an application within the 90-day time limit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2.8)</Label><Text>If a person convicted of murder does not make an application under subsection (1) within the maximum time period allowed by this section, the Commissioner of Correctional Service Canada, or his or her designate, shall immediately notify in writing a parent, child, spouse or common-law partner of the victim that the convicted person did not make an application. If it is not possible to notify one of the aforementioned relatives, then the notification shall be given to another relative of the victim. The notification shall specify the next date on which the convicted person will be eligible to make an application under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 34, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 745.61(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial screening</MarginalNote><Label>745.61</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of an application under subsection 745.6(1), the appropriate Chief Justice shall determine, or shall designate a judge of the superior court of criminal jurisdiction to determine, on the basis of the following written material, whether the applicant has shown, on a balance of probabilities, that there is a substantial likelihood that the application will succeed:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 34, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 745.61(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Criteria</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In determining whether the applicant has shown that there is a substantial likelihood that the application will succeed, the Chief Justice or judge shall consider the criteria set out in paragraphs 745.63(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), with any modifications that the circumstances require.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 34, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 745.61(3) to (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision re new application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Chief Justice or judge determines that the applicant has not shown that there is a substantial likelihood that the application will succeed, the Chief Justice or judge may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>set a time, no earlier than five years after the date of the determination, at or after which the applicant may make another application under subsection 745.6(1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>decide that the applicant may not make another application under that subsection.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>If no decision re new application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Chief Justice or judge determines that the applicant has not shown that there is a substantial likelihood that the application will succeed but does not set a time for another application or decide that such an application may not be made, the applicant may make another application no earlier than five years after the date of the determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation of judge to empanel jury</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the Chief Justice or judge determines that the applicant has shown that there is a substantial likelihood that the application will succeed, the Chief Justice shall designate a judge of the superior court of criminal jurisdiction to empanel a jury to hear the application.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 34, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 745.63(6)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>set a time, no earlier than five years after the date of the determination or conclusion under subsection (4), at or after which the applicant may make another application under subsection 745.6(1); or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 34, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 745.63(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>If no decision re new application</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If the jury does not set a date on or after which another application may be made or decide that such an application may not be made, the applicant may make another application no earlier than five years after the date of the determination or conclusion under subsection (4).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 21</MarginalNote><TitleText>INTERNATIONAL TRANSFER OF OFFENDERS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Subsection 24(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Transfer of Offenders Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Eligibility for parole — murder</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections 17(2) and 19(1), if a Canadian offender was sentenced to imprisonment for life for an offence that, if it had been committed in Canada, would have constituted murder within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, their full parole ineligibility period is 10 years. If, in the Minister’s opinion, the documents supplied by the foreign entity show that the circumstances in which the offence was committed were such that, if it had been committed in Canada after July 26, 1976, it would have been first degree murder within the meaning of section 231 of that Act, the full parole ineligibility period is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>15 years, if the offence was committed before the day on which paragraph 745.6(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> comes into force; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>25 years, if the offence was committed on or after that day.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing applications</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Applications that were made under section 745.6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> as that section read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal> comes into force and are still not finally disposed of on that day are to be dealt with and disposed of in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> as they read immediately before that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Further applications</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who has made an application referred to in subsection (1) and who is the subject of a determination made under subsection 745.61(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as that subsection read before the day on which this subsection comes into force, or a determination or conclusion to which subsection 745.63(8) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as it read before that day, applies, may make an application under subsection 745.6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as amended by subsection 3(1), within 180 days after the end of two years after the day on which the person is the subject of the determination or conclusion.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Further applications</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who has made an application referred to in subsection (1) and in respect of whom a time is set under paragraph 745.61(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 745.63(6)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsections 4(3) and 5(1), respectively, may make an application under subsection 745.6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as amended by subsection 3(1), within 180 days after the end of that time.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>