<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-60</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to correct certain anomalies, inconsistencies and errors and to deal with other matters of a non-controversial and uncomplicated nature in the Statutes of Canada and to repeal certain Acts and provisions that have expired, lapsed or otherwise ceased to have effect</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Miscellaneous Statute Law Amendment Act, 2017</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Miscellaneous Statute Law Amendment Act, 2017</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>26</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2017</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-9-27">90853</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment is the 12th in a series of bills introduced under the Miscellaneous Statute Law Amendment (MSLA) Program. It amends 41 Acts to correct grammatical, spelling, terminological, typographical and cross-referencing errors, update archaic wording and correct discrepancies between the two language versions. It also updates the names of certain organizations, for example, “Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants” is replaced with “Chartered Professional Accountants of Canada”. Finally, it contains amendments repealing eight Acts that no longer have any application, for example, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Maintenance of Ports Operations Act, 1986</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment has been drafted based on the Thirteenth Report of the Standing Committee on Justice and Human Rights tabled in the House of Commons on May 31, 2017 and the Twenty-first Report of the Standing Senate Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs tabled in the Senate on June 21, 2017.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">BACKGROUND AND PROCESS</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The MSLA Program was established in 1975 to allow for minor non-controversial amendments to be made to a number of federal statutes at once, in one bill, instead of making such amendments incrementally when a particular statute is being opened for amendments of a more substantial nature.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The legislative process for introducing an MSLA bill in Parliament is different from the usual legislative process and involves four main steps: the preparation of a document containing the proposed amendments; the tabling of that document in Parliament and its review by a committee of each House; the preparation of an MSLA bill, based on the committees’ reports, that contains the proposed amendments that were approved by both committees; and finally, the introduction of the bill in Parliament.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The proposed amendments must meet all of the following criteria:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>not be controversial;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>not involve the spending of public funds;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>not prejudicially affect the rights of persons;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>not create a new offence or subject a new class of persons to an existing offence.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The document containing the proposed amendments is tabled in the Senate and referred to its Standing Committee on Legal and Constitutional Affairs and in the House of Commons and referred to its Standing Committee on Justice and Human Rights. Each committee reviews the proposed amendments in the document, prepares a report of its findings and presents it to the appropriate House.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Perhaps the most important feature of committee review is that, since a proposed amendment must not be controversial, its approval requires the consensus of the committee. Therefore, if a single member of a committee objects for any reason to a proposed amendment, that proposed amendment will not be included in the MSLA bill.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>After committee review, an MSLA bill is drafted based on the reports of the two committees and contains the proposed amendments that were approved by both committees. Once the bill is introduced in Parliament, it is subject to the ordinary enactment procedures; however, the bill usually receives three readings in each House without debate since the amendments contained in the bill have already been considered and approved by committees of both Houses.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><?Pub Caret?><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Miscellaneous Statute Law Amendment Act, 2017</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Aeronautics Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 4.31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 143 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Economic Action Plan 2014 Act, No. 2</XRefExternal>, is renumbered as section 4.32.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 4.32(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) is exempt from examination, registration and publication under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 4.91(4) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) is exempt from examination, registration and publication under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subsection 7.2(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Appel</MarginalNote><Label>7.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Toute personne concernée peut faire appel au Tribunal de la décision rendue en vertu du paragraphe 6.72(4), de l’alinéa 7(7)a) ou du paragraphe 7.1(7); toute personne concernée ou le ministre peuvent faire appel de celle rendue en vertu du paragraphe 6.9(8) ou de l’alinéa 7(7)b). Dans tous les cas, le délai d’appel est de trente jours suivant la décision.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. B-3; 1992, c. 27, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 25(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment by cheque</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All payments made by a trustee under subsection (1.3) shall be made by cheque drawn on the estate account or in such manner as is specified in directives of the Superintendent.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Paragraph 50.4(8)(c) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the trustee shall, within five days after the day the certificate mentioned in paragraph (b.1) is issued, send notice of the meeting of creditors under section 102, at which meeting the creditors may by ordinary resolution, notwithstanding section 14, affirm the appointment of the trustee or appoint another licensed trustee in lieu of that trustee.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subparagraph 57(c)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if no quorum exists for the purpose of subparagraph (i), send notice, within five days after the day the certificate mentioned in paragraph (b.1) is issued, of the meeting of creditors under section 102,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Paragraph 61(2)(c) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the trustee shall, within five days after the day the certificate mentioned in paragraph (b.1) is issued, send notice of the meeting of creditors under section 102, at which meeting the creditors may by ordinary resolution, notwithstanding section 14, affirm the appointment of the trustee or appoint another licensed trustee in lieu of that trustee.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Paragraph 158(g) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>make disclosure to the trustee of all property disposed of by transfer at undervalue within the period beginning on the day that is five years before the date of the initial bankruptcy event and ending on the date of the bankruptcy, both dates included;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Subsection 254(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of transaction provisions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 95 to 101 apply, with such modifications as the circumstances require, in respect of transactions of a customer with or through a securities firm relating to securities.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Health Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Paragraph (c) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>insured person</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Health Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person serving a term of imprisonment in a penitentiary as defined in Part I of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Corrections and Conditional Release Act</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-34; R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 19</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Competition Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>Subsection 18(1.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Competition Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certified copies</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner need not return any copy of a record produced under section 11 or obtained under section 15 or 16.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 103.3(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to prevent the continuation of conduct that could be the subject of an order under any of sections 75 to 77, 79, 81, 84 or 90.1; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 103.3(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Before making an application for an order to prevent the continuation of conduct that could be the subject of an order under any of sections 75 to 77, 79, 81, 84 or 90.1 by an entity incorporated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cooperative Credit Associations Act</XRefExternal> or a subsidiary of such an entity, the Commissioner must consult with the Minister of Finance respecting the safety and soundness of the entity.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-36</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Subsection 36(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction — employers</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The court may grant the authorization only if the court is satisfied that the company can and will make the payments that would have been required under paragraphs 6(5)(a) and (6)(a) if the court had sanctioned the compromise or arrangement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. I-20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>International River Improvements Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(1)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International River Improvements Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>situated within boundary waters; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Subparagraph 251.05(1)(a)(iii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>that the complaint has been settled between the employer and the employee,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1993, c. 16</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Motor Vehicle Safety Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>Subsection 10.1(7) of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Motor Vehicle Safety Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power to order</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by order, require any company that applies a national safety mark to any vehicle or equipment, sells any vehicle or equipment to which a national safety mark has been applied or imports any vehicle or equipment of a class for which standards are prescribed to give a notice of non-compliance in the manner specified in the order, if the Minister considers that it is in the interest of safety.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 44</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Employment Equity Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subsection 28(4.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Equity Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Acting after expiration of appointment</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>A member whose appointment expires may, with the approval of the Chairperson, conclude any hearing that the member has begun, and a person performing duties under this section is deemed to be a part-time member for the purposes of subsection 48.2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “aboriginal”</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>The English version of the Act is amended by replacing “aboriginal” with “Aboriginal” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>section 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the definitions <DefinitionRef>aboriginal peoples</DefinitionRef>, <DefinitionRef>designated groups</DefinitionRef> and <DefinitionRef>members of visible minorities</DefinitionRef> in section 3;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>section 7;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>subsection 9(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>subsection 18(4); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>paragraph 25(1.1)(a).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 13</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Tobacco Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>The heading of the first column of the schedule to the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tobacco Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by “Article”.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1999, c. 33</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinedTermFr>entreprises fédérales</DefinedTermFr> in subsection 3(1) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>ceux qui se rapportent à la navigation et à la marine marchande, maritimes ou fluviales, notamment en ce qui concerne l’exploitation de navires et le transport par navire;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>Paragraph 44(1)(f) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>publish, arrange for the publication of or distribute through an information clearing-house</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>information respecting pollution prevention,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>pertinent information in respect of all aspects of environmental quality, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a periodic report on the state of the Canadian environment.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 81(1) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Manufacture or import of substances</MarginalNote><Label>81</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a substance is not specified on the Domestic Substances List, no person shall manufacture or import the substance unless</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 81(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 81(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfer of rights in respect of substance</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Where prescribed information with respect to a substance has been provided under subsection (1), (3) or (4) by a person who subsequently transfers the right or privilege in relation to the substance for which the information was provided, the information is, subject to any conditions that may be prescribed, deemed to have been provided by the transferee of that right or privilege.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 81(6) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsections (1), (3) and (4) do not apply to</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 81(8) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver of information requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>On the request of any person to whom subsection (1), (3) or (4) applies, the Minister may waive any of the requirements to provide information under that subsection if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Subsections 82(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver of information requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the request of any person required under subsection (1) to provide information, the Minister may waive any of the requirements for prescribed information if one of the conditions specified in paragraphs 81(8)(a) to (c) is met and, in that case, subsections 81(9) to (13) apply with respect to the waiver.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Text>Paragraphs 89(1)(c) and (d) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting the information to be provided to the Minister under subsection 81(1), (3) or (4) or section 82;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>prescribing dates on or before which information shall be provided under subsection 81(1), (3) or (4);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 106(1) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Manufacture or import of living organisms</MarginalNote><Label>106</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a living organism is not specified on the Domestic Substances List, no person shall manufacture or import the living organism unless</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 106(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 106(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfer of rights in respect of substance</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Where prescribed information with respect to a substance has been provided under subsection (1), (3) or (4) by a person who subsequently transfers the right or privilege in relation to the substance for which the information was provided, the information is, subject to any conditions that may be prescribed, deemed to have been provided by the transferee of that right or privilege.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 106(6) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsections (1), (3) and (4) do not apply to</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 106(8) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver of information requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>On the request of any person to whom subsection (1), (3) or (4) applies, the Minister may waive any of the requirements to provide information under that subsection if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>Subsections 107(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver of information requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the request of any person required under subsection (1) to provide information, the Minister may waive any of the requirements for prescribed information if one of the conditions specified in paragraphs 106(8)(a) to (c) is met and, in that case, subsections 106(9) to (13) apply with respect to the waiver.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>Paragraphs 114(1)(c) and (d) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting the information that shall be provided to the Minister under subsection 106(1), (3) or (4) or section 107 and the form and manner in which it is to be provided;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>prescribing dates on or before which information shall be provided under subsection 106(1), (3) or (4);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 272(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 16(3) or (4), any of subsections 81(1), (3), (4), (10), (11) and (14), 84(2) and 96(3) and (4), section 101, any of subsections 106(1), (3), (4), (10) and (11) and 109(2), section 117 or 123, any of subsections 124(1), (2) and (3), 125(1), (2), (3), (4) and (5), 126(1) and (2) and 139(1), section 142 or 144, subsection 150(3) or (4), section 152, subsection 153(1), section 154, subsection 155(5), section 171 or 181, subsection 185(1), 186(2), 189(1), 202(3) or (4) or 213(3) or (4), paragraph 228(a) or subsection 238(1);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 272(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>contravenes a prohibition imposed under subsection 82(1), paragraph 84(1)(b), subsection 107(1), paragraph 109(1)(b) or subsection 186(1) or 225(4);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Subparagraph 296(1)(b)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in respect of the contravention of subsection 16(4), 81(1), (3) or (4), 82(1), 84(2) or 96(4), section 99, subsection 106(1), (3) or (4), 107(1), 109(1) or (2), 119(1), 148(1), 202(4) or 213(4) or section 227 or 228, or any obligation or prohibition arising from any of those provisions,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Subsection 343(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Examen permanent</MarginalNote><Label>343</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Tous les cinq ans après l’entrée en vigueur de la présente loi, celle-ci est soumise à l’examen d’un comité, soit de la Chambre des communes, soit du Sénat, soit mixte, désigné ou constitué pour examiner son application.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 32</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada National Parks Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Subsection 12(1) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation du public</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le ministre favorise, le cas échéant, la participation du public à l’échelle nationale, régionale et locale — notamment la participation des organisations autochtones, des organismes constitués dans le cadre d’accords sur des revendications territoriales et des représentants des collectivités —, tant à la création des parcs qu’à l’élaboration de la politique et des règlements à leur égard, des plans directeurs, de l’aménagement des terres et du développement des collectivités et des autres mesures qu’il juge utiles.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>Paragraph 33(2)(a) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>être compatible avec le plan directeur du parc où est située la collectivité;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>The first paragraph of the description of Glacier National Park of Canada in Part 1 of Schedule 1 to the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>Toutes les latitudes et longitudes indiquées ci-après font référence au Système géodésique nord-américain de 1927 et tous les accidents topographiques indiqués sont conformes à la première édition de la carte « Map Compilation and Reproduction » MCR 219 (Parcs nationaux des Glaciers et du Mont-Revelstoke) compilée à partir des cartes 82N/3, 82N/4, 82N/5, 82N/6, 82L/16 et 82M/1 de la série 1:50 000 du système national de référence cartographique et d’information fournie par Environnement Canada Parcs; ladite carte MCR a été produite à l’échelle de 1:70 000 par la Direction des levés et de la cartographie, Énergie, Mines et Ressources Canada, 1987;</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>The thirty-seventh paragraph of the description of Jasper National Park of Canada in Part 2 of Schedule 1 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>Said parcel containing about 11 228 square kilometres;</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>The description of Georgian Bay Islands National Park of Canada in Part 5 of Schedule 1 to the French version of the Act is amended by replacing “Baie Georgienne” and “Île Gray” with “baie Georgienne” and “île Gray”, respectively.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>The title of subpart (3) of Part 13 of Schedule 1 to the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><GroupHeading format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText>(3) Parc national Quttinirpaaq du Canada</TitleText></GroupHeading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>The description of Quttinirpaaq National Park of Canada in Part 13 of Schedule 1 to the French version of the Act is amended by replacing “Île d’Ellesmere” with “île d’Ellesmere”.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The second paragraph of the description of Mingan Archipelago National Park Reserve of Canada in Schedule 2 to the French version of the Act is amended by replacing “l’Île au Perroquet” with “l’île au Perroquet”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The fourth paragraph of the description of Mingan Archipelago National Park Reserve of Canada in Schedule 2 to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>Notwithstanding the generality of the foregoing, the following Isles and Islets (without cadastral designation) forming part of the Fief and Seigneurie of the Isles and Islets of Mingan are not included in the present description, namely: Perroquet Island, Havre de Mingan Island, Calculot des Betchouanes Island, De la Maison Island, Wreck Island, Innu Island and that part of Fright Island described in a deed registered at the Saguenay Registry Office on January 15, 1952, under number 13630.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 26</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Shipping Act, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>Paragraph 40(1)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsection 20(2) (failure to return suspended or cancelled Canadian maritime document); and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>The heading before section 87 and sections 87 to 89 of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Brevets</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Personnes occupant un poste à bord</MarginalNote><Label>87</Label><Text>Toute personne occupant à bord d’un bâtiment canadien un poste à l’égard duquel un brevet est exigé sous le régime de la présente partie doit être titulaire du brevet et en respecter les modalités.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Citoyen canadien et résident permanent</MarginalNote><Label>88</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Seuls les citoyens canadiens et les <DefinitionRef>résidents permanents</DefinitionRef> au sens du paragraphe 2(1) de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur l’immigration et la protection des réfugiés</XRefExternal> peuvent être titulaires d’un brevet d’aptitude délivré sous le régime de la présente partie.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Brevet étranger</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le ministre peut, à la demande d’une personne visée au paragraphe (1), délivrer un brevet d’aptitude relativement à certaines exigences prévues sous le régime de la présente loi au titulaire d’un brevet d’aptitude délivré en vertu de lois étrangères s’il est convaincu que les exigences afférentes à ce dernier brevet sont égales ou supérieures à celles prévues sous le régime de la présente loi. Il peut, au préalable, exiger que le titulaire subisse l’examen qu’il précise.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Acceptation d’un brevet étranger</MarginalNote><Label>89</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Dans le cas où le gouvernement d’un État étranger a conclu avec le gouvernement du Canada un arrangement réciproque en vue d’accepter, en remplacement des brevets d’aptitude délivrés par cet État, les brevets d’aptitude délivrés sous le régime de la présente partie, le ministre peut ordonner, sous réserve des conditions qu’il peut imposer, que le brevet d’aptitude étranger soit accepté en remplacement du brevet d’aptitude prévu par la présente partie, s’il est convaincu que les exigences afférentes au premier brevet sont égales ou supérieures à celles afférentes au second.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension ou révocation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le brevet ainsi accepté peut, seulement en ce qui concerne sa validité au Canada, être suspendu ou révoqué par le ministre comme s’il s’agissait d’un document maritime canadien; le brevet ainsi suspendu ou révoqué doit être remis par le titulaire au ministre, qui le renvoie aussitôt à l’autorité qui l’a délivré.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 90(1) to (3) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Communication de renseignements au ministre</MarginalNote><Label>90</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le médecin ou l’optométriste qui a des motifs raisonnables de croire que l’état du titulaire d’un brevet est susceptible de constituer un risque pour la sécurité maritime fait part sans délai de son avis motivé au ministre.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Devoir du patient</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Quiconque est titulaire d’un brevet assorti de normes médicales ou optométriques est tenu de dévoiler ce fait avant l’examen au médecin ou à l’optométriste.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Utilisation des renseignements</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Le ministre peut utiliser ces renseignements pour décider si le titulaire du brevet satisfait aux exigences afférentes à celui-ci.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 90(5) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Présomption</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Le titulaire du brevet est présumé avoir consenti à la communication au ministre des renseignements portant sur son état dans les circonstances qui sont mentionnées au paragraphe (1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 100(c) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>c)</Label><Text>déterminer les catégories et classes de certificats et de brevets qui peuvent être délivrés relativement aux postes à bord des bâtiments — ou catégories de bâtiments — canadiens;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 100(e) and (f) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>e)</Label><Text>régir la façon de déterminer si une personne satisfait aux exigences visées à l’alinéa b) ou si un candidat possède les qualifications requises aux termes de l’alinéa d) pour l’obtention d’une catégorie ou classe de brevet d’aptitude ou d’autre document maritime canadien;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>f)</Label><Text>préciser les modalités dont sont assortis les brevets d’aptitude et autres documents maritimes canadiens délivrés sous le régime de la présente partie;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>44</Label><Text>Section 121 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Aggravating factors</MarginalNote><Label>121</Label><Text>The court, in determining the penalty to be imposed under section 120, shall take into account whether</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>bodily harm or death occurred, or the life or safety of any person was endangered, as a result of the commission of the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the commission of the offence was for the benefit of, at the direction of or in association with a criminal organization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the commission of the offence was for profit, whether or not any profit was realized; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a person was subjected to humiliating or degrading treatment, including with respect to work or health conditions or sexual exploitation as a result of the commission of the offence.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 148(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>not carry to Canada a person who is prescribed or does not hold a prescribed document, or whom an officer directs not to be carried;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 148(1)(d) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>d)</Label><Text>fournir les documents, rapports et renseignements réglementaires;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 148(1)(f) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>f)</Label><Text>sur avis d’un agent ou dans les cas prévus par règlement faire sortir du Canada la personne qu’il a amenée ou fait amener;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 148(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Saisie</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Tout ou partie de la sûreté qu’il a fournie et tout véhicule ou autre marchandise réglementaire dont il est le propriétaire ou l’exploitant peuvent, si l’intéressé contrevient aux obligations prévues par la présente loi, être retenus, saisis ou confisqués au profit de Sa Majesté du chef du Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 7</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Yukon Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>46</Label><Text>Paragraph 34(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the consolidated financial statements present fairly, in all material respects and in accordance with accounting principles recommended for the public sector by that organization or its successor, the financial position of the Yukon Government as at the end of the fiscal year and the results of its operations in, and changes in its financial position for, the fiscal year; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 64(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Garantie du Yukon</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement du Yukon s’engage à indemniser le gouvernement fédéral, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celui-ci, de tous les frais et dépens — y compris les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement — entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant de faits — actes ou omissions — qui sont imputables à lui ou à ses employés et mandataires à l’égard :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 64(2) and (3) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indemnisation: obligations au titre de l’accord</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement du Yukon s’engage à indemniser le gouvernement fédéral, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celui-ci, de tous les frais et dépens — y compris les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement — entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant d’un manquement de sa part ou de celle de ses employés et mandataires aux obligations qu’impose l’accord au gouvernement du Yukon relativement aux fonctionnaires fédéraux.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Garantie envers les premières nations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement du Yukon s’engage à indemniser les premières nations, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celles-ci, de tous les frais et dépens — y compris les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement — entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant de faits — actes ou omissions — qui sont imputables à lui ou à ses employés et mandataires à l’égard de la remise en état de lieux effectuée, en conformité avec l’accord, sur les terres de ces premières nations.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 65(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Garantie du gouvernement fédéral</MarginalNote><Label>65</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement fédéral s’engage à indemniser le gouvernement du Yukon, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celui-ci, de tous les frais et dépens — y compris les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement — entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant de faits — actes ou omissions — qui sont imputables à lui ou à ses employés et mandataires à l’égard :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 65(2) and (3) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Garantie du gouvernement fédéral</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement fédéral s’engage à indemniser le gouvernement du Yukon, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celui-ci, de tous les frais et dépens — y compris les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement — entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant de la prise de mesures au titre des articles 49 à 51 ou 55.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Garantie envers les premières nations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement fédéral s’engage à indemniser les premières nations, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celles-ci, de tous les frais et dépens — y compris les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement — entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant de faits — actes ou omissions — qui sont imputables à lui ou à ses employés et mandataires à l’égard de la remise en état de lieux effectuée, en conformité avec l’accord, sur les terres de ces premières nations.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 29</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Species at Risk Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>49</Label><Text>Subsection 79(2) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Species at Risk Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Réalisations escomptées</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>La personne détermine les effets nocifs du projet sur l’espèce et son habitat essentiel et, si le projet est réalisé, veille à ce que des mesures compatibles avec tout programme de rétablissement et tout plan d’action applicable soient prises en vue de les éviter ou de les amoindrir et les surveiller.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 9; 2012, c. 19, s. 658</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>First Nations Fiscal Management Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>50</Label><Text>Subsection 41(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Fiscal Management Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment by AFOA Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>AFOA Canada, or any other body prescribed by regulation, shall appoint up to three additional directors to hold office during pleasure for a term not exceeding five years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 34; 2013, c. 40, s. 205</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Employment and Social Development Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 71(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Employment and Social Development Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>71</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, the Minister may administer or enforce electronically the Acts, programs and activities referred to in paragraphs 70.1(a) to (e.1), (g) and (h), the Minister of Labour may administer or enforce electronically the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> and the Commission may administer or enforce electronically the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, including for the purposes of</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2005, c. 47, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Wage Earner Protection Program Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>wages</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wage Earner Protection Program Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>wages</DefinedTermEn> includes salaries, commissions, compensation for services rendered, vacation pay, termination pay, severance pay and any other amounts prescribed by regulation. (<DefinedTermFr>salaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>eligible wages</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>wages other than termination pay and severance pay that were earned during the longer of the following periods:</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (b) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>eligible wages</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>termination pay and severance pay that relate to employment that ended during the period referred to in paragraph (a). (<DefinedTermFr>salaire admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>53</Label><Text>Subsection 7(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Amount of payment</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The amount that may be paid under this Act to an individual is the amount of eligible wages owing to the individual up to a maximum of an amount equal to four times the maximum weekly insurable earnings under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, less any amount prescribed by regulation.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 19</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Jobs, Growth and Long-term Prosperity Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>54</Label><Text>Section 309 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Jobs, Growth and Long-term Prosperity Act</XRefExternal> and the heading “Canadian Wheat Board Act” before it are repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 2, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Northwest Territories Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>55</Label><Text>Subsection 59(5) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Montant de l’indemnité</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>La personne ainsi choisie établit la valeur des améliorations par un moyen semblable à l’établissement de la valeur réelle juste de l’amélioration — au moment où le gouverneur en conseil reprend ou obtient, du fait de la renonciation du commissaire, la gestion et la maîtrise des terres —, déterminée conformément à la méthode de calcul de la valeur réelle juste des améliorations foncières prévue dans les lois de la législature d’application générale relatives aux évaluations de taxes foncières. Le montant de l’indemnité doit correspondre à cette valeur.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>56</Label><Text>Paragraph (e) of the definition <DefinedTermFr>intérêt existant</DefinedTermFr> in section 68 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>e)</Label><Text>tout permis qui :</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>soit est en vigueur à cette date et dont la délivrance était assujettie à la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>soit est visé au sous-alinéa (i) et est renouvelé ou remplace un permis visé à ce sous-alinéa ou y succède, si le droit au renouvellement, au remplacement ou à la succession existait à cette date.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>57</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 73(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Indemnisation par le gouvernement territorial</MarginalNote><Label>73</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement des Territoires du Nord-Ouest indemnise le gouvernement du Canada, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celui-ci, des frais et dépens, notamment les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement, entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant de faits — actes ou omissions — qui sont imputables à lui ou à ses employés et mandataires et qui sont survenus :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 73(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indemnisation : obligations au titre de l’accord</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement des Territoires du Nord-Ouest indemnise le gouvernement du Canada, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celui-ci, des frais et dépens, notamment les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement, entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant d’un manquement de sa part ou de celle de ses employés et mandataires aux obligations que lui impose l’accord relativement aux fonctionnaires fédéraux.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>58</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 74(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Indemnisation par le gouvernement du Canada</MarginalNote><Label>74</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement du Canada indemnise le gouvernement des Territoires du Nord-Ouest, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celui-ci, des frais et dépens, notamment les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement, entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant de faits — actes ou omissions — qui sont imputables à lui ou à ses employés et mandataires et qui sont survenus :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 74(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indemnisation des parties autochtones</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le gouvernement du Canada indemnise la partie autochtone, ainsi que les employés et mandataires de celle-ci, des frais et dépens, notamment les sommes versées pour transiger ou pour exécuter un jugement, entraînés par toute réclamation ou tout recours exercés contre eux et découlant de faits — actes ou omissions — qui sont imputables à lui ou à ses employés et mandataires et qui sont survenus à l’égard de mesures d’assainissement exécutées au titre de l’accord sur des terres de cette partie autochtone visées par un règlement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>59</Label><Text>Section 75 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Réserve : consentement écrit</MarginalNote><Label>75</Label><Text>En cas de règlement hors cour, les gouvernements du Canada et des Territoires du Nord-Ouest, les parties autochtones et leurs employés et mandataires ne peuvent être indemnisés en application des articles 73 ou 74 sans le consentement écrit du gouvernement qui est tenu d’indemniser.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 39</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Economic Action Plan 2014 Act, No. 2</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>60</Label><Text>Section 105 of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Economic Action Plan 2014 Act, No. 2</XRefExternal> is amended by replacing the subsection 8.3(3) that it enacts with the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The prescribed date referred to in subsection (1) may not be later than the later of the date of registration of the design and 30 months after the filing date of the application for registration or, if a request for priority is made in respect of the application, the earliest filing date of a previously regularly filed application on which the request for priority is based.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>61</Label><Text>Subsection 111(3) of the English version of the Act is amended by replacing the paragraph 25(g.2) that it enacts with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g.2)</Label><Text>respecting the recording or registration of transfers of applications for the registration of designs or transfers of registered designs;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>Terminology</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants”</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Text>Every reference to “Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants” is replaced by “Chartered Professional Accountants of Canada” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph 12(3.1)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pension Benefits Standards Act, 1985</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trust and Loan Companies Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 313(4), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 328(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 308(4),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 323(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 840(4), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsection 855(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 331(4),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 346(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 641(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsection 887(4), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsection 902(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cooperative Credit Associations Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 292(4), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 307(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nunavut Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 45, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 46(1)(a);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>subsection 23(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Surface Rights Board Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>paragraph 35(5)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Civil Air Navigation Services Commercialization Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 39(5), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 40(4);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>subsection 26(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>subsection 35(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Pension Investment Board Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 33, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 34(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nunavut Waters and Nunavut Surface Rights Tribunal Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 32(2), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 114(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>subsection 28(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Environmental and Socio-economic Assessment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Oil and Gas and Moneys Management Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>sections 48 and 49, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 50(1);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(p)</Label><Text>subsection 58(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pooled Registered Pension Plans Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(q)</Label><Text>subsection 39(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nunavut Planning and Project Assessment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Deletion of “but not limited to”</MarginalNote><Label>63</Label><Text>The English version of the following provisions is amended by striking out “but not limited to”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the portion of paragraph 21(2)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International River Improvements Act</XRefExternal> before subparagraph (i);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the portion of paragraph 11.7(2)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Wildlife Act</XRefExternal> before subparagraph (i);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the portion of paragraph 11.21(3)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Migratory Birds Convention Act, 1994</XRefExternal> before subparagraph (i);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the portion of the definition <DefinitionRef>federal work or undertaking</DefinitionRef> in subsection 3(1) before paragraph (a),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 47(1) before paragraph (a),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 65(3),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 91(5) before paragraph (a),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subparagraph 115(1)(a)(ii),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 209(1) before paragraph (a),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 298(1) before paragraph (a),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>the portion of section 309 before paragraph (a), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>the portion of section 325 before paragraph (a);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the portion of section 10.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Species at Risk Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Antarctic Environmental Protection Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 26(1)(a), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the portion of paragraph 37.03(3)(f) before subparagraph (i).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><TitleText>Repeals</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1986, c. 46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Maintenance of Ports Operations Act, 1986</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>64</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Maintenance of Ports Operations Act, 1986</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1987, c. 40</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Postal Services Continuation Act, 1987</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>65</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Postal Services Continuation Act, 1987</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Postal Services Continuation Act, 1991</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>66</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Postal Services Continuation Act, 1991</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1994, c. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>West Coast Ports Operations Act, 1994</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>67</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">West Coast Ports Operations Act, 1994</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>West Coast Ports Operations Act, 1995</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>68</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">West Coast Ports Operations Act, 1995</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Maintenance of Railway Operations Act, 1995</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>69</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Maintenance of Railway Operations Act, 1995</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1997, c. 34</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Postal Services Continuation Act, 1997</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>70</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Postal Services Continuation Act, 1997</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2007, c. 8</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Railway Continuation Act, 2007</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>71</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Continuation Act, 2007</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 4</Label><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 7</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>72</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinitionRef>other Act</DefinitionRef> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subparagraph <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal>(l)(ii) of this Act comes into force before section 72 of the other Act, then on the day on which that section 72 comes into force, the portion of subsection 34(1) of the other Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Annual audit</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Auditor General of Yukon shall audit the accounts, including those related to the Yukon Consolidated Revenue Fund, and financial transactions of the Yukon Government in each fiscal year in accordance with auditing standards recommended by the Chartered Professional Accountants of Canada or its successor and shall express his or her opinion as to whether</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 72 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subparagraph <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal>(l)(ii) of this Act, then that section 72 is deemed to have come into force before that subparagraph <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal>(l)(ii).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 283 of the other Act comes into force before paragraph <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal>(g) of this Act, then that paragraph <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal>(g) is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If section 283 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as paragraph <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal>(g) of this Act, then that paragraph <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal>(g) is deemed to have come into force before that section 283.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>Bill S-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>73</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill S-2, introduced in the 1st session of the 42nd Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Motor Vehicle Safety for Canadians Act</XRefExternal> (referred to in this section as the “other Act”) receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 8 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 8 of the other Act, then that section 8 is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 8 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>Bill S-5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>74</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill S-5, introduced in the 1st session of the 42nd Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Tobacco Act and the Non-smokers’ Health Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</XRefExternal> (referred to in this section as the “other Act”) receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection 68(2) of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal> is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before subsection 68(2) of the other Act, then that subsection 68(2) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If subsection 68(2) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal> is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>