<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>S-233</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Customs Act and the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (presentation and reporting requirements)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Conveyance Presentation and Reporting Requirements Modernization Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Customs Act and the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (presentation and reporting requirements)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2017</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="">4211621</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to exempt certain persons from the requirement to present themselves to a customs officer if</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>they enter Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or the airspace over Canada on board a conveyance directly from outside Canada and then leave Canada on board the conveyance, as long as they did not land in Canada and the conveyance did not stop while in Canadian waters, including inland waters, or did not land while in Canada; or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>they leave Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or the airspace over Canada on board a conveyance and then re-enter Canada on board the conveyance, as long as they did not land outside Canada and the conveyance did not stop or land while outside Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>unless the officer requires them to comply with subsections 11(1) and (3) of that Act.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>It also exempts the goods imported on board such a conveyance from the requirement to be reported at a customs office unless an officer otherwise requires. Further, it adds a regulation-making authority for defining the expression “make contact with a conveyance”.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Finally, this enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> by adding regulation-making authorities, including one for the exemption of certain persons or categories of persons from the requirement to appear for an examination to determine their right to enter or remain in Canada. It also allows an officer to require these persons or categories of persons to appear for such an examination despite that exemption.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Conveyance Presentation and Reporting Requirements Modernization Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 11(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Entry and departure</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, subsections (1) and (3) do not apply to any of the following persons, unless an officer requires them to comply with those subsections:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person who enters Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or the airspace over Canada on board a conveyance directly from outside Canada and then leaves Canada on board the conveyance, as long as the person was continuously on board that conveyance while in Canada and</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of a conveyance other than an aircraft, the person did not land in Canada and the conveyance did not anchor, moor or make contact with another conveyance while in Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of an aircraft, the conveyance did not land while in Canada; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person who leaves Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or the airspace over Canada on board a conveyance and then re-enters Canada on board the conveyance, as long as the person was continuously on board that conveyance while outside Canada and</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of a conveyance other than an aircraft, the person did not land outside Canada and the conveyance did not anchor, moor or make contact with another conveyance while outside Canada, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of an aircraft, the conveyance did not land while outside Canada.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 12(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — entry and departure</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, unless an officer otherwise requires, this section does not apply in respect of goods on board a conveyance</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that enters Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or the airspace over Canada directly from outside Canada and then leaves Canada, as long as</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of a conveyance other than an aircraft, the conveyance did not anchor, moor or make contact with another conveyance while in Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of an aircraft, the conveyance did not land while in Canada; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that leaves Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or the airspace over Canada and then re-enters Canada, as long as</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of a conveyance other than an aircraft, the conveyance did not anchor, moor or make contact with another conveyance while outside Canada, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of an aircraft, the conveyance did not land while outside Canada.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>12.01</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for the purposes of sections 11 and 12, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing the circumstances under which persons, goods or classes thereof on board a conveyance, or classes thereof, are required to present themselves or to be reported, as the case may be, despite subsection 11(5) or 12(5); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>defining the expression “make contact with another conveyance” for the purposes of subsections 11(5) and 12(5) and prescribing the circumstances under which a conveyance or a class thereof makes contact with another conveyance.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 18(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Examination by officer</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, every person seeking to enter Canada must appear for an examination to determine whether that person has a right to enter Canada or is or may become authorized to enter and remain in Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 18 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of officer</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Even though a person seeking to enter Canada is not, in accordance with regulations made under subsection 26(2), required to appear for an examination, an officer may require the person to do so.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 26 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 26(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemptions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The regulations may exempt persons or categories of persons from the application of section 18 and prescribe the conditions under which the exemption applies.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>If Bill C-21, introduced in the 1st session of the 42nd Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Customs Act</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the first day on which both section 3 of that Act and section 4 of this Act are in force, subsections 95(1) to (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>95</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1.1) and regulations made under paragraph (2)(a), all goods that are exported shall be reported at any prescribed time and place and in any prescribed manner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — entering or leaving temporarily</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Subject to regulations made under paragraphs (2)(c) and (d), subsection (1) does not apply in respect of goods on board a conveyance</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that enters Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or the airspace over Canada directly from outside Canada and then leaves Canada, as long as</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of a conveyance other than an aircraft, the conveyance did not anchor, moor or make contact with another conveyance while in Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of an aircraft, the conveyance did not land while in Canada; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that leaves Canadian waters, including the inland waters, or the airspace over Canada and then re-enters Canada, as long as</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of a conveyance other than an aircraft, the conveyance did not anchor, moor or make contact with another conveyance while outside Canada, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of an aircraft, the conveyance did not land while outside Canada.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of officer</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>However, an officer may require that goods that are exempted under subsection (1.1) or regulations made under paragraph (2)(a) be reported under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing the classes of goods that are exempted from the requirements of subsection (1) and the circumstances in which any of those classes of goods are not so exempted;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prescribing the classes of persons who are required to report goods under subsection (1) and the circumstances in which they are so required;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>prescribing the circumstances in which goods, or classes of goods, on board a conveyance, or a class of conveyances, are required to be reported despite subsection (1.1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>defining the expression “make contact with another conveyance” for the purposes of subsection (1.1) and prescribing the circumstances in which a conveyance or class of conveyances makes contact with another conveyance.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>