<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-238</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the development of a national strategy for the safe and environmentally sound disposal of lamps containing mercury</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">National Strategy for Safe and Environmentally Sound Disposal of Lamps Containing Mercury Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Strategy for Safe and Environmentally Sound Disposal of Lamps Containing Mercury Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>16</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2017</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-02-19">421122</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment provides for the development and implementation of a national strategy to promote the safe and environmentally sound disposal of lamps containing mercury.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Strategy for Safe and Environmentally Sound Disposal of Lamps Containing Mercury Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Strategy</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National strategy</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The Minister of the Environment, in cooperation with representatives of the provincial and territorial governments and with representatives of other interested governments in Canada that are responsible for the environment, and in consultation with all interested persons or organizations that he or she considers appropriate, must develop a national strategy for the safe and environmentally sound disposal of lamps containing mercury. The strategy may include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the identification of practices for the safe and environmentally sound disposal of those lamps;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the establishment of guidelines for facilities where activities involved in the safe and environmentally sound disposal of those lamps are carried out; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the development of a plan to promote public awareness of the importance of those lamps being disposed of safely and in an environmentally sound manner.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of the Environment must prepare a report setting out the national strategy and cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the later of December 31, 2018, and the day that is two years after the day on which this Act receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must post the report on the departmental website within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review and Report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Within five years of the tabling of the report referred to in section 3, and every five years after that, the Minister of the Environment must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national strategy, setting out his or her conclusions and recommendations regarding the strategy, and cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting following the completion of the report.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>