<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber><?Pub Caret1?>C-16</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canadian Human Rights Act and the Criminal Code</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Canadian Human Rights Act and the Criminal Code</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canadian Human Rights Act and the Criminal Code</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>13</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2017</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-5-13">90796</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal> to add gender identity and gender expression to the list of prohibited grounds of discrimination.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The enactment also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to extend the protection against hate propaganda set out in that Act to any section of the public that is distinguished by gender identity or expression and to clearly set out that evidence that an offence was motivated by bias, prejudice or hate based on gender identity or expression constitutes an aggravating circumstance that a court must take into consideration when it imposes a sentence.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. H-6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1998, c. 9, s. 9; 2012, c. 1, s. 137(E)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to extend the laws in Canada to give effect, within the purview of matters coming within the legislative authority of Parliament, to the principle that all individuals should have an opportunity equal with other individuals to make for themselves the lives that they are able and wish to have and to have their needs accommodated, consistent with their duties and obligations as members of society, without being hindered in or prevented from doing so by discriminatory practices based on race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, age, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity or expression, marital status, family status, disability or conviction for an offence for which a pardon has been granted or in respect of which a record suspension has been ordered.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 14, s. 2; 2012, c. 1, s. 138(E)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 3(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibited grounds of discrimination</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For all purposes of this Act, the prohibited grounds of discrimination are race, national or ethnic origin, colour, religion, age, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity or expression, marital status, family status, disability and conviction for an offence for which a pardon has been granted or in respect of which a record suspension has been ordered.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 31, s. 12</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 318(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>identifiable group</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>identifiable group</DefinedTermEn> means any section of the public distinguished by colour, race, religion, national or ethnic origin, age, sex, sexual orientation, gender identity or expression, or mental or physical disability.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 22, s. 6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Subparagraph 718.2(a)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>evidence that the offence was motivated by bias, prejudice or hate based on race, national or ethnic origin, language, colour, religion, sex, age, mental or physical disability, sexual orientation, or gender identity or expression, or on any other similar factor,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>