<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>C-20</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act for granting to Her Majesty certain sums of money for the federal public administration for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2017</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Appropriation Act No. 3, 2016–17</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Appropriation Act No. 3, 2016–17</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>6</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2016</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-5-27">90800</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment grants the sum of $7,014,650,659 towards defraying charges and expenses of the federal public administration for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2017 that are not otherwise provided for.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>MOST GRACIOUS SOVEREIGN,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas it appears by message from His Excellency the Right Honourable David Johnston, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada, and the Estimates accompanying that message, that the sums mentioned below are required to defray certain expenses of the federal public administration, not otherwise provided for, for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2017, and for other purposes connected with the federal public administration;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>May it therefore please Your Majesty, that it may be enacted, and be it enacted by the Queen’s Most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, that:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Appropriation Act No. 3, 2016–17</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>$7,014,650,659 granted for 2016-17</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>There may be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund a sum not exceeding in the aggregate $7,014,650,659 towards defraying the various charges and expenses of the federal public administration for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2017, not otherwise provided for, being the total of the amounts of the items set out in the Supplementary Estimates (A) for that fiscal year as set out in Schedules 1 and 2.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transfers of appropriations</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The transfers of appropriations set out in the Estimates referred to in section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> are deemed to have been authorized on April 1, 2016.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose of each item</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The amount authorized by this Act to be paid in respect of an item may be paid only for the purposes, and subject to any terms and conditions, specified in the item.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effective date</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The provisions of each item in Schedules 1 and 2 are deemed to have effect as of April 1, 2016.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Commitments</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where an item in the Estimates referred to in section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> confers authority to enter into commitments up to an amount stated in those Estimates or increases the amount up to which commitments may be entered into under any other Act, or where a commitment is to be entered into under subsection (2), the commitment may be entered into in accordance with the terms of that item or in accordance with that subsection if the amount of the commitment proposed to be entered into, together with all previous commitments entered into in accordance with this section or under that other Act, does not exceed the total amount of the commitment authority stated in that item or calculated in accordance with that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commitment limits — revenue-spending authority</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an item in the Estimates referred to in section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> or a provision of any Act confers authority to spend revenues, commitments may be entered into in accordance with the terms of that item or provision up to an amount equal to the aggregate of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount, if any, appropriated in respect of that item or provision, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>whichever is greater: the amount of revenues actually received or the amount of the estimated revenues set out in those Estimates for that item or in respect of that provision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Adjustments in accounts of Canada — Schedule 1</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>An appropriation that is granted by this Act or any other Act and referred to in Schedule 1 may be charged after the end of the fiscal year for which the appropriation is granted at any time before the day on which the Public Accounts for that fiscal year are tabled in Parliament, for the purpose of making adjustments in the accounts of Canada for that fiscal year that do not require payments out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Adjustments in accounts of Canada — Schedule 2</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An appropriation that is granted by this Act or any other Act and referred to in Schedule 2 may be charged after the end of the fiscal year following the fiscal year for which the appropriation is granted at any time before the day on which the Public Accounts for that second fiscal year are tabled in Parliament, for the purpose of making adjustments in the accounts of Canada for that second fiscal year that do not require payments out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order of payment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, amounts appropriated by this Act and set out in Schedule 2 may be paid and applied at any time on or before March 31, 2018, so long as every payment is charged first against the relevant amount appropriated under any Act that is earliest in time until that amount is exhausted, next against the relevant amount appropriated under any other Act, including this Act, that is next in time until that amount is exhausted and so on. The balance of amounts so appropriated by this Act that have not been charged, subject to the adjustments referred to in section 37 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, lapse at the end of the fiscal year following the fiscal year ending March 31, 2017.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Public Accounts</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Amounts paid or applied under the authority of this Act are to be accounted for in the Public Accounts under section 64 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule spanlanguages="yes"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 1</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Based on Supplementary Estimates (A), 2016–17, the amount granted is $6,907,856,660, which is the total of the amounts of the items set out in this Schedule.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Sums granted to Her Majesty by this Act for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2017 and the purposes for which they are granted.</Text></Provision><TableGroup pointsize="8" rowbreak="yes" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="all"><tgroup cols="4"><colspec align="center" colname="1" colwidth="7.12*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="62.48*" /><colspec align="right" colname="3" colwidth="15.20*" /><colspec align="right" colname="COLSPEC0" colwidth="15.20*" /><thead><row rowsep="1" topdouble="yes" valign="top"><entry colname="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Vote No.</entry><entry align="center" colname="2" colsep="1" valign="bottom">Items</entry><entry align="center" colname="3" colsep="1" valign="bottom">Amount ($)</entry><entry align="center" colsep="0" valign="bottom">Total ($)</entry></row></thead><tbody><row rowsep="0"><entry colname="1" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="2" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>ADMINISTRATIVE TRIBUNALS SUPPORT SERVICE OF CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="1" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Administrative Tribunals Support Service of Canada – Program expenditures and authority to make recoverable expenditures on behalf of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the Employment Insurance Operating Account</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>2,654,421</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">2,654,421</entry></row><row rowsep="0"><entry colname="1" colsep="1" rowsep="0" /><entry colname="2" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>AGRICULTURE AND AGRI-FOOD</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="1" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" /></row><row rowsep="0"><entry align="center" colname="1" colsep="1" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Agriculture and Agri-Food – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received from, and to offset expenditures incurred in the fiscal year for, collaborative research agreements and research services, the grazing and breeding activities of the Community Pasture Program, the administration of the AgriStability program, and the provision of internal support services to other organizations; and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colname="3" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>2,127,657</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="1" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Agriculture and Agri-Food – Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>7,242,500</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">9,370,157</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>ATLANTIC CANADA OPPORTUNITIES AGENCY</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Atlantic Canada Opportunities Agency – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>8,300,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">8,300,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADA COUNCIL FOR THE ARTS</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to the Canada Council for the Arts under section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Council for the Arts Act</XRefExternal>, to be used for the furtherance of the objects set out in section 8 of that Act</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>40,000,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">40,000,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADA MORTGAGE AND HOUSING CORPORATION</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>To reimburse Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation for the amounts of loans forgiven, grants, contributions and expenditures made, and losses, costs and expenses incurred under the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Housing Act</XRefExternal> or in respect of the exercise of powers or the carrying out of duties or functions conferred on the Corporation pursuant to the authority of any Act of Parliament of Canada other than the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Housing Act</XRefExternal>, in accordance with the Corporation’s authority under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation Act</XRefExternal></Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,069,800,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">1,069,800,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADIAN AIR TRANSPORT SECURITY AUTHORITY</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to the Canadian Air Transport Security Authority for operating and capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>142,272,546</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">142,272,546</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADIAN ENVIRONMENTAL ASSESSMENT AGENCY</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Environmental Assessment Agency – Program expenditures, contributions and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received during the fiscal year arising from the provision of environmental assessment services including the conduct of panel reviews, comprehensive studies, mediations, training and information publications by the Canadian Environmental Assessment Agency</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>4,679,144</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">4,679,144</entry></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADIAN FOOD INSPECTION AGENCY</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Food Inspection Agency – Operating expenditures and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>32,107,561</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Food Inspection Agency – Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>2,068,410</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">34,175,971</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADIAN HERITAGE</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Heritage – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received during the fiscal year by the Canadian Conservation Institute, the Canadian Heritage Information Network, the Canadian Audio-Visual Certification Office and the Capital Experience Program and from the provision of internal support services to other organizations, and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,363,555</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Heritage – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>87,018,263</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">88,381,818</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADIAN INSTITUTES OF HEALTH RESEARCH</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Institutes of Health Research – Operating expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,196,515</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Institutes of Health Research – The grants listed in the Estimates</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>13,550,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">14,746,515</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADIAN NORTHERN ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AGENCY</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Northern Economic Development Agency – Operating expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>4,668,559</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canadian Northern Economic Development Agency – Contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>23,763,634</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">28,432,193</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADIAN TOURISM COMMISSION</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to the Canadian Tourism Commission</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>25,000,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">25,000,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CITIZENSHIP AND IMMIGRATION</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Citizenship and Immigration – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received in a fiscal year from, and to offset related expenditures incurred in the fiscal year arising from, the provision of services related to International Experience Canada, and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>65,318,959</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Citizenship and Immigration – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions including the provision of goods and services</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>126,998,832</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">192,317,791</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AGENCY OF CANADA FOR THE REGIONS OF QUEBEC</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Economic Development Agency of Canada for the Regions of Quebec – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>15,600,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">15,600,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>EMPLOYMENT AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Employment and Social Development – Operating expenditures and</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>authority to make recoverable expenditures on behalf of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the Employment Insurance Operating Account;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend, to offset related expenditures incurred in the fiscal year, revenues received in the fiscal year arising from</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the provision of Public Access Programs Sector services,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>services to assist provinces in the administration of provincial programs funded under Labour Market Development Agreements,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>services offered on behalf of other federal government departments and/or federal government departmental corporations,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the amount charged to any Crown corporation under paragraph 14(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> in relation to the litigation costs for subrogated claims for Crown corporations, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the portion of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> departmental or agency subrogated claim settlements related to litigation costs; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>12,452,090</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Employment and Social Development – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>280,194,535</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">292,646,625</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>ENVIRONMENT</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Environment – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received from, and offset related expenditures incurred in the fiscal year for, the provision of services or the sale of information products arising from the operations of the department funded from this Vote, including research, analysis and scientific services, hydrometric surveys, regulatory and monitoring services, including oil sands, entry fees and permits and real property services, and the provision of internal support services to other organizations, and authority for the Minister of the Environment to engage consultants as may be required by different Boards at such remuneration as those Boards may determine; and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>93,571,679</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Environment – Capital expenditures and authority to make payments to provinces or municipalities as contributions towards construction done by those bodies and authority to make recoverable advances not exceeding the amount of the shares of provincial and outside agencies of the cost of joint projects including expenditures on other than federal property</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>2,867,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Environment – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions, and contributions to developing countries in accordance with the Multilateral Fund for the Implementation of the Montreal Protocol taking the form of monetary payments or the provision of goods, equipment or services</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>6,310,331</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">102,749,010</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>FEDERAL ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AGENCY FOR SOUTHERN ONTARIO</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Federal Economic Development Agency for Southern Ontario – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>22,200,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">22,200,000</entry></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>FISHERIES AND OCEANS</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Fisheries and Oceans – Operating expenditures and</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Canada’s share of expenses of the International Fisheries Commissions, authority to provide free accommodation for the International Fisheries Commissions and authority to make recoverable advances in the amounts of the shares of the International Fisheries Commissions of joint cost projects;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>authority to make recoverable advances for transportation, stevedoring and other shipping services performed on behalf of individuals, outside agencies and other governments in the course of, or arising out of, the exercise of jurisdiction in navigation, including aids to navigation and shipping;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenue received during the fiscal year in the course of, or arising from, the activities of the Canadian Coast Guard and for the provision of internal support services to other organizations; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>131,283,518</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Fisheries and Oceans – Capital expenditures and authority to make payments to provinces, municipalities and local or private authorities as contributions towards construction done by those bodies and authority for the purchase and disposal of commercial fishing vessels</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>138,943,032</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Fisheries and Oceans – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>28,939,067</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">299,165,617</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>FOREIGN AFFAIRS, TRADE AND DEVELOPMENT</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development – Operating expenditures, including those related to the appointment of Canada’s representatives abroad, to the staff of those officials, and to the assignment of Canadians to the staffs of international organizations and authority to make recoverable advances in amounts not exceeding the amounts of the shares of such organizations; expenditures in respect of the provision of office accommodation for the International Civil Aviation Organization; recoverable expenditures for assistance to and repatriation of distressed Canadian citizens and Canadian residents living abroad, including their dependants; and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received in a fiscal year from, and to offset related expenditures incurred in the fiscal year arising from, the provision of services related to: training services provided by the Canadian Foreign Service Institute; trade and education fairs, trade missions and other international business development services; investment development services; international telecommunication services; departmental publications; other services provided abroad to other government departments, agencies, Crown corporations and other non-federal organizations; specialized consular services; and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>39,074,405</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">39,074,405</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>HEALTH</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Health – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to spend revenues to offset expenditures incurred in the fiscal year arising from the provision of services or the sale of products related to health protection, regulatory activities and medical services, and the provision of internal support services to other organizations, and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>53,561,618</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Health – Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>6,223,645</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Health – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions, in the form of monetary payments or the provision of goods or services</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>101,715,753</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">161,501,016</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>INDIAN AFFAIRS AND NORTHERN DEVELOPMENT</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Indian Affairs and Northern Development – Operating expenditures and</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received in a fiscal year through the provision of internal support services to other organizations to offset associated expenditures incurred in the fiscal year;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>expenditures on works, buildings and equipment and expenditures and recoverable expenditures in respect of services provided and work performed on other than federal property;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>authority to provide, in respect of Indian and Inuit economic development activities, for the capacity development for Indians and Inuit and the furnishing of materials and equipment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>authority to sell electric power to private consumers in remote locations when alternative local sources of supply are not available, in accordance with terms and conditions approved by the Governor in Council; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>204,799,222</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Indian Affairs and Northern Development – Capital expenditures and</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>expenditures on buildings, works, land and equipment, the operation, control and ownership of which may be transferred to provincial governments on terms and conditions approved by the Governor in Council, or to Indian bands, groups of Indians or individual Indians at the discretion of the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development, and such expenditures on other than federal property; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>authority to make recoverable expenditures in amounts not exceeding the shares of provincial governments of expenditures on roads and related works</Text></Provision></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>13,266,026</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Indian Affairs and Northern Development – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>981,831,046</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>L20a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Loans to First Nations in British Columbia for the purpose of supporting their participation in the British Columbia Treaty Commission process</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>30,400,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">1,230,296,294</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>INDUSTRY</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Industry – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenue received during the fiscal year, to offset expenditures incurred in the fiscal year, arising from the provision of internal support services to the Canadian Intellectual Property Office and to other organizations, communications research, bankruptcy and corporations and from services and regulatory processes, specifically pre-merger notification filings, advance ruling certificates, advisory opinions and photocopies, provided under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Competition Act</XRefExternal>, and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>7,933,481</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Industry – Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>8,518,900</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Industry – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>522,431,813</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">538,884,194</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>MARINE ATLANTIC INC.</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to Marine Atlantic Inc. in respect of the costs of the management of the Company, payments for capital purposes and for transportation activities including the following water transportation services pursuant to contracts with Her Majesty: Newfoundland ferries and terminals</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>6,100,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">6,100,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>NATIONAL ARTS CENTRE CORPORATION</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to the National Arts Centre Corporation for operating expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>38,000,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">38,000,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>NATIONAL GALLERY OF CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to the National Gallery of Canada for operating and capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,000,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">1,000,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>NATIONAL MUSEUM OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to the National Museum of Science and Technology for operating and capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>45,624,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">45,624,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>NATIONAL RESEARCH COUNCIL OF CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>National Research Council of Canada – Operating expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>924,300</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>National Research Council of Canada – Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>3,350,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>National Research Council of Canada – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions, including the provision of goods and services for the international Thirty Meter Telescope Observatory</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>50,000,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">54,274,300</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>NATURAL RESOURCES</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Natural Resources – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received during the fiscal year from the sale of forestry and information products; licensing, training and certification activities related to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Explosives Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Explosives Regulations, 2013</XRefExternal>; from research, consultation, testing, analysis, and administration services as part of the departmental operations; and for the provision of internal support services to other organizations and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>67,120,072</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Natural Resources – Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>29,270,500</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Natural Resources – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>20,295,798</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">116,686,370</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>NATURAL SCIENCES AND ENGINEERING RESEARCH COUNCIL</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council – Operating expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>827,500</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council – The grants listed in the Estimates</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>14,050,400</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">14,877,900</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>OFFICE OF INFRASTRUCTURE OF CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Office of Infrastructure of Canada – Operating expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" topmarginspacing="-2"><Text>14,690,666</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>10a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Office of Infrastructure of Canada – Contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,383,566,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">1,398,256,666</entry></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>OFFICE OF THE COMMISSIONER FOR FEDERAL JUDICIAL AFFAIRS</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Office of the Commissioner for Federal Judicial Affairs – Operating expenditures, remuneration, allowances and expenses for judges, including deputy judges of the Supreme Court of Yukon, the Supreme Court of the Northwest Territories and the Nunavut Court of Justice, not provided for by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal>, and pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received during the year arising from the provision of administrative services and judicial training services</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,141,190</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Office of the Commissioner for Federal Judicial Affairs – Canadian Judicial Council – Operating expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,500,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">2,641,190</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>PRIVY COUNCIL OFFICE</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Privy Council Offic – Program expenditures, including operating expenditures of Commissions of Inquiry not otherwise provided for and the operation of the Prime Minister’s residence; and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received in a fiscal year through the provision of internal support services to other organizations to offset expenditures incurred in the fiscal year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>23,250,293</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">23,250,293</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>PUBLIC HEALTH AGENCY OF CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Public Health Agency of Canada – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues to offset expenditures incurred in the fiscal year arising from the sale of products, inspection services and the provision of internal support services to other organizations</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,548,503</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">1,548,503</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>PUBLIC WORKS AND GOVERNMENT SERVICES</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Public Works and Government Services – Operating expenditures for the provision of accommodation, common and central services including recoverable expenditures on behalf of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seized Property Management Act</XRefExternal>; authority to expend revenues received during the fiscal year arising from accommodation and central and common services in respect of these services and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, internal support services to other organizations; and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>290,359,023</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Public Works and Government Services – Capital expenditures including expenditures on works other than federal property and authority to reimburse tenants of federal property for improvements authorized by the Minister of Public Works and Government Services</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>60,943,600</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">351,302,623</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>REGISTRAR OF THE SUPREME COURT OF CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Registrar of the Supreme Court of Canada – Program expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>977,041</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">977,041</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>SECURITY INTELLIGENCE REVIEW COMMITTEE</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Security Intelligence Review Committee – Program expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>4,044,756</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">4,044,756</entry></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>SHARED SERVICES CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Shared Services Canada – Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received in the fiscal year to offset expenditures incurred in that fiscal year arising from the provision of information technology services</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>109,675,247</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Shared Services Canada – Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>161,808,663</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">271,483,910</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>SOCIAL SCIENCES AND HUMANITIES RESEARCH COUNCIL</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council – Operating expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>482,400</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council – The grants listed in the Estimates</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>15,459,850</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">15,942,250</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>STANDARDS COUNCIL OF CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to the Standards Council of Canada pursuant to section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Standards Council of Canada Act</XRefExternal></Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>945,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">945,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>TRANSPORT</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Transport – Operating expenditures and</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>authority to make expenditures on other than federal property in the course of, or arising out of the exercise of jurisdiction in, aeronautics;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>authority for the payment of commissions for revenue collection pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenue received during the fiscal year including the provision of internal support services to other organizations; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year</Text></Provision></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>71,576,716</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Transport – Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>24,106,745</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>15a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Transport (Transportation infrastructure) – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>19,031,976</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>20a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Transport (Other) – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>8,627,704</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">123,343,141</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>TREASURY BOARD SECRETARIAT</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Treasury Board Secretariat – Program expenditures and the payment to each member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is a Minister without Portfolio or a Minister of State who does not preside over a Ministry of State of a salary not to exceed the salary paid to Ministers of State who preside over Ministries of State under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, as adjusted pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and pro rata for any period of less than a year and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend revenues received in a fiscal year, and to offset expenditures incurred in the fiscal year, arising from the provision of internal support services to other organizations and from activities of the Treasury Board Secretariat</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>43,371,793</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1" justification="center"><Text>20a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Public Service Insurance – Payments, in respect of insurance, pension or benefit programs or other arrangements, or in respect of the administration of such programs, or arrangements, including premiums, contributions, benefits, fees and other expenditures, made in respect of the public service or any part thereof and for such other persons, as Treasury Board determines, and authority to expend any revenues or other amounts received in respect of such programs or arrangements to offset any such expenditures in respect of such programs or arrangements and to provide for the return to certain employees of their share of the premium reduction under subsection 96(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal></Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1,909,207</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">45,281,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>VIA RAIL CANADA INC.</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Payments to VIA Rail Canada Inc. in respect of the costs of the management of the Company, payments for capital purposes and payments for the provision of rail passenger services in Canada in accordance with contracts entered into pursuant to subparagraph (c)(i) of Transport Vote 52d, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Appropriation Act No. 1, 1977</XRefExternal></Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>6,930,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">6,930,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>WESTERN ECONOMIC DIVERSIFICATION</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Western Economic Diversification – The grants listed in the Estimates and contributions</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>23,100,000</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry /><entry /><entry /><entry align="right" colsep="0">23,100,000</entry></row><row><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">6,907,856,660</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule><Schedule spanlanguages="yes"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Based on Supplementary Estimates (A), 2016–17, the amount granted is $106,793,999, which is the total of the amounts of the items set out in this Schedule.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Sums granted to Her Majesty by this Act for the fiscal year ending March 31, 2017, that may be charged to that fiscal year and the following fiscal year ending March 31, 2018 and the purposes for which they are granted.</Text></Provision><TableGroup pointsize="8" rowbreak="yes" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="all"><tgroup cols="4"><colspec align="center" colname="1" colwidth="7.51*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="62.20*" /><colspec align="right" colname="3" colwidth="15.15*" /><colspec align="right" colname="COLSPEC0" colwidth="15.15*" /><thead><row rowsep="1" topdouble="yes" valign="top"><entry colname="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Vote No.</entry><entry align="center" colname="2" colsep="1" valign="bottom">Items</entry><entry align="center" colname="3" colsep="1" valign="bottom">Amount ($)</entry><entry align="center" colsep="0" valign="bottom">Total ($)</entry></row></thead><tbody><row rowsep="0"><entry colname="1" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="2" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>CANADA BORDER SERVICES AGENCY</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="1" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" /></row><row rowsep="0"><entry align="center" colname="1" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canada Border Services Agency — Operating expenditures and, pursuant to paragraph 29.1(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, authority to expend in the current fiscal year revenues received during the fiscal year related to the border operations of the Canada Border Services Agency: fees for the provision of a service or the use of a facility or for a product, right or privilege; and payments received under contracts entered into by the Agency</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colname="3" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5,311,942</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row rowsep="0"><entry align="center" colname="1" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>5a</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Canada Border Services Agency — Capital expenditures</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colname="3" colsep="1" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>19,614,850</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">24,926,792</entry></row><row><entry align="right" rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>PARKS CANADA AGENCY</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row><row><entry align="center" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>1a</Text></Provision></entry><entry rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>Parks Canada Agency — Program expenditures, including capital expenditures, the grants listed in the Estimates and contributions, including expenditures on other than federal property, and payments to provinces and municipalities as contributions towards the cost of undertakings carried out by those bodies</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><Text>81,867,207</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry rowsep="1" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="top">81,867,207</entry></row><row><entry align="right" rowsep="0" /><entry rowsep="0" /><entry align="right" rowsep="0" /><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">106,793,999</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule></Bill>