<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600023" lims:id="600023" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600024" lims:id="600024"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 966</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600026" lims:id="600026"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-9.2">DEPARTMENT OF INDUSTRY ACT</XRefExternal><XRefExternal reference-type="act">APPROPRIATION ACT NO. 5, 1965</XRefExternal><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="Z-01">APPROPRIATION ACTS</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600027" lims:id="600027">Automotive Manufacturing Assistance Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600028" lims:id="600028">Regulations Respecting the Provision for Adjustment Assistance in Respect of the Manufacture of Automotive Products in Canada</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600029" lims:id="600029"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600030" lims:id="600030" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600031" lims:id="600031"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._966">Automotive Manufacturing Assistance Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600032" lims:id="600032" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600033" lims:id="600033"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600034" lims:id="600034"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600035" lims:id="600035" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>automobile</DefinedTermEn> means a four-wheeled passenger automobile having a seating capacity for not more than 10 persons; (<DefinedTermFr>automobile</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600036" lims:id="600036" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>automotive program</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada-United States Agreement on Automotive Products, Order in Council 1965-99, and the Letters of Commitment addressed to the Minister of Industry from the several automotive products manufacturers, taken together; (<DefinedTermFr>programme de l'industrie automobile</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600037" lims:id="600037" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Board</DefinedTermEn> means the General Adjustment Assistance Board established by the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._971">General Adjustment Assistance Regulations</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Commission</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600038" lims:id="600038" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>bus</DefinedTermEn> means a passenger motor vehicle having a seating capacity for more than 10 persons or a chassis therefor, but does not include any following vehicle or chassis therefor, namely, an electric trackless trolley bus, amphibious vehicle, tracked or half-tracked vehicle or motor vehicle designed primarily for off-highway use; (<DefinedTermFr>autobus</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600039" lims:id="600039" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible manufacturer</DefinedTermEn> means a person, firm or corporation that is not a manufacturer of automobiles or a subsidiary wholly-owned corporation or subsidiary controlled corporation of an automobile manufacturer or its parent corporation, and that in the opinion of the Board is</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600040" lims:id="600040"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a manufacturer in Canada, or a holding company of a manufacturer in Canada, of significant quantities of parts or accessories or both or parts of either, including tires and tubes, or both or either, for use as original equipment in automobiles, buses, off-highway vehicles or specified commercial vehicles,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600041" lims:id="600041"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a supplier in Canada, or a holding company of a supplier in Canada, of significant quantities of materials to a manufacturer of parts or accessories or both or parts of either, including tires and tubes, or both or either, or of tooling for use in the production of parts or accessories or both or parts of either for use as original equipment in automobiles, buses, off-highway vehicles or specified commercial vehicles,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600042" lims:id="600042"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a manufacturer in Canada, or a holding company of a manufacturer in Canada, of significant quantities of tooling for use by a manufacturer of parts and accessories or both or parts of either, including tires and tubes, or both or either, or for use as original equipment for automobiles, buses, off-highway vehicles or specified commercial vehicles, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600043" lims:id="600043"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a manufacturer in Canada, or a holding company of a manufacturer in Canada, of a significant number of buses, off-highway vehicles or specified commercial vehicles or all of them; (<DefinedTermFr>fabricant admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600044" lims:id="600044" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>off-highway vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means a self-propelled truck designed primarily for off-highway use at quarries, mines, gravel or sand pits, construction sites or in logging operations, or a chassis therefor, but does not include machines for felling, skidding, piling, loading, bunching or processing trees or logs, which have been modified for carrying a load, nor any machine or other article required under tariff item 43803-1 to be valued separately under the tariff items regularly applicable thereto; (<DefinedTermFr>véhicule tout terrain</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600045" lims:id="600045" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>specified commercial vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means a motor truck, ambulance or hearse, or a chassis therefor, but does not include any following vehicle or chassis therefor, namely, a bus, electric trackless trolley bus, fire truck, amphibious vehicle, tracked or half-tracked vehicle, golf or invalid cart, straddle carrier or motor vehicle designed primarily for off-highway use, or any machine or other article required under tariff item 43803-1 to be valued separately under the tariff item regularly applicable thereto; (<DefinedTermFr>véhicule commercial spécifié</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600046" lims:id="600046" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>"subsidiary wholly-owned corporation" and "subsidiary controlled corporation"</DefinedTermEn> have the meanings assigned to those expressions by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-3.3">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>corporation filiale entièrement possédée et corporation filiale controlée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600047" lims:id="600047" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>tooling</DefinedTermEn> includes patterns, jigs, fixtures, moulds, models, dies, gauges and punches. (<DefinedTermFr>outillage</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600048" lims:id="600048"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the definition "eligible manufacturer" in subsection (1), a company is the holding company of a manufacturer only if that manufacturer is its subsidiary; and a company is a subsidiary of another company only if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600049" lims:id="600049"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>it is controlled by</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600050" lims:id="600050"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that other company, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600051" lims:id="600051"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that other company and one or more companies each of which is controlled by that other company, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600052" lims:id="600052"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>two or more companies each of which is controlled by that other company; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600053" lims:id="600053"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>it is a subsidiary of a subsidiary of that other company.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600054" lims:id="600054" level="1"><TitleText>General Adjustment Assistance Board</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600055" lims:id="600055"><Label>3</Label><Text>The General Adjustment Assistance Board is hereby declared to be the successor to the Adjustment Assistance Board, and all property, rights, obligations and liabilities of the Adjustment Assistance Board existing immediately before June 29, 1971 shall be deemed to be the property, rights, obligations and liabilities of the General Adjustment Assistance Board.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600056" lims:id="600056"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600057" lims:id="600057"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board shall administer loans made under these Regulations and shall perform such other duties and functions as the Minister of Industry, Trade and Commerce may assign to it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600058" lims:id="600058"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Industry, Trade and Commerce may, after June 30, 1973 and with the approval of the Governor in Council, assign to one or more departments or agencies of the Government of Canada the functions previously exercised by the Board in respect of the administration and servicing of loans made under these Regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600059" lims:id="600059"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600060" lims:id="600060"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the Board may authorize a change in any security required or taken in respect of a loan made under these Regulations before July 1, 1973 and the entry into an agreement on behalf of Her Majesty, amending the terms and conditions of such a loan.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600061" lims:id="600061"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No agreement entered into pursuant to subsection (1) shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600062" lims:id="600062"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>increase the principal amount of a loan, except by the compounding of interest in arrears; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600063" lims:id="600063"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>amend a term or condition that was prescribed by these Regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600064" lims:id="600064"><Label>6</Label><Text>Subject to these Regulations, the Board may make such by-laws and regulations as may be necessary for the conduct of its meetings, the management of its affairs and the performance of its duties.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600065" lims:id="600065"><Label>7</Label><Text>In carrying out its duties and functions under these Regulations, the Board shall use the existing staff and facilities of departments and agencies of the Government of Canada and such staff and facilities shall, to the extent practicable, be made available to the Board.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600066" lims:id="600066" level="1"><TitleText>Adjustment Assistance for Eligible Manufacturers</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600067" lims:id="600067"><Label>8</Label><Text>Where an eligible manufacturer is already indebted to Her Majesty under a loan or loans made to him under these Regulations and</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600068" lims:id="600068"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>default or an event of default under the terms and conditions of the loan or loans has occurred, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600069" lims:id="600069"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the opinion of the Board, Her Majesty's security taken in support of the loan or loans is in imminent danger of being placed in jeopardy,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600070" lims:id="600070"><Text>the Board may, in accordance with these Regulations, if financing is not available through other sources, make a loan to, or give a guarantee of loan made by a lender to, that eligible manufacturer where, in the opinion of the Board, the loan or guarantee would provide that eligible manufacturer with a reasonable prospect of a profitable operation or would provide for the continuation of all or part of the operations of the borrower and would protect Her Majesty's security.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600071" lims:id="600071"><Label>9</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600072" lims:id="600072"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An eligible manufacturer who requires a loan under section 8 shall make application therefor to the Board and shall submit with his application such information as the Board may require.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600073" lims:id="600073"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an application for a loan or a guarantee is approved by the Board, the applicant may enter into an agreement with Her Majesty and that agreement shall, subject to these Regulations, be in such form and contain such provisions as the Board considers necessary.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600074" lims:id="600074"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The amount of a loan made or a payment made under a guarantee given under section 8 shall be paid by the Board out of the moneys appropriated therefor by Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600075" lims:id="600075"><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600076" lims:id="600076"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A loan made pursuant to section 8 shall bear interest at a rate equal to the prevailing rate charged to crown corporations at the time the loan is authorized by the Board for loans of a similar term plus two per cent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600077" lims:id="600077"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A guarantee given pursuant to section 8 shall bear a fee of one per cent per annum of the amount of the guaranteed loan in force from time to time and shall be paid by the borrower under such terms and conditions as may be determined by the Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600078" lims:id="600078"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Board may, to the extent that it deems advisable, take, accept or acquire and hold security of any kind in any form to secure any loan or guarantee provided by it under these Regulations and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, the Board may take, accept or acquire and hold for that purpose</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600079" lims:id="600079"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>stocks, bonds or debentures of municipal and other corporations whether secured by Canadian, provincial, municipal, British, foreign or other government securities, by mortgage or otherwise;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600080" lims:id="600080"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>negotiable warehouse receipts and bills of lading;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600081" lims:id="600081"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>goods, wares and merchandise;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600082" lims:id="600082"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>mortgages or hypothecs on any real or personal, movable or immovable property; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600083" lims:id="600083"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>trustee's or receiver's certificates issued by the trustee or receiver of the assets of an eligible manufacturer.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600084" lims:id="600084"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A loan made pursuant to section 8 shall be for a term not exceeding</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600085" lims:id="600085"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>20 years, if the loan is to be made in respect of the acquisition, modernization, development, conversion or expansion of any buildings or real or immovable property; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600086" lims:id="600086"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>10 years, in any other case.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600087" lims:id="600087"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A guarantee given pursuant to section 8 shall be for such term as may be fixed by the Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600088" lims:id="600088"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A loan made pursuant to section 8 may be repaid in whole or in part in advance of the due date, without notice or bonus, in such manner as may be prescribed by the Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600089" lims:id="600089"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>During the term of loan or guarantee made pursuant to section 8, the borrower shall maintain such insurance coverage as the Board may prescribe.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600090" lims:id="600090"><Label>11</Label><Text>Any security given for a loan or guarantee provided pursuant to section 8 may, with the approval of the Board or such advisory or other committee as the Minister of Industry, Trade and Commerce may designate for the purpose, be surrendered, retransferred or reconveyed in exchange for other security.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600091" lims:id="600091"><Label>12</Label><Text>The Board shall keep such records and books and make such reports on its automotive adjustment assistance activities from time to time as the Minister of Industry, Trade and Commerce may require.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600092" lims:id="600092" level="1"><TitleText>Adjustment Assistance for Employees</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600093" lims:id="600093"><Label>13</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600094" lims:id="600094"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where, in the opinion of the Board,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600095" lims:id="600095"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>10 per cent of the work force or 50 employees, whichever is less, of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600096" lims:id="600096"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an eligible manufacturer or of a particular branch or subdivision of his undertaking,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600097" lims:id="600097"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a manufacturer in Canada of automobiles or of a particular branch or subdivision of his undertaking, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600098" lims:id="600098"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a particular branch or subdivision in Canada of the undertaking of a manufacturer of automobiles</Text></Subparagraph><ContinuedParagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600099" lims:id="600099"><Text>have been or will be laid off for a period of four weeks or more, and</Text></ContinuedParagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600100" lims:id="600100"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the lay-off, or a proportion thereof determined by the Board, was or will be caused by the termination or decrease of production or other activity arising from the implementation of the automotive program,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600101" lims:id="600101"><Text>the Board shall so certify to the Department of Labour.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600102" lims:id="600102"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A certificate issued by the Board under subsection (1) shall contain</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600103" lims:id="600103"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a list of the employees affected by the lay-off, together with their Social Insurance Numbers and their addresses, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600104" lims:id="600104"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the effective date of the lay-off,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600105" lims:id="600105"><Text>and shall state</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600106" lims:id="600106"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in respect of each employee named in the certificate, whether or not he is affected by a supplemental unemployment benefit plan in force at the time the certificate is issued; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="600107" lims:id="600107"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in respect of each employee referred to in paragraph (a) who is so affected, the amount of the benefit to which such employee would be entitled under the supplemental unemployment benefit plan.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></Body></Regulation>