<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528895" lims:id="528895" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528896" lims:id="528896"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1561</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528898" lims:id="528898"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-16">TRANSLATION BUREAU ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528899" lims:id="528899">Translation Bureau Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528900" lims:id="528900">Regulations Respecting the Provision of Translation Services</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528901" lims:id="528901"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528902" lims:id="528902" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528903" lims:id="528903"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1561">Translation Bureau Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528904" lims:id="528904" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528905" lims:id="528905"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528906" lims:id="528906" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>department</DefinedTermEn> means a department of the Public Service and includes both Houses of the Parliament of Canada and all bureaus, branches, commissions and agencies created or appointed by Act of Parliament or by order of the Governor in Council; (<DefinedTermFr>ministère</DefinedTermFr> or <DefinedTermFr>département</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528907" lims:id="528907" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated official</DefinedTermEn> means an employee of a department designated in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 7(1)(b); (<DefinedTermFr>fonctionnaire désigné</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528908" lims:id="528908" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Interdepartmental Committee</DefinedTermEn> means the Interdepartmental Advisory Committee on Government Translations established by section 14; (<DefinedTermFr>comité interministériel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528909" lims:id="528909" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>interpretation</DefinedTermEn> means oral translation; (<DefinedTermFr>interprétation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528910" lims:id="528910" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>proofreading</DefinedTermEn> means the examination and correction of typographical details or of illustrations on sheets printed from type or plates and includes the verification of numbers contained in tables and documents; (<DefinedTermFr>correction d’épreuves</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528911" lims:id="528911" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>revision</DefinedTermEn> means the examination and correction of the meaning and form of a translation and includes the insertion into a translation of changes made in the original text after it has been submitted for translation to the Bureau; (<DefinedTermFr>révision</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528912" lims:id="528912" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>translation</DefinedTermEn> means the written transposition of words and numbers from one language to another and includes an adaptation that accurately conveys the meaning thereof. (<DefinedTermFr>traduction</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528913" lims:id="528913" level="1"><TitleText>Responsibilities of the Bureau</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528914" lims:id="528914"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Bureau shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528915" lims:id="528915"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subject to these Regulations, make all translations requested by departments;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528916" lims:id="528916"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cooperate with departments in revising documents prepared by departments;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528917" lims:id="528917"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>deliver translations or revisions in legible form to the department requesting the translations or revisions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528918" lims:id="528918"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>ensure that translations or revisions made by it conform, in so far as Canadian usage permits, to “le français universel” or Standard English, whichever is applicable;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528919" lims:id="528919"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>subject to these Regulations, provide interpretation services requested by departments; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528920" lims:id="528920"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>give technical advice on questions relating to translation, terminology and style to employees of departments.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528921" lims:id="528921"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528922" lims:id="528922"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except in cases of particular urgency, the Bureau shall make translations in the English or French language in accordance with the following order of priority:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528923" lims:id="528923"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>documents that are required to be published in both the English and French languages including</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528924" lims:id="528924"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>all Parliamentary documents,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528925" lims:id="528925"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>all official departmental documents and publications, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528926" lims:id="528926"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>speeches and press releases;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528927" lims:id="528927"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>handbooks and administrative directions intended for the use of departmental employees;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528928" lims:id="528928"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>documents, including correspondence, that are required to be translated solely for the assistance of an individual who has not a working knowledge of both the English and French languages; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528929" lims:id="528929"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>staff magazines.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528930" lims:id="528930"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Bureau, upon receiving a request for translation from a department, shall forthwith estimate the amount of time required to make the translation and determine whether or not its normal facilities for serving the department will permit the making of the translation within the maximum time available for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528931" lims:id="528931"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the Bureau is of the opinion that its normal facilities for serving a department will not permit the making of a translation within the maximum time available for that purpose, the Bureau shall communicate with the designated official of the department in order</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528932" lims:id="528932"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to obtain an extension of the time available for making the translation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528933" lims:id="528933"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to obtain a change in the department’s translation priorities; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528934" lims:id="528934"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to make any other arrangement with the department for making the translation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528935" lims:id="528935"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528936" lims:id="528936"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Bureau shall make a translation of a document from or into a language other than English or French if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528937" lims:id="528937"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the International Translations Index contained in the National Science Library of the National Research Council has been consulted by the department requesting the translation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528938" lims:id="528938"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where a translation of the document is available elsewhere, a reasonable effort has been made by the department to obtain it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528939" lims:id="528939"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a department does not have the facilities to do so, the Bureau shall prepare the final presentation of a translation of a document from or into a language other than English or French, including the typing, page-setting, printing and proofreading of such a translation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528940" lims:id="528940"><Label>6</Label><Text>When, in the opinion of the Superintendent of the Bureau, the Bureau is unable to deal adequately with requests for translations or interpretations made by departments, the Bureau may, in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-87-402">Government Contracts Regulations</XRefExternal> and in compliance with any security requirements, engage the services of professional translators or interpreters as independent contractors.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528941" lims:id="528941" level="1"><TitleText>Responsibilities of Departments</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528942" lims:id="528942"><Label>7</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528943" lims:id="528943"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The head of every department that uses the services of the Bureau shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528944" lims:id="528944"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>eliminate the need for translation requests to the Bureau based solely on the inability of an employee to read or prepare texts in the English or French language;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528945" lims:id="528945"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>designate an employee in his department who shall communicate with and receive communications from the Bureau in respect of translations and revisions requested from the Bureau by the department;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528946" lims:id="528946"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>provide the Bureau annually with a five-year forecast of its translation requirements, including, in the case of translation requirements in respect of languages other than English or French, a listing of the languages from or into which translations are required;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528947" lims:id="528947"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>include in his production schedules for publications, the time required for translation, such time to be determined in consultation with the Bureau; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528948" lims:id="528948"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>supply to the Bureau’s Terminology Centre two copies in each language of any document that is published by the department in both the English and French languages, upon the publication thereof.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528949" lims:id="528949"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A department shall, in the manner determined by its designated official and the Bureau, send all documents for translation or revision to the Chief of the Translation Division attached to the department or, if no Translation Division has been attached to the department, to the Director of Production of the Bureau, together with two copies of a request for translation in a form approved by the Superintendent of the Bureau.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528950" lims:id="528950"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where a department makes a request for translation, it shall, at the time of making the request, advise the Bureau of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528951" lims:id="528951"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the maximum time available for translation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528952" lims:id="528952"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any security measures that may be necessary in respect of the document, in respect of which the translation is requested.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528953" lims:id="528953"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A department shall attach to all documents, in respect of which translation is requested, any documentation that may be of assistance to the Bureau including</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528954" lims:id="528954"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the original and translated versions of similar previous texts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528955" lims:id="528955"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any document where the text prepared in consequence thereof is submitted for translation into the language used in that document;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528956" lims:id="528956"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>previously prepared scientific or technical vocabularies; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528957" lims:id="528957"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the source of quotations, information or texts used as reference.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528958" lims:id="528958"><Label>8</Label><Text>Where a department intends to request translation of a scientific, technical or specialized document that is being prepared in the department, it shall, upon the completion of the first draft thereof, forward a copy of the draft to the Bureau in order that terminological research may be commenced by the Bureau.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528959" lims:id="528959"><Label>9</Label><Text>Subject to subsection 5(2), a department shall be responsible for the final presentation of translations delivered to it by the Bureau, including the typing, printing, page-setting and proofreading of such translations.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528960" lims:id="528960"><Label>10</Label><Text>A department shall take full responsibility for any changes it makes in translations provided by the Bureau.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528961" lims:id="528961"><Label>11</Label><Text>Where the Bureau has attached a Translation Division to a department, the department shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528962" lims:id="528962"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide suitable office space for the Translation Division;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528963" lims:id="528963"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>acquire for the library of the Translation Division such reference material as the Chief of the Translation Division considers necessary for the performance of his duties and, at the request of the Chief of the Translation Division, place such reference material in the office space occupied by the Translation Division; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528964" lims:id="528964"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>make available to the Translation Division the stenographic and typing services required by it to meet emergencies.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528965" lims:id="528965" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation Services</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528966" lims:id="528966"><Label>12</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528967" lims:id="528967"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The requirements of both Houses of the Parliament of Canada and of the committees thereof in respect of interpretation services shall be given first priority by the Bureau.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528968" lims:id="528968"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1), the Bureau shall provide interpretation services to departments.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528969" lims:id="528969"><Label>13</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528970" lims:id="528970"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a department commences preparation for any conference in respect of which it intends to request the Bureau to provide interpretation services, it shall notify the Bureau in writing and provide the Bureau with any information and documentation that may be useful to the Bureau including agenda, working papers, reports, speeches and specialized vocabularies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528971" lims:id="528971"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where, in the opinion of the Superintendent of the Bureau, a department has not provided sufficient information and documentation to allow reasonable preparation to be made by the Bureau for provision of interpretation services, the Superintendent may limit the services of the Bureau to interpretation that can be made without special preparation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528972" lims:id="528972"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A department that has requested interpretation services for a conference shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528973" lims:id="528973"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>where possible, organize a meeting for the day preceding the conference between the employees of the Bureau who are to provide the interpretation services and specialists attending the conference for the purpose of familiarizing the employees of the Bureau with the material to be discussed at the conference;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528974" lims:id="528974"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide and install at the conference the equipment deemed necessary by the Bureau to enable the Bureau to provide the interpretation services requested; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528975" lims:id="528975"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>make all travel and accommodation arrangements and pay all travel expenses in respect of employees of the Bureau who are to provide interpretation services at conferences held outside of Ottawa.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528976" lims:id="528976" level="1"><TitleText>Interdepartmental Committee</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528977" lims:id="528977"><Label>14</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528978" lims:id="528978"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An Interdepartmental Advisory Committee on Government Translations, consisting of eight members, shall consider questions of priority resulting from requests made for translations and the provision of interpretation services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528979" lims:id="528979"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Interdepartmental Committee shall consist of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528980" lims:id="528980"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>two members appointed by the Under Secretary of State, one of whom shall act as Secretary of the Interdepartmental Committee and shall have no vote;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528981" lims:id="528981"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>one member appointed by the Secretary of the Treasury Board;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528982" lims:id="528982"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Superintendent of the Bureau or his representative;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528983" lims:id="528983"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the Queen’s Printer or his representative;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528984" lims:id="528984"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>one member appointed from the Special Secretariat on Bilingualism of the Privy Council; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528985" lims:id="528985"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>two designated officials representing departments not otherwise represented, selected according to an annual rotation system.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528986" lims:id="528986"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Interdepartmental Committee shall meet once at the beginning of each calendar year to choose its chairman and thereafter at the call of the chairman.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528987" lims:id="528987"><Label>15</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528988" lims:id="528988"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a conflict in priorities arises because of requests made by more than one department for translations or the provision of interpretation services, the Bureau shall refer the conflict to the Interdepartmental Committee for a decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528989" lims:id="528989"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The decision of the Interdepartmental Committee shall be binding upon all departments.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528990" lims:id="528990" level="1"><TitleText>Terminology Centre</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528991" lims:id="528991"><Label>16</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528992" lims:id="528992"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Bureau shall maintain a Terminology Centre that shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528993" lims:id="528993"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>carry out terminological research and prepare and distribute terminological instructions and bulletins;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528994" lims:id="528994"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>make its services available to departments; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528995" lims:id="528995"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>cooperate with universities and other institutions and agencies involved in terminological research.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528996" lims:id="528996"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Departments shall cooperate with the Terminology Centre and supply it with copies of documents containing specialized glossaries and vocabularies that come into their possession.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="528997" lims:id="528997"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Departments shall seek the assistance of and cooperate with the Terminology Centre in the selection of a title for any new body under the jurisdiction of the Parliament of Canada in respect of which a title in both the English and French languages is required.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Regulation>