<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2015-06-18" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2015-06-18" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496888" lims:id="496888" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496889" lims:id="496889"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1152</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496891" lims:id="496891"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="R-4.2">RAILWAY SAFETY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496892" lims:id="496892">Liquefied Petroleum Gases Bulk Storage Regulations</ShortTitle><Note>CANADIAN TRANSPORT COMMISSION</Note><Note>GENERAL ORDER NO. O-31</Note><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496893" lims:id="496893">Regulations Respecting the Design, Location, Construction, Operation and Maintenance of Stationary Bulk Storage Facilities for Liquefied Petroleum Gases</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496894" lims:id="496894"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496895" lims:id="496895" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496896" lims:id="496896"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1152">Liquefied Petroleum Gases Bulk Storage Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496897" lims:id="496897" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496898" lims:id="496898"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496899" lims:id="496899" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>design pressure</DefinedTermEn> is synonymous with the term <DefinedTermEn>maximum allowable working pressure</DefinedTermEn> as used in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">A.S.M.E. Boiler and Pressure Vessel Code for Unfired Pressure Vessels</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>pression nominale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496900" lims:id="496900" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>filling density</DefinedTermEn> means the percentage figure obtained when the maximum weight of liquefied petroleum gas that may be in the container is divided by the water weight capacity of the tank and the result is multiplied by 100; all capacities shall be measured at a liquid temperature of 60°F; (<DefinedTermFr>densité de remplissage</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496901" lims:id="496901" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>liquefied petroleum gases</DefinedTermEn> are gases derived from petroleum or natural gas; they are in the gaseous state at normal atmospheric temperature and pressure, but may be maintained in a liquid state by the application of moderate pressure; the following gases are those most commonly handled as liquefied petroleum gases: propane, normal butane, propylene, isobutane, butylenes; (<DefinedTermFr>gaz de pétrole liquéfiés</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496902" lims:id="496902" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>main track</DefinedTermEn> means a track extending through yards and between stations upon which trains are operated by timetable or train order, or both, or the use of which is governed by block signals or other method of control; (<DefinedTermFr>voie principale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496903" lims:id="496903" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>owning or operating company</DefinedTermEn> means the person or company owning or operating the installation, erected with leave of the Commission granted upon application made therefor by the railway company concerned, on behalf of such person or company; (<DefinedTermFr>compagnie propriétaire or exploitante</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496904" lims:id="496904" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>private track</DefinedTermEn> means a track outside of carrier’s right-of-way, yard and terminals, and of which the carrier does not own either the rails, ties, roadbed or right-of-way; or a track or portion of a track which is devoted to the purpose of its user, either by lease or written agreement, in which case the lease or written agreement is considered as equivalent to ownership; (<DefinedTermFr>voie particulière</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496905" lims:id="496905" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>shall</DefinedTermEn> is used to indicate mandatory provisions; (<DefinedTermFr>le futur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496906" lims:id="496906" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>should</DefinedTermEn> is used to indicate recommendatory [provisions]; (<DefinedTermFr>le conditionnel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496907" lims:id="496907" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Switch heater facility</DefinedTermEn> means an installation comprising a liquefied petroleum gas heating appliance and attendant fuel storage and distribution systems, the purpose of which is to prevent the failure of a railway track switch due to snow or ice.</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496908" lims:id="496908" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>team track</DefinedTermEn> means a track on railway property which is used for loading and unloading purposes by more than one company or person. (<DefinedTermFr>voie de desserte industrielle</DefinedTermFr>) </Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496910" lims:id="496910">SOR/79-201, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496911" lims:id="496911" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496912" lims:id="496912"><Label>3</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to the stationary bulk storage facilities for liquefied petroleum gases on the right-of-way owned or leased by any railway company subject to the jurisdiction of the Commission.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496913" lims:id="496913"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496914" lims:id="496914"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to new installations and additions or changes to existing installations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496915" lims:id="496915"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), installations previously approved by an order of the Commission shall be operated in accordance with these Regulations and, if ordered by the Commission, shall also be made to conform to those parts of these Regulations pertaining to location, construction and design.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496916" lims:id="496916" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Storage Installations</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496917" lims:id="496917" level="2"><TitleText>Application of Part</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496918" lims:id="496918"><Label>5</Label><Text>This Part does not apply with respect to installations with a total storage capacity not exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons of water measured at 60°F, if such installations otherwise comply with all other applicable requirements of these Regulations.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496919" lims:id="496919" level="2"><TitleText>Application for Leave</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496920" lims:id="496920"><Label>6</Label><Text>No person shall begin the construction of storage facilities for liquefied petroleum gases without leave of the Commission granted upon an application made therefor through the railway company concerned.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496921" lims:id="496921"><Label>7</Label><Text>The application shall be submitted to the Secretary of the Commission together with four copies of all drawings, including plans and profiles, which shall comply with the requirements of sections 8 to 13.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496922" lims:id="496922"><Label>8</Label><Text>The plan shall be drawn to a scale of not less than 50 feet to one inch and the profile to a scale of not less than 20 feet to one inch.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496923" lims:id="496923"><Label>9</Label><Text>All drawings shall be dated and bear an identification number and the name of the applicant.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496924" lims:id="496924"><Label>10</Label><Text>The plan shall show the distances between</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496925" lims:id="496925"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the loading or unloading rack or point and</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496926" lims:id="496926"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the gauge side of the nearest rail of the loading or unloading track,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496927" lims:id="496927"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>schools, stations, residential areas, hospitals and other similar places of public assembly within 250 feet of the said loading or unloading rack or point,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496928" lims:id="496928"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>all engine houses, railway shops, grain elevators and other similar buildings within 150 feet of the said loading or unloading rack or point;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496929" lims:id="496929"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the centre line of the loading or unloading track and</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496930" lims:id="496930"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the gauge side of the nearest rail of main track, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496931" lims:id="496931"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the gauge side of the nearest rail of the nearest adjacent track not serving the installation;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496932" lims:id="496932"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the storage tanks and</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496933" lims:id="496933"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>other storage tanks, pumphouses, warehouses, loading and unloading racks, and other structures on the site,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496934" lims:id="496934"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the line of adjoining property,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496935" lims:id="496935"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the gauge side of the nearest rail of the closest track,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496936" lims:id="496936"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the gauge side of the nearest rail of the main track,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496937" lims:id="496937"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>stations, schools, residential areas, hospitals or other similar places of public assembly within 450 feet of the said storage tanks, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496938" lims:id="496938"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>all engine houses, railway shops, grain elevators or other similar buildings within 250 feet of the said storage tanks.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496939" lims:id="496939"><Label>11</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496940" lims:id="496940"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The profile shall show the elevation of the installation in relation to the loading and unloading track and any main track within 200 feet of the nearest tank on the said installation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496941" lims:id="496941"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A second profile is required where it is necessary</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496942" lims:id="496942"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to show the direction of drainage from the site; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496943" lims:id="496943"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to give a clear picture of major features of the installation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496944" lims:id="496944"><Label>12</Label><Text>The drawing shall show the location of the railway right-of-way, property fences, dykes, pipelines under roadways or railways, sewers, ditches, watercourses, highways and other similar structures that are on the installation site.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496945" lims:id="496945"><Label>13</Label><Text>The notes or legend on the drawing shall include the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496946" lims:id="496946"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>evidence that the Provincial Fire Marshal or other authority having jurisdiction in the surrounding area has no objection to the proposed installation. This evidence may take the form of a plan signature by the authority concerned, or of a letter addressed to the owning or operating company by such authority;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496947" lims:id="496947"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a statement that the storage tank and vapourizer design shall be approved by the Pressure Vessel Inspection Branch of the provincial government concerned prior to fabrication of the tanks;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496948" lims:id="496948"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>size, contents and water capacity in Imperial gallons of all storage tanks;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496949" lims:id="496949"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>type and construction of pumphouse, warehouse, compressor house, bottling house, vapourizer house and any other building on the site;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496950" lims:id="496950"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>type of motive power to be used for pumps or compressors;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496951" lims:id="496951"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the type of heating to be used for vapourizer; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496952" lims:id="496952"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>whether the track or tracks serving the installation are team tracks or private tracks.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496953" lims:id="496953"><Label>13.1</Label><Text>Where the Commission has, pursuant to section 6, granted leave for the construction of a storage facility for liquefied petroleum gases, a copy of each of the drawings referred to in section 7 shall be kept by the railway company for the life of the storage facility and retained for at least two years thereafter.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496955" lims:id="496955">SOR/85-471, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="496956" lims:id="496956" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Distances</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496957" lims:id="496957"><Label>14</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496958" lims:id="496958"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The distances prescribed in this section shall be measured from the gauge side of the nearest rail of the nearest adjacent track not serving the installation or the main track, as the case may be, to the centre line of the unloading or loading track.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496959" lims:id="496959"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Loading or unloading tracks, at the loading or unloading site, shall be at least 50 feet from the main track.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496960" lims:id="496960"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Loading or unloading tracks shall be not less than 20 feet from the nearest adjacent track not serving the installation. If the nearest adjacent track is a main track, the distance shall be 50 feet.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496961" lims:id="496961"><Label>15</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496962" lims:id="496962"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>That portion of overhead loading or unloading structures or equipment over four feet above the top of rail shall be at least six feet from the gauge side of the nearest rail of the loading or unloading track. That portion of the structure four feet or less in height above the top of rail shall be at least three feet 7 3/4 inches from the gauge side of the nearest rail of the loading or unloading track, except for non-standard gauge track in the Province of Newfoundland, where this clearance distance shall be at least three feet 10 inches. When the loading or unloading track is curved, the clearance distance shall be increased by one inch per degree of track curvature.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496963" lims:id="496963"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Loading or unloading terminals or structures of an over-all height that is less than four feet above the top of rail shall be located not less than six feet from the gauge side of the nearest rail of the loading or unloading track.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496964" lims:id="496964"><Label>16</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496965" lims:id="496965"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The distances prescribed in this section shall be measured from the centre line of the loading and unloading rack or point to the nearest point of the building or property line, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496966" lims:id="496966"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The loading or unloading racks or points shall be at least 200 feet from any station, office building or other similar place of public assembly on railway property.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496967" lims:id="496967"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>It is recommended that the distance of a loading or unloading rack from schools, hospitals, theatres, residential areas or other similar places of public assembly be not less than 200 feet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496968" lims:id="496968"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Except as provided in subsection (5), the distance of loading or unloading racks or points from engine houses, railway shops, grain elevators or other similar buildings shall be not less than 100 feet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496969" lims:id="496969"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The distance between a loading or unloading rack or point and any storage tank or building on the installation used exclusively by the owning or operating company shall be not less than 10 feet.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496970" lims:id="496970"><Label>17</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496971" lims:id="496971"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In no case shall a liquefied petroleum gas storage tank be located less than 20 feet from the gauge side of the nearest rail of any track, measured from the nearest point on the tank shell.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496972" lims:id="496972"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The following minimum distances from the gauge side of the nearest rail of the main track to the nearest point on the tank shall be observed:</Text><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496973" lims:id="496973" pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="4" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496974" lims:id="496974" frame="topbot"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496975" lims:id="496975" cols="2" align="left"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="265.69*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="282.71*" /><thead lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496976" lims:id="496976"><row topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Water Capacity (Imperial Gallons) at 60°F, Single Tank</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Minimum Distance (Feet)</entry></row></thead><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496977" lims:id="496977"><row><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">0 to  2,000</entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">20</entry></row><row><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">2,001 to 10,000</entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">75</entry></row><row><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">10,001 to 25,000</entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">100</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496978" lims:id="496978"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>It is recommended that the distance of a storage tank from the right-of-way of a provincial highway be not less than half the distance prescribed in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496979" lims:id="496979"><Label>18</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496980" lims:id="496980"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The distances prescribed in this section shall be measured from the nearest point on the tank shell to the nearest point of the building, property line, etc.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496981" lims:id="496981"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A storage tank with a water capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons shall be not less than 50 feet from any location on another property which may be built upon.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496982" lims:id="496982"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For a tank with a water capacity of 2,000 Imperial gallons or less, the distance from any location on another property which may be built upon shall be not less than that prescribed in the current edition of National Fire Protection Association Pamphlet No. 58.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496983" lims:id="496983"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A storage tank with a water capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons shall be at least 400 feet from any station, office building, or other similar places of public assembly on railway property.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496984" lims:id="496984"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>It is recommended that the distance of a storage tank with a water capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons from schools, hospitals, theatres, residential areas or other similar places of public assembly be not less than 400 feet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496985" lims:id="496985"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For a tank with a water capacity of 2,000 Imperial gallons or less, the distance from any of the buildings mentioned in subsections (4) and (5) shall be not less than that prescribed in the current edition of National Fire Protection Association Pamphlet No. 58.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496986" lims:id="496986"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Except as provided in subsection (9), a storage tank with a water capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons shall not be less than 200 feet from engine houses, railway shops, grain elevators or other similar buildings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496987" lims:id="496987"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>For a tank with a water capacity of 2,000 Imperial gallons or less, the distance from any of the buildings mentioned in subsection (7) shall not be less than that prescribed in the current edition of National Fire Protection Association Pamphlet No. 58.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496988" lims:id="496988"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Except as provided in subsection (11), the distance of a storage tank with a water capacity exceeding 100 Imperial gallons from any building on the installation site that is used exclusively by the company owning or operating the installation shall not be less than 10 feet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496989" lims:id="496989"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>A tank with a water capacity of 100 Imperial gallons or less shall not be less than 5 feet horizontally from a building opening located at the same level as the tank vent or below it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496990" lims:id="496990"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>When the construction or occupancy of a building is of such a nature as to constitute a hazard to the storage area, the distance between such a building and the closest tank with a water capacity exceeding 100 Imperial gallons shall not be less than 50 feet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496991" lims:id="496991"><Label>(12)</Label><Text>The distance of any storage tank from the fence surrounding the installation shall not be less than 5 feet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496992" lims:id="496992"><Label>(13)</Label><Text>The clear distance between two storage tanks with an individual water capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons shall not be less than 5 feet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496993" lims:id="496993"><Label>(14)</Label><Text>The clear distance between a tank containing liquefied petroleum gas and a tank containing a flammable liquid shall not be less than 20 feet, except that liquefied petroleum gas installations with a storage capacity exceeding 150,000 Imperial gallons of water measured at 60°F shall be located not less than 100 feet from the above ground storage of flammable liquids.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496994" lims:id="496994"><Label>(15)</Label><Text>A liquefied petroleum gas storage tank shall not be located within a diked area containing a flammable liquid storage tank.  The distance between a tank measured from the nearest point on the tank shell and the centre line of a dike shall not be less than 10 feet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496995" lims:id="496995"><Label>(16)</Label><Text>The distance between any tank of one group and any tank of another group, as defined in section 22, shall not be less than 25 feet.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496996" lims:id="496996"><Label>19</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496997" lims:id="496997"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Pumphouses or compressor houses and outdoor pumps or compressors driven by internal combustion engines shall be located not less than 10 feet from any storage tank, loading or unloading point or building.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496998" lims:id="496998"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to outdoor pumps or compressors driven by explosion proof motors marked or labelled Class I, Division I, Group D and wired in accordance with the Canadian Electrical Code for Class I, Division I, Group D locations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="496999" lims:id="496999"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The distance of pumphouses or compressor houses and outdoor pumps or compressors from a source of ignition or any location on another property which may be built upon shall not be less than 25 feet.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497000" lims:id="497000"><Label>20</Label><Text>Where the distances prescribed in this Part cannot be obtained, lesser distances may be approved by the Commission if suitable fire barrier walls and fire controlling systems are employed.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="497001" lims:id="497001" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Storage Tanks</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497002" lims:id="497002"><Label>21</Label><Text>A cylinder or tank with a water capacity not exceeding 100 Imperial gallons and manufactured, filled, operated and maintained in accordance with a Canadian Transport Commission or an Interstate Commerce Commission specification, which is approved by either of these authorities for liquefied petroleum gas, is exempt from the provisions of this Part, except sections 23, 27 and 32.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497003" lims:id="497003"><Label>22</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497004" lims:id="497004"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The water capacity of any storage tank located on carrier’s right-of-way and used for liquefied petroleum gas shall not exceed 25,000 Imperial gallons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497005" lims:id="497005"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The aggregate water capacity of tanks assembled in a group shall not exceed 150,000 Imperial gallons.  Groups of tanks shall be segregated as prescribed in subsection 18(16).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497006" lims:id="497006"><Label>23</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497007" lims:id="497007"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except as provided in subsection (7), storage tanks shall be securely installed on solid foundations of steel or concrete with reinforced concrete footings extending below the frost line, or resting on bedrock.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497008" lims:id="497008"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except as provided in subsection (6), steel foundations shall be fireproofed with a material having a fire resistance of not less than 2 hours.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497009" lims:id="497009"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Foundations shall be of sufficient width and thickness to adequately support the tank and its contents.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497010" lims:id="497010"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Provision shall be made for the thermal expansion and contraction of a tank.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497011" lims:id="497011"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Only two saddles shall be used on horizontal tanks.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497012" lims:id="497012"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Steel saddles, which are welded to a tank, need not be fireproofed if the tank capacity does not exceed 500 Imperial gallons or if the over-all height of the saddle does not exceed 18 inches.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497013" lims:id="497013"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Footings for tanks with a water capacity less than 500 Imperial gallons need not be installed below frost line if adequate provision is made to protect the piping against the effects of setting.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497014" lims:id="497014"><Label>24</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497015" lims:id="497015"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Storage tanks shall be constructed in accordance with the 1956, 1959 or 1962 issue of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">A.S.M.E. Boiler and Pressure Vessel Code for Unfired Pressure Vessels</XRefExternal> to a design working pressure not less than 125 per cent of the vapour pressure of the liquefied petroleum gas at 100°F, but not less than 250 psig for liquefied propane.  The factor of safety shall not be less than 4.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497016" lims:id="497016"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The tank design drawings and specifications shall be approved by the Pressure Vessel Inspection Branch of the provincial government concerned prior to fabrication of the tank.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497017" lims:id="497017"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Tank design drawings and specifications shall be in accordance with the requirements of Canadian Standards Association Pamphlet B-51.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497018" lims:id="497018"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Welding to any parts of a tank subject to internal pressure shall be in accordance with the code under which the tank was fabricated.  Non-code welding is permitted only on saddle plates, lugs or brackets attached to the container by the tank manufacturer.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497019" lims:id="497019"><Label>25</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497020" lims:id="497020"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All tanks shall be inspected and tested prior to operation at the pressure specified by the A.S.M.E. Code by a qualified unfired pressure vessel inspector in accordance with the applicable regulations of the province concerned.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497021" lims:id="497021"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A copy of the tank test and inspection report shall be filed with the Commission.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497022" lims:id="497022"><Label>26</Label><Text>The storage tank shall be permanently marked or labelled as required by the A.S.M.E. Code under which the tank was manufactured and the Pressure Vessel Inspection Branch of the provincial government concerned.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497023" lims:id="497023"><Label>27</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497024" lims:id="497024"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Storage tanks shall not be installed inside buildings or in a location that would restrict the natural dispersal of fumes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497025" lims:id="497025"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Storage tanks shall not be installed one above the other.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497026" lims:id="497026"><Label>28</Label><Text>Each storage tank exceeding 1,000 Imperial gallons water capacity shall be electrically grounded for protection against static electricity and lightning, as prescribed in National Fire Protection Association Pamphlet No. 77. The resistance to electrical discharge to ground should be as low as possible and preferably not more than 6 ohms.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497027" lims:id="497027"><Label>29</Label><Text>The filing density for storage tanks of liquefied petroleum gas shall not exceed the maximum filing density prescribed in the current edition of Pamphlet No. 58 of the National Fire Protection Association.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497028" lims:id="497028"><Label>30</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497029" lims:id="497029"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Unless filing is controlled by weighing, tanks shall be equipped with a fixed tube liquid level, a rotary tube, or an adjustable slip tube gauge, or other gauging device that will ensure that the maximum permitted filing density is not exceeded.  If the gauging device is a float type or a pressure differential type, the container shall also be provided with a fixed dip tube, rotary tube or adjustable slip tube gauge.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497030" lims:id="497030"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Gauge glasses of the columnar type shall be restricted to charging plants where the fuel is withdrawn in the liquid phase only.  They shall be equipped with valves having metallic hand wheels; with excess flow valves and with extra heavy glass protected with a metal housing applied by the manufacturer.  These gauges shall be shielded against the direct rays of the sun.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497031" lims:id="497031"><Label>31</Label><Text>Each tank with a water capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons shall be equipped with a suitable pressure gauge graduated from 0 to 400 psi.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497032" lims:id="497032"><Label>32</Label><Text>The below ground installation of liquefied petroleum gas tanks is not recommended.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="497033" lims:id="497033" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Piping and Transfer Equipment</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497034" lims:id="497034"><Label>33</Label><Text>Pumps and compressors used for transferring liquefied petroleum gas shall be of a type suitable for liquefied petroleum gas service, shall be designed for the maximum working pressure to which they will be subjected, and shall be so recommended and permanently marked or labelled by the manufacturer.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497035" lims:id="497035"><Label>34</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497036" lims:id="497036"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Pipelines of 1/2 inch nominal diameter or under shall be wrought iron, steel, brass or copper pipe, or seamless copper, brass, steel or aluminium tubing. Copper tubing may be of the standard grade K or L or equivalent and shall have a minimum wall thickness of 0.032 inch. Aluminium tubing shall not be used in exterior locations or where it will come in contact with masonry or plaster walls or insulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497037" lims:id="497037"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All piping and fittings over 1/2 inch nominal diameter shall be made of steel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497038" lims:id="497038"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Pipe joints may be screwed, flanged, welded, soldered or brazed with a material having a melting point exceeding 1,000°F.  Joints on seamless copper, brass, steel or nonferrous gas tubing shall be made by means of approved gas tubing fittings, soldered or brazed with a material having a melting point exceeding 1,000°F. Welded joints or welding flanges are recommended for container connections exceeding 2 inches in diameter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497039" lims:id="497039"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Welding may only be done by a qualified welder recognized as such by the Boiler and Pressure Vessel Inspection Branch of the provincial government concerned.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497040" lims:id="497040"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For working pressures of 125 psig or less, pipe and pipe fittings and tubing shall be designed for a pressure of at least 125 psig, and for working pressures above 125 psig, they shall be designed for the maximum pressure to which they may be subjected or 250 psig, whichever is the greater.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497041" lims:id="497041"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For pressures of 250 psig or greater, extra heavy pipe and fittings shall be used for threaded piping. Tubing shall be of heavy walled seamless construction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497042" lims:id="497042"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The bursting strength of any pipe or tubing and fittings shall be not less than four times the design pressure of the tank to which they are connected and not less than four times that pressure to which in any instance they may be subjected in service by the action of a pump or other device.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497043" lims:id="497043"><Label>35</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497044" lims:id="497044"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except as provided in subsection (3), all openings in containers, except those for safety relief valves and those connections protected by an opening not larger than No. 54 drill size (0.0550 inch), shall be equipped with excess flow valves or other suitable automatic valves or devices which will automatically prevent loss of the tank contents in the event of a connection or line failure.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497045" lims:id="497045"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Excess flow valves shall be designed with a by-pass not to exceed a No. 60 drill size (0.0400 inch) opening to allow equalization of pressure.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497046" lims:id="497046"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An excess flow valve or other automatic device as prescribed in subsection (1) is not required for withdrawal connections of tanks with a water capacity of 1,500 Imperial gallons or less if the connection is protected by a controlling orifice not exceeding 5/16 inch diameter on vapour withdrawal and not exceeding 1/8 inch diameter on liquid withdrawal, a manually operated shut-off valve and pressure-reducing regulator, all of which are assembled to the connection as prescribed in 2.2(d), Division II of the 1958 edition of National Fire Protection Association Pamphlet No. 58.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497047" lims:id="497047"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Excess flow valves shall be permanently marked or labelled by the manufacturer with their maximum working pressure, rated capacity, and the letters “LPG” to indicate suitability for use in liquefied petroleum gas service.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497048" lims:id="497048"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Excess flow valves or other automatic devices, as referred to in subsection (1), shall be installed in such a manner that rupture of the line or connections will not adversely affect the protective device.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497049" lims:id="497049"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The line or connection housing an excess flow valve shall have a greater capacity than the rated capacity of the excess flow valve.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497050" lims:id="497050"><Label>36</Label><Text>All storage tank inlet and outlet connections, except those for safety relief valves, liquid level gauging devices and pressure gauges, shall be labelled to indicated whether they communicate with the vapour or liquid phase during normal operations.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497051" lims:id="497051"><Label>37</Label><Text>All connections, except those for pressure or liquid level gauges, safety relief valves, or plugged openings, shall be provided with shut-off valves located as close to the storage tank as possible.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497052" lims:id="497052"><Label>38</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497053" lims:id="497053"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All shut-off valves, throttling valves, gauges, fittings and accessory equipment shall be of a type suitable for liquefied petroleum gas service, and designed for not less than the maximum working pressure to which they will be subjected, except that the rated working pressure of valves, fittings, etc., subject to container pressure shall not be less than 250 psig.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497054" lims:id="497054"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All valves, gauges, fittings and accessory equipment mentioned in subsection (1) shall be permanently marked or labelled with the “maximum working pressure” and “L.P.G.”; e.g. “250<Leader leader="dot" length="5pc" />L.P.G.”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497055" lims:id="497055"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Cast iron pipe, valves and fitting are prohibited in piping carrying liquefied petroleum gas in the liquid phase or on liquefied petroleum gas containers and their connections.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497056" lims:id="497056"><Label>39</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497057" lims:id="497057"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Piping shall be carried on permanent supports of steel or concrete and supports for pipelines more than 4 feet above ground shall rest on footings that extend below the frost line.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497058" lims:id="497058"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Pipelines shall be protected by guard rails against damage from moving vehicles and other traffic.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497059" lims:id="497059"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Provision shall be made in the pipeline for expansion, contraction, jarring, vibration and settling.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497060" lims:id="497060"><Label>40</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497061" lims:id="497061"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Hose and hose connections subject to container pressure shall be designed to have a bursting pressure not less than five times the maximum working pressure to which they may be subjected.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497062" lims:id="497062"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The hose as assembled for use shall be tested for leaks at twice the maximum working pressure to which it may be subjected before being put into service and should be tested annually thereafter at 1 1/2 times the maximum working pressure.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497063" lims:id="497063"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The hose shall be clearly and permanently marked or labelled “L.P. Gas” together with maximum working pressure, manufacturer’s name or symbol, and year of manufacture.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497064" lims:id="497064"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Hose and hose connections shall be resistant to the action of liquefied petroleum gas under the service conditions to which they are subjected.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497065" lims:id="497065"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Testing procedures as prescribed by the Underwriters’ Laboratories, Inc. Pamphlet <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Hose for Conducting L.P. Gas</XRefExternal> are recommended.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497066" lims:id="497066"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Hose and hose connections located on the low pressure side of regulators or reducing valves shall be designed for a working pressure of not less than 125 psig and in no case less than five times the pressure setting of the safety relief devices protecting the system.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497067" lims:id="497067"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Flexible hose connections to appliances shall be as prescribed in the current edition of National Fire Protection Association Pamphlet No. 58.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497068" lims:id="497068"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Where hose is to be used for transferring liquid, wet hose is recommended.  Such hose shall be equipped with a shut-off valve on the discharge end and provision shall be made to prevent excessive hydrostatic pressure in the hose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497069" lims:id="497069"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The use of hose is prohibited for inter-connecting stationary containers.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497070" lims:id="497070"><Label>41</Label><Text>Provision shall be made in loading and unloading lines for relief of pressure before disconnection.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497071" lims:id="497071"><Label>42</Label><Text>All piping, subject to external corrosion, shall be painted or otherwise protected.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497072" lims:id="497072"><Label>43</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497073" lims:id="497073"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Pipelines running parallel to a track, except those between adjacent loading or unloading racks, shall not be closer than 10 feet to the gauge side of the nearest rail of that track and shall comply with subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497074" lims:id="497074"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except for pipelines between adjacent loading or unloading racks, pipelines on the railway right-of-way and within 20 feet of a track shall be laid not less than 3 feet below ground, be enclosed in a reinforced concrete or steel trench, as prescribed in section 44, be carried on an overhead pipe bridge with a clearance above ground of not less than 13 feet or be enclosed by a suitable fence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497075" lims:id="497075"><Label>44</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497076" lims:id="497076"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except as prescribed in subsections (2) and (3), below ground liquefied petroleum gas pipelines shall be laid not less than 3 feet below ground level or be enclosed in a reinforced concrete or steel trench with a recessed removable cover which shall be flush with the ground.  The trench shall be of sufficient strength to support all traffic that may pass over it and shall be provided with drainage.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497077" lims:id="497077"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Pipelines under railways shall be installed in accordance with <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pipe Crossings Under Railways (No. E-10) Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497078" lims:id="497078"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Pipelines under roadways on railway property shall be enclosed in an encasing pipe of sufficient strength to support all traffic which may pass over it and shall not be less than 3 feet below the surface of the road.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497079" lims:id="497079"><Label>45</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497080" lims:id="497080"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The piping system shall be electrically grounded for protection against the build-up of static electricity, as prescribed in the latest edition of the National Fire Protection Association Pamphlet No. 77.  The resistance to ground should be as low as possible and preferably not more than 6 ohms.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497081" lims:id="497081"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All pipelines shall be bonded at the joints with a No. 6 electrical conductor where flow to ground is interrupted by a gasket, joint compound, etc.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497082" lims:id="497082"><Label>46</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497083" lims:id="497083"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The use of stationary internal combustion engines for the operation of liquefied petroleum gas pumps, compressors or vapourizers is not recommended, but if necessary, the installation shall be in accordance with subsections (2), (3), (5), (6) and (7).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497084" lims:id="497084"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If housed, an internal combustion engine shall be isolated from the pump or compressor by fireproof and vapourproof walls.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497085" lims:id="497085"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Except for the frame, the building shall be constructed of non-combustible or fire restraint materials.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497086" lims:id="497086"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The spark plugs and ignition system should be shielded and the engine equipped with a spark arrestor muffler.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497087" lims:id="497087"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The entire system shall be maintained in good operating condition at all times.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497088" lims:id="497088"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The exhaust shall terminate outside the building.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497089" lims:id="497089"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The building shall be cross ventilated near the floor level with permanently open louvers.</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497090" lims:id="497090" first-line-indent="0" language-align="no" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="3.5"><Label>NOTE:</Label><Text>Electric motors used for the operation of liquefied petroleum gas pumps, compressors or vapourizers shall be explosion proof, as prescribed in section 69.</Text></Provision></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497091" lims:id="497091"><Label>47</Label><Text>All materials such as joint compounds, gaskets, valve seats and packing shall be resistant to the action of liquefied petroleum gas under the service conditions to which they are subjected.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497092" lims:id="497092"><Label>48</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497093" lims:id="497093"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All piping, valves and fittings shall be inspected and tested after assembly and prior to commencing operations for the first time and be proven gastight at a pressure not less than the working pressure of the tank, pump or device to which they are connected, or at 150 psig, if this is a higher pressure.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497094" lims:id="497094"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The results of the test of subsection (1) shall be reported to the Commission.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497095" lims:id="497095"><Label>49</Label><Text>When loading or unloading racks are not employed for loading or unloading tank cars, the filling or discharge terminals shall be protected on all sides by a guard rail of metal or other material of equivalent strength and permanence.  Guard rails shall be not less than 3 feet in height.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497096" lims:id="497096"><Label>50</Label><Text>Loading or unloading lines shall be equipped with shut-off valves at the tank car end of the line.  These valves shall not be used for throttling purposes but shall be either fully open or fully closed in order not to interfere with the operation of excess flow valves on the tank car.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="497097" lims:id="497097" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Safety Relief Devices</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497098" lims:id="497098"><Label>51</Label><Text>A cylinder or tank with a water capacity not exceeding 100 Imperial gallons and manufactured, filled, operated and maintained in accordance with a Canadian Transport Commission or an Interstate Commerce Commission specification, which is approved by either of these authorities for liquefied petroleum gas use, is exempt from the provisions of this Part.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497099" lims:id="497099"><Label>52</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497100" lims:id="497100"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every storage tank and vapourizer (except as provided in Part VII) shall be provided with one or more safety relief valves of the spring loaded type or an equivalent type which have been approved for the intended service by the Boiler and Pressure Vessel Committee of the A.S.M.E. or the Compressed Gas Association, Inc. or Underwriters’ Laboratories.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497101" lims:id="497101"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Such valves shall be of a size that will ensure a rate of discharge not less than specified in the current edition of National Fire Protection Association’s Pamphlet No. 58.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497102" lims:id="497102"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The rate of discharge prescribed in subsection (2) shall be obtained before the pressure is in excess of 120 per cent of the maximum (not including the permitted plus tolerance of 10 per cent) permitted start to discharge pressure setting of the device.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497103" lims:id="497103"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Safety relief valves shall be installed in a manner that will ensure that the full relief requirements are always satisfied.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497104" lims:id="497104"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Storage tank and vapourizer safety relief valves shall be set to start to discharge at pressures as prescribed in the current edition of the National Fire Protection Association’s Pamphlet No. 58 for vessels designed according to the A.S.M.E. Code.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497105" lims:id="497105"><Label>53</Label><Text>A safety relief valve venting to the outside atmosphere shall be installed between each pair of shut-off valves on liquefied petroleum gas liquid lines where liquid may be trapped.  The start to discharge pressure setting shall not be in excess of 5000 psig.  The minimum setting shall not be lower than 140 per cent of the container relief valve setting, except that for 1.C.C. or B.T.C. containers, the minimum setting shall not be lower than 400 psig.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497106" lims:id="497106"><Label>54</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497107" lims:id="497107"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For tanks exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons water capacity, the discharge from tank safety relief devices shall be vented vertically to the outside atmosphere at a point not less than 7 feet above the storage tank.  Such discharge should be at least 100 feet and in no case shall it be less than 50 feet from any open flame or source of ignition.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497108" lims:id="497108"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For tanks with a water capacity of 2,000 Imperial gallons or less, the discharge from safety relief devices shall be vented vertically to the outside atmosphere in a manner that will prevent the gases from impinging on the tank.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497109" lims:id="497109"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The ends of relief valve discharge pipes shall be fitted with loose rain caps that cannot freeze in place.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497110" lims:id="497110"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>All storage tank relief devices shall be located on the storage tank and shall have direct communication with the vapour space of the storage tank.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497111" lims:id="497111"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the design of the safety relief system is such that liquid can collect on the discharge side of the disc, provision shall be made for drainage of the liquid.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497112" lims:id="497112"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Return bends and restrictive pipe fittings are not permitted in relief valve piping.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497113" lims:id="497113"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Safety relief devices shall be so arranged that the possibility of tampering will be minimized.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497114" lims:id="497114"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>External pressure settings or adjustments shall be sealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497115" lims:id="497115"><Label>55</Label><Text>The safety relief device shall be permanently marked or labelled with the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497116" lims:id="497116"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>start to discharge pressure in psig;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497117" lims:id="497117"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>full-open rate of discharge in c.f.m. of air at 60°F and 14.7 psia;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497118" lims:id="497118"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>manufacturer’s name or symbol;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497119" lims:id="497119"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>year of manufacture;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497120" lims:id="497120"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>letters “LPG” to indicate suitability for liquefied petroleum gas service; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497121" lims:id="497121"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>A.S.M.E. or Compressed Gas Association or Underwriters’ Laboratories approval symbol.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497122" lims:id="497122"><Label>56</Label><Text>Safety relief valves and devices shall be inspected and tested prior to being put into service and shall be tested periodically as prescribed in the Compressed Gas Association Pamphlet <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">Safety Relief Device Standards for Compressed Gas Storage Containers</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="497123" lims:id="497123" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Loading and Unloading</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497124" lims:id="497124"><Label>57</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497125" lims:id="497125"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The tank car, during loading and unloading operations, shall be protected on the connected end or ends of the siding by a sign of metal or other suitable material 12 inches by 15 inches in size and reading “STOP — TANK CAR CONNECTED”. The word “stop” shall be in letters at least 4 inches high and the other words in letters at least 2 inches high. Letters shall be white on a blue background.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497126" lims:id="497126"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The “Stop” sign shall be placed on the tank car or on the loading or unloading track in a manner that will ensure it is always visible to the crew of an engine on the same track.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497127" lims:id="497127"><Label>58</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497128" lims:id="497128"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>During loading or unloading operations, tank car hand brakes shall be kept applied and the wheels at both ends of the tank car shall be blocked.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497129" lims:id="497129"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Tank cars shall be disconnected from pipelines immediately after the completion of loading or unloading operations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497130" lims:id="497130"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>At least one experienced operator supplied by the consignee or the consignor, as the case may be, shall supervise the loading or unloading operation.  During the absence of the operator supervising the loading or unloading operation from the installation site, operations shall be discontinued.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497131" lims:id="497131"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Gas or liquid shall not be vented to the atmosphere to assist in transferring the contents of one container to another.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497132" lims:id="497132"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Loading or unloading operations shall only be carried out during the hours of daylight unless adequate permanent lighting installed in accordance with section 69 is provided.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497133" lims:id="497133"><Label>59</Label><Text>The direct transfer of liquefied petroleum gas between tank trucks and tank cars on carrier’s right-of-way is prohibited.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497134" lims:id="497134"><Label>60</Label><Text>All loading and unloading tracks shall be grounded and bonded at the loading and unloading site in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Electric Sparks Prevention Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497135" lims:id="497135"><Label>61</Label><Text>The loading and unloading of tank cars located on carrier’s tracks are subject to the following conditions:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497136" lims:id="497136"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>except as provided in paragraph (c), tank car discharge connections shall be equipped with excess flow valves;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497137" lims:id="497137"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>lading shall be piped directly to permanent storage tanks of sufficient capacity to receive the entire contents of the tank car; the tanks and all of the facilities associated with them shall be in accordance with all applicable provisions of these Regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497138" lims:id="497138"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>tank cars of the I.C.C. 106A type may be loaded or unloaded on carrier’s track if written permission is obtained from the carrier concerned and equipment is provided for the safe loading or unloading of the unit tanks, but such tanks shall not be stored on carrier’s property except as provided in these Regulations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497139" lims:id="497139"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>when the carrier’s track is a team track, it is recommended that, where practicable, the tank car be protected during loading or unloading by a locked derail located at least one car length from the tank car on the connected end or ends of the team track.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="497140" lims:id="497140" level="1"><Label>PART VII</Label><TitleText>Vapourizers</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497141" lims:id="497141"><Label>62</Label><Text>Except as otherwise provided in this Part, vapourizer design, location, construction and operation shall be in accordance with the current edition of National Fire Protection Association Pamphlet No. 58.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497142" lims:id="497142"><Label>63</Label><Text>Vapourizers, heating devices for vapourizers, and vapourizers buildings shall be separated from loading and unloading sites, tanks, location on an adjoining property which may be built upon or other buildings by distances not less than the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497143" lims:id="497143"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>indirect fired vapourizers, 10 feet;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497144" lims:id="497144"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>heating devices for indirect fired vapourizers, 25 feet;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497145" lims:id="497145"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>direct fired vapourizers, with a capacity of 100 gallons per hour or less, 25 feet; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497146" lims:id="497146"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>direct fired vapourizers with a capacity exceeding 100 gallons per hour, 50 feet.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497147" lims:id="497147"><Label>64</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497148" lims:id="497148"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Vapourizers, if housed, should be installed in detached buildings used exclusively for liquefied petroleum gas vapourization and if the vapourizer is installed in a lean-to, shed or room of a building, such building may only be used for liquefied petroleum gas operations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497149" lims:id="497149"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The vapourizer building or room, as the case may be, shall be constructed of non-combustible or fire resistant materials, shall be cross-ventilated at the floor and ceiling levels by louvered openings, and should be provided with not less than 1 square foot of explosion relief venting on the open side per 40 cubic feet of inside space.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497150" lims:id="497150"><Label>65</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497151" lims:id="497151"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A direct fired vapourizer or the heating device which supplies steam, hot water, or other fire-safe heating medium for an indirect fired vapourizer shall be separated from all other liquefied petroleum gas equipment, such as pumps or gas mixing devices by fireproof and vapourproof walls.  Access to such vapourizer and heating device shall be from the outside only.  The firewall shall be of not less than 1 hour fire resistance.  Other parts of the room housing the heating device shall be constructed of noncombustible or fire resistant material.  Cross ventilation shall be provided by other means than doors and windows.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497152" lims:id="497152"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This section does not apply to domestic water heaters which may supply heat for a vapourizer in a domestic system.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497153" lims:id="497153"><Label>66</Label><Text>The use of a direct gas-fired tank heater or the mounting of any vapourizer on a liquefied petroleum gas storage tank is prohibited on the railway right-of-way.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="497154" lims:id="497154" level="1"><Label>PART VIII</Label><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497155" lims:id="497155"><Label>67</Label><Text>The area within 25 feet of a tank with a water capacity exceeding 200 Imperial gallons, a loading or unloading rack, a pump, building, etc. shall be free of debris, and grass and weeds shall be kept cut to a height not exceeding 6 inches.  The general housekeeping and maintenance of buildings, tanks, etc. shall be of the highest standard.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497156" lims:id="497156"><Label>68</Label><Text>Defective piping, valves or fittings shall be repaired immediately.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497157" lims:id="497157"><Label>69</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497158" lims:id="497158"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Installations with a total water capacity not exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons that provide fuel directly to heating, cooking or welding appliances on the installation site are exempt from the requirements of this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497159" lims:id="497159"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All electric motors, switches, motor controllers, circuit breakers, wiring and any other electrical facility inside a building housing a liquefied petroleum gas pump or other similar equipment, or within 25 feet of an outdoor liquefied petroleum gas storage tank, loading or unloading point, pump or other similar equipment, shall conform to the regulations set forth in the latest edition of the Canadian Electrical Code for Class 1, Group D, Division I hazardous locations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497160" lims:id="497160"><Label>70</Label><Text>Smoking and the use of portable open flame lights or equipment shall be prohibited except in certain isolated and clearly designated safe areas, and signs to this effect shall be posted at the plant entrances and at the loading and unloading sites.  (See Section 75 for restrictions applying to welding)</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497161" lims:id="497161"><Label>71</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497162" lims:id="497162"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Water, dry powder, carbon dioxide, or other fire extinguishers suitable for liquefied petroleum gas fires shall be available on installations with storage capacities exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons.  At least one fire extinguisher shall be kept on the outside premises.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497163" lims:id="497163"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each storage area with a capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons should be protected by at least one standard fire hydrant so located that a 2 1/2-inch hose stream may be used for controlling a fire on the site or cooling a tank in case of adjacent fires.  Consultation with the local fire authority on these matters is recommended.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497164" lims:id="497164"><Label>72</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497165" lims:id="497165"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Uninsulated liquefied petroleum gas storage tanks with water capacities exceeding 100 Imperial gallons, which are installed out-of-doors, shall be painted with a heat reflective paint.  Paint should be white enamel or slow chalking, white paint rather than aluminium paint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497166" lims:id="497166"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The words “CAUTION-PROPANE” (or other liquefied petroleum gas name) not less than 6 inches high shall be painted on each outdoor storage tank with a water capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497167" lims:id="497167"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On application, the Railway Transport Committee may approve means of identification other than those prescribed by subsections (1) and (2).</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497169" lims:id="497169">SOR/81-144, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497170" lims:id="497170"><Label>73</Label><Text>Each liquefied petroleum gas installation with a storage capacity exceeding 2,000 Imperial gallons of water shall be completely enclosed within a steel mesh fence not less than 5 feet high.  The mesh shall be made from steel wire of not less than 0.10 inch diameter.  The opening in the mesh shall not be greater than 6 inches.  The fence gates shall be locked when the installation is unattended and at least two means of access through the fencing shall be provided.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497171" lims:id="497171"><Label>74</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497172" lims:id="497172"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except for the frame, all buildings, compartments, bottling rooms, lean-tos or platforms shall be constructed of non-combustible or fire resistant materials.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497173" lims:id="497173"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All enclosures where liquefied petroleum gas is handled shall be provided with cross ventilation by means of permanently open louvers near floor level.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497174" lims:id="497174"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Containers of flammable liquids or gases shall not be stored in a room occupied by liquefied petroleum gas equipment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497175" lims:id="497175"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Buildings shall be maintained in a clean and tidy condition.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497176" lims:id="497176"><Label>75</Label><Text>Welding shall not be permitted within 150 feet of a loading or unloading site while loading or unloading operations are in progress.  At other times, welding may only be allowed when carried out under close supervision and in accordance with the provisions of Canadian Standards Association Pamphlet W-117.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497177" lims:id="497177"><Label>76</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497178" lims:id="497178"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All liquefied petroleum gases shall be effectively odourized by an approved agent of such character as positively indicates, by distinct odour, the presence of gas down to concentrations in air of not over one-fifth the lower limit of flammability.  For propane the lower limit of flammability is 2.37 per cent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497179" lims:id="497179"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Exemption from the requirements of this section may be granted if it is established to the satisfaction of the Commission that the odourant will be harmful in subsequent processing or use of the gas.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497180" lims:id="497180"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The requirements of subsection (1) shall be deemed to be complied with if 1 pound of Ethyl Mercaptan, 1 pound of Thiophane, or 1.4 pounds of Amyl Mercaptan per 10,000 gallons of liquefied petroleum gas is used.  The listing of odourants in this section is not intended to exclude the use of other odourants which meet the requirements of subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497181" lims:id="497181"><Label>77</Label><Text>Under ordinary circumstances, the diking of liquefied petroleum gas storage tanks is not required, except that the Commission may require erection of a dike under those circumstances where a dike would provide protection for adjoining property.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497182" lims:id="497182"><Label>78</Label><Text>All liquefied petroleum gas installations are subject to inspection at any time by any duly authorized officer of the Commission.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497183" lims:id="497183"><Label>79</Label><Text>The owning or operating company shall report immediately by wire to the railway company concerned and to the Director of Operation, Canadian Transport Commission, Ottawa, Ontario, every fire resulting in damage to the installation, every explosion or major pipe line or tank failure occurring on the installation, and shall submit a detailed report by mail of such accident.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497184" lims:id="497184"><Label>80</Label><Text>For further details, the following publications are suggested:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497185" lims:id="497185"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>liquefied petroleum gas Pamphlets Nos. 58 and 59 published by the National Fire Protection Association, 60 Batterymarch Street, Boston 10, Massachusetts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497186" lims:id="497186"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="other">Handbook of Butane and Propane Gases</XRefExternal> published by Jenkins Publications, Inc., 198 South Alvarado Street, Los Angeles 4, California;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497187" lims:id="497187"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Compressed Gas Association pamphlet <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">Safety Relief Device Standards for Compressed Gas Storage Containers</XRefExternal> published by the Compressed Gas Association, Inc., 500 Fifth Ave., New York 36, New York; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497188" lims:id="497188"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>Underwriters’ Laboratories, Inc., pamphlet <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Hose for Conducting LP Gas</XRefExternal> published by Underwriters’ Laboratories of Canada, P.O. Box 38, O’Connor Postal Station, Toronto 16, Ontario, or Underwriters’ Laboratories, Inc., 161 Sixth Avenue, New York 13, New York.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-06-18" lims:fid="497189" lims:id="497189" level="1"><Label>PART IX</Label><TitleText>Switch Heater Facilities</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497190" lims:id="497190"><Label>81</Label><Text>This Part applies to switch heater facilities with a storage capacity of 2000 imp. gal. or less.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497192" lims:id="497192">SOR/79-201, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497193" lims:id="497193"><Label>82</Label><Text>Switch heater facilities shall be designed, located, constructed, operated and maintained in full compliance with these Regulations.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497195" lims:id="497195">SOR/79-201, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497196" lims:id="497196"><Label>83</Label><Text>Foundations shall be built in accordance with sound engineering practice and in such a way as to prevent damage to the tank and piping system.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497198" lims:id="497198">SOR/79-201, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497199" lims:id="497199"><Label>84</Label><Text>Copper tubes up to 3/4 inch nominal diameter may be used.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497201" lims:id="497201">SOR/79-201, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497202" lims:id="497202"><Label>85</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497203" lims:id="497203"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The area within 25 feet of a tank and above ground piping shall be kept free of debris and combustible materials, other than ties that are in place on the track.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497204" lims:id="497204"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The area within 10 feet of a tank and above ground piping shall be kept free of vegetation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497205" lims:id="497205"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The maintenance of the facilities shall be of the highest standard.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497207" lims:id="497207">SOR/79-201, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497208" lims:id="497208"><Label>86</Label><Text>At the end of every year, the railway company shall, by mail, inform the Secretary of the Railway Transport Committee of the mileage point and the name of the subdivision at which switch heater facilities were constructed during the year.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497210" lims:id="497210">SOR/79-201, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>