<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499426" lims:id="499426" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499427" lims:id="499427"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 121</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499429" lims:id="499429"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499430" lims:id="499430">Victoria International Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499431" lims:id="499431">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Victoria International Airport</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499432" lims:id="499432"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499433" lims:id="499433" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499434" lims:id="499434"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._121">Victoria International Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499435" lims:id="499435" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499436" lims:id="499436"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499437" lims:id="499437" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means Victoria International Airport, Saanich Peninsula, in the Province of British Columbia; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499438" lims:id="499438" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499439" lims:id="499439" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane, the lower end of which is a horizontal line at right angles to the centre line of a strip and passing through a point at the strip end on the centre line of the strip; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499440" lims:id="499440" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>horizontal surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary horizontal plane centering on and located 150 feet above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point; (<DefinedTermFr>surface horizontale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499441" lims:id="499441" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Revoked, SOR/93-401, s. 2]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499442" lims:id="499442" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means a rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport especially prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction and being</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499443" lims:id="499443"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>1,200 feet in width, including the runway, in the case of the runway designated as 08-26, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499444" lims:id="499444"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>1,000 feet in width, including the runways, in the case of the runways designated as 02-20 and 13-31; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499445" lims:id="499445" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from the outer lateral limits of a strip and its approach surface to an intersection with the horizontal surface or other transitional surfaces. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499447" lims:id="499447">SOR/93-401, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499448" lims:id="499448"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the airport reference point is deemed to be 43 feet above sea level.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499449" lims:id="499449" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499450" lims:id="499450"><Label>4</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, as more particularly described in Part II of the schedule.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499451" lims:id="499451" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499452" lims:id="499452"><Label>5</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct, on any land to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of the highest point any of the surfaces hereinafter set out that project immediately over and above the surface of the land at that location, namely,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499453" lims:id="499453"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a horizontal surface, the outer limit of which may be described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499454" lims:id="499454" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the high water mark on the Southeast corner of the property owned by Towner Bay Country Club; THENCE, Northerly along the East boundary of the said property to the Westerly production of the North boundary of Lot 4 of Plan 5468; THENCE, Easterly along the said production and Northerly boundaries of said Lot 4 of Plan 5468, and A, B and C of Plan 11925 to the Southeast corner of Lot 2, Plan 6228; THENCE, Northerly along the East boundary and production of said Lot 2, Plan 6228 to the Northerly limit of Downey Road; THENCE, Easterly along said Northerly limit to the Southeast corner of Lot 6 of Plan 6710; THENCE, Northerly along the East boundaries of Lots 6 and 12 of said Plan 6710 and continuing on a Northerly production to the Northerly limit of Wain Road; THENCE, Easterly along said Northerly limit of Wain Road to the West boundary of Section 19, R. 1 W.; THENCE, Northerly along the West boundary of said Section 19 to the Northwest corner of said Section; THENCE, Easterly along the North boundaries of R. 1 W. and R. 1 and 2 E. Section 19 to the high water mark; THENCE, Easterly along the high water mark to the Northwest corner of Lot 4, Plan 6621; THENCE, Easterly along the Northerly boundaries of Lots 4 and 8, Plan 6621 to the Westerly limit of Dunne Road; THENCE, Southeasterly along the Southwesterly limits of Dunne, Kedge Anchor, and Inwood Roads to the Westerly production of the South boundary of Plan 9207; THENCE, Easterly along the South boundary of said Plan 9207 to the high water mark; THENCE, Southerly along the last-mentioned high water mark to the Southeasterly corner of Lot 2, Plan 16852; THENCE, Southeasterly in a straight line to the Southwesterly corner of Lot 9, Plan 1170; THENCE, Easterly and Southerly along the high water mark to an intersection of the Southerly limit of Bazan Bay Avenue with said high water mark; THENCE, South 73°57′20″ East astronomic for 3,200 feet; THENCE, South 16°02′40″ West astronomic for 3,146 feet; THENCE, North 73°57′20″ west astronomic to the high water mark; THENCE, Southerly along the said high water mark to the intersection of the Northerly limit of Amity Drive; THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly and Easterly limits of Amity Drive, Moxon and Emard Terraces, and East Saanich Road to the South boundary of Section 4, R. 2 E.; THENCE, Westerly and Northerly along the South and West boundaries, respectively, of Sections 4 and 5, R. 2 E., to the Northeast corner of Section 5, R. 1 E.; THENCE, Westerly along the North boundaries of Section 5, Ranges 1E. and 1 and 2W. to the high water mark; THENCE, Westerly along the high water mark to the Westerly limit of Glenelg Avenue; THENCE, Northerly and Westerly along the Westerly limits of Glenelg and Aboyne Avenues to the Northwest corner of Lot 4, Block 18, Plan 1936; THENCE, Northerly along the West boundaries of Lots 9 and 2, Block 14, Plan 1936 and across Braemer Road to the South boundary of said Lot 4, Block 11 to the Easterly limit of Ardmore Drive; THENCE, Northerly along the said Easterly limit to the Southerly limit of Dalkeith Avenue; THENCE, Westerly along the Southerly limit of Dalkeith Avenue to the high water mark; THENCE, Northeasterly along the last-mentioned high water mark to the Northeasterly corner of Lot 1, Plan 1237; THENCE, North 73°57′20″ west astronomic for 4,200 feet; THENCE, North 16°02′40″ east astronomic for 3,188 feet; THENCE, South 73°57′20″ east to the high water mark; THENCE, Northwesterly along the said high water mark to the point of commencement,</Text></Provision></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499455" lims:id="499455"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the approach surfaces abutting each end of the strip designated as 08-26 and extending outward therefrom, the dimensions of which approach surfaces are six hundred (600) feet on each side of the centre line of the strip at the strip ends and two thousand (2,000) feet on each side of the projected centre line of the strip at the outer ends, the said outer ends being two hundred (200) feet above the elevations at the strip ends, and measured horizontally ten thousand (10,000) feet from the said strip ends; the approach surfaces abutting each end of the strip designated as 13-31 and strip 20 and extending outward therefrom, the dimensions of which approach surfaces are five hundred (500) feet on each side of the centre line of the strip at the strip ends and one thousand two hundred and fifty (1,250) feet on each side of the projected centre line of the strip at the outer ends, the said outer ends being two hundred and fifty (250) feet above the elevations at the strip ends and measured horizontally ten thousand (10,000) feet from the said strip ends; and the approach surface abutting the end of the strip designated as 02 and extending outward therefrom, the dimensions of which approach surface are five hundred (500) feet on each side of the centre line of the strip at the strip end and five hundred (500) feet on each side of the projected centre line of the strip at the outer end, the said outer end being five hundred (500) feet above the elevation at the strip end, and measured horizontally ten thousand (10,000) feet from the said strip end, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499456" lims:id="499456"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the several transitional surfaces, each rising at an angle determined on the basis of a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically for every seven (7) feet measured horizontally from the outer lateral limits of the strips and their abutting surfaces,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499457" lims:id="499457"><Text>as shown on Plan E.900 dated March 15, 1966, of record in the Department of Transport at Ottawa.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499458" lims:id="499458" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499459" lims:id="499459"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499460" lims:id="499460" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499461" lims:id="499461" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Southwest corner of section 8, Range 1 East; THENCE, Easterly a distance of three hundred and seventy (370) feet to the centre line of Runway 02-20; THENCE, North 44°06′50″ East astronomic a distance of five thousand four hundred (5,400) feet; THENCE, Southeasterly at right angles to the centre line of Runway 02-20, a distance of one hundred and ninety (190) feet.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499462" lims:id="499462" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of Lands to Which These Regulations Apply</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499463" lims:id="499463" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ALL AND SINGULAR those certain parcels or tracts of land and premises, situate, lying and being on the Saanich Peninsula, in the Province of British Columbia, and composed of the whole of sections Two (2) Range Four (4) East, Four (4), Five (5) and Six (6), Ranges Two (2) and Three (3) East, Seven (7) Ranges One (1), Two (2) and Three (3) East, and Ranges One (1) and Two (2) West, Eight (8) Ranges One (1), Two (2), Three (3) and Four (4) East, and Ranges One (1), Two (2) and Three (3) West, Nine (9) Ranges One (1), Two (2), Three (3) and Four (4) East and Ranges One (1), Two (2) and Three (3) West, Ten (10), Eleven (11) and Twelve (12) Ranges One (1), Two (2), Three (3) and Four (4) East and Ranges One (1) and Two (2) West, Thirteen (13), Fourteen (14), Sixteen (16), Eighteen (18) and Nineteen (19) Range One (1) West, and Ranges One (1), Two (2), Three (3) and Four (4) East, Fifteen (15) and Seventeen (17) Ranges One (1), Two (2) and Three (3) East, and Range 1 West; and parts of sections Two (2) and Twenty (20), Range Three (3) East, Three (3) Ranges Two (2) and Three (3) East, Five (5) Ranges Two (2) and Three (3) West, Six (6) Ranges One (1), Two (2) and Three (3) East, and Ranges One (1), Two (2) and Three (3) West, Seven (7) Range Two (2) East and Range Three (3) West, Fifteen (15), Sixteen (16), Seventeen (17), Eighteen (18) and Nineteen (19) Range Two (2) West, and the waters of Tsehum (Shoal) Harbour, Blue Heron Basin, All Bay and Roberts Bay, whose outermost boundaries are described as the horizontal surface limits of paragraph 5(a) of these Regulations where all lands, waters and roads enclosed by the boundaries of the description are affected by these Regulations, but excluding all lands, waters and roads therefrom within the area whose outermost boundary is described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499464" lims:id="499464" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Northwesterly corner of Lot 13, Plan 2818; THENCE, Northeasterly along the Easterly limit of West Saanich Road to the Northwest corner of Lot 14, Plan 1498; THENCE, Easterly and Northerly along the boundary of Plan 1498 to an intersection with the Southerly limit of Mills Road; THENCE, Easterly along said Southerly limit of Mills Road to the Northeast corner of Lot 9, Plan 1001; THENCE, Southerly along the Easterly boundaries of Lots 9, 10, and 11, Plan 1001, to the Southerly limit of Henry Avenue; THENCE, Easterly along the aforesaid Southerly limit to the Northeast corner of Lot B, Plan 113; THENCE, Southerly along the Easterly boundaries of Lot B, Plan 113, and Lot 1, Plan 3861 (Expropriation Instrument No. 13510S) and extension thereof to the Southerly limit of Beacon Avenue; THENCE, Easterly along the Southerly limit of Beacon Avenue to the Westerly limit of the Patricia Bay Highway; THENCE, Southerly along the Westerly limit of the said Patricia Bay Highway to the Northerly limit of Ocean Avenue; THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly limit of Ocean Avenue to the Easterly limit of Canora Road; THENCE, Northerly along the said Easterly limit of Canora Road to the Southwest corner of Plan 115; THENCE, Easterly, Northerly and Westerly along the boundaries of Plan 115 and continuing Westerly to the Westerly limit of Canora Road; THENCE, Southerly along the Westerly limit of Canora and East Saanich Roads to the Northerly limit of Brickyard Road; THENCE, Westerly along the said Northerly limit of Brickyard Road to a Northerly production of the Westerly boundary of Lot 1, Block 9, Plan 1433; THENCE, Southerly along the aforesaid Northerly production of the Westerly boundary of Lot 1, Block 9, Plan 1433, to the Northeast corner of Lot A, Plan 3632; THENCE, Westerly and Southerly along the northerly and westerly boundaries of Block A, Plan 3632, to the Westerly limit of East Saanich Road; THENCE, Southerly along the said Westerly limit of East Saanich Road to the Northeast corner of Lot 4, Block 8, Plan 1433; THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundaries of Lots 4 and 3 and its production to the Westerly limit of Basswood Road; THENCE, Southerly along the said Westerly limit of Basswood Road to the Northerly limit of Dickson Avenue; THENCE, Westerly along the said Northerly limit of Dickson Avenue to the Easterly limit of Creswell Road; THENCE, Northerly along the said Easterly limit of Creswell Road to the Northerly boundary of Section 7. R. 1 E.; THENCE, Westerly along the said Northerly boundary of Section 7, R. 1 E. to the Easterly limit of Montrose Avenue; THENCE, Northerly along the said Easterly limit of Montrose Avenue to the Southerly boundary of Section 9, R. 1 E; THENCE, Westerly and Northerly along the Southerly and Westerly boundaries respectively of Sections 9 and 10, R. 1 E. to the Northeasterly corner of Lot 13, Plan 2818; THENCE, Northwesterly along the Northerly boundary of Lot 13, Plan 2818, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499465" lims:id="499465" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>THE WHOLE as shown within coloured lines on Plan E.900 dated March 15, 1966, of record in the Department of Transport at Ottawa.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="499466" lims:id="499466" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>All plans referred to in the above description are on record at the Victoria Land Registry Office at Victoria, British Columbia.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>