<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503433" lims:id="503433" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503434" lims:id="503434"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1320</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503436" lims:id="503436"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-29.4">FOREIGN MISSIONS AND INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503437" lims:id="503437">United Nations Remission Order</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503438" lims:id="503438">Order for the Remission of Certain Duties and Taxes on Goods Imported or Purchased by the United Nations</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503439" lims:id="503439"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503440" lims:id="503440" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503441" lims:id="503441"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Order may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1320">United Nations Remission Order</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503442" lims:id="503442" level="1"><TitleText>Free Entry, Refund or Remission</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503443" lims:id="503443"><Label>2</Label><Text>Authority is hereby granted, effective January 2, 1952, for the refund or remission of the excise stamp tax on official cheques and for free entry, refund or remission of the following customs duties and the consumption or sales tax imposed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-15">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> on the goods listed in the schedule, when imported into Canada or purchased therein either for sale, use or free distribution by the United Nations or its agents, subject to compliance with the conditions and procedures set out in the schedule.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503444" lims:id="503444" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503445" lims:id="503445"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(s. 2)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503446" lims:id="503446" pointsize="7" topmarginspacing="4" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503447" lims:id="503447" frame="topbot"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503448" lims:id="503448" cols="3"><colspec colname="1" /><colspec colname="2" /><colspec colname="3" /><thead lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503449" lims:id="503449"><row topdouble="yes"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Revenue Exemption or Privilege</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Conditions</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" align="center" valign="bottom">Procedure</entry></row></thead><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503450" lims:id="503450"><row topmarginspacing="8"><entry rowheader="yes" colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>1</Label><Text>Exempt from the excise stamp tax on official cheques.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>When such cheques are drawn on official funds of the United Nations.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Cheques issued against personal accounts are subject to the excise stamp tax.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /></row><row><entry rowheader="yes" colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>2</Label><Text>Exempt from customs duties, including the consumption or sales tax, and from prohibitions and restrictions on imports and exports in respect of articles imported or exported by the United Nations for its official use.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Articles which have been admitted free under these Regulations and which have been in the use and possession of the importer in Canada for a period of at least one year may be sold or disposed of in Canada without payment of duty and taxes. Otherwise they shall be subject to the ordinary provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-15">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Official use</DefinedTermEn> means use to advance the objects of the United Nations and not enuring to the financial benefit of the importer or any other individual.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>Upon execution of the usual import and export entries as required.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>The following statement should be endorsed by the importer on customs entries where applicable: “Free under provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privileges and Immunities (International Organizations) Act</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes" colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>3</Label><Text>Exempt from any prohibition or restriction on import, export, use or sale of its publications, printed matter, films and sound recordings, and exempt from customs duties and excise taxes in respect thereof.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Publications, printed matter, films, and sound recordings may be imported, exported, used or sold without payment of customs duty, sales or excise taxes.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>Upon execution of the usual import and export entries as required.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Import entries should bear the endorsement outlined in section 2, where applicable.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes" colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>4</Label><Text>When goods are purchased under appropriate certificates from manufacturers or wholesalers who are licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-15">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the United Nations should, under Article II, section 8 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privileges and Immunities (International Organizations) Act</XRefExternal>, be eligible to claim for the remission or refund of the excise tax and/or the consumption or sales tax on goods imported or purchased in Canada for the official use of the United Nations as a body.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Provided, however, that any article which is exempted from these taxes, other than publications, printed matter, films or sound recordings shall be subject thereto at existing rates if sold or otherwise disposed of in Canada within a period of one year from the date of purchase, and the vendor shall be liable for such tax.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>Such exemption is to be effected by remission or refund where the United Nations is making taxable purchases, for official use, of goods on which such taxes have been charged or are chargeable. A senior officer or authorized agent should, when ordering the goods, include a certificate over his signature to the effect that the account is to be paid with the funds of the United Nations and that exemption is properly allowable under provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privileges and Immunities (International Organizations) Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes" colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>5</Label><Text>The United Nations shall have the right to use codes and to dispatch and receive its correspondence by courier or in bags which shall have the same immunities and privileges as diplomatic couriers and bags.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to preclude the adoption of appropriate security precautions to be determined by agreement between the United Nations and the Government of Canada.</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>When any despatch bag or package arrives in Canada addressed to the United Nations or to any of the senior officials of the United Nations which, from such examination as can be made thereof without breaking the seal, shall appear to contain only official documents, it shall be forwarded with detention by the customs authorities direct to the official to whom addressed.</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule></Regulation>