<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549489" lims:id="549489" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549490" lims:id="549490"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 322</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549492" lims:id="549492"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">APPROPRIATION ACT NO. 3, 1976</XRefExternal><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="Z-01">APPROPRIATION ACTS</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549493" lims:id="549493">Development Tax and Redevelopment Tax Grant Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549494" lims:id="549494">Regulations Respecting Payments in Lieu of Development and Redevelopment Taxes on Federal Property</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549495" lims:id="549495"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549496" lims:id="549496" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549497" lims:id="549497"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._322">Development Tax and Redevelopment Tax Grant Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549498" lims:id="549498" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549499" lims:id="549499"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549500" lims:id="549500" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>defined area</DefinedTermEn> means an area within a municipality in which a development tax or redevelopment tax is levied; (<DefinedTermFr>zone déterminée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549501" lims:id="549501" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>development tax or redevelopment tax</DefinedTermEn> means a compulsory levy imposed by a municipality on real property situated within a defined area that is</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549502" lims:id="549502"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>payable by a taxable owner of real property by virtue of his ownership of such property or of specified actions undertaken by him to develop such property,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549503" lims:id="549503"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>calculated by reference to all or part of the frontage, area or other attribute of land or buildings of the owner,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549504" lims:id="549504"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>assessed at a uniform rate upon owners of real property liable to pay the tax, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549505" lims:id="549505"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>levied for the purpose of financing all or part of the capital cost of the construction or reconstruction of a trunk or arterial road or any other capital service that has been, is being or will be carried out within the defined area,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedDefinition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549506" lims:id="549506"><Text>but does not include a levy in respect of which payments by way of a grant may be made under section 4 or 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Municipal Grants Act</XRefExternal> or a levy on real property paid to a municipality in the form of a land transfer or of cash in lieu thereof; (<DefinedTermFr>taxe d'aménagement ou de réaménagement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></ContinuedDefinition></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549507" lims:id="549507" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal property</DefinedTermEn> means federal property as defined in subection 6(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Municipal Grants Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>propriété fédérale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549508" lims:id="549508" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>other attribute of land or buildings</DefinedTermEn> includes the actual or estimated cost of construction on a site, the number of rooms, living units or beds or the number of persons in occupancy. (<DefinedTermFr>autre caractéristique des biens immeubles</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549509" lims:id="549509" level="1"><TitleText>Grants</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549510" lims:id="549510"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to section 4, on receipt of an application from a municipality in a form prescribed by the Minister, the Minister may pay to the municipality, in respect of federal property, a grant in lieu of a development tax or redevelopment tax not exceeding the amount of tax that would be payable if federal property were taxable property.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549511" lims:id="549511"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Minister may, in determining the amount of a grant payable to a municipality under these Regulations in respect of federal property within a defined area, deduct from the amount that would otherwise be payable an amount that, in the opinion of the Minister, is equal to the product of the total proceeds of the development tax or redevelopment tax in respect of that area multiplied by a fraction the denominator of which is the said total proceeds and the numerator of which is that portion of the said total proceeds that relates to the financing of services of a kind that the federal government, at its own expense, has carried out, is carrying out or plans to carry out.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549512" lims:id="549512" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549513" lims:id="549513"><Label>5</Label><Text>These Regulations apply in respect of a development tax or redevelopment tax on federal property that would, if the federal property were taxable property, have become due and payable on or after January 1, 1974.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>