<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561750" lims:id="561750" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561751" lims:id="561751"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 77</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561753" lims:id="561753"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561754" lims:id="561754">Calgary International Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561755" lims:id="561755">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Calgary International Airport</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561756" lims:id="561756"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561757" lims:id="561757" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561758" lims:id="561758"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._77">Calgary International Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561759" lims:id="561759" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561760" lims:id="561760"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561761" lims:id="561761" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means Calgary International Airport near and in Calgary, in the Province of Alberta; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561762" lims:id="561762" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561763" lims:id="561763" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from each end of a strip along and at right angles to the projected centre line thereof, which approach surface is more particularly described in Part III of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561764" lims:id="561764" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561765" lims:id="561765" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>outer surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary surface located above and in the immediate vicinity of the airport, which outer surface is more particularly described in Part IV of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface extérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561766" lims:id="561766" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means the rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport including the runway prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction, which strip is more particularly described in Part V of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561767" lims:id="561767" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from the lateral limits of a strip and its approach surfaces, which transitional surface is more particularly described in Part VI of the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561768" lims:id="561768"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the airport reference point is deemed to be 3,531 feet above sea level.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561769" lims:id="561769" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561770" lims:id="561770"><Label>4</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all the lands and lands under water, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, that consist of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561771" lims:id="561771"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the lands the outer limits of which are described in Part II of the schedule, other than such lands as from time to time form part of the airport; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561772" lims:id="561772"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the lands directly beneath the approach surfaces, other than such lands as from time to time form part of the airport.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561773" lims:id="561773" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561774" lims:id="561774"><Label>5</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct, on any land or any land under water to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of that highest point any of the surfaces hereinafter set out that project immediately over and above the surface of the land at that location, namely,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561775" lims:id="561775"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the approach surfaces;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561776" lims:id="561776"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the outer surface; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561777" lims:id="561777"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the transitional surfaces.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561778" lims:id="561778" level="1"><TitleText>Natural Growth</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561779" lims:id="561779"><Label>6</Label><Text>Where an object of natural growth on any land to which these Regulations apply exceeds in elevation any of the surfaces referred to in section 5, the Minister may make a direction that the owner or occupier of the land on which that object is growing remove the excessive growth.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561781" lims:id="561781">SOR/81-168, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561782" lims:id="561782"><Label>7</Label><Text><Repealed>[Revoked, SOR/81-168, s. 1]</Repealed></Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561783" lims:id="561783" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561784" lims:id="561784"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561785" lims:id="561785" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561786" lims:id="561786" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a point located at the Southwest corner of the Southwest Quarter of Section Twelve (12), Township Twenty-five (25), Range One (1), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian in the Province of Alberta.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561787" lims:id="561787" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Limits of Lands</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561788" lims:id="561788" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Northeast corner of the Southeast Quarter Section Fifteen (15), Township Twenty-five (25), Range Twenty-nine (29), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian; THENCE, southerly along the easterly boundaries of said Quarter Section Fifteen (15), and Sections Ten (10) and Three (3), and across intervening road allowances, and continuing southerly along the easterly boundary of Section Thirty-four (34), in Township Twenty-four (24), Range Twenty-nine (29), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian, to the Northeast corner of Plan 455 J.K.; THENCE, westerly along the northerly limit of said Plan 455 J.K. to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, southerly along the westerly limit of the said Plan 455 J.K. to the Southwest corner thereof; THENCE, easterly along the northerly limit of Forty-fourth (44th) Avenue Northeast as shown on Plan 7610067 to the easterly boundary of the said Section Thirty-four (34); THENCE, southerly along the said easterly boundary of Section Thirty-four (34), to the Southeast corner of the Northeast Quarter of the said Section Thirty-four (34); THENCE, westerly along the southerly boundary of the said Northeast Quarter Section Thirty-four (34), to the Southwest corner thereof; THENCE, southerly along the easterly boundary of the Southwest Quarter of the said Section Thirty-four (34), and continuing southerly along the easterly boundary of the Northwest Quarter Section Twenty-seven (27), to the northern limit of Rundleville Drive as shown on Plan 7610016; THENCE, westerly along the northerly limit of the said Rundleville Drive, to the Southeast corner of Lot One (1) Block Twelve (12), Plan 7610016; THENCE, northerly along the eastern limit of said Lot One (1), Block Twelve (12), Plan 7610016, to the Northeast corner thereof; THENCE, westerly along the northern limits of Lots One (1) to Ten (10) inclusive to the Northeast corner of Lot Eleven (11), all in Block Twelve (12), Plan 7610016; THENCE, southwesterly along the northwesterly limit of said Lot Eleven (11), to the Northeast corner of Lot R-50 as shown on said Plan 7610016; THENCE, westerly along the northern limit of Lot R-50, to the northwest corner thereof; THENCE, southerly along the western limit of the said Lot R-50, all in Block Twelve (12), Plan 7610016, to the point of intersection with the South boundary of the said Northwest Quarter Section Twenty-seven (27), Township Twenty-four (24), Range Twenty-nine (29), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian; THENCE, westerly along the southerly boundary of the said Northwest Quarter Section Twenty-seven (27), and its extension westerly across Thirty-six (36) Street Northeast; THENCE, westerly along the southern limit of Block B, Plan 4880 A.F. to the Northeast corner of Block B, Plan 4023 A.G.; THENCE, westerly along the northern limit of the said Block B, Plan 4023 A.G., to the point of intersection with the easterly limit of Twenty-fifth (25th) Street Northeast; THENCE, southerly along the said easterly limit of Twenty-fifth (25th) Street Northeast to the point of intersection with the easterly production of the northern limit of Block Thirty-two (32), Plan 4023 A.G.; THENCE, westerly along the said northern limit of Block Thirty-two (32) and its production easterly to the Northwest corner thereof; all in Section Twenty-eight (28), Township Twenty-four (24), Range Twenty-nine (29), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian; THENCE, on the production westerly of the said northern limit of Block Thirty-two (32), across the Barlow Trail to the Northeast corner of Block Thirty-two (32), Plan 3013 A.C. in the Southeast Quarter Section Twenty-five (25), Township Twenty-four (24), Range One (1), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian; THENCE, southerly along the eastern limit of Blocks Thirty-two (32) and Thirty-one (31), said Plan 3013 A.C., and of Blocks Twenty-two (22) and Twenty-one (21), Plan 5886 X. and their projections across intervening roadways to the Southeast corner of the said Block Twenty-one (21); THENCE, generally westerly following the westerly and northerly boundaries of Highways Number One (1) and Number Two (2), as same shown on road Plans 44 H.X., 8208 G.X., and 731424, to the point of intersection with the northeasterly limit of Block T. Plan 1442 J.K. in the Southeast Quarter Section Twenty-six (26), Township Twenty-four (24), Range One (1), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian; THENCE, northwesterly along the said northeasterly limit of the said Block T, to the northeasterly corner thereof; THENCE, westerly along the northern limits of the said Block T, and Block S, of the said Plan 1442 J.K. to the Southeast corner of Block One (1), Plan 2113 J.K.; THENCE, northerly along the easterly limit of Block One (1), said Plan 2113 J.K., to the Northeast corner thereof; THENCE, westerly along the northerly limit of the said Block One (1), to the point of intersection with the easterly limit of Seventh (7th) Street Northeast; THENCE, northerly along the said easterly limit of Seventh (7th) Street Northeast to the northern limit of Twenty-fourth (24th) Avenue Northeast; THENCE, westerly along the northerly limits of Twenty-fourth (24th) Avenue Northeast and Twenty-fourth (24th) Avenue Northwest and their productions across roadways to the westerly limit of Fourth (4th) Street Northwest; THENCE, northerly along the said westerly limit of Fourth (4th) Street Northwest and its production across roadways to the southerly limit of Fortieth (40th) Avenue Northwest; THENCE, northwesterly along the said southerly limit of Fortieth (40th) Avenue Northwest to the point of intersection with the southerly production of the easterly limit of the Hudson Road; THENCE, northerly along the said easterly limit of Hudson Road and its productions to the northerly limit of Forty-fourth (44th) Avenue Northwest; THENCE, westerly along the said northerly limit of Forty-fourth (44th) Avenue Northwest and its production across roadways to the westerly limit of Northmount Drive; THENCE, northerly along the said westerly limit of Northmount Drive and its productions across roadways to the northerly limit of Trafford Drive Northwest; THENCE, northwesterly along the northerly limit of Trafford Drive Northwest to the southeasterly limit of Block R-22 Plan 7510527 in the Southeast Quarter Section Four (4), Township Twenty-five (25), Range One (1), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian; THENCE, northeasterly along the said southeasterly limit of the said Block R-22 to the most easterly corner thereof; THENCE, northwesterly along the northeasterly limit of the said Block R-22, to the southeasterly limit of Thames Close; THENCE, northeasterly along the southeasterly limit of Thames Close, to the northeasterly limit thereof; THENCE, northwesterly along the northeasterly limit of Thames Close to the southeasterly limit of Norfork Drive Northwest; THENCE, northeasterly following the southeasterly and easterly limits of Norfork Drive Northwest and Hunterview Drive, and their productions across intervening roadways to intersect the south boundary of Southwest Quarter Section Sixteen (16); THENCE, easterly along the South boundary of the said Southwest Quarter Section Sixteen (16) to the Southeast corner thereof; THENCE, northerly along the easterly boundaries of the West half of the said Section Sixteen (16), and Southwest Quarter Section Twenty-one (21), to the Northeast corner thereof; THENCE, easterly along the northerly boundaries of the Southeast Quarter Section Twenty-one (21), and the South half of Section Twenty-two (22), and their productions across intervening road allowances, to the Southwest corner of the Northwest Quarter Section Twenty-three (23); THENCE, northerly along the westerly boundaries of the said Northwest Quarter Section Twenty-three (23), to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, easterly along the northerly boundary of the said Northwest Quarter Section Twenty-three (23), to the northeast corner thereof; THENCE, northerly along the westerly boundary of the Southeast Quarter Section Twenty-six (26), and its production across road Plan 7598 J.K. to the Northwest corner of said Southeast Quarter Section Twenty-six (26); THENCE, easterly along the northerly boundary of the said Southeast Quarter Section Twenty-six (26), and its production across road allowance, to the Southwest corner of the Northwest Quarter Section Twenty-five (25); THENCE, northerly along the western boundary of the said Northwest Quarter Section Twenty-five (25), to the commencement of the easterly limit of road Plan 8078 J.K.; THENCE, northerly and easterly following the easterly and southerly limits of said road Plan 8078 J.K. to its intersection with the North boundary of the said Section Twenty-five (25); THENCE, easterly along the northern boundaries of the said Northeast Quarter Section Twenty-five (25), the northern halves of Sections Twenty-eight (28), and Twenty-seven (27), in Township Twenty-five (25), Range Twenty-nine (29), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian, and their productions across road Plan 7598 J.K. and intervening road allowances, to the Northeast corner of the said Section Twenty-seven (27); THENCE, southerly along the eastern boundaries of the East halves of Sections Twenty-seven (27), Twenty-two (22), and the Northeast Quarter Section Fifteen (15), and their productions across intervening road allowances, to the Northeast corner of the Southeast Quarter Section Fifteen (15), being the point of commencement.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561789" lims:id="561789" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Approach Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561790" lims:id="561790" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a surface abutting each end of the strips associated with the runways designated 34L-16R, 34R-16L, 25-07 and 28-10 and more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561791" lims:id="561791" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 34L, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally, rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, one thousand (1,000) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and fifty thousand (50,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being seven thousand and six hundred (7,600) feet from the projected centre line,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561792" lims:id="561792" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 34R, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally, rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, one thousand (1,000) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip, and fifty thousand (50,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being eight thousand (8,000) feet from the projected centre line,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561793" lims:id="561793" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 25, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally, rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, two hundred (200) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and ten thousand (10,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being two thousand (2,000) feet from the projected centre line,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561794" lims:id="561794" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 28, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally, rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, two hundred (200) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and ten thousand (10,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being two thousand (2,000) feet from the projected centre line,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561795" lims:id="561795" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 16L, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally, rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, one thousand (1,000) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and fifty thousand (50,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being eight thousand (8,000) feet from the projected centre line,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561796" lims:id="561796" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 16R, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally, rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, one thousand (1,000) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and fifty thousand (50,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being seven thousand and six hundred (7,600) feet from the projected centre line,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561797" lims:id="561797" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 10, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally, rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, two hundred (200) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and ten thousand (10,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being two thousand (2,000) feet from the projected centre line, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561798" lims:id="561798" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 07, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to thirty (30) feet measured horizontally, rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, three hundred and thirty-three and thirty-three hundredths (333.33) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and ten thousand (10,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being two thousand (2,000) feet from the projected centre line,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561799" lims:id="561799" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>which approach surfaces are shown on Department of Transport Calgary Zoning Plan dated April 26, 1977.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561800" lims:id="561800" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561801" lims:id="561801" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being an imaginary surface consisting of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561802" lims:id="561802" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a common plane established at a constant elevation of one hundred and fifty (150) feet above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561803" lims:id="561803" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where the common plane described in paragraph (a) is less than thirty (30) feet above the surface of the ground, an imaginary surface located thirty (30) feet above the surface of the ground,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561804" lims:id="561804" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>which outer surface is shown on Department of Transport Calgary Zoning Plan dated April 26, 1977.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561805" lims:id="561805" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Strip</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561806" lims:id="561806" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Each strip is described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561807" lims:id="561807" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the strip associated with the runway designated 34L-16R is one thousand two hundred (1,200) feet in width, six hundred (600) feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and thirteen thousand one hundred and forty (13,140) feet in length,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561808" lims:id="561808" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the strip associated with the runway designated 34R-16L is one thousand (1,000) feet in width, five hundred (500) feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and fourteen thousand four hundred (14,400) feet in length,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561809" lims:id="561809" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the strip associated with the runway designated 28-10 is one thousand and two hundred (1,200) feet in width, six hundred (600) feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and nine thousand five hundred (9,500) feet in length, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561810" lims:id="561810" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the strip associated with the runway designated 25-07 is one thousand two hundred (1,200) feet in width, six hundred (600) feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and six thousand seven hundred (6,700) feet in length,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561811" lims:id="561811" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>which strips are shown on Department of Transport Calgary Zoning Plan dated April 26, 1977.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561812" lims:id="561812" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Transitional Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561813" lims:id="561813" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a surface consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to seven (7) feet measured horizontally at right angles to the centre line and centre line produced of each strip extending upward and outward from the lateral limits of each strip and its approach surfaces to an intersection with the outer surface, and approach surface or another transitional surface of an adjoining strip, which surfaces are shown on Department of Transport Calgary Zoning Plan dated April 26, 1977.</Text></Provision><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="561815" lims:id="561815">SOR/85-233, s. 1; SOR/87-146, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule></Regulation>