<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2008-04-04" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-04-04" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602727" lims:id="602727" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602728" lims:id="602728"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 984</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602730" lims:id="602730"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="J-1">JUDGES ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602731" lims:id="602731">Judges Act (Removal Allowance) Order</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602732" lims:id="602732"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602733" lims:id="602733"><Label>1</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, SI/2003-143, s. 2]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602734" lims:id="602734" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602735" lims:id="602735"><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Order,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602736" lims:id="602736" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="J-1">Judges Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602737" lims:id="602737" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>financial institution</DefinedTermEn> means any bank to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-1.01">Bank Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Quebec Savings Banks Act</XRefExternal> applies and any institution incorporated in Canada that accepts deposits of money from its members or the public and makes loans and includes a branch, agency or office of any such bank or institution; (<DefinedTermFr>institution financière</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602738" lims:id="602738" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>former residence</DefinedTermEn> of a judge means the residence that a judge had immediately before that judge was required to change the judge’s place of residence to assume or perform the functions or duties of a judge, or, in the case of the judge’s retirement, resignation or death, the residence at the place or in the area where the judge was required to reside to assume or perform the judge’s function or duties as a judge; (<DefinedTermFr>ancienne résidence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602739" lims:id="602739" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>new residence</DefinedTermEn> of a judge means the residence</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602740" lims:id="602740"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>at the place or in the area where the judge is required to reside to assume or perform the judge’s functions and duties as a judge, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602741" lims:id="602741"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to which</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602742" lims:id="602742"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the judge moves during one of the two-year periods referred to in paragraphs 40(1)(c) and (e) of the Act, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602743" lims:id="602743"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the judge’s survivor or child moves within two years after the judge’s death. (<DefinedTermFr>nouvelle résidence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602745" lims:id="602745">SI/79-130, s. 1; SI/91-16, s. 1(F); SI/2003-143, s. 3; SI/2007-48, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602746" lims:id="602746" level="1"><TitleText>Prescribed Kinds of Expenses</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602747" lims:id="602747"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602748" lims:id="602748"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of subsection 40(2) of the Act, the following expenses are hereby prescribed to be the kinds of moving and other expenses for which a removal allowance shall be paid under section 40 of the Act:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602749" lims:id="602749"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>travelling costs, including amounts expended for meals and lodging, incurred in the course of moving the judge, a member of the judge’s household, or the judge’s survivor or child, from the former residence to the new residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602750" lims:id="602750"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>costs incurred in transporting or storing household effects of the judge, a member of the judge’s household, or the judge’s survivor or child in the course of moving from the former residence to the new residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602751" lims:id="602751"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>amounts expended for meals and lodging for a member of the judge’s household or the judge’s survivor or child during any temporary stay near the former residence or the new residence, not exceeding in the aggregate 30 days, or such longer period the Minister of Justice determines, taking into account market conditions and the special needs of the family;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602752" lims:id="602752"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the cost of cancelling any lease of the former residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602753" lims:id="602753"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the selling costs incurred in respect of the sale of the former residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602754" lims:id="602754"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the cost of legal services in respect of the purchase of the new residence and of any taxes imposed on the transfer or registration of title to the new residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602755" lims:id="602755"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>child-care expenses incurred while the judge and the judge’s spouse or common-law partner, or the judge’s survivor are away looking for a new residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602756" lims:id="602756"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>where the interest charges on the mortgage for the new residence are higher than the interest charges on the mortgage for the former residence, the difference between those charges up to a maximum of $5,000 per year for a maximum of five years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602757" lims:id="602757"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the cost of a mortgage default insurance premium and of an insurance processing fee where</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602758" lims:id="602758"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the judge, the judge’s spouse or common-law partner, or the judge and the judge’s spouse or common-law partner, or the survivor or child, or the estate or succession of the judge owned the former residence,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602759" lims:id="602759"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the equity of the judge, the judge’s spouse or common-law partner, or the judge and the judge’s spouse or common-law partner, or the survivor or child, or the estate or succession on their behalf, in the former residence is transferred to the new residence,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602760" lims:id="602760"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the equity of the judge, the judge’s spouse or common-law partner, or the judge and the judge’s spouse or common-law partner, or the survivor in the new residence is less than 25 per cent of the cost of the new residence, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602761" lims:id="602761"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the premium is levied in one payment;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602762" lims:id="602762"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the cost to the judge or the judge’s spouse, common-law partner, survivor or child of maintaining the former residence, minus any rent received in respect of it, for a period of not more than six months after the date the judge vacates the residence, including amounts expended for mortgage interest payments, insurance, property taxes and heating; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602763" lims:id="602763"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>where a judge is required to move to a new place of residence on appointment or transfer, the travelling and lodging costs, including amounts expended for meals, incurred by the judge before the establishment of the permanent new residence or in order to visit from time to time members of the judge’s household still resident in the former residence, within the six-month period after the judge’s appointment or transfer.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602764" lims:id="602764"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where, on account of unfavourable conditions in the real estate market, the judge’s former residence cannot be sold within the six month period referred to in paragraph (1)(j) or (k), the Governor in Council may prescribe such an additional period as is reasonable in the circumstances.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602765" lims:id="602765"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the travelling costs referred to in paragraph (1)(a) do not include those incurred by the judge after the establishment of the judge in the new residence during one of the periods referred to in subparagraph (b)(i) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>new residence</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 or those incurred by the judge in order to visit from time to time members of the judge’s household during one of those periods.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-04-04" lims:fid="602767" lims:id="602767">SI/78-107, s. 1; SI/83-46, s. 1; SI/86-99, s. 1; SI/91-16, s. 2; SI/2003-143, s. 4; SI/2007-48, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602768" lims:id="602768" level="1"><TitleText>Interest on Loans</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602769" lims:id="602769"><Label>3.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602770" lims:id="602770"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of subsection 40(2) of the Act, where a judge or a judge’s survivor or child is entitled to a removal allowance under section 40 of the Act, the interest on any short term demand loan with a financial institution to purchase a new residence and any legal fees related to that loan are hereby prescribed to be an expense for which a removal allowance shall be paid, if the loan has been arranged by</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602771" lims:id="602771"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602772" lims:id="602772"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the judge and the judge’s spouse or common-law partner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602773" lims:id="602773"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the judge’s spouse or common-law partner; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602774" lims:id="602774"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case where the judge is deceased, the judge’s survivor or child.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602775" lims:id="602775"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No removal allowance shall be paid pursuant to subsection (1) unless</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602776" lims:id="602776"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>at the time the loan referred to in subsection (1) is arranged, the judge or the judge’s spouse, common-law partner, survivor or child, or the estate or succession of the judge, is the owner of the former residence or the judge is an owner with the judge’s spouse or common-law partner of the former residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602777" lims:id="602777"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the former residence has been offered for sale; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602778" lims:id="602778"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the judge provides the Minister of Justice with receipts or other documents evidencing</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602779" lims:id="602779"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the purchase by the judge, the judge’s spouse, common-law partner, survivor or child of a new residence or the joint purchase by the judge and the judge’s spouse or common-law partner of a new residence, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602780" lims:id="602780"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the terms and conditions of the loan.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602781" lims:id="602781"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The amount of the loan referred to in subsection (1) shall not exceed the amount that is equal to the price at which the former residence is listed for sale minus any amount owing in respect of a mortgage or other encumbrance on the residence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602782" lims:id="602782"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (5), no removal allowance shall be paid pursuant to subsection (1) in respect of any interest that accrues</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602783" lims:id="602783"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>after 10 days have elapsed following the day on which the transaction for the sale of the former residence is completed, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602784" lims:id="602784"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>after six months have elapsed from the day on which the loan was made,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602785" lims:id="602785"><Text>whichever is the earlier.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602786" lims:id="602786"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Where, on account of unfavourable conditions in the real estate market, a judge or a judge’s survivor or child who is entitled to a removal allowance under section 40 of the Act has not been able to sell the former residence within the six-month period referred to in paragraph (4)(b), the Governor in Council may prescribe any additional period that is reasonable in the circumstances in respect of which a removal allowance shall be paid pursuant to subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602788" lims:id="602788">SI/79-130, s. 2; SI/83-46, s. 2; SI/91-16, s. 3; SI/2003-143, s. 5</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602789" lims:id="602789" level="1"><TitleText>Home Sale Assistance</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602790" lims:id="602790"><Label>3.2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602791" lims:id="602791"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602792" lims:id="602792" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>appraisal report</DefinedTermEn> means the form entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Appraisal Report Home Ownership Units</XRefExternal> that is used by the Appraisal Institute of Canada and that is on file with the Minister of Justice; (<DefinedTermFr>rapport d’évaluation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602793" lims:id="602793" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>appraiser</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is a member in good standing of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602794" lims:id="602794"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Appraisal Institute of Canada or of an institute or society of appraisers that has entered into an agreement with the Appraisal Institute of Canada permitting the use by that institute’s or society’s members of the designation “Accredited Appraiser Canadian Institute” and, in either case, who holds the designation of “Accredited Appraiser Canadian Institute”, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602795" lims:id="602795"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">La Corporation professionnelle des évaluateurs agréés du Québec</Emphasis> and who holds the designation of <Emphasis style="italic">évaluateur agréé</Emphasis>. (<DefinedTermFr>évaluateur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602796" lims:id="602796"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 40(2) of the Act, and subject to this section, where a judge or a judge’s spouse or common-law partner, survivor or child, or the estate or succession on their behalf, is unable to sell the judge’s former residence at a price that is equal to or greater than the fair market value, determined in accordance with this section, the difference between the sale price of the former residence and its fair market value is hereby prescribed to be an expense for which a removal allowance shall be paid under section 40 of the Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602797" lims:id="602797"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The removal allowance referred to in subsection (2) shall not be greater than 10 per cent of the fair market value of the former residence, determined in accordance with this section, and in no case shall the sum of the removal allowance and the sale price of the former residence be greater than the fair market value.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602798" lims:id="602798"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In order to determine the fair market value of the former residence, at the request of the person, estate or succession referred to in subsection (2), two appraisers shall be appointed, one by that person or that estate or succession, and one by the Minister of Justice, each to carry out a market appraisal to submit to the Minister and to that person or estate or succession an appraisal report of the former residence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602799" lims:id="602799"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Where the difference between the market appraisals carried out pursuant to subsection (4) is</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602800" lims:id="602800"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>less than or equal to five per cent of the higher market appraisal, the fair market value shall be the average of the two market appraisals, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602801" lims:id="602801"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>more than five per cent of the higher market appraisal, another appraiser shall be appointed by the Minister of Justice to carry out a third market appraisal and to submit to the Minister of Justice and to the person, estate or succession referred to in subsection (2) an appraisal report of the former residence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602802" lims:id="602802"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Where the difference between the third market appraisal carried out pursuant to paragraph 5(b) and the first two appraisals is</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602803" lims:id="602803"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>less than or equal to five per cent of one of the first two market appraisals, which percentage is based on the higher of the market appraisals being compared at a time, the fair market value of the former residence shall be the average of the two market appraisals that are within five per cent of each other,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602804" lims:id="602804"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>less than or equal to five per cent of each of the first two appraisals, which percentage is based on the higher of the market appraisals being compared at a time, the fair market value of the former residence shall be the average of all of the market appraisals carried out, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602805" lims:id="602805"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>more than five per cent of each of the first two market appraisals, which percentage is based on the higher of the two appraisals being compared at a time, the fair market value of the former residence shall be the average or median, whichever is the greater, of all of the market appraisals carried out.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602806" lims:id="602806"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>When the fair market value of the former residence has been determined in accordance with this section, the Minister of Justice shall, in writing, advise thereof the person, estate or succession referred to in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602807" lims:id="602807"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>No removal allowance shall be paid to a person, estate or succession referred to in subsection (2) where the former residence is not sold within six months after the day on which they receive written notice from the Minister of Justice advising of the fair market value of the former residence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602808" lims:id="602808"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Where, on account of unfavourable conditions in the real estate market, a person, estate or succession referred to in subsection (2) who is entitled to a removal allowance under section 40 of the Act has not been able to sell the former residence within the six-month period referred to in subsection (8), the Governor in Council may prescribe such additional period as is reasonable in the circumstances in respect of which they may sell the former residence and be eligible to receive a removal allowance pursuant to subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602810" lims:id="602810">SI/90-4, s. 1; SI/91-16, s. 4; SI/2003-143, s. 6</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602811" lims:id="602811" level="1"><TitleText>Terms and Conditions of Allowance Payments</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602812" lims:id="602812"><Label>4</Label><Text>A judge, judge’s survivor or child who makes a claim for the payment of a removal allowance under section 40 of the Act shall provide the Minister of Justice with receipts evidencing the expenses in respect of which the claim is made and any other documents that the Minister may require to enable the Minister to authorize the payment of the claim under section 5.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602814" lims:id="602814">SI/2003-143, s. 7</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602815" lims:id="602815"><Label>5</Label><Text>The Minister of Justice shall authorize the payment of a claim for a removal allowance where the Minister receives the claim and is satisfied that the expenses in respect of which the claim is made</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602816" lims:id="602816"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>are the kinds of expenses prescribed by sections 3, 3.1 and 3.2,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602817" lims:id="602817"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>have actually been incurred by the judge, a member of the judge’s household, or the judge’s survivor or child;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602818" lims:id="602818"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>are reasonable in the circumstances, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602819" lims:id="602819"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>are not payable to the judge or the judge’s survivor or child under any provision of the Act except section 40.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="602821" lims:id="602821">SI/79-130, s. 3; SI/90-4, s. 2; SI/2003-143, s. 8</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>