<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549938" lims:id="549938" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549939" lims:id="549939"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 342</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549941" lims:id="549941"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">APPROPRIATION ACT NO. 1, 1977</XRefExternal><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="Z-01">APPROPRIATION ACTS</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549942" lims:id="549942">Railway Passenger Services Adjustment Assistance Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549943" lims:id="549943">Regulations Respecting the Implementation of Adjustment Assistance to Railway Companies and Employees Affected by Changes in Railway Passenger Services</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549944" lims:id="549944"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549945" lims:id="549945" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549946" lims:id="549946"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._342">Railway Passenger Services Adjustment Assistance Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549947" lims:id="549947" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549948" lims:id="549948"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549949" lims:id="549949"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549950" lims:id="549950" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>benefits</DefinedTermEn> means the benefits and expenses referred to in subparagraph (c)(ii) of Department of Transport Vote 52d, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Appropriation Act No. 1, 1977</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>bénéfices</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549951" lims:id="549951" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>changes</DefinedTermEn> means changes in the provision, management or operation of selected Railway Passenger Services as a result of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549952" lims:id="549952"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the implementation of the provisions of the contract between the Minister of Transport and VIA Rail Canada Inc., entered into pursuant to Department of Transport Vote 52d of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Appropriation Act No. 1, 1977</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549953" lims:id="549953"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the discontinuance of a Railway Passenger Service; (<DefinedTermFr>changements</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549954" lims:id="549954" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>cost</DefinedTermEn> means the cost incurred by a railway company with respect to the provision of benefits; (<DefinedTermFr>coûts</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549955" lims:id="549955" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>government arrangement</DefinedTermEn> means an arrangement between the Minister of Transport and a railway company with respect to the reimbursement of the prescribed portion of the cost; (<DefinedTermFr>entente gouvernementale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549956" lims:id="549956" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>prescribed portion</DefinedTermEn> means the portion prescribed from time to time by the Governor in Council; (<DefinedTermFr>proportion déterminée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549957" lims:id="549957" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Railway Passenger Service</DefinedTermEn> means a passenger train service that does not accommodate principally persons who commute between points on the railway; (<DefinedTermFr>service de transport ferroviaire de passagers</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549958" lims:id="549958" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>special agreement</DefinedTermEn> means an agreement between a railway company or railway companies and a trade union or trade unions with respect to the provision of benefits that result from the special agreement process; (<DefinedTermFr>accord spécial</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549959" lims:id="549959" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>special agreement process</DefinedTermEn> means the negotiating process between a railway company and a trade union commenced with the undertaking between the parties that the arbitration provisions set out in these Regulations will apply to and be binding upon the parties in the event of the dispute between them on any matter arising in respect of the benefits and conditions referred to in subsection 5(2); (<DefinedTermFr>processus d’accord spécial</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549960" lims:id="549960" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>trade union</DefinedTermEn> means an employee organization certified or recognized as bargaining agent for employees of a railway company. (<DefinedTermFr>syndicat</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549961" lims:id="549961"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any word or expression used in these Regulations that is not defined in subsection (1) shall have the same meaning as in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Act</XRefExternal>. </Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549963" lims:id="549963">SOR/85-701, s. 1; SOR/88-401, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549964" lims:id="549964" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549965" lims:id="549965"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Minister of Transport may reimburse a railway company for the prescribed portion of the cost incurred by the company for the provision of benefits where</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549966" lims:id="549966"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the cost results from changes implemented during the period beginning on March 29, 1977 and ending on December 31, 1990;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549967" lims:id="549967"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a special agreement exists between the railway company and a trade union or trade unions; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549968" lims:id="549968"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a government arrangement exists between the railway company and the Minister of Transport. </Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549970" lims:id="549970">SOR/81-25, s. 1; SOR/85-701, s. 2; SOR/86-56, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549971" lims:id="549971" level="1"><TitleText>Special Agreements</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549972" lims:id="549972"><Label>4</Label><Text>In negotiating a special agreement, the parties to the special agreement process shall, inasmuch as the following are generally incorporated in their existing job security agreements, give consideration to the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549973" lims:id="549973"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in so far as possible, ensuring continuing employment for the employees concerned;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549974" lims:id="549974"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where preferred and to the extent possible, keeping employees in gainful employment at the same location;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549975" lims:id="549975"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where necessary, training employees for alternative employment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549976" lims:id="549976"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>when required, providing appropriate assistance in relocation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549977" lims:id="549977"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>in so far as possible, avoiding loss of employees’ earnings;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549978" lims:id="549978"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>developing a separation plan for the assistance of employees close to or eligible for retirement who wish to leave the work force;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549979" lims:id="549979"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>minimizing seniority obstacles for the purpose of facilitating</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549980" lims:id="549980"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>continuing employment by Canadian National Railway Company, Canadian Pacific Railway Limited, Toronto Terminal Railway Company or Toronto, Hamilton and Buffalo Railway Company, where mutually agreed to by the parties, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549981" lims:id="549981"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the transfer of employees to VIA Rail Canada Inc.;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549982" lims:id="549982"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>where employees are laid off, providing reasonable weekly lay-off benefits or severance payments; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549983" lims:id="549983"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>assisting employees unable to maintain their jobs to secure employment outside the railway industry. </Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549985" lims:id="549985">SOR/81-735, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549986" lims:id="549986"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549987" lims:id="549987"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A special agreement shall provide for the benefits and the terms and conditions of those benefits contained in</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549988" lims:id="549988"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Railway Job Security, Technological, Operational, Organizational Changes Agreements between Canadian National Railway Company, Canadian Pacific Railway Limited and non-operating shop-craft or other unions; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549989" lims:id="549989"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Railway Material Change Agreements between Canadian National Railway Company, Canadian Pacific Railway Limited and United Transportation Union and Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549990" lims:id="549990"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A special agreement may provide for benefits and conditions in addition to those referred to in subsection (1), consistent with the principles referred to in section 4.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549991" lims:id="549991"><Label>6</Label><Text>A special agreement shall be the only instrument applicable with respect to benefits and the words, terms and conditions of such an instrument shall not be amended, revised or otherwise changed without</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549992" lims:id="549992"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a joint request from the parties to the special agreement; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549993" lims:id="549993"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the consent, in writing, of the Minister of Labour.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549994" lims:id="549994"><Label>7</Label><Text>A special agreement shall not provide for benefits to employees other than those adversely affected by the implementation of changes.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549995" lims:id="549995" level="1"><TitleText>Arbitration</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549996" lims:id="549996"><Label>8</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549997" lims:id="549997"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where, in negotiating a special agreement, a settlement has not been reached by the parties to the special agreement process (hereinafter referred to as “the parties”) on any issue arising under subsection 5(2) within 60 days after the date a railway company has served notice on a trade union, either party may inform the Minister of Labour, by notice in writing, of their failure to reach a settlement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549998" lims:id="549998"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within a reasonable period after his receipt of a notice referred to in subsection (1), the Minister of Labour or a representative designated by him shall confer with the parties in order to assist them in reaching a settlement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="549999" lims:id="549999"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the Minister of Labour or his representative is unsuccessful in assisting the parties in reaching a settlement, either party may, within seven days following the conference with the Minister of Labour or his representative, request, by notice in writing to the other party, that the matter be referred to a single arbitrator.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550000" lims:id="550000"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where, within seven days of a request referred to in subsection (3), the parties cannot agree on the selection of an arbitrator, either party may submit to the Minister of Labour an application to appoint an arbitrator.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550001" lims:id="550001"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Within a reasonable period after his receipt of an application referred to in subsection (4), the Minister of Labour shall select and appoint an arbitrator.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550002" lims:id="550002"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>On the appointment of an arbitrator, the parties shall prepare a joint statement of any issues arising under subsection 5(2) that remain in dispute and shall submit that statement to the arbitrator prior to the hearing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550003" lims:id="550003"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Within 21 days of his appointment the arbitrator shall convene a hearing of the parties.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550004" lims:id="550004"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Within 60 days of his appointment the arbitrator shall make an award.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550005" lims:id="550005"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An arbitral award shall be final and binding on the parties and for the purposes of these Regulations shall be deemed to be an integral part of the special agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550006" lims:id="550006"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>An arbitral award, notwithstanding a decision to the contrary by the arbitrator as to its duration, shall be the only arbitral award applicable in respect of any matter referred to arbitration under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550007" lims:id="550007"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Any time limit established pursuant to this section may be extended by agreement between the parties.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550008" lims:id="550008" level="1"><TitleText>Non-unionized Employees</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550009" lims:id="550009"><Label>9</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550010" lims:id="550010"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where non-unionized employees have been adversely affected by the implementation of changes, they shall be provided with benefits consistent with existing railway policies and practices and may be provided with additional benefits.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550011" lims:id="550011"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every railway company affected by changes in Railway Passenger Services shall provide a detailed statement of the benefits to be provided to non-unionized employees pursuant to subsection (1) to the Minister of Transport and that statement shall, for the purposes of these Regulations, be considered to be a special agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550012" lims:id="550012" level="1"><TitleText>Government Arrangement</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550013" lims:id="550013"><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550014" lims:id="550014"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A government arrangement shall not provide for the reimbursement of a greater portion of the cost than the prescribed portion.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550015" lims:id="550015"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A government arrangement shall not be executed until the appropriate special agreement has been signed by the parties to the special agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550016" lims:id="550016" level="1"><TitleText>Reimbursement</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550017" lims:id="550017"><Label>11</Label><Text>Reimbursement to a railway company of the prescribed portion of the cost shall be made in accordance with the appropriate government arrangement.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550018" lims:id="550018" level="1"><TitleText>Records</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="550019" lims:id="550019"><Label>12</Label><Text>A railway company shall keep detailed records of all transactions made by the company with respect to cost and shall make the records available for inspection by the Minister of Transport or his authorized representative on an agreed periodic basis.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>