<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503342" lims:id="503342" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503343" lims:id="503343"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1317</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503345" lims:id="503345"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-29.4">FOREIGN MISSIONS AND INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503346" lims:id="503346">Privileges and Immunities Accession Order (United Nations)</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503347" lims:id="503347">Order Respecting the Accession to Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the United Nations</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503348" lims:id="503348"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503349" lims:id="503349" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503350" lims:id="503350"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Order may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1317">Privileges and Immunities Accession Order (United Nations)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503351" lims:id="503351" level="1"><TitleText>Privileges and Immunities</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503352" lims:id="503352"><Label>2</Label><Text>The United Nations shall have the legal capacities of a body corporate.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503353" lims:id="503353"><Label>3</Label><Text>The United Nations shall in Canada have the immunities and privileges set out in sections 2, 3, 4, 5, 7 and 9 of the Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the United Nations, hereinafter referred to as the "Convention".</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503354" lims:id="503354"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503355" lims:id="503355"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Representatives of Members to the principal and subsidiary organs of the United Nations and to conferences convened by the United Nations shall, while exercising their functions and during their journey to and from the place of meeting, have in Canada the privileges and immunities set out in section 11 of the Convention.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503356" lims:id="503356"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Representatives of Members to the principal and subsidiary organs of the United Nations and to conferences convened by the United Nations shall continue to have the immunities set forth in paragraph 11(a) of the Convention in respect of words spoken or written and all acts done by them in discharging their duties notwithstanding that they are no longer the representatives of Members.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503357" lims:id="503357"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the incidence of any form of taxation depends upon residence, periods during which the representatives of Members to the principal and subsidiary organs of the United Nations and to conferences convened by the United Nations are present in Canada for the discharge of their duties shall not be considered as periods of residence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503358" lims:id="503358"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections (1), (2) and (3) do not apply to a representative of Canada or to a Canadian citizen.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503359" lims:id="503359"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, the expression "representatives" includes delegates, deputy delegates, advisers, technical experts and secretaries of delegations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503360" lims:id="503360"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503361" lims:id="503361"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Officials of the United Nations whose names are included in the categories specified by the Secretary-General pursuant to section 17 of the Convention shall in Canada have the immunities and privileges set forth in section 18 of the Convention.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503362" lims:id="503362"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Secretary-General and all Assistant Secretaries-General, their spouses and minor children shall in Canada have the privileges and immunities, exemptions and facilities accorded to diplomatic envoys, in accordance with international law.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503363" lims:id="503363"><Label>6</Label><Text>Experts, other than officials of the United Nations within the meaning of section 4 of this Order, performing missions for the United Nations shall in Canada have the privileges and immunities set forth in paragraphs 22(a), (b), (c), (d), (e) and (f) of the Convention except in so far as any such privilege or immunity is waived by the Secretary-General pursuant to section 23 of the Convention.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="503364" lims:id="503364"><Label>7</Label><Text>Nothing in this Order shall be construed as exempting a Canadian citizen residing or ordinarily resident in Canada from taxation imposed by any law in Canada on salaries and emoluments.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>