<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529992" lims:id="529992" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529993" lims:id="529993"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1579</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529995" lims:id="529995"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="V-1">DEPARTMENT OF VETERANS AFFAIRS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529996" lims:id="529996">Guardianship of Veterans’ Property Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529997" lims:id="529997">Regulations Respecting the Guardianship of Veterans’ Property</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529998" lims:id="529998"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529999" lims:id="529999" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530000" lims:id="530000"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1579">Guardianship of Veterans’ Property Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530001" lims:id="530001" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530002" lims:id="530002"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530003" lims:id="530003" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="V-1">Department of Veterans Affairs Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530004" lims:id="530004" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Department</DefinedTermEn> means the Department of Veterans Affairs; (<DefinedTermFr>ministère</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530005" lims:id="530005" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Deputy Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Deputy Minister of Veterans Affairs; (<DefinedTermFr>sous-ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530006" lims:id="530006" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Veterans Affairs. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530007" lims:id="530007" level="1"><TitleText>Guardianship Assumed by Deputy Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530008" lims:id="530008"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Deputy Minister may receive and retain any property of, or moneys payable to or on behalf of, any person who is being or has been cared for under the provisions of the Act either by medical treatment, training or otherwise, or his dependants.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530009" lims:id="530009"><Label>4</Label><Text>Where an insane person is being or has been cared for under the provisions of the Act either by medical treatment, training or otherwise, the Deputy Minister may assume guardianship in whole or in part in respect of any property held or moneys payable by the Crown or any other authority or person on behalf of such insane person or his dependants.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530010" lims:id="530010"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where, as a result of a person having served in the naval, army or air forces of any country other than Canada, moneys become payable to him or to his dependants or to any other person, the Deputy Minister, when requested to do so by the authority or person making the payment, may assume guardianship of such moneys.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530011" lims:id="530011"><Label>6</Label><Text>Where guardianship is assumed by the Deputy Minister under these Regulations, he may do all acts and things required by such guardianship, and any notice given in writing by him of the assumption of such guardianship shall be acceptable as evidence thereof.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530012" lims:id="530012"><Label>7</Label><Text>A receipt signed by the Deputy Minister or by an officer of the Department, authorized by the Deputy Minister to sign such receipt, in respect of property and moneys received by the Deputy Minister pursuant to these Regulations, shall constitute a full and complete discharge for any property or moneys so received.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530013" lims:id="530013"><Label>8</Label><Text>The Deputy Minister may dispose of any property or moneys held by him under section 3, 4 or 5, to the person on whose behalf the property or moneys is held or to the dependants of such person, or, where the person is deceased, to his estate, or in such other manner on behalf of such person or his dependants as the Deputy Minister may deem expedient or advisable.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530014" lims:id="530014"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Deputy Minister may accept and administer in accordance with the conditions imposed, thereon or, if no conditions are imposed, as he may deem advisable, property and moneys bequeathed or donated for the benefit of persons coming within the terms or provisions of any Act or Order in Council, administered by the Minister and may designate two or more officers of the Department to serve with him as the trustees thereof.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530015" lims:id="530015"><Label>10</Label><Text>Moneys received by the Deputy Minister pursuant to these Regulations, other than moneys pertaining to the Disablement Fund, shall be deposited to the credit of the Receiver General to be held in a special account or accounts, subject to such withdrawals as may from time to time be authorized in accordance with these Regulations.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530016" lims:id="530016"><Label>11</Label><Text>The Deputy Minister may authorize payment of interest, at the rate fixed from time to time by the Minister of Finance with the approval of the Governor in Council, on all moneys held under these Regulations and paid into the Consolidated Revenue Fund for a special purpose.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="530017" lims:id="530017"><Label>12</Label><Text>The Deputy Minister may, by an instrument in writing, designate two or more officers of the Department to exercise any of the powers vested in and perform any of the duties imposed upon him by these Regulations.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>