<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537321" lims:id="537321" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537322" lims:id="537322"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 239</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537324" lims:id="537324"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-6">AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS MARKETING ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537325" lims:id="537325">P.E.I. Vegetable Seizure (Interprovincial and Export) Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537326" lims:id="537326">Regulations Respecting Seizures of Certain Vegetables Produced in Prince Edward Island and Marketed in Interprovincial and Export Trade</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537327" lims:id="537327"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537328" lims:id="537328" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537329" lims:id="537329"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._239">P.E.I. Vegetable Seizure (Interprovincial and Export) Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537330" lims:id="537330" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537331" lims:id="537331"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537332" lims:id="537332" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Prince Edward Island Vegetable Growers Cooperative Association and includes any sub-agents thereof; (<DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537333" lims:id="537333" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commodity Board</DefinedTermEn> means the Prince Edward Island Vegetable Commodity Marketing Board; (<DefinedTermFr>Office de commercialisation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537334" lims:id="537334" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>container</DefinedTermEn> means any bag, box or other receptacle in which vegetable is or can be packed, transported or marketed; (<DefinedTermFr>contenant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537335" lims:id="537335" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> means any individual, firm, partnership, association or corporation that grows or markets vegetable and includes any servants or agents thereof; (<DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537336" lims:id="537336" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>vegetable</DefinedTermEn> means any turnip produced in the Province of Prince Edward Island. (<DefinedTermFr>légumes</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537337" lims:id="537337" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537338" lims:id="537338"><Label>3</Label><Text>These Regulations apply only to vegetable when marketed in interprovincial and export trade and to persons and property situated in the Province of Prince Edward Island.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537339" lims:id="537339" level="1"><TitleText>Stopping Vehicles</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537340" lims:id="537340"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537341" lims:id="537341"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where it appears to a member or an authorized representative of the Commodity Board or a police constable that a vehicle is transporting vegetable in violation of any regulation or order of the Commodity Board, he may order the person in control of the vehicle to stop the vehicle.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537342" lims:id="537342"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an order is given pursuant to subsection (1), the person in control of the vehicle shall forthwith stop the vehicle and permit it to be searched by the person who gave the order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537343" lims:id="537343" level="1"><TitleText>Seizure</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537344" lims:id="537344"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where, in the opinion of any member or authorized representative of the Commodity Board, any vegetable is being or has been marketed in violation of any regulation or order of the Commodity Board, he may seize the vegetable and container and remove them from the motor vehicle or the premises in which they were seized and deliver them to the Commodity Board.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537345" lims:id="537345" level="1"><TitleText>Detention</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537346" lims:id="537346"><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537347" lims:id="537347"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any vegetable that is seized pursuant to section 5 may be detained by</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537348" lims:id="537348"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>attaching a detention tag on the premises where the vegetable was seized; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537349" lims:id="537349"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>delivering a notice in writing of the seizure to any person who appears to be in control of the motor vehicle or in charge of the premises in which the vegetable was seized.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537350" lims:id="537350"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person other than a member or an authorized representative of the Commodity Board shall, without written authority from the Commodity Board, move, destroy, sell or offer for sale any vegetable in respect of which a detention tag has been attached or a notice of detention has been given pursuant to subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537351" lims:id="537351" level="1"><TitleText>Hearing</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537352" lims:id="537352"><Label>7</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537353" lims:id="537353"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any vegetable that is seized pursuant to section 5 may be disposed of by the Commodity Board after the expiration of 10 days from the day of seizure unless before that time the owner of the vegetable or the person from whom it was seized applies in writing to the Commodity Board for a hearing to show cause why the vegetable should not be disposed of.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537354" lims:id="537354"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where, at the conclusion of the hearing referred to in subsection (1), the Commodity Board determines that the vegetable seized was not marketed in violation of these Regulations or, if so marketed was marketed inadvertently, the Commodity Board may return the vegetable to its owner or the person from whom it was seized or market it through the Agency on behalf of the owner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537355" lims:id="537355"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where, at the conclusion of the hearing referred to in subsection (1), the Commodity Board determines that the vegetable seized was being marketed in violation of these Regulations, the Commodity Board may dispose of the vegetable in the manner described in section 8.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537356" lims:id="537356" level="1"><TitleText>Disposal</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537357" lims:id="537357"><Label>8</Label><Text>Where any vegetable is seized pursuant to section 5, the Commodity Board may order it to be sold through the Agency on behalf of the owner and the Agency may deduct from the proceeds of sale an amount, for the handling and marketing of the vegetable, equal to $1 per 100 pounds plus the cost of grading, washing and cartage and any expenses of the Commodity Board arising out of or relating to the seizure and sale of the vegetable, and the balance, if any, shall be paid by the Agency to the owner or the person from whom the vegetable was seized.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537358" lims:id="537358" level="1"><TitleText>Appeal</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="537359" lims:id="537359"><Label>9</Label><Text>Any person aggrieved by any act or decision of a member or authorized representative of the Commodity Board or the Agency may appeal to the Commodity Board and, if not satisfied with the decision of the Commodity Board, may appeal to the Prince Edward Island Marketing Board.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>