<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497211" lims:id="497211" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497212" lims:id="497212"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 116</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497214" lims:id="497214"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497215" lims:id="497215">Sudbury Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497216" lims:id="497216">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Sudbury Airport</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497217" lims:id="497217"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497218" lims:id="497218" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497219" lims:id="497219"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._116">Sudbury Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497220" lims:id="497220" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497221" lims:id="497221"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497222" lims:id="497222" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means Sudbury Airport, in the Regional Municipality of Sudbury, in the Province of Ontario; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497223" lims:id="497223" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>(point de repère de l’aéroport)</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497224" lims:id="497224" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from each end of a strip along and at right angles to the projected centre line thereof, which approach surface is more particularly described in Part III of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497225" lims:id="497225" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497226" lims:id="497226" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>outer surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary surface located above and in the immediate vicinity of the airport, which outer surface is more particularly described in Part IV of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface extérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497227" lims:id="497227" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means the rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport including the runway prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction, which strip is more particularly described in Part V of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497228" lims:id="497228" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from the lateral limits of a strip and its approach surfaces, which transitional surface is more particularly described in Part VI of the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497229" lims:id="497229"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the airport reference point is deemed to be 1,126 feet above sea level.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497230" lims:id="497230" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497231" lims:id="497231"><Label>4</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all the lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, the outer limits of which lands are described in Part II of the schedule, other than such lands as from time to time form part of the airport.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497232" lims:id="497232" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497233" lims:id="497233"><Label>5</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct, on any land to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of that point any of the surfaces hereinafter set out that project immediately over and above the surface of the land at that location, namely,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497234" lims:id="497234"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the approach surfaces;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497235" lims:id="497235"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the outer surface; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497236" lims:id="497236"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the transitional surfaces.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497237" lims:id="497237" level="1"><TitleText>Natural Growth</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497238" lims:id="497238"><Label>6</Label><Text>No owner or occupier of any land to which these Regulations apply shall permit any object of natural growth to exceed in elevation any of the surfaces set out in paragraphs 5(a) to (c) that project immediately over and above the surface of the land at the location of the object.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497239" lims:id="497239"><Label>7</Label><Text>Where an owner or occupier referred to in section 6 permits an object of natural growth to exceed in elevation any of the surfaces set out in paragraphs 5(a) to (c) contrary to section 6, the Minister may make a direction that any person enter upon the land on which the object is growing and remove the excessive growth thereof.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497240" lims:id="497240" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497241" lims:id="497241"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497242" lims:id="497242" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497243" lims:id="497243" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a point at the intersection of a line drawn parallel to and distant 500 feet measured southerly at right angles from the centre line of runway 11-29 and a line drawn parallel to and distant 500 feet measured southeasterly at right angles from the centre line of runway 04-22.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497244" lims:id="497244" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of Outer Limits of Lands</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497245" lims:id="497245" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the southwesterly corner of Lot 4, Concession 1, in the Township of Capreol, now in the Town of Valley East, in the Regional Municipality of Sudbury; THENCE, northerly along the western boundary of the said Lot 4 to the intersection thereof with a line drawn North 83°19′56′′ West from the southwesterly corner (Ontario Grid Co-ordinates 16,946,093.08 N. 1,048,027.13 E.) of the area of Sudbury Airport designated as strip 11-29 and which strip is more particularly described in Part V of this schedule and the plans referred to in Part V; THENCE, North 83°19′56′′ West to a point distant 50,559.38 feet therealong from the southwesterly corner of the said strip 11-29; THENCE, North 15°11′55′′ East, a distance of 16,000 feet to a point; THENCE, South 66°16′ and 14′′ East to the intersection thereof with the western boundary Lot 3, Concession 2, in the said Township of Capreol; THENCE, northerly along the western boundary of the said Lot 3 to the northwesterly corner thereof; THENCE, easterly along the northern boundary of Lots 3, 2 and 1, in the said Concession 2, to the northeasterly corner of the said Lot 1; THENCE, northerly along the eastern boundary of Lot 1, Concession 3, in the said Township of Capreol to the northwesterly corner of Lot 12, Concession 2, in the Township of MacLennan, now in the Town of Nickel Centre, in the said Regional Municipality of Sudbury; THENCE, easterly along the northern boundary of Lots 12, 11 and 10, in the said Concession 2, to the southwesterly corner of Lot 9, Concession 3, in the said Township of MacLennan; THENCE, northerly along the western boundary of the said Lot 9, a distance of 2,300 feet to a point; THENCE, due East along a straight line to the intersection thereof with a line drawn North 20°49′34′′ East from the northwesterly corner (Ontario Grid Co-ordinates 16,948,501.33 N. 1,051,893.10 E.) of the area of Sudbury Airport designated as strip 04-22 and which strip is more particularly described in Part V of this schedule and the plans referred to in Part V; THENCE, North 20°49′34′′ East to a point distant 50,559.38 feet therealong from the northwesterly corner of the said strip 04-22; THENCE, South 60°38′35′′ East, a distance of 16,000 feet to a point; THENCE, South 37°53′16′′ West to the intersection thereof with the western boundary of Lot 6, Concession 3, in the said Township of MacLennan; THENCE, southerly along the said western boundary and along the western boundary of Lot 6, Concession 2, in the said Township to the southwesterly corner of the said Lot 6; THENCE, easterly along the southern boundary of Lot 6, in the said Concession 2, to the northeasterly corner of Lot 6, Concession 1, in the said Township; THENCE,southerly along the eastern boundary of Lot 6, in the said Concession 1, and its production southerly to the intersection thereof with a line drawn South 83°19′56′′ East from the northeasterly corner (Ontario Grid Co-ordinates 16,945,642.47 N. 1,053,499.58 E.) of the said strip 11-29; THENCE, South 83°19′56′′ East to a point distant 50,559.38 feet therealong from the northeasterly corner of the said strip 11-29; THENCE, South 15°11′55′′ West, a distance of 16,000 feet to a point; THENCE, North 66°16′14″ West to the intersection thereof with the northern boundary of Lot 5, Concession 5, in the Township of Falconbridge, in the said Town of Nickel Centre; THENCE, westerly along the northern boundary of Lots 5, 6 and 7, in the said Concession 5, to the northeasterly corner of Lot 8, in the said Concession; THENCE, southerly along the eastern boundary of the said Lot 8 to the southeasterly corner thereof; THENCE, westerly along the southern boundary of Lots 8, 9, 10, 11 and 12, in the said Concession 5, to the intersection thereof with a line drawn South 20°49′34″ West from the southeasterly corner (Ontario Grid Co-ordinates 16,941,910.98 N. 1,049,333.35 E.) of the said strip 04-22; THENCE, South 20°49′34″ West to a point distant 50,559.38 feet therealong from the southeasterly corner of the said strip 04-22; THENCE, North 60°38′35″ West, a distance of 16,000 feet to a point; THENCE, North 37°53′16″ East to the intersection thereof with the southern boundary of Lot 2, Concession 5, in the Township of Garson, in the said Town of Nickel Centre; THENCE, westerly along the southern boundary of the said Lot 2 to the southwesterly corner thereof; THENCE, northerly along the western boundary of the said Lot 2 to the northwesterly corner thereof; THENCE, westerly along the southern boundary of Lot 3, Concession 6, in the said Township of Garson, to the southwesterly corner of the said Lot 3; THENCE, northerly along the western boundary of the said Lot 3 to the northwesterly corner thereof, the said corner being on the line between the said Township of Garson and the said Township of Capreol; THENCE, westerly along the said line being along the southern boundary of Lot 4, Concession 1, in the said Township of Capreol, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497246" lims:id="497246" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Approach Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497247" lims:id="497247" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a surface abutting each end of the strips associated with the runways designated 04-22 and 11-29, consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of each strip one thousand (1,000) feet above the elevation at the end of each strip measured vertically and fifty thousand (50,000) feet from the end of each strip measured horizontally, the outer ends of each imaginary horizontal line being eight thousand (8,000) feet from each projected centre line, which approach surfaces are shown on Department of Transport Plans Nos. T2863A and T2863B, dated April 1, 1974.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497248" lims:id="497248" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497249" lims:id="497249" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being an imaginary surface consisting of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497250" lims:id="497250" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a common plane established at a constant elevation of one hundred and fifty (150) feet above the elevation of the airport reference point, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497251" lims:id="497251" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where the common plane described in paragraph (a) is less than thirty (30) feet above the surface of the ground, an imaginary surface located thirty (30) feet above the surface of the ground,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497252" lims:id="497252" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>which outer surface is shown on Department of Transport Plans Nos. T2863A and T2863B, dated April 1, 1974.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497253" lims:id="497253" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Strip</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497254" lims:id="497254" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Each strip is described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497255" lims:id="497255" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 04-22 is one thousand (1,000) feet in width, five hundred (500) feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and seven thousand (7,000) feet in length,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497256" lims:id="497256" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 11-29 is one thousand (1,000) feet in width, five hundred (500) feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and five thousand four hundred (5,400) feet in length,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497257" lims:id="497257" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>which strips are shown on Department of Transport Plans Nos. T2863A and T2863B, dated April 1, 1974.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497258" lims:id="497258" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Transitional Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="497259" lims:id="497259" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a surface consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to seven (7) feet measured horizontally at right angles to the centre line and centre line produced of each strip and extending upward and outward rising from the lateral limits of each strip and its approach surfaces to an intersection with the outer surface or another transitional surface of an adjoining strip, all as shown on Department of Transport Plans Nos. T2863A and T2863B, dated April 1, 1974.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>