<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566253" lims:id="566253" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566254" lims:id="566254"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 84</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566256" lims:id="566256"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566257" lims:id="566257">Grande Prairie Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566258" lims:id="566258">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Grande Prairie Airport</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566259" lims:id="566259"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566260" lims:id="566260" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566261" lims:id="566261"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._84">Grande Prairie Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566262" lims:id="566262" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566263" lims:id="566263"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566264" lims:id="566264" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means Grande Prairie Airport, in the vicinity of Grande Prairie, in the Province of Alberta; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566265" lims:id="566265" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point determined in the manner set out in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l'aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566266" lims:id="566266" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from each end of a strip along and at right angles to the projected centre line thereof, which approach surface is more particularly described in Part III of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d'approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566267" lims:id="566267" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566268" lims:id="566268" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>outer surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary surface located above and in the immediate vicinity of the airport, which outer surface is more particularly described in Part IV of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface extérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566269" lims:id="566269" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means the rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport including the runway prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction, which strip is more particularly described in Part V of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566270" lims:id="566270" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from the lateral limits of a strip and its approach surfaces, which transitional surface is more particularly described in Part VI of the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566271" lims:id="566271"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the airport reference point is deemed to be 2,188 feet above sea level.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566272" lims:id="566272" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566273" lims:id="566273"><Label>4</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all the lands and lands under water, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, the outer limits of which lands are described in Part II of the schedule, other than such lands as from time to time form part of the airport.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566274" lims:id="566274" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566275" lims:id="566275"><Label>5</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct on any land or any land under water to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of the highest point any of the surfaces hereinafter set out that project immediately over and above the surface of the land at that location, namely,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566276" lims:id="566276"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the approach surfaces;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566277" lims:id="566277"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the outer surfaces; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566278" lims:id="566278"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the transitional surfaces.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566279" lims:id="566279" level="1"><TitleText>Natural Growth</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566280" lims:id="566280"><Label>6</Label><Text>Where an object of natural growth on any land to which these Regulations apply exceeds in elevation any of the surfaces referred to in section 5, the Minister may make a direction that the owner or occupier of the land on which that object is growing remove the excessive growth.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566282" lims:id="566282">SOR/81-172, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566283" lims:id="566283"><Label>7</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/81-172, s. 1]</Repealed></Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566284" lims:id="566284" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566285" lims:id="566285"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566286" lims:id="566286" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566287" lims:id="566287" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the intersection of runways 06-24 and 11-29, THENCE, easterly along the centre line of runway 06-24 for a distance of two thousand (2,000) feet, THENCE, southerly and perpendicular to the centre line a distance of five hundred (500) feet to a point being the airport reference point.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566288" lims:id="566288" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of Outer Limits of Lands</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566289" lims:id="566289" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Southeast corner of Section Three (3), Township Seventy-Two (72), Range Six (6), West of the Sixth (6th) Meridian; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary thereof to the Northeast corner of the Southeast Quarter of said Section; THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of said Quarter Section to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of the Northwest Quarter of said Section to the Northeast corner thereof; THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of said quarter Section to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, Northerly along the Western boundary of Section Ten (10) to the Northwest corner of the Southwest Quarter of said Section; THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundaries of the South Halves of Sections Nine (9), Eight (8) and Seven (7) and their productions across Road Allowances to the Northwest corner of the Southwest Quarter of Section Seven (7); THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of said Quarter Section to the Southwest corner thereof; THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of Section One (1), Township Seventy-two (72), Range Seven (7), West of the Sixth (6th) Meridian and its production across the Road Allowance to the Northeast corner of the Northwest Quarter thereof; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern boundary of said Quarter Section to the Southeast corner thereof; THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of the Southwest Quarter of said Section to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of said Quarter Section and its production across the Road Allowance to the Northwest corner of Section Thirty-six (36), Township Seventy-one (71), Range Seven (7) West of the Sixth (6th) Meridian; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundaries of Sections Thirty-six (36) and Twenty-five (25) to the intersection with the Northern limit of Road Plan 2457 J.Y.; THENCE, Southerly on a straight line to the intersection of the Southern limit of said Plan and the Eastern limit of Road Plan 5273 K.S.; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern limit of said Plan 5273 K.S. to its intersection with the Northern boundary of Section Thirteen (13); THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of the Northwest Quarter of said Section Thirteen (13) to the Northeast corner thereof; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern boundary of said Quarter Section to the Southeast corner thereof; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern Boundary of the Southeast Quarter of said Section and its production across the Road Allowance to Northwest corner of the Southwest Quarter of Section Eighteen (18), Township Seventy-One (71), Range Six (6), West of the Sixth (6th) Meridian; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of said Quarter Section to its intersection with the Northern limit of Right-of-Way Plan 3399 C.L.; THENCE, Easterly along said Northern limit through Sections Eighteen (18) and Seventeen (17) and its production across the Road Allowance to its intersection with the Western boundary of Lot Eighteen (18) in the Flyingshot Lake Settlement, as shown on a Plan of Survey of said Settlement, signed at Ottawa on November 11, 1908; THENCE, Northeasterly along the Northern limit of said Right-of-Way Plan 3399 C.L. through Lots Eighteen (18), Two (2) and Three (3) of said Settlement and its production across Road Allowances to its intersection with the Southern limit of the Road Allowance through Lot Three (3) of said Settlement; THENCE, Easterly along the Southern limit of the Road Allowance through Lots Three (3) and Four (4) of said Settlement and its production across the Road Allowance to its intersection with the Western boundary of Lot Five (5) of said Settlement; THENCE, Easterly along the Southern limit of Road Plan 2783 C.L. and its production across the Road Allowance to its intersection with the Western boundary of Lot Six (6) of said Settlement; THENCE, Southerly along the said Western boundary of said Lot Six (6) of said Settlement to the Southwest corner thereof; THENCE, Easterly along the Southern limit of said Lot to the Southeast corner thereof; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of said Lot and its production across Road Plan 7442 A.U. to intersect the Northern limit of said Road Plan; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern limit of said Plan to its intersection with the Western limit of Road Plan 2358 N.Y.; THENCE, Northerly along the Western limit of said plan to its intersection with the Southern limit of Right-of-Way Plan 3399 C.L.; THENCE, Northeasterly along the Southern limit of said Plan and its production across said Plan 2358 N.Y. to its intersection with the original Eastern boundary of Section Twenty-Two (22); THENCE, Northerly along the original Eastern boundaries of Sections Twenty-two (22), Twenty-seven (27) and Thirty-four (34) and their productions across Road Allowances to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566290" lims:id="566290" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Description of Approach Surfaces</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566291" lims:id="566291" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a surface abutting each end of the strips associated with the runways designated 11-29 and 06-24, and more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566292" lims:id="566292" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 11,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566293" lims:id="566293" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 29,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566294" lims:id="566294" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 06, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566295" lims:id="566295" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 29,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566296" lims:id="566296" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to fifty (50) feet measured horizontally rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, two hundred (200) feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and ten thousand (10,000) feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being two thousand (2,000) feet from the projected centre line, which approach surfaces are shown on Department of Public Works Plan No. E. 1191 dated October 14, 1975.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566297" lims:id="566297" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566298" lims:id="566298" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being an imaginary surface consisting of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566299" lims:id="566299" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a common plane established at a constant elevation of one hundred and fifty (150) feet above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566300" lims:id="566300" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where the common plane described in paragraph (a) is less than thirty (30) feet above the surface of the ground, an imaginary surface located thirty (30) feet above the surface of the ground,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566301" lims:id="566301" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>which outer surface is shown on Department of Public Works Plan No. E. 1191 dated October 14, 1975.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566302" lims:id="566302" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Strip</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566303" lims:id="566303" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Each strip is described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566304" lims:id="566304" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 06-24 is one thousand (1,000) feet in width, five hundred (500) feet being on each side of the centre of the runway, and six thousand six hundred (6,600) feet in length,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566305" lims:id="566305" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 11-29 is one thousand (1,000) feet in width, five hundred (500) feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and six thousand nine hundred (6,900) feet in length,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566306" lims:id="566306" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>which strips are shown on Department of Public Works Plan No. E. 1191 dated October 14, 1975.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566307" lims:id="566307" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Transitional Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="566308" lims:id="566308" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a surface consisting of an inclined plane rising at a ratio of one (1) foot measured vertically to seven (7) feet measured horizontally at right angles to the centre line and centre line produced of each strip and extending upward from the lateral limits of each strip and its approach surfaces to an intersection with the outer surface or another transitional surface of an adjoining strip, all as shown on Department of Public Works Plan No. E. 1191 dated October 14, 1975.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>