<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504102" lims:id="504102" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504103" lims:id="504103"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1357</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504105" lims:id="504105"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-36">PUBLIC SERVICE SUPERANNUATION ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504106" lims:id="504106">Counting of Service by Former Members of the Senate or House of Commons Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504107" lims:id="504107">Regulations Respecting the Counting of Service by Former Members of the Senate or House of Commons</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504108" lims:id="504108"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504109" lims:id="504109" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504110" lims:id="504110"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1357">Counting of Service by Former Members of the Senate or House of Commons Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504111" lims:id="504111" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504112" lims:id="504112"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504113" lims:id="504113" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-36">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504114" lims:id="504114" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>contributor</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is a contributor under the Act; (<DefinedTermFr>contributeur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504115" lims:id="504115" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the President of the Treasury Board. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504116" lims:id="504116" level="1"><TitleText>Election</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504117" lims:id="504117"><Label>3</Label><Text>A contributor may elect to count a period of service in respect of which he contributed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="M-5">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal> as pensionable service for the purposes of Part I of the Act if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504118" lims:id="504118"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>he elects to do so in a form prescribed by the Minister; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504119" lims:id="504119"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a contributor who is entitled to an allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="M-5">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal> for service in respect of which he made contributions, he surrenders his rights to that allowance.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504120" lims:id="504120"><Label>4</Label><Text>A contributor who makes an election pursuant to section 3 shall, for the purposes of Part I of the Act, be credited with a period of pensionable service equal to the aggregate of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504121" lims:id="504121"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the periods of pensionable service to his credit pursuant to subsection 24(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="M-5">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal> at the time he ceased to be a member of the Senate or House of Commons; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504122" lims:id="504122"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the period of pensionable service in respect of which he made contributions under Part I or VI of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="M-5">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal> that has not been counted for the purpose of establishing the periods of pensionable service referred to in paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504123" lims:id="504123" level="1"><TitleText>Medical Examination</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504124" lims:id="504124"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504125" lims:id="504125"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A contributor who elects within one year of becoming a contributor to count pensionable service pursuant to section 3 shall be medically examined unless he has, during the five-year period immediately prior to the election, been employed without interruption in the Public Service or as a member of the regular force, the Force, the Senate or House of Commons or in any combination of those employments.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504126" lims:id="504126"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A contributor who elects after one year of becoming a contributor to count pensionable service pursuant to section 3 shall be medically examined.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504127" lims:id="504127"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), a contributor who elects to count pensionable service pursuant to section 3 and to whom paragraph 3(b) applies shall be medically examined.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504128" lims:id="504128"><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504129" lims:id="504129"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A medical examination referred to in section 5 shall be conducted by a physician licensed or otherwise authorized to practise medicine in the jurisdiction in which the examination is performed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504130" lims:id="504130"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A medical examination referred to in section 5 shall provide the information required by, and be reported in accordance with, Department of National Health and Welfare Form NHW 365 or NHW-SNBS 366.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504131" lims:id="504131"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The form referred to in subsection (2) shall, on completion, be submitted to the Medical Services Branch of the Department of National Health and Welfare.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504133" lims:id="504133">SOR/94-624, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504134" lims:id="504134"><Label>6.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504135" lims:id="504135"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), a medical examination required by section 5 shall be performed not more than three months before, nor more than six months after, the making of the election.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504136" lims:id="504136"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a person without fault fails to undergo a medical examination required by section 5 within the time set out in subsection (1), the person may undergo the medical examination within 30 days after being notified by the Minister that an examination is required.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504137" lims:id="504137"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person shall be determined to have passed a medical examination required by section 5 where the Minister receives a report, prepared by the Assistant Deputy Minister of the Medical Services Branch of the Department of National Health and Welfare from the information contained in the form submitted pursuant to section 6, stating that the person</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504138" lims:id="504138"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is capable of five years of continuous employment performing the duties that the contributor was performing at the time of the medical examination; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504139" lims:id="504139"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has a normal life expectancy.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504140" lims:id="504140"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where the Assistant Deputy Minister of the Medical Services Branch determines that the information contained in a form submitted pursuant to section 6 is insufficient to enable a report in respect of a person to be prepared under subsection (3), the Assistant Deputy Minister may require the person to undergo a further medical examination in accordance with section 6, to obtain the necessary information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504141" lims:id="504141"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who, in the circumstances referred to in subsection (4), does not undergo a further medical examination required by that subsection shall be determined not to have been medically examined in accordance with section 5.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504143" lims:id="504143">SOR/94-624, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504144" lims:id="504144"><Label>7</Label><Text>The election of a contributor who fails to pass a medical examination required by subsection 5(2) or (3) is void.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504145" lims:id="504145" level="1"><TitleText>Payments to the Superannuation Account</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504146" lims:id="504146"><Label>8</Label><Text>A contributor who makes an election pursuant to section 3 and to whom paragraph 3(b) applies shall pay</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504147" lims:id="504147"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to the Superannuation Account, on the same basis had he continued to pay in accordance with the payment plan he elected under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="M-5">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal>, an amount equal to the amount he had elected to contribute</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504148" lims:id="504148"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>pursuant to section 7 of that Act minus the amount of contributions he paid pursuant to section 9 of that Act, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504149" lims:id="504149"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>pursuant to section 19 of that Act minus the amount of contributions he paid pursuant to section 20 of that Act,</Text></Subparagraph><ContinuedParagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504150" lims:id="504150"><Text>as the case may be;</Text></ContinuedParagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504151" lims:id="504151"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to the Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Account an amount equal to the amount of any allowance paid to him pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="M-5">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal> for any period commencing in any month commencing after he has been a contributor under the Act for one year together with simple interest at four per cent per annum; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504152" lims:id="504152"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to the Supplementary Retirement Benefits Account an amount equal to the amount of any supplementary retirement benefit paid to him pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-24">Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act</XRefExternal> in respect of an allowance paid to him pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="M-5">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal> for any period commencing in any month commencing after he has been a contributor under the Act for one year together with simple interest at four per cent per annum.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504153" lims:id="504153"><Label>9</Label><Text>A contributor who makes an election pursuant to section 3 and to whom paragraph 3(b) does not apply shall pay to the Superannuation Account an amount calculated</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504154" lims:id="504154"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in accordance with paragraph 6(1)(e) of the Act, if he elects within one year of becoming a contributor, or from December 23, 1976, whichever is later; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504155" lims:id="504155"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in accordance with paragraph 6(1)(j) of the Act, if he elects at a later date.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504156" lims:id="504156"><Label>10</Label><Text>Where a contributor makes an election pursuant to section 3, there shall be transferred to the Superannuation Account</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504157" lims:id="504157"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>all amounts paid by the contributor to the Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Account less any amount paid to him as a withdrawal allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="M-5">Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504158" lims:id="504158"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>all amounts credited to that Account pursuant to section 4 of that Act in respect of the contributor.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504159" lims:id="504159"><Label>11</Label><Text>Any amount required to be paid by a contributor pursuant to these Regulations other than paragraph 8(a) shall be paid by him</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504160" lims:id="504160"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in a lump sum at the time of making the election; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="504161" lims:id="504161"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in instalments computed on such terms as are prescribed by section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1358">Public Service Superannuation Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section></Body></Regulation>