<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583151" lims:id="583151" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583152" lims:id="583152"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 92</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583154" lims:id="583154"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583155" lims:id="583155">Lethbridge Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583156" lims:id="583156">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Lethbridge Airport</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583157" lims:id="583157"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583158" lims:id="583158" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583159" lims:id="583159"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._92">Lethbridge Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583160" lims:id="583160" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583161" lims:id="583161"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583162" lims:id="583162" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means Lethbridge Airport, Lethbridge, in the Province of Alberta; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583163" lims:id="583163" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583164" lims:id="583164" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane the lower end of which is a horizontal line at right angles to the centre line of a strip and passing through a point at the strip end on the centre line of the strip; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583165" lims:id="583165" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>horizontal surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary horizontal plane centering on and located 150 feet above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point; (<DefinedTermFr>surface horizontale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583166" lims:id="583166" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Revoked, SOR/93-401, s. 2]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583167" lims:id="583167" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means a rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport, 1,200 feet in width, including the runway, especially prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583168" lims:id="583168" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from the outer lateral limits of a strip and its approach surface to an intersection with the horizontal surface or other transitional surfaces. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583170" lims:id="583170">SOR/93-401, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583171" lims:id="583171"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the airport reference point is deemed to be 3,002 feet above sea level.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583172" lims:id="583172" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583173" lims:id="583173"><Label>4</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, as more particularly described in Part II of the schedule.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583174" lims:id="583174" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583175" lims:id="583175"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583176" lims:id="583176"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct, on any land to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of the highest point any of the surfaces hereinafter set out that project immediately over and above the surface of the land at that location, namely,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583177" lims:id="583177"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a horizontal surface, the outer limits of which may be described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583178" lims:id="583178" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Northwest corner of Section Thirty-one (31), Township Seven (7), Range Twenty-one (21), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian; THENCE, Southerly along the Westerly boundary of the said section to the Southerly boundary of Legal Subdivision Thirteen (13); THENCE, Easterly along the Southerly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Thirteen (13) and Fourteen (14) of the said Section Thirty-one (31) to the Southeast corner of the said Legal Subdivision Fourteen (14); THENCE, Southerly along the Easterly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Eleven (11) and Six (6) of the said Section Thirty-one (31) to the Southerly boundary of the said Legal Subdivision Six (6); THENCE, Easterly along the Southerly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Seven (7) and Eight (8), Section Thirty-one (31) and production thereof to the Westerly boundary of Section Thirty-two (32); THENCE, Southerly along the Westerly boundary of the said Section Thirty-two (32) to the Southwest corner thereof; THENCE, Easterly along the Southerly boundaries of Sections Thirty-two (32) and Thirty-three (33) to the Easterly boundary of the said Section Thirty-three (33); THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly boundary of Section Thirty-three (33) to a point being the intersection of the said Easterly boundary of the said Section Thirty-three (33) and the Westerly production of the Southerly boundary of Legal Subdivision Five (5), Section Thirty-four (34); THENCE, Easterly along the said Westerly production of the Southerly boundary of Legal Subdivision Five (5), Section Thirty-four (34) and continuing Easterly along the Southerly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Five (5), Six (6), Seven (7) and Eight (8) and production thereof to the Westerly boundary of Section Thirty-five (35); THENCE, Northerly along the Westerly boundary of the said Section Thirty-five (35) to the Southerly boundary of Legal Subdivision Twelve (12) of the said Section Thirty-five (35); THENCE, Easterly along the said Southerly boundary of Legal Subdivision Twelve (12) to the Southeast corner thereof; THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Twelve (12) and Thirteen (13), Section Thirty-five (35), Township Seven (7), Range Twenty-one (21), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian and continuing Northerly along the Easterly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Four (4) and Five (5), Section Two (2), Township Eight (8), Range Twenty-one (21), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian, to the Southerly boundary of the Northwest Quarter of the said Section Two (2); THENCE, Easterly along the said Southerly boundary of the Northwest Quarter of Section Two (2) to the Southeast corner thereof; THENCE, Northerly along Easterly boundaries of the said Northwest Quarter of Section Two (2), the West Half of Section Eleven (11), and Southwest Quarter of Section Fourteen (14) to the Northeast corner of the said Southwest Quarter of Section Fourteen (14); THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundary of the said Southwest Quarter of Section Fourteen (14) and production thereof to the Southeast corner of the Northeast Quarter of Section Fifteen (15); THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly boundary of the said Northeast Quarter of Section Fifteen (15) to the Northeast corner thereof; THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundary of the said Northeast Quarter of Section Fifteen (15) to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly boundary of the Southwest Quarter of Section Twenty-two (22) to the Northeast corner thereof; THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundary of the said Southwest Quarter of Section Twenty-two (22) and production thereof to the Southeast corner of Legal Subdivision Nine (9), Section Twenty-one (21); THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly boundary of the said Legal Subdivision Nine (9), Section Twenty-one (21) to the Northeast corner thereof; THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Nine (9), Ten (10), Eleven (11) and Twelve (12) of Sections Twenty-one (21) and Twenty (20) respectively and production thereof to the Easterly boundary of Section Nineteen (19); THENCE, Southerly along the Easterly boundary of Section Nineteen (19) to the Northeast corner of the Southeast Quarter of the said Section Nineteen (19); THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundary of the said Southeast Quarter of Section Nineteen (19) to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, Southerly along the Westerly boundary of the said Southeast Quarter of Section Nineteen (19) to the Southwest corner thereof; THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundary of Section Eighteen (18) and production thereof to the Northeast corner of Section Thirteen (13), Township Eight (8), Range Twenty-two (22), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian; THENCE, Southerly along the Easterly boundary of the said Section Thirteen (13) to the Northeast corner of Legal Subdivision One (1) of the said Section Thirteen (13); THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundary of the said Legal Subdivision One (1) to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, Southerly along the Westerly boundary of Legal Subdivision One (1) of Section Thirteen (13) and production thereof and continuing Southerly along the Westerly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Sixteen (16), Nine (9), Eight (8) and One (1) of Section Twelve (12) and production thereof and Legal Subdivision Sixteen (16) of Section One (1) to the Southwest corner of the said Legal Subdivision Sixteen (16) Section One (1); THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly boundary of Legal Subdivision Ten (10) Section One (1) to the Northwest corner thereof; THENCE, Southerly along the Westerly boundary of the East Half of the said Section one (1) and production thereof to the Northerly boundary of Section Thirty-six (36), Township Seven (7), Range Twenty-two (22), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian; THENCE, Easterly along the said Northerly boundary of Section Thirty-six (36) and production thereof to the point of commencement,</Text></Provision></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583179" lims:id="583179"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the approach surfaces abutting each end of the strip designated as 05-23 and the strip designated as 12-30 and extending outward therefrom, the dimensions of which approach surfaces are Six Hundred (600) feet on each side of the centre line of the strip at the strip ends and Two Thousand (2,000) feet on each side of the projected centre line of the strip at the outer ends, the said outer ends being Two Hundred (200) feet above the elevations at the strip ends, and measured horizontally Ten Thousand (10,000) feet from the strip ends, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583180" lims:id="583180"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the several transitional surfaces, each rising at an angle determined on the basis of a ratio of one (1) foot vertically for every seven (7) feet measured horizontally from the outer lateral limits of the strips and their abutting surfaces,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583181" lims:id="583181"><Text>as shown on Plan E. 603 dated July 30, 1958 of record in the Department of Transport at Ottawa.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583182" lims:id="583182" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583183" lims:id="583183"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583184" lims:id="583184" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583185" lims:id="583185" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the intersection of the centre lines of Runways 05-23 and 12-30 of Lethbridge Airport, THENCE, Northwesterly along the centre line of Runway 12-30 a distance of One Thousand Six Hundred (1,600) feet to a point; THENCE, at right angles Southwesterly a distance of One Thousand Six Hundred (1,600) feet to a point henceforth designated as the airport reference point, the said point having an assigned elevation of Three Thousand and two (3,002) feet above sea level.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583186" lims:id="583186" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of Lands to Which These Regulations Apply</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="583187" lims:id="583187" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ALL AND SINGULAR those certain parcels or tracts of land and premises, situate, lying and being in the Municipal District of Lethbridge No. 25 in the Province of Alberta and composed of part of Sections One (1), Twelve (12), and Thirteen (13), Township Eight (8), Range Twenty-two (22), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian; the whole of Sections three (3), Six (6), Seven (7), Ten (10), Fifteen (15), and Eighteen (18) and part of Sections Two (2), Four (4), Five (5), Eight (8), Nine (9), Eleven (11), Fourteen (14), Sixteen (16), Seventeen (17), Nineteen (19), Twenty (20), Twenty-one (21), and Twenty-two (22), Township Eight (8), Range Twenty-one (21), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian and the whole of Sections Thirty-two (32) and Thirty-three (33) and part of Sections Thirty-one (31), Thirty-four (34) and Thirty-five (35), Township Seven (7), Range Twenty-one (21), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian, whose outermost boundaries are described as the horizontal surface limits in paragraph 5(a) of these Regulations where all lands, waters and roads enclosed by the boundaries of the description are affected by these Regulations but excluding all lands, waters and roads therefrom within the area whose outermost boundary is described as follows: COMMENCING at the Southeast corner of Legal Subdivision Sixteen (16), Section Four (4), Township Eight (8), Range Twenty-one (21), West of the Fourth (4th) Meridian; THENCE, Westerly along the Southerly boundaries of Legal Subdivisions Sixteen (16), Fifteen (15), Fourteen (14) and Thirteen (13) to a point lying on the said Southerly boundary of Legal Subdivision Thirteen (13), Six Hundred and Sixty (660) feet distant from the Southwest corner of the said Legal Subdivision Thirteen (13) Section Four (4); THENCE, Southerly and parallel to the Westerly boundary of the said Section Four (4) to the Southerly boundary of the Northwest Quarter of said Section Four (4); THENCE, Westerly along the Southerly boundaries of the North halves of Section Four (4) and its prolongation and Section Five (5) to the Westerly boundary of the said Section Five (5); THENCE, Northerly along the Westerly boundaries of Section Five (5) and Eight (8) to a point lying on the said Westerly boundary of Section Eight (8) One Thousand Three Hundred and Twenty (1,320) feet distant Northerly from the Southwest corner of the said Section Eight (8); THENCE, Easterly along a line lying parallel to the Southerly boundary of the said Section Eight (8) to a point lying One Thousand Three Hundred and Twenty (1,320) feet perpendicularly distant from the Easterly boundary of the said Section Eight (8); THENCE, Northerly along a line and its prolongation lying parallel to the Easterly boundaries of Sections Eight (8) and Seventeen (17) and one thousand three hundred and twenty (1,320) feet perpendicularly distant therefrom to a point lying One Thousand Three Hundred and Twenty (1,320) feet perpendicularly distant from the Southerly boundary of the said Section Seventeen (17); THENCE, Easterly along a line and its prolongation lying parallel to the Southerly boundaries of Sections Seventeen (17) and Sixteen (16) and One Thousand Three Hundred and Twenty (1,320) feet perpendicularly distant therefrom to the Westerly limit of the No. 5 Highway as shown on Plan 3881 B.M.; THENCE, Southerly along the said Westerly limit of the No. 5 Highway as shown on Plans 3881 B.M. and 816 E.Z. and continuing Southerly along the Easterly boundaries of Sections Nine (9) and Four (4) to the point of commencement. All plans referred to in the above description are on record at the Land Titles Office for the South Alberta Land Registration District at Calgary, Alberta. The above described lands are shown within colored lines on Plan E. 603 dated July 30, 1958 of record in the Department of Transport at Ottawa.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>