<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582785" lims:id="582785" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582786" lims:id="582786"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 90</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582788" lims:id="582788"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582789" lims:id="582789">Lakehead Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582790" lims:id="582790">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Lakehead Airport</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582791" lims:id="582791"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582792" lims:id="582792" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582793" lims:id="582793"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._90">Lakehead Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582794" lims:id="582794" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582795" lims:id="582795"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582796" lims:id="582796" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means Lakehead Airport, Thunder Bay, in the Province of Ontario; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582797" lims:id="582797" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582798" lims:id="582798" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane the lower end of which is a horizontal line at right angles to the centre line of a strip and passing through a point at the strip end on the centre line of the strip; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582799" lims:id="582799" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>horizontal surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary horizontal plane centering on and located 150 feet above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point; (<DefinedTermFr>surface horizontale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582800" lims:id="582800" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Revoked, SOR/93-401, s. 2]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582801" lims:id="582801" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means a rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport, 1,100 feet in width, including the runway, especially prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582802" lims:id="582802" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane extending upward and outward from the outer lateral limits of a strip and its approach surface to an intersection with the horizontal surface or other transitional surfaces. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582804" lims:id="582804">SOR/93-401, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582805" lims:id="582805"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the airport reference point is deemed to be 635 feet above sea level.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582806" lims:id="582806" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582807" lims:id="582807"><Label>4</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, as more particularly described in Part II of the schedule.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582808" lims:id="582808" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582809" lims:id="582809"><Label>5</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct, on any land to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of the highest point any of the surfaces hereinafter set out that project immediately over and above the surface of the land at that location, namely,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582810" lims:id="582810"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a horizontal surface, the outer limits of which may be described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582811" lims:id="582811" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Northeasterly angle of Lot 6, in Concession 4, North of the river, in the Township of Neebing; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern boundary of said Lot 6 to the Southeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Easterly in a straight line across Edward Street to the Northwesterly angle of Lot 5, in Concession 3, North of the river; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of said Lots 5 and 4 to the Northeasterly angle of said Lot 4; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern boundary of said Lot 4 to the high water mark of the Southern bank of the Neebing River; THENCE, Westerly along the said high water mark to the intersection thereof with a line drawn parallel to and distant 33 feet perpendicularly Westerly from the Eastern boundary of said Lot 4; THENCE, Southerly along the said parallel line and along the Western limit of Tarbutt Street to the Southern limit of Victoria Avenue; THENCE, Easterly along the Southern limit of Victoria Avenue to the intersection thereof with the Northwestern limit of Waterloo Street; THENCE, Southwesterly along the Northwestern limit of Waterloo Street to the intersection thereof with the Northern limit of Arthur Street; THENCE, Westerly along the Northern limit of Arthur Street to the intersection thereof with the production Northerly of the Easterly boundary of Lot 41 as shown on a plan of subdivision registered in the Registry Office for the Registry Division of the District of Fort William as Plan 723; THENCE, Southerly along that production and along the said Easterly boundary of Lot 41 to the Northwestern limit of the right-of-way land of the Canadian National Railway; THENCE, Southwesterly along the said limit of the said right-of-way land to the Northeasterly angle of Lot 160, as shown on Plan 759; THENCE, Easterly in a straight line to the Northwesterly angle of Lot 2, as shown on Plan 725; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of Lots 2 and 1, as shown on said Plan 725 to the Northeasterly angle of said Lot 1; THENCE, Southwesterly along the Northwestern limit of Kingsway Street to the Southeasterly angle of Lot 31, as shown on Plan 733; THENCE, Southerly in a straight line across Christina Street to the Northeasterly angle of Lot 32, as shown on the said Plan 733; THENCE, Southerly along the Western limit of Ford Street to the intersection thereof with the Northern boundary of Lot “A”, as shown on Plan 735; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of Lot “A” to the Northeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern boundary of Lots “A” and “B”, as shown on the said Plan 735 to the natural high water mark of the North bank of the Kaministiqua River; THENCE, in a general Westerly and Southerly direction along the said high water mark to the intersection thereof with a line drawn South 60 degrees 50 minutes East from a point on the Easterly limit of Neebing Avenue the said point being distant 1,263.8 feet measured Southerly along the said Easterly limit from the Southerly limit of Montreal Street; THENCE, North 60 degrees 50 minutes West along the said line and its production Westerly to the intersection thereof with the Eastern boundary of Lot 11, in Concession 1, North of the river; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of the said Lot 11 to the Southern limit of Broadway Street; THENCE, Westerly along the said Southern limit to the Western boundary of the said Lot 11; THENCE, Southerly along the said Western boundary and its production Southerly to the intersection thereof with the natural high water mark of the South bank of the said river; THENCE, Easterly along the said high water mark to the intersection thereof with the production Northerly of the Eastern boundary of Lot 11, in Concession 1, South of the river; THENCE, Southerly along that production and along the said Eastern boundary of said Lot 11 to the Southeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Westerly along the Southern boundary of the said Concession to the Southwesterly angle of Lot 20; THENCE, Northerly along the Western boundary of said Lot 20 and the production Northerly thereof, to the natural high water mark of the North bank of the Kaministiqua River; THENCE, in a general Northerly and Westerly direction along the said high water mark of the North bank of the river to the intersection thereof with the production Southerly of the Western boundary of Lot 23, in Concession 1, North of the river; THENCE, Northerly along that production and along the Western boundary of said Lot 23 to the Northwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Northerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between Concession 1 and 2, North of the river, to the Southwesterly angle of Lot 23, in said Concession 2; THENCE, Northerly along the Western boundary of Lot 23, in Concession 2 and Lot 23, in Concession 3, North of the river, to the Northwesterly angle of the last said Lot; THENCE, Northerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between Concessions 3 and 4, North of the river, to the Southwesterly angle of Lot 23, in said Concession 4; THENCE, Northerly along the Western boundary of Lot 23, in the said Concession 4 and Lot 23, in Concession 5, North of the river, to the Northwesterly angle of the last said Lot; THENCE, Northerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between the Township of Neebing and the Township of McIntyre to the Southwesterly angle of the Jean Langlois Mineral Location in the Township of McIntyre; THENCE, Northerly along the Western boundary of the said Mineral Location and along the Western boundary of the John C. T. Cochrane Mineral Location to the Northwesterly angle thereof; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of the John C. T. Cochrane Mineral Location to the Northeasterly angle thereof; THENCE, Northerly along the Western boundary of the J. J. Vickers Mineral Location to the Northwesterly angle thereof; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of the J. J. Vickers Mineral Location to the Northeasterly angle thereof; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of Section 55, in the said Township of McIntyre to the Northeasterly angle of the said section; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern boundary of the said section to the Southeasterly angle thereof; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern limit of the said allowance for road between the said Townships to the intersection thereof with the production Northerly of the Eastern boundary of Lot 6, in Concession 4, North of the river, in the Township of Neebing; THENCE, Southerly along that production to the point of commencement; SAVING AND EXCEPTING thereout and therefrom all of the Kaministiqua River lying within the above described parcel,</Text></Provision></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582812" lims:id="582812"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the approach surface abutting each end of the strip designated as 12-30 and extending outward therefrom, the dimensions of which are five hundred and fifty (550) feet on each side of the centre line of the strip at the strip ends and one thousand two hundred and fifty (1,250) feet on each side of the projected centre line of the strip at the outer ends, the said outer end of approach 12 being two hundred (200) feet, and the outer end of approach 30 being two hundred and fifty (250) feet respectively above the elevation at the strip ends and ten thousand (10,000) feet measured horizontally therefrom; and the approach surface abutting each end of the strip designated as 7-25 and extending outward therefrom, the dimensions of which are five hundred and fifty (550) feet on each side of the centre line of the strip at the strip ends and two thousand (2,000) feet on each side of the projected centre line of the strip at the outer ends, the said outer ends being two hundred (200) feet above the elevation at the strip ends and ten thousand (10,000) feet measured horizontally therefrom, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582813" lims:id="582813"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the several transitional surfaces, other than the transitional surfaces associated with the strip designated as 2-20, each rising at an angle determined on the basis of a ratio of one (1) foot vertically for every seven (7) feet horizontally from the outer lateral limits of the strips and their abutting surfaces,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582814" lims:id="582814"><Text>as shown on plan No. T2173 dated September 16, 1964, of record in the Department of Transport.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582816" lims:id="582816">SOR/80-70, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582817" lims:id="582817" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582818" lims:id="582818"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582819" lims:id="582819" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582820" lims:id="582820" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the intersection of the Eastern boundary of Lot Eleven (11), in Concession Three (3), North of the Kaministiqua River, in the Township of Neebing, in the District of Thunder Bay, with the Southern limit of the King’s Highway Number 17, as widened, the said intersection being distant seventeen feet (17′) measured Southerly along the said Eastern boundary from the Northeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the said Eastern boundary of Lot Eleven (11), a distance of one thousand four hundred and eighty-four and twenty-five one-hundredths feet (1,484.25′) to the intersection thereof with the production Northeasterly of the centre line of runway 7-25 of Lakehead Airport; THENCE, Southwesterly along that production and along the said centre line of the said runway, a distance of four thousand and twelve and sixty-four one-hundredths feet (4,012.64′); THENCE, Northwesterly at right angles to the said centre line, a distance of eight hundred feet (800′), to a point henceforth designated as the airport reference point, the said point have an assigned elevation of six hundred and thirty-five feet (635′) above sea level.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582821" lims:id="582821" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of Lands to Which These Regulations Apply</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582822" lims:id="582822" level="2"><Label>DIVISION 1</Label><TitleText>Township of Neebing, Fort William Registry Office</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582823" lims:id="582823" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ALL AND SINGULAR, those certain parcels or tracts of land and premises, situated, lying and being in the Township of Neebing, in the District of Thunder Bay and Province of Ontario, and which said parcels may be more particularly described hereinafter as Parcels “A” and “B”.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582824" lims:id="582824" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>PARCEL “A”: Concession One (1) South of the Kaministiqua River.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582825" lims:id="582825" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being composed of Lots Eleven (11), Twelve (12), Thirteen (13), Fourteen (14), Fifteen (15), Sixteen (16), Seventeen (17), Eighteen (18), Nineteen (19) and Twenty (20), in Concession One (1) South of the Kaministiqua River; part of the Allowance for Road along the South bank of the Kaministiqua River; all of the Allowance for Road between Lots Fifteen (15) and Sixteen (16), in the said Concession; and all of the plans of subdivisions registered in the Registry Office for the Registry Division of the District of Fort William as Plan Numbers 689 and 695, the outermost limits of the said parcel may be more particularly described as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582826" lims:id="582826" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Southeasterly angle of said Lot Eleven (11); THENCE, Westerly along the Southern boundary of the said Concession to the Southwesterly angle of said Lot Twenty (20); THENCE, Northerly along the Western boundary of said Lot Twenty (20) and the production Northerly thereof, to the natural High Water Mark of the Kaministiqua River; THENCE, in a general Easterly direction along the said natural High Water Mark to the intersection thereof with the production Northerly of the Eastern boundary of said Lot Eleven (11); THENCE, Southerly along the last said production and along the Eastern boundary of Lot Eleven (11) to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582827" lims:id="582827" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>PARCEL “B”: Concessions North of the Kaministiqua River.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582828" lims:id="582828" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being composed of part of Lot 11, Lots 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, and lot lettered “A”, in Concession 1, North of the river; Lots 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, in Concession 2, North of the river; Lots 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, in Concession 3, North of the river; Lots 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23 in Concession 4, North of the river; Lots 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, in Concession 5, North of the river, which include all of the plans of subdivision registered in the Registry Office for the Registry Division of the District of Fort William as Plan Numbers 680, 693, 694, 682, 687, 684, 679, 658, 305, 781, 704, 728, 714, 692, 743, 783, 185, 742, 738, 744, 254, 578, 255, 180, 726, 218, 639, 698, 281, 289 and 215; all the allowance for road between Lot 15 and lot lettered “A” and between Lots 15 and 16 and between Lots 20 and 21, in the said Concession 1; part of the allowance for road along the North bank of the Kaministiqua River; part of the allowance for road between Concessions 1 and 2; all of the allowance for road between Lots 15 and 16 and between 20 and 21, in the said Concessions 2, 3, 4 and 5; part of the allowance for road between the said Concessions 3 and 4; and part of the allowance for road between the said Concession 5, in the Township of Neebing and the Township of McIntyre, which said parcels are more particularly described as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582829" lims:id="582829" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Northwesterly angle of Lot 23, in Concession 5, North of the river; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of Lot 23, in the said Concession 5 and Lot 23, in said Concession 4, to the Southwesterly angle of Lot 23, in Concession 4; THENCE, Southerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between Concessions 3 and 4, to the Northwesterly angle of Lot 23, in Concession 3; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of the last said Lot 23 and Lot 23, in Concession 2, to the Southwesterly angle of the last said Lot; THENCE, Southerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between said Concessions 1 and 2 to the Northwesterly angle of Lot 23, in Concession 1; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of said Lot 23 and the production Southerly thereof to the natural high water mark of the North bank of Kaministiqua River; THENCE, in a general Easterly direction along the said natural high water mark to the intersection thereof with the production Southerly of the Western boundary of Lot 11, in Concession 1; THENCE, Northerly along that production and along the Western boundary of said Lot 11 to the intersection thereof with the Southerly limit of Broadway Street; THENCE, Easterly along the Southerly limit of Broadway Street to the Eastern boundary of the said Lot 11; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of said Lot 11 to the Northeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Northerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between Concessions 1 and 2 to the Southeasterly angle of Lot 11, in Concession 2; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot 11, in Concession 2 and Lot 11, in Concession 3 to the Northeasterly angle of the last said Lot; THENCE, Northerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between Concessions 3 and 4 to the Southeasterly angle of Lot 11, in Concession 4; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot 11, in Concession 4 and Lot 11, in Concession 5 and the production Northerly thereof to the Northern limit of the allowance for road between the Township of Neebing and the Township of McIntyre; THENCE, Westerly along the said Northern limit to the intersection thereof with the production Northerly of the Western boundary of Lot 23, in Concession 5, in the Township of Neebing; THENCE, Southerly along that production to the point of commencement. SAVING AND EXCEPTING thereout and therefrom the following parcels which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582830" lims:id="582830" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All the plans of subdivision registered in the Land Titles Office for the District of Fort William as Plans Numbered M-53 and M-60.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582831" lims:id="582831" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All of those parts of Lots Twelve (12) and Thirteen (13), in said Concession Two (2), registered in the said Land Titles Office as Parcels 3522, 3955, 3524, 3521 and 3817 (Neebing).</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582832" lims:id="582832" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>All of Lot Twenty-three (23), in said Concession Three (3) as registered in the said Land Titles Office as Parcel 948 (Neebing).</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582833" lims:id="582833" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Part of Lot Twelve (12), in said Concession Four (4) which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582834" lims:id="582834" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at a point in the Northern limit of the King’s Highway, as widened, according to a plan deposited in the said Registry Office as 3563, distant seven hundred and seventy-nine and eight tenths feet (779.8′) measured South eighty-nine degrees fifty-five minutes thirty seconds East (S89°55′30″E) along the said limit from the intersection thereof with the Western boundary of said Lot Twelve (12); THENCE, North nineteen degrees forty-two minutes thirty seconds West (N19°42′30″W), a distance of four hundred and twenty-five and sixty-six one-hundredths feet (425.66′), more or less, to the High Water Mark of the South bank of the Neebing River; THENCE, Northeasterly along the said High Water Mark to a point thereon perpendicularly distant one hundred and fifty feet (150′) from the production Northerly of the last described courses; THENCE, South nineteen degrees forty-two minutes thirty seconds East (S19°42′30″E) to the said limit of the said Highway; THENCE, North eighty-nine degrees fifty-five minutes thirty seconds West (N89°55′30″W) along the said limit, a distance of one hundred and fifty-nine and four tenths feet (159.4′) to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582835" lims:id="582835" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Being composed of part of Lot Three (3) as shown on a plan of subdivision registered in the Registry Office for the District of Fort William as Plan 738 and being more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582836" lims:id="582836" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Southwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Easterly along the Southern boundary of the said Lot, a distance of one hundred and twenty-five feet (125′); THENCE, Northerly and parallel to the Western boundary of the said Lot, a distance of one hundred and fifty feet (150′); THENCE, Westerly and parallel to said Southern boundary, a distance of one hundred and twenty-five feet (125′), more or less, to the Western boundary of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the said Western boundary, a distance of one hundred and fifty feet (150′), more or less, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582837" lims:id="582837" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>All those parts of Lots Eleven (11), Twelve (12), Thirteen (13), Fourteen (14), Fifteen (15), and Sixteen (16), in Concession Two (2) and Lots Eleven (11), Twelve (12), Thirteen (13), Fourteen (14), Fifteen (15), Sixteen (16) and Seventeen (17), in Concession Three (3); part of the Allowance for Road between said Lots Fifteen (15) and Sixteen (16), in the said Concession Two (2) and Concession Three (3); and part of the plan of subdivision registered in the said Registry Office as Plan 180, which lie within the limits of Lakehead Airport and which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582838" lims:id="582838" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>PREMISING that the bearings hereinafter mentioned are astronomical and are referred to the Southern limit of the King’s Highway No. 17, as widened, in Lot Eighteen (18), in Concession Three (3), North of the River, as having a bearing of South eighty-nine degrees fifty-three minutes East (S89°53′E.);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582839" lims:id="582839" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the intersection of the Eastern boundary of Lot Twelve (12), in Concession Three (3), North of the River, with the Southern limit of the King’s Highway, as widened, according to a plan deposited in the said Registry Office as Number 3563; THENCE, Westerly along the said Southern limit, a distance of five hundred and sixty-five feet (565′); THENCE, Southerly and parallel to the said Eastern boundary of Lot Twelve (12) to the intersection thereof with the straight line drawn Northeasterly from a point in the Southern boundary of the North half of the said Lot, distant seven hundred and ninety feet (790′) measured Westerly along the said Southern boundary from the Easterly boundary of said Lot Twelve (12), to a point distant two hundred and sixty-five feet (265′) measured Northerly from the said Southern boundary, on a line drawn West of, parallel with, and forty feet (40′) perpendicularly distant from the said Eastern boundary of Lot Twelve (12); THENCE, Southwesterly along the said straight line to the Southern boundary of the North half of Lot Twelve (12); THENCE, Westerly along the Southern boundary of the North half of Lots Twelve (12), Thirteen (13) and Fourteen (14) to the Eastern boundary of Lot Fifteen (15); THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot Fifteen (15), a distance of two hundred feet (200′); THENCE, Westerly and parallel to the Southern boundary of Lot Fifteen (15), to the Western boundary of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of Lot Fifteen (15) to a point distant one thousand three hundred and twenty feet (1320′) from the Southwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Westerly and parallel to the Southern boundary of Lot Fifteen (15), across the Allowance for Road between Lots Fifteen (15) and Sixteen (16), in Concession Three (3), a distance of sixty-six feet (66′); THENCE, Westerly and parallel to the Southern boundary of Lot Sixteen (16), a distance of one hundred and eighteen feet (118′); THENCE, North seventy-three degrees twenty-eight minutes thirty seconds West (N73°28′30″W), a distance of one thousand two hundred and sixty-one and thirty-nine one hundredths feet (1261.39′), more or less, to a point in the Western boundary of Lot Sixteen (16), distant one thousand six hundred and eight and ninety-six one-hundredths feet (1608.96′), measured South fourteen minutes fifty-five seconds West (S00°14′55″W) along the said boundary from the intersection thereof with the said Southern limit of the said Highway; THENCE, North fourteen minutes fifty-five seconds East (N00°14′55″E) along the said Western boundary of Lot Sixteen (16), a distance of six hundred and six and eleven one-hundredths feet (606.11′); THENCE, North forty-four degrees five minutes forty-five seconds West (N44°05′45″W), a distance of one hundred and ninety-five and ninety-eight one-hundredths feet (195.98′); THENCE, South eighty-nine degrees nine minutes thirty seconds West (S89°09′30″W), a distance of one hundred and twenty and six tenths feet (120.6′); THENCE, North forty-seven degrees twenty-six minutes forty-five seconds West (N47°26′45″W), a distance of one hundred and ninety-three and four tenths feet (193.4′); THENCE, North thirteen minutes forty-five seconds East (N00°13′45″E), a distance of thirteen feet (13′); THENCE, South eighty-nine degrees fifty-nine minutes West (S89°59′W), parallel to the said Southern limit of the said Highway, a distance of two hundred and sixty-three and six tenths feet (263.6′); THENCE, South thirteen minutes forty-five seconds West (S00°13′45″W), a distance of two thousand five hundred and seventy-nine and fifty-seven one-hundredths feet (2579.57′) more or less, to the Southern boundary of Lot Seventeen (17) in the said Concession Three (3); THENCE, Easterly along the said Southern boundary, a distance of six hundred and sixty-three and six tenths feet (663.6’) to the Northwesterly angle of Lot Sixteen (16), in Concession Two (2); THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of the said Lot Sixteen (16) to the intersection thereof with the Northern limit of the right-of-way lands of the Canadian Pacific Railway; THENCE, Easterly along the said limit of the said right-of-way lands to the intersection thereof with the Western boundary of Lot Twelve (12), in Concession Two (2); THENCE, Northerly along the Western boundary of Lot Twelve (12), to the intersection thereof with a line drawn parallel to the Northern boundary of Lot Twelve (12) from a point in the Western limit of the Canadian National Railway right-of-way located on said Lot Twelve (12) and distant Northerly thereon five hundred and forty-nine and five one-hundredths feet (549.05′) from the said Northern limit of the Canadian Pacific Railway right-of-way; THENCE, Easterly along the said parallel line to the said Western limit of Canadian National Railway right-of-way; THENCE, Northerly along the said Western limit of the said right-of-way to the Southern boundary of a plan of subdivision registered in the said Registry Office as Plan 180; THENCE, Westerly along the Southern boundary of the said Plan 180 to the Western limit of Sifton Avenue; THENCE, Northerly along the Western limit of Sifton Avenue to the intersection thereof with the production Westerly of the Northern boundary of Lot Nineteen (19), in Block Eight (8); THENCE, Easterly along that production and along the Northern boundary of said Lot Nineteen (19) to the Northeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot Twenty (20), in Block Eight (8) to the intersection thereof with the production Westerly of the Southern boundary of Lot Sixty-six (66), in Block Eight (8); THENCE, Easterly along the production Westerly of the Southern boundary of Lot Sixty-six (66), in Block Eight (8), and along the said Southern boundary to the Southeasterly angle of Lot Sixty-six (66); THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lots Sixty-six (66) and Sixty-five (65), in block Eight (8), to the intersection thereof with the production Westerly of the Southern boundary of Lot Twenty-three (23), in Block Nine (9); THENCE, Easterly along that production and along the Southern boundary of said Lot Twenty-three (23) to the Southeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lots Twenty-three (23) and Twenty-four (24), in Block Nine (9), to the intersection thereof with the production Westerly of the Southern boundary of Lot Sixty-two (62) in Block Nine (9); THENCE, Easterly along that production and along the Southern boundary of Lot Sixty-two (62) to the Southeasterly angle of said Lot Sixty-two (62); THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot Sixty-two (62) to the intersection thereof with the production Westerly of the Southern boundary of Lot Twenty-six (26), in Block Ten (10); THENCE, Easterly along that production and along the Southern boundary of Lot Twenty-six (26), to the Southeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, continuing Easterly along the production Westerly of the Southern boundary of Lot Sixty-one (61), in Block Ten (10) and along that boundary to the Southeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Northerly along the Western limit of Neebing Avenue to the Northeasterly angle of Lot Thirty-three (33), in Block Twenty (20); THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of Lot Thirty-three (33) to the Northwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of Lots Thirty-three (33), Thirty-four (34), Thirty-five (35) and Thirty-six (36), in Block Twenty (20), to the intersection thereof with the production Easterly of the Northern boundary of Lot Four (4), in Block Twenty (20); THENCE, Westerly along that production and along the Northern boundary of said Lot Four (4) to the Northwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of said Lot Four (4) to the Southwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Westerly across William Avenue to the Northeasterly angle of Lot Thirty-eight (38), in Block Nineteen (19); THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of said Lot Thirty-eight (38) to the Northwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of said Lot Thirty-eight (38) to the intersection thereof with the production Easterly of the Northern boundary of Lot Two (2), in Block Nineteen (19); THENCE, Westerly along that production to the Northeasterly angle of said Lot Two (2); THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lots Three (3) and Four (4), in Block Nineteen (19), to the Northeasterly angle of Lot Four (4); THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of Lot Four (4) to the Northwesterly angle of said Lot Four (4); THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of Lots One (1), Two (2), Three (3) and Four (4), in Block Nineteen (19), and along the production Southerly thereof to the Southern limit of Terminal Street; THENCE, Westerly along the Southern limit of Terminal Street to the Northwesterly angle of Lot Twenty-one (21), in Block Fourteen (14); THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of Lots Twenty-one (21) and Twenty-two (22), in Block Fourteen (14), to the intersection thereof with the production Easterly of the Northern boundary of Lot Eighteen (18), in Block Fourteen (14); THENCE, Westerly along that production and along the Northern boundary of said Lot Eighteen (18) to the Northwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Westerly across Wilson Avenue to the Northeasterly angle of Lot Twenty-three (23), in Block Fifteen (15); THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of said Lot Twenty-three (23) and the production Westerly thereof and continuing Westerly along the Northern boundary of Lot Eighteen (18), in Block Fifteen (15), to the Northwesterly angle of said Lot Eighteen (18); THENCE, Southerly along the Western boundary of said Lot Eighteen (18) to the Southwesterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Westerly along the production Westerly of the Southern boundary of said Lot Eighteen (18) to the Eastern boundary of Lot Twelve (12), in Concession Three (3), North of the River; THENCE, Northerly along the said Eastern boundary of Lot Twelve (12) to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582840" lims:id="582840" level="2"><Label>DIVISION 2</Label><TitleText>City of Fort William, Fort William Registry Office</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582841" lims:id="582841" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ALL AND SINGULAR those certain parcels or tracts of land and premises, situate, lying and being in the Township of Neebing, now in the City of Fort William in the District of Thunder Bay and Province of Ontario, being composed of part of Lots 6, 7, 8, 9 and 10, in Concession 1, North of the river; part of Lots 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 and 10, in Concession 2, North of the river; Lots 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 and 10, in Concession 3, North of the river; and Lots 6, 7, 8, 9 and 10, in Concession 4, North of the river; and part of the Town Plot of Fort William, including all of the plans of subdivision registered in the Registry Office for the Registry Division of the District of Fort William as Plan Numbers 681, 219, 379, 521, 744, 771, 196, 232, 251, 42, 749, 70, 423, 222, 440, 61, 507, 735, 394, 748, 722, 287, 729, 733, 427, 759, 725, 716, 740, 723, 750, 755, 756, 766, 677, 628, 762, 148, 757, 760, 772, 390, 129, 295, 796, 188, 788, 790, 797, 411, 211, 777, 768, 690, 776, 764, 252, 784, 787, 153 and 170, all of the allowance for road between Lots 5 and 6, in the said Concessions, and between the Town Plot of Fort William and Lot 6, in said Concession 1, now known as Edward Street; all of the allowance for road between Lots 10 and 11, in the said Concessions, now known as Neebing Avenue; part of the allowance for road between the said Concessions 2 and 3, now known as Arthur Street; and part of the allowance for road between Concession 4, North of the river, in the Township of Neebing and Township of McIntyre, now known as William Street, which said parcels are more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582842" lims:id="582842" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Northeasterly angle of Lot 6, in Concession 4, North of the river; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern boundary of said Lot 6 to the Southeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Southeasterly in a straight line across Edward Street to the Northwesterly angle of Lot 5, in the said Concession 3; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of said Lot 5 to the Northeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the Easterly boundary of the said Lot to the Southeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Easterly along the Southern boundary of Lots 4 and 3, in the said Concession 3 to the intersection thereof with the production Northerly of the Easterly boundary of Lot 41, as shown on Plan 723; THENCE, Southerly along that production and along the said Easterly boundary of Lot 41 to the Northwestern limit of the right-of-way lands of the Canadian National Railway; THENCE, Southwesterly along the said limit of the said right-of-way land to the Northeasterly angle of Lot 160, as shown on Plan 759; THENCE, Easterly in a straight line to the Northwesterly angle of Lot 2, as shown on Plan 725; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of Lots 2 and 1, as shown on said Plan 725 to the Northeasterly angle of said Lot 1; THENCE, Southwesterly along the Northwestern limit of Kingsway Street to the Southeasterly angle of Lot 31, as shown on Plan 733; THENCE, Southwesterly in a straight line across Christina Street to the Northeasterly angle of Lot 32, as shown on the said Plan 733; THENCE, Southerly along the Western limit of Ford Street to the intersection thereof with the Northern boundary of Lot “A”, as shown on Plan 735; THENCE, Easterly along the Northern boundary of Lot “A” to the Northeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the Eastern boundary of Lots “A” and “B”, as shown on the said Plan 735 to the natural high water mark of the North bank of the Kaministiqua River; THENCE, in a general Westerly and Southerly direction along the said high water mark to the intersection thereof with a line drawn South 60 degrees 50 minutes East from a point on the Easterly limit of Neebing Avenue, the said point being distant 1,263.8 feet measured Southerly along the said Easterly limit from the Southerly limit of Montreal Street; THENCE, North 60 degrees 50 minutes West along the said line and its production Westerly to the intersection thereof with the Eastern boundary of Lot 11, in Concession 1, North of the river; THENCE, Northerly along the said Eastern boundary of said Lot 11, to the Northeasterly angle of the said Lot; THENCE, Northerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between Concessions 1 and 2, to the Southeasterly angle of Lot 11, in Concession 2; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot 11, in Concession 2 and Lot 11, in Concession 3, to the Northeasterly angle of the last said Lot; THENCE, Northerly in a straight line across the allowance for road between Concessions 3 and 4, to the Southeasterly angle of Lot 11, in Concession 4; THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot 11, in Concession 4 and Lot 11, in Concession 5, and the production Northerly thereof, to the Northern limit of the allowance for road between the Township of Neebing and the Township of McIntyre; THENCE, Easterly along the said Northern limit of the said allowance for road to the intersection thereof with the production Northerly of the Eastern boundary of Lot 6, in Concession 4, in the Township of Neebing; THENCE, Southerly along that production to the point of commencement. SAVING AND EXCEPTING thereout and therefrom the following parcels which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582843" lims:id="582843" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Parcels 60, 1902, 1903, 1904, 1923 and 1995, being all of Lots 24 to 33 both inclusive, in Block 10, as shown on Plan 153.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582844" lims:id="582844" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All of Lot 10, in Concession 2, North of the river, being two plans of subdivision registered in the Land Titles Office for the District of Fort William as Plans M-49 and M-79.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582845" lims:id="582845" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>All of the plans of subdivision of part of Lot 8, in Concession 2, North of the river, registered in the Land Titles Office for the District of Fort William as Plans M-38, M-85 and M-88.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582846" lims:id="582846" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>All that portion of the Allowance for Road between Lot Ten (10), in Concession Two (2), North of the River, and Lot Eleven (11), in Concession Three (3), North of the River, and now known as Neebing Avenue, lying between the production Westerly of the Northern limit of Wilcox Street, as shown on a plan of subdivision of said Lot Ten (10), registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-49, and the production Easterly of the Northern boundary of Lot Thirty-three (33), in Block Twenty (20), as shown on a plan of subdivision of said Lot Eleven (11) and registered in the said Registry Office as Plan 180.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582847" lims:id="582847" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Parcel 373 being all of Lot Two Hundred and Eighty-five (285) as shown on a plan of subdivision registered in the said Registry Office as Plan 42.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582848" lims:id="582848" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Parcel 2822 being composed of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582849" lims:id="582849" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>part of Lot Seventeen (17), in Block “O”, as shown on Plan 61, which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582850" lims:id="582850" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at a point on the Easterly boundary of said Lot Seventeen (17) distant ten feet (10′) Southerly from the Northeasterly angle of said Lot seventeen (17); THENCE, Westerly and parallel to the Northern boundary of the said Lot, a distance of sixty-six feet (66′); THENCE, Southerly and parallel to the Eastern boundary of the said Lot one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less, to the Southern boundary of the said Lot; THENCE, Easterly along the said Southern boundary, a distance of sixty-six feet (66′), more or less, to the Southeasterly angle of Lot Seventeen (17); THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot Seventeen (17), a distance of one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less to the point of commencement; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582851" lims:id="582851" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>all of Lots Twenty-eight (28) and Twenty-nine (29), in Block “O”, as shown on Plan 70.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582852" lims:id="582852" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Parcel 3124 being composed of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582853" lims:id="582853" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>all of Lots Thirty-seven (37), Thirty-eight (38), Thirty-nine (39), Forty (40) and Forty-one (41), as shown on Plan 722; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582854" lims:id="582854" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>being composed of part of Lots Forty-three (43) and Forty-four (44) on the North side of Frederica Street as shown on the Town Plot of Fort William and which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582855" lims:id="582855" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Southwesterly angle of Lot Forty-four (44); THENCE, Northerly along the West limit of the said Lot, a distance of seventy-five and sixty-five one-hundreths feet (75.65′), more or less, to the Southeasterly boundary of Lot Thirty-seven (37), as shown on Plan 722; THENCE, Northeasterly along the Southeasterly boundary of Lot Thirty-seven (37), a distance of ninety-one and thirty-one one-hundredths feet (91.31′), more or less, to the Southerly limit of the lane as defined by the City of Fort William By-Law 1043; THENCE, Easterly along the said Southerly limit of the said lane, a distance of one hundred and eighty-seven feet (187′), more or less, to the Easterly boundary of the Westerly thirty-three feet (33′) throughout from front to rear of the Easterly half of said Lot Forty-three (43); THENCE, Southerly along the said Easterly boundary, a distance of one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less, to the Southern boundary of Lot Forty-three (43); THENCE, Westerly along the Southern boundary of Lots Forty-three (43) and Forty-four (44) to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582856" lims:id="582856" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Parcel 3300 being composed of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582857" lims:id="582857" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>part of the lane lying to the North of Lots Thirty-seven (37), Thirty-eight (38), Thirty-nine (39), Forty (40) and Forty-one (41) as shown on Plan 722, which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582858" lims:id="582858" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Northwesterly angle of said Lot Forty-one (41); THENCE, Northerly along the production Northerly of the Western boundary of Lot Forty-one (41), a distance of ten feet (10′); THENCE, East and parallel to the Northern boundary of Lots Forty-one (41), Forty (40), Thirty-nine (39), Thirty-eight (38) and the Easterly production thereof, a distance of one hundred and seventy-seven and twenty-four one-hundredths feet (177.24′) to the Northeasterly angle of Lot Thirty-seven (37); THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of Lot Thirty-seven (37), a distance of forty-six and twenty-four one-hundredths feet (46.24′) to the Northwesterly angle of Lot Thirty-seven (37); THENCE, West along the Northern boundary of Lots Thirty-eight (38), Thirty-nine (39), Forty (40) and Forty-one (41), a distance of one hundred and thirty-two and one tenth feet (132.1′), more or less, to the point of commencement; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582859" lims:id="582859" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>part of Lot Forty-two (42) on the North side of Frederica Street as shown on the Town Plot of Fort William, and which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582860" lims:id="582860" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Southwesterly angle of said Lot Forty-two (42); THENCE, Easterly along the Southern boundary of the said Lot, a distance of ninety-nine feet (99′); THENCE, Northerly and parallel to the Western boundary of the said Lot, a distance of one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less, to a point distant ten feet (10′) perpendicularly Southerly from the Northern boundary of the said Lot; THENCE, Westerly and parallel to the said Northern boundary, a distance of ninety-nine feet (99′), more or less, to the Western boundary of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the said Western boundary, a distance of one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′) more or less, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582861" lims:id="582861" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Parcel 2187 being composed of the Northerly one hundred and twenty-five feet (125′) in perpendicular width of Lot Ten (10), in Block “T”, as shown on Plan 61.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582862" lims:id="582862" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Part of Parcel 1619 and part of Parcel 2149 being composed of Blocks Three (3) and Four (4) lying South of Montreal Street, as shown on Plan 42, SAVING AND EXCEPTING that portion of Block Three (3) conveyed to the Grand Trunk Pacific Railway Company and more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582863" lims:id="582863" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at a point in the Western limit of Lot One (1), in Block “Z”, as shown on Plan 61, distant two and fourteen one-hundredths feet (2.14′) Northerly from the Southwesterly angle of Lot One (1); THENCE, South sixty-two degrees thirty minutes West (S62°30′W.) along the Southern limit of Montreal Street, a distance of seventy-five feet (75′); THENCE, South twenty-eight degrees six minutes thirty seconds East (S28°06′30″E.), a distance of one hundred and nine and six tenths feet (109.6′); THENCE, North sixty-two degrees thirty minutes East (N62°30′E.), a distance of sixteen and nine tenths feet (16.9′); THENCE, North along the Eastern limit of Block Three (3), a distance of one hundred and twenty-three and three tenths feet (123.3′), more or less, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582864" lims:id="582864" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Parcel 2733 being composed of part of Lot Ten (10), in Concession One (1), North of the River, and which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582865" lims:id="582865" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at a point in the Western limit of Lot Ten (10), distant one thousand two hundred and sixty-three and eight tenths feet (1,263.8′), measured Southerly thereon from the Southern limit of Montreal Street as now established; THENCE, Southerly along the said limit of Lot Ten (10), a distance of five hundred and eighty-seven feet (587′); THENCE, on a course of South sixty degrees fifty minutes East (S60°50′E.), a distance of two hundred and ninety feet (290′), more or less, to the original water’s edge of the left bank of the Kaministiqua River; THENCE, Northerly following the said water’s edge downstream to a point in a line drawn on a course of South sixty degrees fifty minutes East (S60°50′E.) through the point of commencement; THENCE, North sixty degrees fifty minutes West (N60°50′W.), a distance of three hundred and forty-seven feet (347′), more or less, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582866" lims:id="582866" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(12)</Label><Text>All of the plan of subdivision of part of Lots 6 and 7, in Concession 4, North of the river, registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-104.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582867" lims:id="582867" level="2"><Label>DIVISION 3</Label><TitleText>Township of Neebing Land Titles Office, Fort William</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582868" lims:id="582868" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ALL AND SINGULAR those certain parcels or tracts of land and premises, situate, lying and being in the Township of Neebing, in the District of Thunder Bay and the Province of Ontario, being composed of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582869" lims:id="582869" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>FIRSTLY:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582870" lims:id="582870" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All of Lot Twenty-three (23), in Concession Three (3), in the said Township, filed as Parcel 948 in the Land Titles Office for The Registry Division of the District of Fort William.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582871" lims:id="582871" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>SECONDLY:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582872" lims:id="582872" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All of Lots One (1), Two (2), Three (3), Four (4), Five (5), as shown on a plan of subdivision registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-60.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582873" lims:id="582873" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>THIRDLY:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582874" lims:id="582874" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Part of Lot Twelve (12), in Concession Two (2), in the said Township, being composed of all of Parcel 3521, 3522, 3524, 3955, as registered in the said Land Titles Office.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582875" lims:id="582875" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>FOURTHLY:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582876" lims:id="582876" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Part of Lot Thirteen (13), in Concession Two (2), in the said Township, being composed of all of Parcel 3817, as registered in the said Land Titles Office.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582877" lims:id="582877" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>FIFTHLY:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582878" lims:id="582878" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>All of Lots One (1) to One Hundred and Eight (108) both inclusive, all of Machray, Pennington, Bowman and Metcalfe Avenues and all of Florence Street, as shown on a plan of subdivision registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-53.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582879" lims:id="582879" level="2"><Label>DIVISION 4</Label><TitleText>City of Fort William Land Titles Office, Fort William</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582880" lims:id="582880" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ALL AND SINGULAR those certain parcels or tracts of land and premises, situate, lying and being in the Township of Neebing, now in the City of Fort William, in the District of Thunder Bay and Province of Ontario, being composed of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582881" lims:id="582881" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Parcels 60, 1902, 1903, 1904, 1923 and 1995 being all of Lots Twenty-four (24) to Thirty-three (33) both inclusive, in Block Ten (10), as shown on Plan 153.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582882" lims:id="582882" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All of the plans of subdivision of Lot 10, in Concession 2, North of the river, registered in the Land Titles Office for the District of Fort William as Plan M-79, SAVING AND EXCEPTING thereout and therefrom all of Block “E” as shown on Plan M-79.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582883" lims:id="582883" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>All of the plans of subdivision of part of Lot 8, in Concession 2, North of the river, registered in the Land Titles Office for the District of Fort William as Plans M-38, M-85 and M-88.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582884" lims:id="582884" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Parcel 373 being all of Lot Two Hundred and Eighty-five (285) as shown on a plan of subdivision registered in the said Registry Office as Plan 42.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582885" lims:id="582885" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Parcel 2822 being composed of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582886" lims:id="582886" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>part of Lot Seventeen (17), in Block “0” as shown on Plan 61, which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582887" lims:id="582887" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at a point on the Easterly boundary of said Lot Seventeen (17), distant ten feet (10′) Southerly from the Northeasterly angle of said Lot Seventeen (17); THENCE, Westerly and parallel to the Northern boundary of the said Lot, a distance of sixty-six feet (66′); THENCE, Southerly and parallel to the Eastern boundary of the said Lot, one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less, to the Southern boundary of the said Lot; THENCE, Easterly along the said Southern boundary, a distance of sixty-six feet (66′), more or less, to the Southeasterly angle of Lot Seventeen (17); THENCE, Northerly along the Eastern boundary of Lot Seventeen (17), a distance of one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less, to the point of commencement; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582888" lims:id="582888" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>all of Lots Twenty-eight (28) and Twenty-nine (29), in Block “0”, as shown on Plan 70.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582889" lims:id="582889" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Parcel 3124 being composed of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582890" lims:id="582890" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>all of Lots Thirty-seven (37), Thirty-eight (38), Thirty-nine (39), Forty (40) and Forty-one (41) as shown on Plan 722; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582891" lims:id="582891" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>part of Lots Forty-three (43) and Forty-four (44) on the North side of Frederica Street as shown on the Town Plot of Fort William and which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582892" lims:id="582892" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Southwesterly angle of Lot Forty-four (44); THENCE, Northerly along the West limit of the said Lot, a distance of seventy-five and sixty-five one-hundredths feet (75.65′), more or less, to the Southeasterly boundary of Lot Thirty-seven (37) as shown on Plan 722; THENCE, Northeasterly along the Southeasterly boundary of Lot Thirty-seven (37), a distance of ninety-one and thirty-one one-hundredths feet (91.31′), more or less, to the Southerly limit of the lane as defined by the City of Fort William By-Law 1043; THENCE, Easterly along the said Southerly limit of the said lane, a distance of one hundred and eighty-seven feet (187′), more or less, to the Easterly boundary of the Westerly thirty-three feet (33′) throughout from front to rear of the Easterly half of said Lot Forty-three (43); THENCE, Southerly along the said Easterly boundary, a distance of one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less, to the Southern boundary of Lot Forty-three (43); THENCE, Westerly along the Southern boundary of Lots Forty-three (43) and Forty-four (44) to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582893" lims:id="582893" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Parcel 3300 being composed of</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582894" lims:id="582894" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>part of the lane lying to the North of Lots Thirty-seven (37), Thirty-eight (38), Thirty-nine (39), Forty (40) and Forty-one (41), as shown on Plan 722, which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582895" lims:id="582895" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Northwesterly angle of said Lot Forty-one (41); THENCE, Northerly along the production Northerly of the Western boundary of Lot Forty-one (41), a distance of ten feet (10′); THENCE, East and parallel to the Northern boundary of Lots Forty-one (41), Forty (40), Thirty-nine (39), Thirty-eight (38) and the Easterly production thereof, a distance of one hundred and seventy-seven and twenty-four one-hundredths feet (177.24′) to the Northeasterly angle of Lot Thirty-seven (37); THENCE, Westerly along the Northern boundary of Lot Thirty-seven (37), a distance of forty-six and twenty-four one-hundredths feet (46.24′) to the Northwesterly angle of Lot Thirty-seven (37); THENCE, West along the Northern boundary of Lots Thirty-eight (38), Thirty-nine (39), Forty (40) and Forty-one (41), a distance of one hundred and thirty-two and one tenth feet (132.1′), more or less, to the point of commencement; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582896" lims:id="582896" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Part of Lot Forty-two (42) on the North side of Frederica Street, as shown on the Town Plot of Fort William and which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582897" lims:id="582897" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the Southwesterly angle of said Lot Forty-two (42); THENCE, Easterly along the Southern boundary of the said Lot, a distance of ninety-nine feet (99′); THENCE, Northerly and parallel to the Western boundary of the said Lot, a distance of one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less, to a point distant ten feet (10′) perpendicularly Southerly from the Northern boundary of the said Lot; THENCE, Westerly and parallel to the said Northern boundary, a distance of ninety-nine feet (99′), more or less, to the Western boundary of the said Lot; THENCE, Southerly along the said Western boundary, a distance of one hundred and fifty-five feet (155′), more or less, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582898" lims:id="582898" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Parcel 2187 being composed of the Northerly one hundred and twenty-five feet (125′) in perpendicular width of Lot Ten (10), in Block “T”, as shown on Plan 61.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582899" lims:id="582899" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Part of Parcel 1619 and part of Parcel 2149 being composed of Blocks Three (3) and Four (4) lying South of Montreal Street as shown on Plan 42, SAVING AND EXCEPTING that portion of Block Three (3) conveyed to the Grand Trunk Pacific Railway Company and more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582900" lims:id="582900" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at a point in the Western limit of Lot One (1), in Block “Z”, as shown on Plan 61, distant two and fourteen one-hundredths feet (2.14′) Northerly from the Southwesterly angle of Lot One (1); THENCE, South sixty-two degrees thirty minutes West (S62°30′W) along the Southern limit of Montreal Street, a distance of seventy-five feet (75′); THENCE, South twenty-eight degrees six minutes thirty seconds East (S28°06′30″E), a distance of one hundred and nine and sixth tenths feet (109.6′); THENCE, North sixty-two degrees thirty minutes East (N62°30′E), a distance of sixteen and nine tenths feet (16.9′); THENCE, North along the Eastern limit of Block Three (3), a distance of one hundred and twenty-three and three tenths feet (123.3′), more or less, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582901" lims:id="582901" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Parcel 2733 being composed of part of Lot Ten (10), in Concession One (1), North of the River, and which may be more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582902" lims:id="582902" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at a point in the Western limit of Lot Ten (10), distant one thousand two hundred and sixty-three and eight tenths feet (1,263.8′) measured Southerly thereon from the Southern limit of Montreal Street, as now established; THENCE, Southerly along the said limit of Lot Ten (10), a distance of five hundred and eighty-seven feet (587′); THENCE, on a course of South sixty degrees fifty minutes East (S60°50′E), a distance of two hundred and ninety feet (290′), more or less, to the original water’s edge of the left bank of the Kaministiqua River; THENCE, Northerly following the said water’s edge downstream to a point in a line drawn on a course of South sixty degrees fifty minutes East (S60°50′E) through the point of commencement; THENCE, North sixty degrees fifty minutes West (N60°50′W), a distance of three hundred and forty-seven feet (347′), more or less, to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582903" lims:id="582903" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>All of the plan of subdivision of part of Lots Three (3) and Four (4), in Concession Three (3) North of the River, registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-63.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582904" lims:id="582904" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(12)</Label><Text>All of Lots Seventy-four (74) to Eighty-four (84) both inclusive, and all of the public lanes lying adjacent to the said Lots and part of Tarbutt Street lying adjacent to said Lots Seventy-four (74), Seventy-five (75), Seventy-six (76), Seventy-seven (77) and Seventy-eight (78), as shown on a plan of subdivision registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-51.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582905" lims:id="582905" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(13)</Label><Text>All of Lots One (1) to Five (5) both inclusive, Lots Ten (10) to Thirty-six (36) both inclusive, and all of the public lanes lying adjacent to the said Lots, and that part of Tarbutt Street lying adjacent to said Lots One (1), Two (2), Three (3), Four (4) and Five (5), and that part of Sills Street lying adjacent to said Lots Ten (10) to Twenty (20) both inclusive and all of Ford Street as shown on a plan of subdivision registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-47.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582906" lims:id="582906" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(14)</Label><Text>Being all of that portion of Lot Four (4), in Concession Three (3), lying North of the Northern limit of a plan of subdivision registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-63, and being composed of Parcels 2077, 2360, 2613, 2818 and 2982.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582907" lims:id="582907" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(15)</Label><Text>All of the plan of subdivision of part of Lot 3, in Concession 3, North of the river, registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-75.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582908" lims:id="582908" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(16)</Label><Text>All of the plan of subdivision of part of Lots 6 and 7, in Concession 4, North of the river, registered in the said Land Titles Office as Plan M-104.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582909" lims:id="582909" level="2"><Label>DIVISION 5</Label><TitleText>Township of Mcintyre Registry Office, Port Arthur</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="582910" lims:id="582910" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ALL AND SINGULAR those certain parcels or tracts of land and premises, situate, lying and being in the Township of McIntyre, in the District of Thunder Bay and Province of Ontario, being composed of all of the John C. T. Cochrane Mineral Location, Jean Langlois Mineral Location, Van Koughnet Mineral Location, J. J. Vickers Mineral Location and Section Fifty-five (55), in the said Township.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>