<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535770" lims:id="535770" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535771" lims:id="535771"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1623</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535773" lims:id="535773"><OtherAuthority>OTHER THAN STATUTORY AUTHORITY</OtherAuthority></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535774" lims:id="535774">Memorial Cross Order (World War II)</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535775" lims:id="535775">ORDER RESPECTING THE AWARD OF THE MEMORIAL CROSS TO MOTHERS AND WIDOWS OF SAILORS, SOLDIERS, AIRMEN, MERCHANT SEAMEN AND FIRE FIGHTERS—WORLD WAR II</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535776" lims:id="535776"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535777" lims:id="535777" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535778" lims:id="535778"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Order may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Memorial Cross Order (World War II)</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535779" lims:id="535779" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535780" lims:id="535780"><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Order,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535781" lims:id="535781" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cross</DefinedTermEn> means the Memorial Cross, which shall be a cross patonce in silver, suspended by a purple ribbon; at the end of the upright a crown; at the foot, and at the end of each arm, a maple leaf; in the centre, within a wreath of laurel, the Royal Cypher of the reigning monarch; engraved with the number, rank and name of the sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or fire fighter commemorated; (<DefinedTermFr>Croix</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535782" lims:id="535782" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>fire fighter</DefinedTermEn> means any person who served during World War II as a member of the Corps of (Civilian) Canadian Fire Fighters for Service in the United Kingdom, who was on service while in receipt of pay and allowances as a fire fighter outside the continents of North and South America, the islands adjacent thereto and the territorial waters thereof, including service in Greenland, Iceland or the Aleutian Islands but not including service in Newfoundland, Bermuda or the West Indies; (<DefinedTermFr>pompier</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535783" lims:id="535783" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>merchant seaman</DefinedTermEn> means any person who served during World War II as Master, Officer or member of the crew of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535784" lims:id="535784"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a ship registered in Canada,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535785" lims:id="535785"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a United Kingdom ship registered in Canada or elsewhere, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535786" lims:id="535786"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a registered ship of one of the countries allied with His Majesty during World War II</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedDefinition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535787" lims:id="535787"><Text>if, in the case of a person who served on other than a ship registered in Canada, that person was born or domiciled in Canada or Newfoundland, or was an ordinary resident in Canada or Newfoundland at anytime during the period between September 9, 1929 and the date on which he commenced to so serve; (<DefinedTermFr>marin de la marine marchande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></ContinuedDefinition></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535788" lims:id="535788" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Veterans Affairs; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535789" lims:id="535789" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>mother</DefinedTermEn> means the natural mother or, where the sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or fire fighter was not raised from childhood by his natural mother, the woman who, in the opinion of the Minister, raised him from childhood; (<DefinedTermFr>mère</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535790" lims:id="535790" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>sailor, soldier or airman</DefinedTermEn> means any person who served during World War II in the naval, army or air forces of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535791" lims:id="535791"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>His Majesty raised in Canada,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535792" lims:id="535792"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>His Majesty, other than those raised in Canada, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535793" lims:id="535793"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>one of the countries allied with His Majesty during World War II</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedDefinition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535794" lims:id="535794"><Text>if, in the case of a person who served in other than the naval, army or air forces of His Majesty raised in Canada, that person was born or domiciled in Canada or Newfoundland or was an ordinary resident in Canada or Newfoundland at any time during the period between September 9, 1929 and the date on which he commenced to so serve; (<DefinedTermFr>marin, soldat, aviateur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></ContinuedDefinition></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535795" lims:id="535795" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>widow</DefinedTermEn> includes the legal widow or widower of a sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or fire fighter and any other person who is pensionable as a widow under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-6">Pension Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Civilian War Pensions and Allowances Act</XRefExternal> by reason of death of the sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or fire fighter or who, if the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-6">Pension Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Civilian War Pensions and Allowances Act</XRefExternal> had applied to her, could have been deemed to be the widow of the sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or fire fighter, but does not include any person who was at the time of the death of the sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or fire fighter, divorced, judicially separated or separated pursuant to a written or other agreement from him; (<DefinedTermFr>veuve</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535796" lims:id="535796" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>World War II</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-6">Pension Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Seconde Guerre mondiale</DefinedTermFr>) <HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem>SI/91-69, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535797" lims:id="535797" level="1"><TitleText>Award of the Cross</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535798" lims:id="535798"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to section 5, a Cross may be issued as a memento of personal loss and sacrifice on the part of the mother and widow of a sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or fire fighter of Canada or Newfoundland who laid down his life for his country during World War II or who dies or died from causes attributable to service during World War II.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535799" lims:id="535799"><Label>4</Label><Text>A Cross referred to in section 3 shall be issued in respect of a sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or firefighter described in that section to only the following persons, namely,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535800" lims:id="535800"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to the mother, if alive,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535801" lims:id="535801"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to the widow, if alive,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535802" lims:id="535802"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where there is no person referred to in paragraph (a) or (b), to the eldest living child,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535803" lims:id="535803"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>where there is no person referred to in paragraphs (a) to (c), to the father, if alive, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535804" lims:id="535804"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>where there is no person referred to in paragraphs (a) to (d), to the brother or sister, if alive, whichever is the eldest</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535805" lims:id="535805"><Text>of the sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or firefighter. <HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem>SI/81-31, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535806" lims:id="535806"><Label>5</Label><Text>A Cross or Crosses may be issued in respect of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535807" lims:id="535807"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>each sailor, soldier or airman who</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535808" lims:id="535808"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>was killed in action during World War II,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535809" lims:id="535809"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>died while on active service during World War II, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535810" lims:id="535810"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>died or dies from causes attributable to service during World War II in the naval, military or air forces, whether his death occurred or occurs while serving on active service or subsequent thereto,</Text></Subparagraph><ContinuedParagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535811" lims:id="535811"><Text>except that, where death occurred or occurs subsequent to his discharge from the naval, military or air forces, a Cross may be issued to the widow or her next of kin only if she was married to the sailor, soldier or airman at the time of his discharge;</Text></ContinuedParagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535812" lims:id="535812"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>each merchant seaman who lost his life through enemy action during World War II or who died or dies from causes attributable to service as a merchant seaman during World War II, except that the Cross may be issued to the widow or her next of kin only if she was married to the merchant seaman at the time he sustained the injury or disability which resulted in his death; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535813" lims:id="535813"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>each fire fighter whose death occurred during his service while in receipt of pay and allowances as a fire fighter during World War II or who died or dies from causes attributable to such service, except that the Cross may be issued to the widow or her next of kin only if she was married to the fire fighter at the time he sustained the injury or disability which resulted in his death.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535814" lims:id="535814"><Label>6</Label><Text>A Cross shall not be issued to a person referred to in section 4 unless that person furnishes proof of the death and service of the sailor, soldier, airman, merchant seaman or firefighter in respect of whom the cross may be issued and the eligibility of the person to be issued the Cross. </Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="535816" lims:id="535816">SI/81-31, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>