<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529659" lims:id="529659" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529660" lims:id="529660"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1566</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529662" lims:id="529662"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-18">DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORT ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529663" lims:id="529663">Transport Control Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529664" lims:id="529664">Regulations Respecting Transport Control</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529665" lims:id="529665"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529666" lims:id="529666" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529667" lims:id="529667"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1566">Transport Control Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529668" lims:id="529668" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529669" lims:id="529669"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations and in any order,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529670" lims:id="529670" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>bulk transport facilities</DefinedTermEn> includes any property, real or personal, designed or suited, or capable of being used, for the transportation of goods in bulk either by means of ships or by a company to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Act</XRefExternal> applies including any facilities for loading, unloading and storing goods in bulk and any facilities owned or controlled by or in possession of any person operating transport facilities, and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, <DefinedTermEn>transport facilities</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529671" lims:id="529671"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>railway facilities designed or suited, as to design, or capable of being used for the transportation of goods in bulk,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529672" lims:id="529672"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>ships of 1,000 gross registered tons or over so designed or suited, or capable of being so used, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529673" lims:id="529673"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>storage facilities used or capable of being used in connection with transporting goods in bulk; (<DefinedTermFr>installations de transport en vrac</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529674" lims:id="529674" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Controller</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>Transport Controller</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Deputy Controller</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>Deputy Transport Controller</DefinedTermEn> mean, respectively, the Transport Controller or Deputy Transport Controller appointed by the Governor in Council under section 3; (<DefinedTermFr>régisseur or régisseur des transports and sous-régisseur or sous-régisseur des transports</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529675" lims:id="529675" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>dealing in or with</DefinedTermEn> includes buying, selling, owning, leasing, hiring, lending, borrowing, exchanging, acquiring, importing, storing, supplying, chartering, operating, delivering, transporting, distributing, dispensing, shipping, conveying, installing or using; (<DefinedTermFr>s'occupant ou disposant de</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529676" lims:id="529676" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>equipment</DefinedTermEn> includes any property, real or personal, and any goods owned by or under the control of any person for the purpose of operating bulk transport facilities and any articles, substances or things to be included in or excluded from equipment for the purposes of these Regulations or any part thereof; (<DefinedTermFr>matériel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529677" lims:id="529677" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>goods in bulk</DefinedTermEn> includes grain, and grain products, ore and minerals (crude, screened, sized, refined or concentrated, but not otherwise processed), ferrous metals, iron and steel scrap, sand, stone and gravel, pulpwood, woodpulp, poles and logs, coal and coke, and sulphur and phosphate; (<DefinedTermFr>denrées en vrac</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529678" lims:id="529678" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>grain</DefinedTermEn> includes wheat, flour, flax, barley, rye, buckwheat, corn, oats, mill feed and grain screenings; (<DefinedTermFr>grains</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529679" lims:id="529679" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>order</DefinedTermEn> means an order made under these Regulations; (<DefinedTermFr>ordonnance</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529680" lims:id="529680" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>services</DefinedTermEn> means any accommodations or undertakings sold or supplied by any person owning, operating, controlling or having in his possession any bulk transport facilities or equipment of the operation thereof; (<DefinedTermFr>services</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529681" lims:id="529681" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>ship</DefinedTermEn> means a ship, as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-9">Canada Shipping Act</XRefExternal>, that is registered in Canada. (<DefinedTermFr>navire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529682" lims:id="529682" level="1"><TitleText>Appointment and Duties of Controllers</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529683" lims:id="529683"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, may appoint a Transport Controller and one or more Deputy Transport Controllers.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529684" lims:id="529684"><Label>4</Label><Text>A Deputy Transport Controller may exercise any and all powers conferred upon the Controller by these Regulations, subject to any restrictions that the Controller may impose and subject in all cases to review by the Controller; but any order by a Deputy Transport Controller is final and binding unless and until it has been reviewed and varied or vacated by the Transport Controller.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529685" lims:id="529685"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529686" lims:id="529686"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Transport Controller may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529687" lims:id="529687"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>order any person dealing in or with bulk transport facilities to transport goods in bulk in such priority over any other goods in bulk or over other goods, and as between them or any of them, as the Controller directs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529688" lims:id="529688"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>fix minimum quotas, amounts or quantities of any goods in bulk that shall be moved in any bulk transport facilities during such period as he directs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529689" lims:id="529689"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>fix minimum ratios or proportions of any goods in bulk in relation to any other goods in bulk or to other goods, that shall be moved in any bulk transport facilities during such period as he directs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529690" lims:id="529690"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>fix minimum quotas, amounts or quantities of any goods in bulk that any person dealing in or with bulk transport facilities shall transport or cause to be transported in such facilities during such period as he directs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529691" lims:id="529691"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>fix minimum ratios or proportions of any goods in bulk in relation to any other goods in bulk or to other goods that any person dealing in or with bulk transport facilities shall transport or cause to be transported in such facilities during such period as he directs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529692" lims:id="529692"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>order any person dealing in or with bulk transport facilities to limit, discontinue or cease to operate, except for the transportation of such goods in bulk as he designates, any such facilities for such time as he directs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529693" lims:id="529693"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>order any person dealing in or with bulk transport facilities to extend, furnish, supply or make use of any bulk transport facilities, services or equipment for transporting any goods in bulk at such times and places and in such manner as he directs; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529694" lims:id="529694"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>order or require any person dealing in or with bulk transport facilities or goods in bulk or any agent, employee or representative of any such person, to furnish in such form and within such time as the Controller may prescribe such facts, data or information as the Controller may deem necessary or advisable; and the Controller may require the same to be furnished under oath or affirmation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529695" lims:id="529695"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order may be either general or with respect to a specific or particular matter, thing, activity or undertaking.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529696" lims:id="529696"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any violation of an order made under this section shall be deemed to be a violation of these Regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529697" lims:id="529697"><Label>6</Label><Text>Where any person fails to fulfil any contract, charter or obligation, whether made or assumed before or after June 1, 1954 or any order, and such failure is due to compliance on the part of such person with any order made after such contract, charter or obligation was made or assumed, proof of that fact is a good defence to any action or proceeding against such person in respect of such failure.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529698" lims:id="529698"><Label>7</Label><Text>The Controller, a Deputy Controller or any person acting for or on behalf of or under the authority of the Controller is not liable to any person for anything done or omitted to be done in the exercise or purported exercise of any power or authority vested in the Controller by these Regulations.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529699" lims:id="529699"><Label>8</Label><Text>Such staff and organization at Ottawa and elsewhere in Canada as may be required by the Controller may be appointed in the manner prescribed by law.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="529700" lims:id="529700"><Label>9</Label><Text>Any person who violates any of the provisions of these Regulations is guilty of an offence and is liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding $500 or to imprisonment for a term of six months, or to both, and in the case of conviction on indictment to a fine not exceeding $5,000 or to imprisonment for a term of five years, or to both.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>