<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2013-06-07" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508874" lims:id="508874" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508875" lims:id="508875"><InstrumentNumber>C.R.C., c. 1392</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508877" lims:id="508877"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="R-10.6">ROYAL CANADIAN MOUNTED POLICE PENSION CONTINUATION ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508878" lims:id="508878">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Pension Continuation Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508879" lims:id="508879">Regulations made pursuant to the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Pension Continuation Act</LongTitle></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508880" lims:id="508880"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508881" lims:id="508881" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508882" lims:id="508882"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1392">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Pension Continuation Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508883" lims:id="508883" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508884" lims:id="508884"><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508885" lims:id="508885" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="R-10.6">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Pension Continuation Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508886" lims:id="508886" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>authorized advisor</DefinedTermEn> means a member of the Force, a person employed in the public service or a person whose services were retained by the Minister for the purposes of the Act. (<DefinedTermFr>conseiller autorisé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508888" lims:id="508888">SOR/2013-125, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508889" lims:id="508889" level="1"><TitleText>Service in the Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508890" lims:id="508890"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508891" lims:id="508891"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any period of service of a person as a special constable in the Force or as a member of a provincial police force of a province with which the Governor in Council entered into an arrangement under section 5 of the Act as it was before the coming into force of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="R-11">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>, shall be deemed to be a period during which that person served in the Force and to be service for the purposes of the Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508892" lims:id="508892"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), any period of service of a person as a member of a provincial police force described in subsection (1) shall be deemed to be a period during which he served in the Force and to be service for the purposes of section 5 of the Act only if his service in the Force has been continuous since the date of absorption of that police force into the Force and the disability sustained during that period, in respect of which the application for compensation under section 5 of the Act is made, is a disability for which that person is not and was not eligible to receive compensation under a law of a province that provides for the payment of workmen’s compensation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508893" lims:id="508893"><Label>4</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/2013-125, s. 2]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508894" lims:id="508894" level="1"><TitleText>Allowances to Be Included as Pay</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508895" lims:id="508895"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508896" lims:id="508896"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 34(2) of the Act, the amount of allowances for pension purposes to be received by any constable of the Force shall be</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508897" lims:id="508897"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the value of free meals or quarters, or of single or double rations, supplied or received as part of the remuneration of the constable, determined where applicable as provided from time to time for the purposes of any Act of the Parliament of Canada respecting income taxes; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508898" lims:id="508898"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>service pay received by him after October 1, 1966, as compensation for long service in the Force.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508899" lims:id="508899"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a member has not received an allowance specified in subsection (1) due to absence on authorized leave with or without pay, the rate of pay for pension purposes shall not be reduced.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508900" lims:id="508900"><Label>5.1</Label><Text>For the purpose of section 11 of the Act, the amount of allowances for purposes of pension to be received by the Commissioner and other officers of the Force shall include service pay received by them after April 1, 1981.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508902" lims:id="508902">SOR/84-315, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508903" lims:id="508903" level="1"><TitleText>Royal Canadian Mounted Police (Dependants) Pension Fund</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508904" lims:id="508904"><Label>6</Label><Text>For the purpose of subsection 55(3) of the Act, the rate of interest shall be the rate described in subsection 30(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1393">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Regulations</XRefExternal> calculated in respect of each quarter in each fiscal year on the last day of June, September, December and March on the balance to the credit of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police (Dependants) Pension Fund on the last day of the preceding quarter.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508905" lims:id="508905" level="1"><TitleText>Full-time Attendance at a School or University Substantially Without Interruption</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508906" lims:id="508906"><Label>7</Label><Text>For the purpose of paragraph 47(8)(b) of the Act, the expression “full-time attendance at a school or university” shall have the same meaning as in section 19 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1393">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Regulations</XRefExternal> and the circumstances under which attendance at a school or university shall be determined to be substantially without interruption shall be as specified in section 19 of those Regulations.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508907" lims:id="508907" level="1"><TitleText>Election in Respect of Surviving Spouse Pension</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508908" lims:id="508908"><Label>8</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 9 to 26,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508909" lims:id="508909" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>election</DefinedTermEn> means an election under section 20.1 of the Act; (<DefinedTermFr>choix</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508910" lims:id="508910" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>level of reduction</DefinedTermEn> means, in respect of a pension, one of the three amounts determined pursuant to section 17, where levels one, two and three correspond to a reduction that provides a surviving spouse with a pension that is equal to 30, 40 or 50 per cent, respectively, of a pension referred to in subparagraph 17(b)(i), if paragraph 17(b) were read without reference to supplementary benefits payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-24">Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>niveau de réduction</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508911" lims:id="508911" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>officer</DefinedTermEn> means an officer referred to in section 20.1 of the Act; (<DefinedTermFr>officier</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508912" lims:id="508912" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>spouse</DefinedTermEn> means a spouse referred to in section 20.1 of the Act. (<DefinedTermFr>conjoint</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508914" lims:id="508914">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508915" lims:id="508915"><Label>9</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 20.1 of the Act, an officer may make an election to reduce the amount of the officer’s pension not later than one year after the later of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508916" lims:id="508916"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the day on which this section comes into force, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508917" lims:id="508917"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which the officer and the spouse are married.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508919" lims:id="508919">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508920" lims:id="508920"><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508921" lims:id="508921"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 9, an officer may make the election after the expiration of the period provided for in that section if the officer has received, from an authorized advisor who normally gives information about these matters, erroneous or misleading information regarding the period during which the officer could make an election or materially erroneous or misleading information regarding the amount of the reduction of the officer’s pension or the amount of the pension to which the spouse would be entitled and, in making the election, acted on that information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508922" lims:id="508922"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The election may be made not later than three months after the day on which a written notice containing the corrected information is sent to the officer.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508924" lims:id="508924">SOR/94-348, s. 1; SOR/2013-125, s. 3</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508925" lims:id="508925"><Label>11</Label><Text>An election shall be made in writing and shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508926" lims:id="508926"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>indicate the level of reduction in respect of the officer’s pension;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508927" lims:id="508927"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>indicate the date of birth of the officer’s spouse and the date of the spouse’s marriage to the officer; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508928" lims:id="508928"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>be signed and dated by the officer and signed by a witness other than the officer’s spouse.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508930" lims:id="508930">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508931" lims:id="508931"><Label>12</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508932" lims:id="508932"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An election is valid only if it is sent to the Minister, or to a person designated by the Minister, within the period set out in section 9 or subsection 10(2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508933" lims:id="508933"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An election is made on the day on which it is sent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508934" lims:id="508934"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The day of the sending of the election is the day on which it is delivered or, if it is sent by mail, the day on which it is mailed and the postmark is evidence of that day.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508936" lims:id="508936">SOR/94-348, s. 1; SOR/2013-125, s. 4</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508937" lims:id="508937"><Label>13</Label><Text>The officer, or a person acting on behalf of the officer, shall, within one year after the day on which an election is made, send to the Minister or to a person designated by the Minister</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508938" lims:id="508938"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a document that is evidence of the date of birth of the spouse;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508939" lims:id="508939"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a document that is evidence of the marriage of the officer and the spouse; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508940" lims:id="508940"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where the name of the spouse as indicated on a document referred to in paragraph (a) is not the same as the name of the spouse as indicated on a document referred to in paragraph (b), any other document that confirms that the evidence of the birth and the marriage relates to the spouse, or a statutory declaration by which the spouse declares that the documents are in respect of the spouse.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508942" lims:id="508942">SOR/94-348, s. 1; SOR/2013-125, s. 5(F)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508943" lims:id="508943"><Label>14</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508944" lims:id="508944"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Proof of age of the officer’s spouse is established by a birth certificate issued by a civil authority.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508945" lims:id="508945"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a birth certificate referred to in subsection (1) cannot be obtained, proof of age of the spouse is established by</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508946" lims:id="508946"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a statutory declaration of the spouse in which the spouse attests to the spouse’s date of birth and explains the reasons why the birth certificate cannot be obtained; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508947" lims:id="508947"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a document that was created</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508948" lims:id="508948"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within five years after the date of birth of the spouse and that indicates the name of the spouse and the date of birth or age of the spouse, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508949" lims:id="508949"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>at least 20 years before the day on which the election is made and that indicates the name of the spouse and the date of birth of the spouse, which document is accompanied by a statutory declaration by which a person, other than the officer or the spouse, attests that the date stated in the document is the correct date of birth of the spouse.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508950" lims:id="508950"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where a document or statutory declaration referred to in paragraph (2)(b) is to be submitted but cannot be obtained, the statutory declaration referred to in paragraph (2)(a) shall set out the reasons why the document or statutory declaration cannot be obtained.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508952" lims:id="508952">SOR/94-348, s. 1; SOR/2013-125, s. 6</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508953" lims:id="508953"><Label>15</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508954" lims:id="508954"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), proof of the marriage between the officer and the spouse is established by a marriage certificate issued by a civil authority.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508955" lims:id="508955"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a marriage certificate referred to in subsection (1) cannot be obtained, proof of the marriage between the officer and the spouse is established by</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508956" lims:id="508956"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a statutory declaration by which the officer or the spouse attests to the date of the marriage and explains the reasons why the marriage certificate cannot be obtained; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508957" lims:id="508957"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a document that is similar to a marriage certificate and is issued in relation to the marriage ceremony, or a statutory declaration by a person who attended the marriage ceremony, other than the officer or the spouse, attesting to the person’s knowledge of the marriage.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508959" lims:id="508959">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508960" lims:id="508960" level="1"><TitleText>Non-compliance with Requirements to Submit Evidence</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508961" lims:id="508961"><Label>16</Label><Text>An election is considered not to have been made where any document or statutory declaration that is required by any of sections 13 to 15 is not submitted within one year after the day on which the election is made.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508963" lims:id="508963">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508964" lims:id="508964" level="1"><TitleText>Calculation of the Reduction</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508965" lims:id="508965"><Label>17</Label><Text>The amount of the reduction of the monthly instalment of the pension of an officer who makes an election is equal to the amount determined as follows:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508966" lims:id="508966"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>calculate the actuarial present value of the pension to which the officer is entitled under Part II of the Act immediately before the election, and the supplementary benefits payable in respect thereof under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-24">Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508967" lims:id="508967"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>convert the amount determined in accordance with paragraph (a) into a joint and survivor pension benefit that consists of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508968" lims:id="508968"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a pension that is payable, during the life of the officer, by monthly instalments beginning on the first day of the month after the month in which the election is made, and that is determined taking into account the supplementary benefits payable of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-24">Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act</XRefExternal>, as if the pension were a pension payable under Part II of the Act, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508969" lims:id="508969"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a pension that is payable during the life of the surviving spouse, by monthly instalments beginning on the first day of the month after the month in which the officer died and that is equal to 30, 40 or 50 per cent, in accordance with the election made by the officer, of the pension determined in accordance with subparagraph (i), and that is determined taking into account the supplementary benefits payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-24">Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act</XRefExternal>, as if the pension were a pension payable under Part II of the Act; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508970" lims:id="508970"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subtract the first monthly instalment of the pension referred to in subparagraph (b)(i) from the first monthly instalment of the pension referred to in paragraph (a), and adjust the amount obtained to take into account</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508971" lims:id="508971"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that the reduction is effective during the lesser of</Text><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508972" lims:id="508972"><Label>(A)</Label><Text>the period of the life of the officer,</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508973" lims:id="508973"><Label>(B)</Label><Text>the period of the life of the spouse, and</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508974" lims:id="508974"><Label>(C)</Label><Text>the duration of the marriage,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508975" lims:id="508975"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that the reduction becomes effective in the month referred to in subsection 22(1) or (2), as the case may be, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508976" lims:id="508976"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>that the increase in the reduction under section 18 will apply to the reduction in each year referred to in that section.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508978" lims:id="508978">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508979" lims:id="508979" level="1"><TitleText>Indexation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508980" lims:id="508980"><Label>18</Label><Text>The amount of the reduction determined in accordance with section 17 is increased on January 1 of each year after the year in which the reduction is first in effect, by the amount that would be payable as a supplementary benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-24">Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act</XRefExternal> if the amount of the reduction determined under section 17 were a pension that became payable under Part II of the Act on January 1 of the year in which the election was made.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="508982" lims:id="508982">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508983" lims:id="508983" level="1"><TitleText>Demographic Assumptions</TitleText><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508985" lims:id="508985">SOR/2013-125, s. 7</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508986" lims:id="508986"><Label>19</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508987" lims:id="508987"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 17, the following are the only demographic assumptions on which the actuarial present values are to be based:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508988" lims:id="508988"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the rate of mortality for any officer is that set out in the actuarial valuation report laid before Parliament in accordance with section 30 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="R-11">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>, taking into account the mortality projection factors set out in the report;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508989" lims:id="508989"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the rates of mortality of surviving spouses are those set out for spouses in the actuarial valuation report laid before Parliament in accordance with section 45 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-36">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>, taking into account the mortality projection factors set out in the report; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508990" lims:id="508990"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the rates of divorce shall be those established by the Superintendent of Financial Institutions in accordance with the most recent statistics on divorce published by Statistics Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508991" lims:id="508991"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), the actuarial valuation reports referred to in that subsection are the most recent actuarial valuation reports, or, where the most recent actuarial valuation reports were tabled less than two months before the day on which the officer made an election, the previously tabled reports.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508993" lims:id="508993">SOR/94-348, s. 1; SOR/2013-125, s. 8</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508994" lims:id="508994"><Label>20</Label><Text>For the purposes of the determination referred to in section 17, the rates of interest to be used are those determined in respect of fully indexed pensions in accordance with the section entitled “Pension Commuted Values” of the <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">Standards of Practice — Practice-Specific Standards for Pension Plans</XRefExternal>, published by the Canadian Institute of Actuaries, as amended from time to time.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508996" lims:id="508996">SOR/94-348, s. 1; SOR/2013-125, s. 9</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508997" lims:id="508997" level="1"><TitleText>Revision of an Election</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508998" lims:id="508998"><Label>21</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="508999" lims:id="508999"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An officer who has made an election may revise the level of reduction where</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509000" lims:id="509000"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the officer has received, from an authorized advisor who normally gives information about these matters, materially erroneous or misleading information regarding the amount of the reduction of the officer’s pension or the amount of the pension to which the spouse would be entitled and, in making the election, acted on that information; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509001" lims:id="509001"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount of the pension that is payable to the officer is adjusted in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-6.7">Pension Benefits Division Act</XRefExternal> after the day on which the election was made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509002" lims:id="509002"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The revision of the level of reduction shall be in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509003" lims:id="509003"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The revision is valid only if it is sent to the Minister, or to a person designated by the Minister,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509004" lims:id="509004"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>within three months after the day on which a written notice containing the corrected information is sent to the officer; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509005" lims:id="509005"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>within three months after the day on which the pension is adjusted in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-6.7">Pension Benefits Division Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509006" lims:id="509006"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A revision of the level of reduction is effective on the day on which it is sent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509007" lims:id="509007"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The day of the sending of the revision is the day on which it is delivered or, if it is sent by mail, the day on which it is mailed and the postmark is evidence of that day.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509009" lims:id="509009">SOR/94-348, s. 1; SOR/2013-125, s. 10</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509010" lims:id="509010" level="1"><TitleText>Effective Dates of Reduction</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509011" lims:id="509011"><Label>22</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509012" lims:id="509012"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the amount of the reduction of an officer’s pension, calculated in accordance with section 17, shall be subtracted from the monthly instalment of the pension payable to the officer, effective on the first day of the second month after the month in which the election is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509013" lims:id="509013"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an officer has revised the level of reduction pursuant to subsection 21(1), the revised amount of the reduction shall be subtracted from the monthly instalments of the pension payable to the officer, effective on the first day of the month after the month in which the revision was made.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509015" lims:id="509015">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509016" lims:id="509016" level="1"><TitleText>Cessation of Effect of Election</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509017" lims:id="509017"><Label>23</Label><Text>An election ceases to have effect on the earliest of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509018" lims:id="509018"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the day on which the spouse dies,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509019" lims:id="509019"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which the annulment of the marriage of the officer and the spouse takes effect, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509020" lims:id="509020"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the day on which the divorce between the officer and the spouse takes effect.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509022" lims:id="509022">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509023" lims:id="509023" level="1"><TitleText>Revocation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509024" lims:id="509024"><Label>24</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 20.1(5) of the Act, an election made by an officer is deemed to be revoked on the day on which the officer is required to contribute to the Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Account pursuant to subsection 5(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="R-11">Royal Canadian Mounted Police Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509026" lims:id="509026">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509027" lims:id="509027" level="1"><TitleText>Termination of Reduction</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509028" lims:id="509028"><Label>25</Label><Text>Where an election ceases to have effect pursuant to section 23 or is deemed to be revoked pursuant to section 24, the reduction ceases on the first day of the month in which the election is revoked or ceases to have effect.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509030" lims:id="509030">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-06-07" lims:fid="509031" lims:id="509031" level="1"><TitleText>Surviving Spouse Allowance</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509032" lims:id="509032"><Label>26</Label><Text>The pension to which a spouse is entitled on the death of the officer who made an election is equal to an amount determined in accordance with subparagraph 17(b)(ii), if paragraph 17(b) were read without reference to supplementary benefits payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-24">Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="509034" lims:id="509034">SOR/94-348, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>