<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2013-01-11" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-11" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626643" lims:id="626643" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626644" lims:id="626644"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2013-3</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2013</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>13</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626646" lims:id="626646"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">AN ACT TO IMPLEMENT CONVENTIONS BETWEEN CANADA AND MOROCCO, CANADA AND PAKISTAN, CANADA AND SINGAPORE, CANADA AND THE PHILIPPINES, CANADA AND THE DOMINICAN REPUBLIC AND CANADA AND SWITZERLAND FOR THE AVOIDANCE OF DOUBLE TAXATION WITH RESPECT TO INCOME TAX</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626647" lims:id="626647">Proclamation Giving Notice that the Protocol Amending the Convention between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Singapore for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income Came into Force on August 31, 2012</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2012-1638</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626648" lims:id="626648"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626649" lims:id="626649" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>DAVID JOHNSTON</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626650" lims:id="626650" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626651" lims:id="626651" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626652" lims:id="626652" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626653" lims:id="626653" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>TO ALL TO WHOM these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626654" lims:id="626654" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626655" lims:id="626655" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">WILLIAM PENTNEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626656" lims:id="626656" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626657" lims:id="626657" level="1"><TitleText>A Proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626658" lims:id="626658" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas by Order in Council P.C. 2012-1638 of December 6, 2012, the Governor in Council pursuant to section 19 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to Implement Conventions between Canada and Morocco, Canada and Pakistan, Canada and Singapore, Canada and the Philippines, Canada and the Dominican Republic and Canada and Switzerland for the Avoidance of Double Taxation with respect to Income Tax</XRefExternal>, directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice that the annexed supplementary convention, signed on November 29, 2011 and intended to amend the Convention between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Singapore for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income, done in Singapore on 6 March, 1976, came into force on August 31, 2012;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626659" lims:id="626659" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our Proclamation give notice that the annexed supplementary convention, signed on November 29, 2011 and intended to amend the Convention between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Singapore for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income, done in Singapore on 6 March, 1976, came into force on August 31, 2012.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626660" lims:id="626660" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of all which Our loving subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626661" lims:id="626661" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN TESTIMONY WHEREOF, We have caused this Our Proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. WITNESS: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved David Johnston, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626662" lims:id="626662" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>AT OUR GOVERNMENT HOUSE, in Our City of Ottawa, this eleventh day of January in the year of Our Lord two thousand and thirteen and in the sixty-first year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626663" lims:id="626663" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="12" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="16 pc"><SignatureName justification="right" topmarginspacing="4">JOHN KNUBLEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-11" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-11" lims:fid="626664" lims:id="626664" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Protocol Amending the Convention Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Singapore for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with Respect to Taxes on Income, Done in Singapore on 6 March 1976</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF SINGAPORE,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DESIRING</Emphasis> to amend the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Singapore for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income</XRefExternal>, done in Singapore on 6 March 1976 (“the Convention”),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED</Emphasis> as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE I</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" type="amending"><Text><Emphasis style="regular">The text of Article 25 (Exchange of Information) of the Convention is deleted and replaced by the following:</Emphasis></Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>“1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall exchange such information as is foreseeably relevant for carrying out the provisions of this Convention or to the administration or enforcement of the domestic laws concerning taxes of every kind and description imposed on behalf of the Contracting States, insofar as the taxation thereunder is not contrary to the Convention. The exchange of information is not restricted by Articles 1 and 2.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any information received under paragraph 1 by a Contracting State shall be treated as secret in the same manner as information obtained under the domestic laws of that State and shall be disclosed only to persons or authorities (including courts and administrative bodies) concerned with the assessment or collection of, the enforcement in respect of, the determination of appeals in relation to taxes, or the oversight of the above. Such persons or authorities shall use the information only for such purposes. They may disclose the information in public court proceedings or in judicial decisions.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>In no case shall the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 be construed so as to impose on a Contracting State the obligation:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to carry out administrative measures at variance with the laws and administrative practice of that or of the other Contracting State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to supply information which is not obtainable under the laws or in the normal course of the administration of that or of the other Contracting State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to supply information which would disclose any trade, business, industrial, commercial or professional secret or trade process, or information, the disclosure of which would be contrary to public policy (ordre public).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>If information is requested by a Contracting State in accordance with this Article, the other Contracting State shall use its information gathering measures to obtain the requested information, even though that other State may not need such information for its own tax purposes. The obligation contained in the preceding sentence is subject to the limitations of paragraph 3 but in no case shall such limitations be construed to permit a Contracting State to decline to supply information solely because it has no domestic interest in such information.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>In no case shall the provisions of paragraph 3 be construed to permit a Contracting State to decline to supply information solely because the information is held by a bank, other financial institution, nominee or person acting in an agency or a fiduciary capacity or because it relates to ownership interests in a person.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE II</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Each of the Contracting States shall notify the other through diplomatic channels of the completion of the procedures required by its law for the bringing into force of this Protocol. This Protocol shall enter into force 30 days after the date of the later of these notifications and its provisions shall have effect from the date of entry into force.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE III</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Protocol, which shall form an integral part of the Convention, shall remain in force as long as the Convention remains in force and shall apply as long as the Convention itself is applicable.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis>, the undersigned, duly authorised thereto by their respective governments, have signed this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in duplicate at Singapore, this 29th day of November 2011, in the English and French languages, each version being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" /><colspec colname="col2" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no"><Text>DAVID SEVIGNY</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no"><Text>MOSES LEE</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF SINGAPORE</Emphasis></Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>