<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2017-02-16" lims:lastAmendedDate="2017-02-16" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="630999" lims:id="630999" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631000" lims:id="631000"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2017-15</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631002" lims:id="631002"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631003" lims:id="631003">Proclamation giving notice of the Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru and the Administrative Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Peru for the Implementation of the Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru Come into Force on March 1, 2017</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631004" lims:id="631004"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631005" lims:id="631005" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>David Johnston</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631006" lims:id="631006" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631007" lims:id="631007" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631008" lims:id="631008" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631009" lims:id="631009" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="13pc"><SignatureName justification="left" topmarginspacing="8">William Pentney</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left">Deputy Attorney General</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631010" lims:id="631010" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="20" list-item="no"><Text>To all to whom these presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631011" lims:id="631011" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Greeting:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631012" lims:id="631012" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631013" lims:id="631013" level="1"><TitleText>A Proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631014" lims:id="631014" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas by Order in Council P.C. 2014-687 of June 12, 2014, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article 27 of the Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru, and Article 7 of the Administrative Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Peru for the Implementation of the Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru, signed at Ottawa on April 10, 2014, the Convention and the Administrative Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party notifies the other by diplomatic note that it has completed the internal legal procedures necessary for the entry into force of the Convention and the Administrative Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631015" lims:id="631015" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas that Order in Council was laid before the House of Commons and the Senate on September 15, 2014, as required under the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631016" lims:id="631016" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after that Order in Council had been laid before Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631017" lims:id="631017" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, that Order in Council came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it had been laid before Parliament, being November 5, 2014;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631018" lims:id="631018" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, in accordance with Article 27 of the Convention and Article 7 of the Administrative Agreement, both the Convention and the Administrative Agreement are to enter into force on March 1, 2017;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631019" lims:id="631019" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2017-86 of February 3, 2017, the Governor in Council, pursuant to subsection 41(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, directed that a proclamation be issued giving notice of the entry into force on March 1, 2017 of the Convention and the Administrative Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631020" lims:id="631020" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our proclamation give notice of the entry into force on March 1, 2017 of the Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru and the Administrative Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Peru for the Implementation of the Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru, copies of which are annexed to this proclamation.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631021" lims:id="631021" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of all which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these presents may concern are required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631022" lims:id="631022" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In testimony whereof, We have caused this Our Proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be affixed to it.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631023" lims:id="631023" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Witness:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631024" lims:id="631024" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved David Johnston, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631025" lims:id="631025" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>AT OUR GOVERNMENT HOUSE, in Our City of Ottawa, this sixteenth day of February in the year of Our Lord two thousand and seventeen and in the sixty-sixth year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631026" lims:id="631026" format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-next="yes" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By command,</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631027" lims:id="631027" format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left" topmarginspacing="8">John Knubley</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:lastAmendedDate="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631028" lims:id="631028" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Convention on Social Security Between Canada and the Republic of Peru</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF PERU,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>hereinafter referred to as the “Parties”,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>RESOLVED to co-operate in the field of social security,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>HAVE DECIDED to conclude a convention for this purpose, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>HAVE AGREED as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Convention:</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>benefit</DefinedTermEn> means, any cash benefit that is provided for in the legislation of a Party and includes any supplement or increase applicable to that cash benefit;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn> means,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>for Canada, the Minister or Ministers responsible for the application of the legislation of Canada specified in Article 2; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>for the Republic of Peru (“Peru”), the Ministry of Labour and Employment Promotion and the Ministry of Economy and Finance;</Text></Provision></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent institution</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>for Canada, the competent authority; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>for Peru, the institution or agency responsible for the application of the legislation referred to in Article 2;</Text></Provision></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>creditable period</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>for Canada, a period of contribution used to acquire the right to a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>; a period during which a disability pension is paid under that Plan; and a period of residence used to acquire the right to a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>for Peru, a period of contribution used to acquire the right to a benefit under the legislation of Peru and includes any period deemed as equivalent to a period of contribution;</Text></Provision></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>legislation</DefinedTermEn> means the laws and regulations and provisions specified in Article 2;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>liaison agency”</DefinedTermEn> means the agency that is responsible for co-ordinating the Convention, exchanging information between the institutions of the Parties, and informing persons concerned of the rights and obligations stemming from this Convention.</Text></Definition></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A term that is not defined in this Article shall have the meaning assigned to it in the applicable legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label><TitleText>Legislative Scope</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall apply to the following legislation:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with respect to Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> and the Regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the Regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>with respect to Peru:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>legislation concerning old age, disability and survivor pensions under the National Pension System (SNP) and the Private Pension Fund System (SPP).</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Convention shall also apply to future laws, regulations and provisions that amend, supplement, consolidate, or supersede the legislation specified in paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>This Convention shall also apply to future laws and regulations and provisions that extend the legislation of a Party to new categories of beneficiaries or to new benefits, unless the Party implementing the changes advises the other Party of its objection not later than three months following the entry into force of those laws and regulations.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label><TitleText>Personal Scope</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties shall apply this Convention to any person who is or who has been subject to the legislation of Canada or Peru, or both, and to any person who derives a right from that person under the legislation of either Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Convention shall not affect benefits obtained by any person in accordance with other treaties that are concluded between one Party and a third State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label><TitleText>Equality of Treatment</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>All persons described in Article 3 shall be treated equally in regard to rights and obligations within the legislation of a Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label><TitleText>Export of Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Convention, a benefit payable under the legislation of a Party to any person described in Article 3, including a benefit paid by virtue of this Convention, shall not be reduced, modified, suspended, cancelled, or withheld by reason only of the fact that the person resides in or is present in the territory of the other Party or in the territory of a third State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Canada shall pay an allowance and a guaranteed income supplement to a person who is outside Canada only to the extent permitted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning the Applicable Legislation</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label><TitleText>General Rules for Employed and Self-Employed Persons</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Subject to Articles 7 to 10:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>An employed person who works in the territory of a Party shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of that Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A self-employed person who resides in the territory of a Party and who works for his or her own account in the territory of the other Party or in the territories of both Parties shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label><TitleText>Special Provisions for Detached Workers</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>An employed person who is subject to the legislation of a Party and who is sent by their employer to work in the territory of the other Party shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party as though that work was performed in its territory. The maximum period of a detachment is 36 months, unless the competent authorities of both Parties consent to an extension.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 8</Label><TitleText>Government Employment</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any provision of this Convention, the provisions regarding social security of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</XRefExternal> of 18 April 1961, and the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Consular Relations</XRefExternal> of 24 April 1963, continue to apply.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A person employed by the government of a Party, who is not covered by the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Consular Relations</XRefExternal>, and who is sent to work in the territory of the other Party shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 9</Label><TitleText>Exceptions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The Parties may, by mutual consent, modify the application of Articles 6 to 8 in the interest of any person or categories of persons.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 10</Label><TitleText>Coverage and Residence under the Legislation of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of calculating a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>If a person is subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during any period of presence or residence in Peru, that period shall be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person; it shall also be considered to be a period of residence in Canada for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with that person and who are not subject to the legislation of Peru by reason of employment or self-employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>If a person is subject to the legislation of Peru during any period of detachment in Canada, that period for that person, and for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with him or her, shall be determined according to the provisions of Canadian legislation.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the application of paragraph 1:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A person shall be considered to be subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during a period of presence or residence in Peru only if that person makes contributions pursuant to the plan concerned during that period by reason of employment or self-employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A person shall be considered to be subject to the legislation of Peru during a period of presence or residence in Canada only if that person makes contributions pursuant to that legislation during that period by reason of employment or self-employment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPTER 1</Label><TitleText>Totalizing</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 11</Label><TitleText>Periods under the Legislation of Canada and Peru</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is not eligible for a benefit due to insufficient creditable periods under the legislation of a Party, that person’s eligibility shall be determined by totalizing these periods and those specified in paragraphs 2 through 4, provided that the periods do not overlap.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>For the purposes of determining eligibility for a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, a creditable period under the legislation of Peru shall be considered as a period of residence in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>For the purposes of determining eligibility for a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, three months in a calendar year which are creditable under the legislation of Peru shall be considered as a calendar year that is creditable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of determining eligibility for an old age benefit under the legislation of Peru:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A calendar year that is a creditable period under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as 12 months that are creditable under the legislation of Peru;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A month that is a creditable period under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> of Canada and that does not overlap with a creditable period under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as a month that is creditable under the legislation of Peru.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of determining eligibility for a disability benefit, survivor’s benefit, or funeral costs under the legislation of Peru, a calendar year that is a creditable period under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as 12 months that are creditable under the legislation of Peru.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>All creditable periods under the legislation of Peru, including those creditable periods completed prior to the date on which the contributor reaches the age of 18, shall be taken into account to determine an applicant’s eligibility to a benefit under the legislation of Canada. However, a benefit shall not be paid unless the deceased or disabled person’s contributory period is at least equivalent to the minimum qualifying period required under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> to establish eligibility to that benefit for that person.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 12</Label><TitleText>Periods under the Regime of a Third State</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is not eligible for a benefit on the basis of the creditable periods under the legislation of the Parties, totalized as provided in Article 11, the eligibility of that person for that benefit shall be determined by totalizing these periods and periods completed under the regime of a third State with which both Parties are bound by social security instruments that provide for the totalizing of periods.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 13</Label><TitleText>Minimum Period to be Totalized</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If the total duration of the creditable periods accumulated under the legislation of a Party is less than one year and if, taking into account only those periods, the right to a benefit does not exist under the legislation of that Party, that Party shall not be required to pay a benefit in respect of those periods. The other Party shall, however, take these creditable periods into consideration to determine whether a person is eligible for the benefit under the legislation of that other Party through the application of Chapter 1.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPTER 2</Label><TitleText>Benefits under the Legislation of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 14</Label><TitleText>Benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is eligible for a pension or allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> based solely on the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, Canada shall calculate the amount of the pension or allowance payable to that person in accordance with the provisions of that Act governing the payment of a partial pension or allowance, based solely on the periods of residence in Canada that may be considered under that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 1 shall also apply to a person outside Canada who would be eligible for a full pension in Canada but who has not resided in Canada for the minimum period required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of a pension outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Canada shall pay an Old Age Security pension to a person who is outside Canada only if that person’s periods of residence, when totalized in accordance with Chapter 1, are at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of a pension outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 15</Label><TitleText>Benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is eligible for a benefit based solely on the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, Canada shall calculate the amount of benefit payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The amount of the earnings-related portion of the benefit shall be determined in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, based solely on the pensionable earnings under that Plan;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The amount of the flat-rate portion of the benefit shall be pro-rated by multiplying:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the benefit determined in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>by</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>the fraction representing the ratio of the periods of contribution to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in relation to the minimum qualifying period required under that Plan to establish eligibility for that benefit. That fraction shall not exceed the value of one.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPTER 3</Label><TitleText>Benefits under the Legislation of Peru</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 16</Label><TitleText>Calculating the Amount of Benefit Payable</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If the conditions for eligibility for a benefit are met under the legislation of Peru without the creditable periods accumulated under the legislation of Canada, Peru shall determine the amount of that benefit based solely on the creditable periods accumulated under its legislation.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>If eligibility for a benefit under the legislation of Peru can be established only through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, Peru shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>calculate the theoretical amount of the benefit which would be paid if the totalized creditable periods had been accumulated under the legislation of Peru alone; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on the basis of the theoretical amount of the benefit calculated in accordance with subparagraph (a), determine the amount of benefit payable by applying the ratio of the length of the creditable periods accumulated under the legislation of Peru to the totalized creditable periods.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Administrative and Miscellaneous Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 17</Label><TitleText>Administrative Agreements</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties shall conclude Administrative Agreements that establish the measures necessary for the application of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Parties shall designate their competent institutions and liaison agencies in the Administrative Agreements.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 18</Label><TitleText>Exchange of Information and Mutual Assistance</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>communicate to each other, to the extent permitted by the laws of each Party, any information necessary for the application of this Convention;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide assistance to one another for the purpose of determining eligibility for, and the amount of, any benefit under this Convention, or under the legislation, as if the matter involved the application of their own legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>communicate to each other, as soon as possible, all information about the measures taken by them for the application of this Convention or about changes in their respective legislation, if these changes affect the application of this Convention.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Parties shall provide the assistance referred to in paragraph 1(b) free of charge, unless otherwise specified in an Administrative Agreement concluded pursuant to Article 17 for the reimbursement of certain types of expenses.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Unless disclosure is required under the laws of a Party, any information about a person which is transmitted in accordance with this Convention from one Party to the other Party is confidential and shall be used only for purposes of implementing this Convention and the legislation to which this Convention applies. Information about a person obtained by the receiving Party shall not be disclosed subsequently to any other person, body or country unless the sending Party is notified and considers it advisable and the information is disclosed only for the same purpose for which it was originally disclosed.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 19</Label><TitleText>Exemption or Reduction of Dues, Fees or Charges</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If one Party’s legislation provides that a person shall be exempt from paying all or part of an administrative fee for issuing a certificate or document required to apply its legislation, the same exemption shall apply to any fee for a certificate or document required to apply the legislation of the other Party. This exemption shall not apply if a medical report is required by the competent institution of a Party solely in support of a claim for a benefit under the legislation of that Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Documents of an official nature required for the application of this Convention shall be exempt from any authentication by diplomatic or consular authorities.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 20</Label><TitleText>Language of Communication</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The Parties may communicate directly with one another in English, French, or Spanish.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 21</Label><TitleText>Submitting an Application, a Notice or an Appeal</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties shall treat applications, notices, and appeals concerning eligibility for, or the amount of, a benefit under the legislation of a Party which should, for the purposes of that legislation, have been submitted within a prescribed period to a competent authority or liaison agency of that Party, but which are submitted within the same period to a competent authority or liaison agency of the other Party, as if they had been submitted to the competent authority or liaison agency of the first Party. The date of submission of applications, notices and appeals to the competent authority or liaison agency of the other Party shall be deemed to be the date of their submission to the competent authority or liaison agency of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The date that an application for a benefit is submitted under the legislation of a Party shall be deemed to be the date of submission of an application for the corresponding benefit under the legislation of the other Party, provided that the applicant at the time of application provides information indicating that creditable periods have been completed under the legislation of the other Party. The preceding sentence shall not apply to an application submitted before the date of entry into force of this Convention or if the applicant requests that the payment of the benefit under the legislation of the other Party be delayed.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Party to which an application, a notice or an appeal has been submitted shall transmit it without delay to the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 22</Label><TitleText>Payment of Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>A Party shall pay benefits under this Convention in a freely convertible currency directly to a beneficiary, or representative authorized under the laws of that Party, who resides outside its territory without any deduction for its administrative expenses.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 23</Label><TitleText>Resolution of Disputes</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties, through their liaison agencies or competent authorities, shall resolve all disputes of an administrative nature that arise in interpreting or applying this Convention in accordance with the spirit and fundamental principles of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Parties shall promptly settle any dispute that is not resolved in accordance with paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Special Provision</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 24</Label><TitleText>Understandings with a Province of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The relevant authority of Peru and a province of Canada may conclude understandings concerning any social security matter within provincial jurisdiction in Canada provided that those understandings are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Transitional and Final Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 25</Label><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties shall take into account any creditable period completed before the date of entry into force of this Convention for the purposes of determining the right to a benefit and the amount of that benefit under this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Convention does not confer the right, under any circumstances, to receive payment of a benefit for a period that precedes the date of entry into force of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Parties shall pay a benefit, other than a lump sum death benefit, in respect of events that precede the date of entry into force of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of Article 7, if a person’s detachment commences prior to the date of entry into force of this Convention, the period of that detachment shall be considered to begin on the date of entry into force of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subject to paragraphs 1 and 2, if a person submitted an application for a benefit under the legislation of a Party and that application was denied prior to the entry into force of this Convention, that person may submit a new application for that benefit and the relevant Party shall determine the person’s eligibility for that benefit according to the terms and conditions of this Convention and the legislation to which this Convention applies.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 26</Label><TitleText>Duration and Denunciation</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall remain in force indefinitely.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A Party may terminate this Convention at any time by providing the other Party with 12 months’ notice in writing through diplomatic channels.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>If this Convention is terminated, any benefit obtained by a person or any concurrent period of detachment shall be maintained in accordance with the provisions of this Convention. This Convention shall continue to have effect in relation to all persons who, prior to its termination, applied for rights, and would have acquired those rights by virtue of this Convention if it had not been terminated.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 27</Label><TitleText>Entry into Force</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Each Party shall notify the other by diplomatic note that it has completed the internal legal procedures necessary for the entry into force of this Convention. This Convention enters into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the last note is received.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Parties may, by mutual agreement, make amendments to this Convention in accordance with the entry into force provisions of paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-next="yes" language-align="yes"><Text>DONE in duplicate at Ottawa, this 10th day of April 2014, in the English, French and Spanish languages, each text being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="50*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="50*" /><tbody><row rowsep="0"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>Candice Bergen</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>For Canada</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>Eda Rives Franchini</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>For the Republic of Peru</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2017-02-16" lims:lastAmendedDate="2017-02-16" lims:fid="631029" lims:id="631029" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Administrative Agreement Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Peru for the Implementation of the Convention on Social Security Between Canada and the Republic of Peru</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>PURSUANT to Article 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru</XRefExternal>, done at Ottawa on 10 April 2014, hereinafter referred to as the “Convention”,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The Parties have agreed as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>In this Administrative Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>Convention</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru</XRefExternal>, done at Ottawa on 10 April 2014.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>Administrative Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Administrative Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Peru for the Implementation of the Convention on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Peru</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Any other term shall have the meaning assigned to it in the Convention.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label><TitleText>Liaison Agencies and Competent Institutions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties designate the following organizations as their liaison agencies:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the International Operations Division, Service Canada, Department of Human Resources and Skills Development, in regard to all provisions except Articles 6 to 9 of the Convention and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Legislative Policy Directorate, Canada Revenue Agency for the application of Articles 6 to 9 of the Convention and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for the Republic of Peru (“Peru”):</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Oficina de Normalización Previsional</XRefExternal> (ONP) for all provisions of the Convention regarding the rights of insured persons of the National Pension System (SNP), except Articles 6 to 9 of the Convention and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Superintendencia de Banca, Seguros y Administradoras Privadas de Fondos de Pensiones</XRefExternal> (SBS), for all provisions of the Convention regarding the supervision of the rights of members of the Private Pension System (SPP), except Articles 6 to 9 of the Convention and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the Ministry of Labour and Employment Promotion for the provisions relating to Articles 6 to 9 of the Convention and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Peru designates the following organizations as its competent institutions:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for Article 6 to 9 of the Convention, the Ministry of Labour and the Promotion of Employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for retirement, disability and survival pensions and, if applicable, burial expenses:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Private Pension Fund Administrators (AFP) for members of the Private Pension System; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Oficina de Normalización Previsional</XRefExternal> (ONP) for persons insured under the National Pension System.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for medical evaluations, the determination of disability and eligibility for a pension, as appropriate and in accordance with its legislation:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Medical Committee of the Private Administrators of Pension Funds (COMAFP), and the Medical Commissions of the Superintendency (COMEC) for members of the Private Pension System;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Medical Commissions of ESSALUD (Health Social Security), Ministry of Health (MINSA), and Private Health Institutions (EPS) are the authorities for the state of incapacity or disability in the National Pension System.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Applicable Legislation</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label><TitleText>Issuing a Certificate of Detachment</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>In the cases set out in Articles 6 to 9 of the Convention, the Party whose legislation applies shall, on request, issue a certificate of fixed duration certifying that, in respect of the work in question, the employed person and that person’s employer or the self-employed person are subject to that legislation. That Party shall send a copy of the certificate to the employed person, that person’s employer, or the self-employed person, and the liaison agency or competent institution of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The consent referred to in Article 7 of the Convention should be requested before the end of the current term of the detachment. If the request for the extension is received after the certificate of detachment expires, the Party that receives the request shall examine the reasons for the delay and, if it determines that the delay is justifiable, shall send the request to the liaison agency or the competent institution of the other Party to obtain consent.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label><TitleText>Processing an Application</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>A Party that receives an application for a benefit under the legislation of the other Party shall promptly send the application to the liaison agency or competent institution of the other Party, and indicate the date of receipt of the application.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Along with the application, a Party shall transmit any documentation available to it that may be necessary for the liaison agency or competent institution of the other Party to establish the applicant’s eligibility for a benefit. If the legislation of a Party requires that the documentation be certified, and if it cannot be exempted under Article 19 of the Convention, the certification by the respective liaison agency or competent institution of the other Party alone shall be accepted.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>A Party shall certify the personal information contained in the application, and shall confirm that the information is corroborated by documentary evidence. Once a Party transmits the certified forms to the liaison agency or competent institution of the other Party, it shall be exempt from sending the documentary evidence. The Parties shall mutually decide on the type of information to which this exemption applies.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>A Party shall, to the extent permitted by law, provide free of charge, to the liaison agency or competent institution of the other Party, available medical examination reports, information and documentation concerning the disability of an applicant or beneficiary.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>In addition to the application and documentation, a Party shall send to the liaison agency or competent institution of the other Party a liaison form which shall indicate, in particular, the creditable periods under the legislation which it applies.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>6</Label><Text>A Party shall determine the applicant’s eligibility and shall notify the liaison agency or competent institution of the other Party of its decision to grant or deny the benefit and the reason for its denial.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Miscellaneous Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label><TitleText>Exchange of Statistics</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The Parties shall exchange statistics on an annual basis regarding the payments that each has made under the Convention. These statistics shall include data on the number of beneficiaries and the total amount of benefits paid, by type of benefit.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label><TitleText>Forms and Detailed Procedures</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties shall decide on the forms and detailed procedures necessary to implement the Convention and this Administrative Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Parties shall use the mutually accepted forms to communicate with each other.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label><TitleText>Entry into Force</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Administrative Agreement shall enter into force on the date of receipt of the second notification by which the Parties notify each other by diplomatic note that they have completed the internal legal procedures necessary for the entry into force of this Administrative Agreement. This Administrative Agreement shall remain in force for the same period as the Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto, have signed this Administrative Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>DONE in duplicate at Ottawa, this 10th day of April 2014, in the English, French and Spanish languages, each version being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="50*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="50*" /><tbody><row rowsep="0"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>Candice Bergen</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>For the Government of Canada</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>Eda Rives Franchini</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>For the Government of the Republic of Peru</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>