<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2021-07-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2021-07-26" lims:current-date="2025-07-24" lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313174" lims:id="1313174" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313175" lims:id="1313175"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2021-41</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>8</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313176" lims:id="1313176"><OtherAuthority>OTHER THAN STATUTORY AUTHORITY</OtherAuthority></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313177" lims:id="1313177">Proclamation Announcing the Appointment of the Governor General</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313178" lims:id="1313178"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313179" lims:id="1313179" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>By Her Excellency the Right Honourable Mary May Simon, Chancellor and Principal Companion of the Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of the Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of the Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief in and over Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313180" lims:id="1313180" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="1pc"><Text>TO ALL TO WHOM these Presents shall come,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313181" lims:id="1313181" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="1pc"><Text>GREETING:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313182" lims:id="1313182" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="1pc"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313183" lims:id="1313183" level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">A Proclamation</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313184" lims:id="1313184" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="1pc"><Text>WHEREAS HER MAJESTY QUEEN ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by Commission under the Great Seal of Canada bearing date the twenty-first day of July, in the year of Our Lord two thousand and twenty-one, was graciously pleased to appoint me to be, during the Royal Pleasure, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief in and over Canada, and further, in and by that Commission, authorized, empowered and commanded me to exercise and perform all and singular the powers and directions contained in Letters Patent under the Great Seal of Canada, bearing date the eighth day of September in the year of Our Lord one thousand nine hundred and forty-seven constituting the Office of Governor General and Commander-in-Chief in and over Canada and in any other Letters Patent adding to, amending or substituted for the same.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313185" lims:id="1313185" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>AND WHEREAS, in accordance with these Letters Patent, I have caused the Commission under the Great Seal of Canada appointing me to be, during the Royal Pleasure, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief in and over Canada to be read and published with all due solemnity in the presence of the Chief Justice or other Judge of the Supreme Court of Canada and of Members of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada, and have taken the Oaths prescribed by those Letters Patent.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313186" lims:id="1313186" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, KNOW YOU that I have thought fit to issue this Proclamation in order to make known Her Majesty’s appointment and to make known that I have entered upon the duties of the Office of Governor General and Commander-in-Chief in and over Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313187" lims:id="1313187" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>AND I DO HEREBY require and command that all and singular Her Majesty’s Officers and Ministers in Canada do continue in the execution of their several and respective offices, places and employments, and that Her Majesty’s loving subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern do take notice and govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313188" lims:id="1313188" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>GIVEN under my Hand and Seal of Office at Ottawa, this twenty-sixth day of July in the year of Our Lord two thousand and twenty-one and in the seventieth year of Her Majesty’s Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-07-26" lims:enacted-date="2021-07-26" lims:fid="1313189" lims:id="1313189" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="1pc"><SignatureBlock width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="left">MARY MAY SIMON</SignatureName><SignatureName justification="left" topmarginspacing="1pc">[Privy seal]</SignatureName></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order></Regulation>