<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2014-06-03" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-06-03" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627555" lims:id="627555" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627556" lims:id="627556"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2014-56</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>2</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627558" lims:id="627558"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">AN ACT TO IMPLEMENT CONVENTIONS FOR THE AVOIDANCE OF DOUBLE TAXATION WITH RESPECT TO INCOME TAX BETWEEN CANADA AND FRANCE, CANADA AND BELGIUM AND CANADA AND ISRAEL</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627559" lims:id="627559">Proclamation Giving Notice that the Protocol Amending the Convention between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital signed on May 2, 1975, as amended by the Protocol signed on January 16, 1987 and as further amended by the Protocol signed on November 30, 1995 Came into Force on December 27, 2013</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627560" lims:id="627560"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627561" lims:id="627561" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>DAVID JOHNSTON</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627562" lims:id="627562" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627563" lims:id="627563" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627564" lims:id="627564" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627565" lims:id="627565" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>TO ALL TO WHOM these presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627566" lims:id="627566" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627567" lims:id="627567" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">WILLIAM PENTNEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627568" lims:id="627568" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627569" lims:id="627569" level="1"><TitleText>A Proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627570" lims:id="627570" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2014-592 of May 15, 2014, the Governor in Council, pursuant to subsection 10(4) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to implement conventions for the avoidance of double taxation with respect to income tax between Canada and France, Canada and Belgium and Canada and Israel</XRefExternal>, directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice of the entry into force on December 27, 2013 of the February 2, 2010 supplementary agreement, entitled Protocol Amending the Convention between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital signed on May 2, 1975, as amended by the Protocol signed on January 16, 1987 and as further amended by the Protocol signed November 30, 1995;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627571" lims:id="627571" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our proclamation give notice of the entry into force on December 27, 2013 of the attached February 2, 2010 supplementary agreement, entitled Protocol Amending the Convention between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital signed on May 2, 1975, as amended by the Protocol signed on January 16, 1987 and as further amended by the Protocol signed November 30, 1995.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627572" lims:id="627572" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of all which Our loving subjects and all others whom these presents may concern are required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627573" lims:id="627573" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN TESTIMONY WHEREOF, We have caused this Our proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be affixed to it. WITNESS: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved David Johnston, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627574" lims:id="627574" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>AT OUR GOVERNMENT HOUSE, in Our City of Ottawa, this third day of June in the year of Our Lord two thousand and fourteen and in the sixty-third year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627575" lims:id="627575" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627576" lims:id="627576" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="right">JOHN KNUBLEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627577" lims:id="627577" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Protocol Amending the Convention Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with Respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital Signed on May 2, 1975, as Amended by the Protocol Signed on January 16, 1987 and as Further Amended by the Protocol Signed November 30, 1995</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">THE GOVERNMENT OF THE FRENCH REPUBLIC,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DESIRING</Emphasis> to conclude a Protocol to amend further the Convention between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic for the avoidance of double taxation and the prevention of fiscal evasion with respect to taxes on income and on capital, signed on May 2, 1975 as amended by the Protocol signed on January 16, 1987 and as further amended by the Protocol signed November 30, 1995 (hereinafter referred to as “the Convention”),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED</Emphasis> as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE I</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text><Emphasis style="regular">Paragraphs 1 and 2 of Article 26 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Emphasis></Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>“1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall exchange such information as is foreseeably relevant for carrying out the provisions of this Convention or to the administration or enforcement of the domestic laws concerning taxes of every kind and description imposed on behalf of the Contracting States, insofar as the taxation thereunder is not contrary to the Convention. The exchange of information is not restricted by Articles 1 and 2.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any information received under paragraph 1 by a Contracting State shall be treated as secret in the same manner as information obtained under the domestic laws of that State and shall be disclosed only to persons or authorities (including courts and administrative bodies) concerned with the assessment or collection of, the enforcement or the prosecution in respect of, the determination of appeals in relation to taxes, or the oversight of the above. Such persons or authorities shall use the information only for such purposes. They may disclose the information in public court proceedings or in judicial decisions.”</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>In no case shall the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 be construed so as to impose on a Contracting State the obligation:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>a)</Label><Text>to carry out administrative measures at variance with the laws and the administrative practice of that or of the other Contracting State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>b)</Label><Text>to supply information that is not obtainable under the laws or in the normal course of the administration of that or of the other Contracting State; or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>c)</Label><Text>to supply information that would disclose any trade, business, industrial, commercial or professional secret or trade process, or information, the disclosure of which would be contrary to public policy (<Language xml:lang="fr">ordre public</Language>).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>If information is requested by a Contracting State in accordance with this Article, the other Contracting State shall use its information gathering measures to obtain the requested information, even though the other State may not need such information for its own tax purposes. The obligation contained in the preceding sentence is subject to the limitations of paragraph 3 but in no case shall such limitations be construed to permit a Contracting State to decline to supply information solely because it has no domestic interest in such information.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>In no case shall the provisions of paragraph 3 be construed to permit a Contracting State to decline to supply information solely because the information is held by a bank, other financial institution, nominee or person acting in an agency or fiduciary capacity or because the information relates to ownership interests in a person.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE II</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" type="amending"><Text><Emphasis style="regular">Paragraphs 1 and 2 of Article 28 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Emphasis></Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>“1</Label><Text>This Convention shall apply, with respect to France, to the European and Overseas Departments (Guadeloupe, Guyane, Martinique and Réunion) of the French Republic, to the Territorial Authority of Saint-Pierre-et-Miquelon as well as to New Caledonia.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Convention may be extended, either in its entirety or with any necessary modifications, to any other Overseas Territory of the French Republic which imposes taxes substantially similar in character to those to which the Convention applies. Any such extension shall take effect from such date and subject to such modifications and conditions, including conditions as to termination, as may be specified and agreed between the Contracting States in notes to be exchanged through diplomatic channels or in any other manner in accordance with their constitutional procedures.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE III</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Each Contracting State shall notify to the other, through diplomatic channel, of the completion of the internal procedures required for the bringing into force of this Protocol. The Protocol shall enter into force on the day on which the later of these notifications is received and its provisions shall apply:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>a)</Label><Text>in Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in respect of tax withheld at source, for amounts paid or credited to non-residents on or after the first day of January in the calendar year following that in which the Protocol enters into force; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in respect of other taxes, for any taxation year beginning on or after the first day of January in the calendar year following that in which the Protocol enters into force;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>b)</Label><Text>in France:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in respect of the withholding taxes, for any amount paid on or after the first day of January in the calendar year following that in which the Protocol enters into force;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in respect of taxes on income which are not levied by way of withholding tax, to income relating to any calendar year or relating to any accounting period beginning on or after the first day of January in the calendar year following that in which the Protocol enters into force; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in respect of other taxes, to taxable events occurring on or after the first day of January in the calendar year following that in which the Protocol enters into force.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE IV</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Protocol shall remain in force as long as the Convention remains in force.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Contracting States shall be empowered, after the entry into force of the Protocol, to publish the text of the Convention as amended by the Protocols of January 16, 1987 and November 30, 1995 and by this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis> the undersigned, duly authorised thereto by their respective governments, have signed this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in duplicate at Paris, this 2nd day of February 2010, in the English and French languages, both texts being equally authoritative.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.98*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.02*" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>MARC LORTIE</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no" topmarginspacing="2"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>PHILIPPE GOMES</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no" topmarginspacing="2"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE FRENCH REPUBLIC</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>