<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2014-02-13" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-02-13" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627095" lims:id="627095" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627096" lims:id="627096"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2014-15</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627098" lims:id="627098"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627099" lims:id="627099">Proclamation Giving Notice that the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria and the Administrative Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Bulgaria for the Implementation of the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria are in force as of March 1, 2014</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627100" lims:id="627100"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627101" lims:id="627101" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>PATRICIA JATON</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627102" lims:id="627102" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="0" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627103" lims:id="627103" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627104" lims:id="627104" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627105" lims:id="627105" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>To all to whom these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627106" lims:id="627106" justification="right" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627107" lims:id="627107" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">WILLIAM PENTNEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627108" lims:id="627108" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627109" lims:id="627109" level="1"><TitleText>A Proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627110" lims:id="627110" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas by Order in Council P.C. 2013-0280 of March 7, 2013, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article 30 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</XRefExternal> and Article 8 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Administrative Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Bulgaria for the Implementation of the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</XRefExternal>, signed at Ottawa, on October 5, 2012, the Agreement and the Administrative Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the Parties have exchanged written notifications that they have complied with all requirements for the entry into force of the Agreements;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627111" lims:id="627111" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Order in Council was laid before the House of Commons on March 19, 2013 and the Senate on March 20, 2013 as required under the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627112" lims:id="627112" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order had been laid before both Houses of Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627113" lims:id="627113" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it had been laid before Parliament, being May 23, 2013;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627114" lims:id="627114" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the exchange of the written notices was completed in November 2013;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627115" lims:id="627115" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Agreements shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the Parties have exchanged written notifications that they have complied with all requirements for the entry into force of the Agreements, being March 1, 2014;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627116" lims:id="627116" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2014-32 of January 28, 2014, the Governor in Council, pursuant to subsection 41(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, directed that a proclamation be issued giving notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Administrative Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Bulgaria for the Implementation of the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</XRefExternal> are in force as of March 1, 2014;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627117" lims:id="627117" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our proclamation give notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Administrative Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Bulgaria for the Implementation of the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</XRefExternal>, copies of which are annexed to this proclamation, are in force as of March 1, 2014.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627118" lims:id="627118" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of all which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these presents may concern are required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627119" lims:id="627119" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In testimony whereof, We have caused this Our proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. WITNESS: PATRICIA JATON, Deputy of Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved David Johnston, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627120" lims:id="627120" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>AT OTTAWA, this thirteenth day of February in the year of Our Lord two thousand and fourteen and in the sixty-third year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627121" lims:id="627121" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627122" lims:id="627122" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="right">JOHN KNUBLEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General Of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627123" lims:id="627123" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Agreement on Social Security Between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF BULGARIA (“BULGARIA”)</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>hereinafter referred to as the “Parties”,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">RESOLVED</Emphasis> to co-operate in the field of social security,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE DECIDED</Emphasis> to conclude an agreement for this purpose, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED</Emphasis> as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART I</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Definitions</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn> means, for Canada, the Minister or Ministers responsible for the application of the legislation of Canada specified in Article 2(1)(a); and, for Bulgaria, the Minister of Labour and Social Policy;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent institution</DefinedTermEn> means, for Canada, the competent authority; and, for Bulgaria, the institutions responsible for the application of the legislation specified in Article 2(1)(b) of this Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>compliance verification</DefinedTermEn> means, for a Party, the verification that the eligibility for and the payment of pensions are in conformity with the legislation of the relevant Party;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>creditable period</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>for Canada, a period of contribution used to acquire the right to a pension under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>; a period during which a disability pension is paid under that Plan; and a period of residence used to acquire the right to a pension under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>; and,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>for Bulgaria, any period of insurance and any other period recognized as equivalent to a period of insurance under the legislation of Bulgaria;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(e)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>legislation</DefinedTermEn> means, for a Party, the laws and regulations specified in Article 2 of this Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(f)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>pension</DefinedTermEn> means, for a Party, any cash benefit, pension or allowance provided for in the legislation of that Party and includes any supplements or increases applicable to that cash benefit, pension or allowance;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(g)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>residence</DefinedTermEn> means, for Canada, the meaning assigned to it in the applicable laws and regulations and, for Bulgaria, a person’s habitual place of residence.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any term not defined in this Article has the meaning assigned to it in the applicable legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Legislative Scope</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall apply to the following legislation:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with respect to Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Ac</XRefExternal>t and the Regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the Regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>with respect to Bulgaria, the Social Insurance Code and regulations regarding pensions from the State Social Insurance for periods of insurance and age, invalidity due to general disease and resulting survivors’ pensions, as well as the relevant contributions.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 3, this Agreement shall also apply to laws and regulations which amend, supplement, consolidate or supersede the legislation specified in paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>This Agreement shall also apply to laws and regulations which extend the legislation of a Party to new categories of beneficiaries or to new pensions or benefits unless the Party implementing the changes communicates to the other Party, within three months of the entry into force of those laws and regulations, that they shall not apply.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Personal Scope</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Agreement shall apply to any person who is or who has been subject to the legislation of Canada or Bulgaria or both Parties and to persons who derive rights from that person within the meaning of the applicable legislation of either Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Equality of Treatment</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Persons described in Article 3 shall be subject to the obligations of the legislation of the other Party and shall be eligible for the pensions of that legislation under the same conditions as citizens of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Export of Pensions</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement, pensions payable under the legislation of a Party to any person described in Article 3, including pensions acquired by virtue of this Agreement, shall not be reduced, modified, suspended or cancelled by reason only of the fact that the person resides in or is present in the territory of the other Party. A person who is entitled to a pension shall continue to be entitled to that pension when that person resides in or is present in the territory of a third state.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>As regards Canada, an allowance and a guaranteed income supplement shall be payable to a person who is outside Canada only to the extent permitted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART II</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Applicable Legislation</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">General Rules for Employed and Self-Employed Persons</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Subject to Articles 7 to 11:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>An employed person who works in the territory of a Party shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of that Party;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A self-employed person who resides in the territory of a Party and who works for his or her own account in the territory of the other Party or in the territories of both Parties shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Detachments</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>An employed person who is subject to the legislation of a Party and who is sent by their employer to work in the territory of the other Party shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party as though that work was performed in its territory. A detachment shall not exceed 60 months, unless the designated competent institutions of both Parties consent to an extension.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 8</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Crews of Ships</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>A person who is subject to the legislation of both Parties in respect of employment as a member of the crew of a ship shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of Canada if that person resides in the territory of Canada and only to the legislation of Bulgaria if the employer’s registered office or place of business is in the territory of Bulgaria. In any other case the competent authorities or the designated competent institutions of both Parties shall determine, by mutual consent, the legislation applicable to the person concerned.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 9</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Staff of Diplomatic Missions and Consular Offices</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any provision of this Agreement, the provisions regarding social security of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</XRefExternal> of 18 April 1961 and the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Consular Relations</XRefExternal> of 24 April 1963 shall continue to apply.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A person who resides in the territory of a Party and who is locally engaged by a diplomatic mission or a consular office of the other Party shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 10</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Civil Service and Government Employment</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Subject to Article 9, a person employed in the government or civil service of a Party shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of that Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 11</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Exceptions</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent authorities or designated competent institutions of the Parties may, by mutual consent, modify the application of the provisions of Articles 6 to 10 with respect to any person or categories of persons.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 12</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Coverage and Residence under the Legislation of Canada</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of calculating pensions under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>If a person is subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during any period of presence or residence in Bulgaria, that period shall be considered to be a period of residence in Canada for that person; it shall also be considered to be a period of residence in Canada for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with that person and who are not subject to the legislation of Bulgaria by reason of employment or self-employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>If a person is subject to the legislation of Bulgaria during any period of presence or residence in Canada, that period for that person, and for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with him or her, shall be determined according to the provisions of the legislation of Canada.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the application of paragraph 1:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A person shall be considered to be subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during a period of presence or residence in Bulgaria only if that person makes contributions pursuant to the plan concerned during that period by reason of employment or self-employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A person shall be considered to be subject to the legislation of Bulgaria during a period of presence or residence in Canada only if that person is subject to compulsory insurance pursuant to that legislation during that period by reason of employment or self-employment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART III</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Pensions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">Chapter 1</Emphasis></Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Totalizing</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 13</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Periods under the Legislation of Canada and Bulgaria</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is not eligible for a pension due to insufficient creditable periods under the legislation of a Party, that person’s eligibility shall be determined by totalizing these periods and those specified in paragraphs 2 through 5, provided that the periods do not overlap.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>To determine eligibility for:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A pension under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> of Canada, a creditable period under the legislation of Bulgaria shall be considered as a period of residence in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A pension under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, a calendar year with at least three months or 90 days which are creditable periods under the legislation of Bulgaria shall be considered as a year which is creditable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>To determine eligibility for old age, early retirement, or resulting survivor pensions under the legislation of Bulgaria:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A calendar year which is a creditable period under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as one year which is creditable under the legislation of Bulgaria;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A creditable period under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> of Canada and which does not overlap with a creditable period under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as a creditable period under the legislation of Bulgaria.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>To determine eligibility for a disability pension or survivor pension derived from the right to a disability pension under the legislation of Bulgaria, a calendar year which is a creditable period under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as a year which is creditable under the legislation of Bulgaria.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>If one Party’s legislation provides that a period is creditable for pension eligibility only when that period is completed in a specific activity or occupation; then that Party’s competent institution shall consider periods completed under the legislation of the other Party only when those periods are completed in that specific activity or occupation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 14</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Periods Completed in a Third State</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is not eligible for a pension on the basis of the creditable periods under the legislation of the Parties, totalized in accordance with Article 13, the eligibility of that person for that pension shall be determined by totalizing these periods and periods completed under the program of a third State with which both Parties are bound by bilateral social security instruments which provide for the totalizing of periods.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 15</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Minimum Period to be Totalized</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If the total duration of the creditable periods accumulated under the legislation of a Party is less than one year and if, taking into account only those periods, the right to a pension does not exist under the legislation of that Party, the competent institution of that Party shall not be required to pay a pension in respect of those periods. These creditable periods shall, however, be taken into consideration by the competent institution of the other Party to determine whether a person is eligible for the pension under the legislation of that Party through the application of Chapter 1.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">Chapter 2</Emphasis></Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Pensions under the Legislation of Canada</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 16</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Pensions under the Old Age Security Act</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is eligible for a pension or allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> based solely on the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of the pension or allowance payable to that person in accordance with the provisions of that Act governing the payment of a partial pension or allowance, based solely on the periods of residence in Canada which may be considered under that Act and this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 1 shall also apply to a person outside Canada who would be eligible for a full pension in Canada but who has not resided in Canada for the minimum period required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of a pension outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>A person who is outside of Canada shall be paid an Old age Security Pension only if that person’s periods of residence, when totalized in accordance with Chapter 1, are at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of a pension outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 17</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Pensions under the Canada Pension Plan</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is eligible for a pension solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of pension payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount of the earnings-related portion of the pension shall be determined in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, based solely on the pensionable earnings under that Plan;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the pension shall be pro-rated by multiplying:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the pension determined in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>by</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>the fraction representing the ratio of the periods of contribution to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in relation to the minimum qualifying period required under that Plan to establish eligibility for that pension. That fraction shall not exceed the value of one.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">Chapter 3</Emphasis></Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Pensions under the Legislation of Bulgaria</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 18</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Calculating the Pension Payable</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is eligible for a pension solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, the competent institution of Bulgaria shall calculate the amount of pension payable according to the Bulgarian legislation only on the basis of Bulgarian creditable periods and according to the income on which insurance contributions have been paid during these periods.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>When determining the amount of an invalidity pension, the insurance period recognized for the time between the occurrence of invalidity and the date of acquiring the right to an old age pension under the Bulgarian legislation shall be reduced by the length of the periods of contribution completed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> after the date of occurrence of invalidity.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART IV</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Administrative and Miscellaneous Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 19</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Administrative Instruments</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The Parties shall conclude administrative agreements or arrangements which establish the measures necessary for the application of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 20</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Exchange of Information and Mutual Assistance</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities and the competent institutions responsible for the application of this Agreement shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>To the extent permitted by the legislation which they administer, communicate to each other any information necessary for the application of this Agreement and the legislation to which this Agreement applies, including the exchange of information necessary for the purposes of compliance verification activities and debt recovery means referred to in Article 21 of this Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Provide assistance to one another for the application and administration of this Agreement as if the matter involved the application of their own legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Communicate to each other, as soon as possible, all information about the measures taken by them for the application of this Agreement or about changes in the respective legislation of the Parties when these changes affect the application of this Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The assistance referred to in sub-paragraph 1 (b) shall be provided free of charge, subject to any provision contained in an administrative agreement or arrangement concluded pursuant to Article 19 for the reimbursement of certain types of expenses.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Unless disclosure is required under the laws of a Party, any information about a person which is transmitted in accordance with this Agreement from a Party to the other Party is confidential and shall be used only for purposes of the application of this Agreement and the legislation to which this Agreement applies. Information about a person obtained by the receiving Party shall not be disclosed subsequently to any other person, body or country unless the sending Party is notified and considers it advisable and the information is disclosed only for the same purpose for which it was originally disclosed.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 21</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Compliance Verification and Debt Recovery</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Where by virtue of this Agreement a Party pays a pension to a person, the competent authority or competent institution of that Party may undertake compliance verification activities.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Compliance verification and debt recovery shall be carried out in accordance with an administrative agreement or arrangement concluded pursuant to Article 19 of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>If a competent authority or competent institution of a Party determines that a person received an overpayment, that Party is entitled to recover that overpayment and may use any means existing under the laws of that Party to recover that overpayment.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 22</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Exemption or Reduction of Dues, Fees or Charges</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If one Party’s laws and regulations provide that a person shall be exempt from paying all or part of a legal, consular or administrative fee for issuing a certificate or document required to apply its legislation, the same exemption shall apply to any fee for a certificate or document required to apply the legislation of the other Party. This exemption shall not apply if a medical report is required by the competent institution of a Party solely in support of a claim for a pension under the legislation of that Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Documents of an official nature required to apply this Agreement shall be exempt from any authentication by diplomatic or consular authorities.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 23</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Language of Communication</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent authorities and competent institutions of the Parties may communicate directly with one another in any official language of either Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 24</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Submitting a Claim, Notice or Appeal</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>A claim, notice or appeal regarding eligibility for a pension, or, the amount of, a pension, under the legislation of a Party which should, for the purposes of that legislation, have been submitted within a prescribed period to a competent authority or competent institution of that Party, but which is submitted within the same period to a competent authority or competent institution of the other Party, shall be treated as if it had been submitted to the competent authority or institution of the first Party. The date of submission of a claim, notice or appeal to the competent authority or institution of the other Party shall be deemed to be the date of its submission to the competent authority or institution of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The date that a claim for a pension is submitted under the legislation of a Party is deemed to be the date of submission of a claim for the corresponding pension under the legislation of the other Party, provided that the applicant at the time of application provides information indicating that creditable periods have been completed under the legislation of the other Party. This paragraph shall not apply if a claim is submitted before the date of entry into force of this Agreement or if the applicant requests that the claim to the pension under the legislation of the other Party be delayed.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The competent authority or institution of a Party to which a claim, notice or appeal has been submitted shall transmit it without delay to the competent authority or institution of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 25</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Payment of Pensions</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>A Party shall pay pensions under this Agreement to a beneficiary who resides outside its territory in a freely convertible currency according to its legislation.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A Party shall pay pensions under this Agreement directly to a beneficiary without any deduction for its administrative expenses.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 26</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Resolution of Disputes</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Parties shall resolve, to the extent possible, any disputes which arise in interpreting or applying this Agreement in accordance with the spirit and fundamental principles of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any dispute which has not been resolved in accordance with paragraph 1 shall be promptly settled by negotiations between the Parties.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 27</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Understandings with a Province of Canada</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The relevant authority of Bulgaria and a province of Canada may conclude understandings concerning any social security matter within provincial jurisdiction in Canada provided that those understandings are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART V</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Transitional and Final Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 28</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Transitional Provisions</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any creditable period completed before the date of entry into force of this Agreement shall be taken into account for the purposes of determining the right to a pension under this Agreement and its amount.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Agreement does not confer a right to receive payment of a pension for a period preceding the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 2, a pension, other than a lump sum pension, shall be paid under this Agreement in respect of events which precede the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of Article 7, if a person’s detachment precedes the entry into force of this Agreement, the period of the detachment is considered to begin on the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 29</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Duration and Termination</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall remain in force indefinitely. It may be terminated at any time by either Party with 12 months’ notice in writing through diplomatic channels to the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the event that this Agreement is terminated, any right acquired by a person in accordance with its provisions shall be maintained. This Agreement shall continue to have effect in relation to all persons who, prior to its termination, had applied for rights, and would have acquired those rights by virtue of this Agreement, had it not been terminated.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 30</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Entry into Force</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the Parties exchange diplomatic notes confirming that they have fulfilled all of the requirements for the entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis>, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in duplicate at Ottawa, this 5th day of October 2012, in the English, French and Bulgarian languages, each text being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="4"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="50*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="50*" /><tbody><row rowsep="0"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">DIANE FINLEY<Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">TOTYU MLADENOV<Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE REPUBLIC OF BULGARIA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2014-02-13" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-02-13" lims:fid="627124" lims:id="627124" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Administrative Agreement Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Republic of Bulgaria for the Implementation of the Agreement on Social Security Between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">PURSUANT</Emphasis> to Article 19 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</XRefExternal>, done at Ottawa on 5 October, 2012, the Parties:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED</Emphasis> on the following:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 1</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>In this Administrative Agreement, <DefinedTermEn>Agreement on Social Security</DefinedTermEn> means the Agreement on <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Bulgaria</XRefExternal>, done at Ottawa on 5 October, 2012.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Administrative Agreement, <DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn> means the Department of Human Resources and Skills Development of Canada, the Canada Revenue Agency, and the Minister of Labour and Social Policy of Bulgaria.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Any other term shall have the meaning assigned to it in the Agreement on Social Security or the applicable legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 2</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Liaison Agencies</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities designate the following organizations as their liaison agencies:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the International Operations Division, Service Canada, Department of Human Resources and Skills Development for all matters except the application of Articles 6 to 11 of the Agreement on Social Security and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Legislative Policy Directorate, Canada Revenue Agency for the application of Articles 6 to 11 of the Agreement on Social Security and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for Bulgaria:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>The National Social Insurance Institute for all matters except the application of Part II of the Agreement on Social Security and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>The National Revenue Agency for the application of Articles 6 to 11 of the Agreement on Social Security and Article 3 of this Administrative Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The objective of the liaison agencies is to facilitate the application of the Agreement on Social Security and to ensure that necessary measures are taken to ensure efficiency and administrative simplicity.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 3</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Coverage for Employed and Self-Employed Persons</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>In the cases set out in Article 6(b), Article 7, Article 8 and Article 11 of the Agreement on Social Security, the responsible liaison agency whose legislation is applicable shall, on request, issue a certificate of fixed duration certifying that, in respect of the work in question, the employed person and that person’s employer or the self-employed person are subject to that legislation. The employed person as well as that person’s employer or the self-employed person and the liaison agency shall receive a copy of the certificate from the issuing liaison agency.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A certificate confirming the applicable legislation shall be issued for each individual period of detachment. The total period of detachment shall not exceed 60 months unless it is extended under Article 7 of the Agreement on Social Security.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The liaison agency of a Party which issues a certificate confirming the applicable legislation shall send a copy of that certificate to the liaison agency of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 4</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Processing a Claim</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a liaison agency receives a claim for a pension under the legislation applied by the other liaison agency, it shall, without delay, send the claim to the other liaison agency, and indicate the date on which the claim was received.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Along with the claim, the liaison agency shall transmit any documentation available to it which may be necessary for the other liaison agency to establish the claimant’s eligibility for a pension.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The liaison agency shall certify the personal information regarding an individual contained in the claim and shall confirm that the information is corroborated by documentary evidence. Once the liaison agency transmits the certified form to the other liaison agency, it is exempt from sending the documentary evidence. The liaison agencies shall mutually decide on the type of information to which this applies.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>A liaison agency shall, to the extent permitted by law, provide to the other liaison agency the available medical information and documentation concerning the disability of a claimant or beneficiary.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>In addition to the claim and documentation referred to in paragraphs 1, 2, 3, and 4, the liaison agency initiating the process shall send to the other liaison agency a liaison form which indicates, in particular, the creditable periods under the legislation which it applies.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>6</Label><Text>The liaison agency responsible for adjudicating a claim shall determine the claimant’s eligibility and shall notify both the claimant and the other liaison agency of its decision to grant the pension. This notification shall include information regarding the amount of the pension, the method of payment of the pension, the effective date of payment and any retroactive payment that may be granted.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>7</Label><Text>The liaison agency responsible for adjudicating a claim shall notify both the claimant and the other liaison agency of its decision to deny a pension, the reason for the denial of the pension, the claimant’s right to appeal and describe how the claimant may exercise the right to appeal.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 5</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Medical Examinations</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a medical examination is required by a liaison agency for a claimant or a beneficiary who resides in the territory of the country where the other liaison agency is situated, that liaison agency, at the request of the first liaison agency, shall arrange this examination according to the rules applied by the liaison agency making the arrangements. The liaison agency which requests the medical examination shall pay for the examination.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>On receipt of a detailed annual statement of the costs incurred, to be issued by 1 January of each year, each liaison agency shall, by 31 March of the same year, reimburse the other liaison agency for the amounts due as a result of applying the provisions of paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>A liaison agency may refuse to make arrangements for additional medical examinations if the other liaison agency does not comply with paragraph 2.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 6</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Exchange of Statistics</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent institutions shall exchange statistics on an annual basis regarding the payments which each has made under the Agreement on Social Security. These statistics shall include data on the number of beneficiaries and the total amount of pensions paid, by type of pension.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 7</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Forms and Detailed Procedures</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The liaison agencies shall mutually agree on the forms and the details of the procedures necessary to implement the Agreement on Social Security and this Administrative Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A liaison agency may refuse to accept information from, or provide information to, the other liaison agency if that other liaison agency does not request or provide information using the forms that the liaison agencies have mutually decided on.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 8</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Entry into Force</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Administrative Agreement shall enter into force on the date of entry into force of the Agreement on Social Security and shall terminate upon termination of the Agreement on Social Security.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis>, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Administrative Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in duplicate at Ottawa, this 5th day of October 2012, in the English, French and Bulgarian languages, each text being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="4"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="50*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="50*" /><tbody><row rowsep="0"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">DIANE FINLEY<Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">TOTYU MLADENOV<Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR GOVERNENMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF BULGARIA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>