<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2025-07-24" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611173" lims:id="611173" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611174" lims:id="611174"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2004-34</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2004</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611176" lims:id="611176"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611177" lims:id="611177">Proclamation Giving Notice that the Agreement on Social Security Between Canada and the Kingdom of the Netherlands will be in force on April 1, 2004</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611178" lims:id="611178"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611179" lims:id="611179" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ADRIENNE CLARKSON</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611180" lims:id="611180" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="0" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611181" lims:id="611181" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611182" lims:id="611182" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Elizabeth the Second, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611183" lims:id="611183" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>To All To Whom these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611184" lims:id="611184" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611185" lims:id="611185" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="16 pc"><SignatureName justification="left">MORRIS ROSENBERG</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611186" lims:id="611186" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>A Proclamation</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611187" lims:id="611187" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2001-1650 of September 20, 2001, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article XXX of the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of the Netherlands, signed on June 27, 2001, the Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month after the date of the last notification between the parties of the completion of their respective requirements for the entry into force of the Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611188" lims:id="611188" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas that Order in Council was laid before Parliament on October 4, 2001;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611189" lims:id="611189" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order had been laid before Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611190" lims:id="611190" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it had been laid before Parliament, being December 4, 2001;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611191" lims:id="611191" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the completion of the requirements for the entry into force of the Agreement occurred on December 5, 2003;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611192" lims:id="611192" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the final day of the month in which the instruments of ratification are exchanged, being April 1, 2004;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611193" lims:id="611193" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2004-235 of March 22, 2004, the Governor in Council directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice that the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of the Netherlands shall enter into force on April 1, 2004;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611194" lims:id="611194" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now Know You that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our Proclamation give notice that the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of the Netherlands, signed on June 27, 2001, a copy of which is annexed hereto, shall enter into force on April 1, 2004.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611195" lims:id="611195" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of All Which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611196" lims:id="611196" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Testimony Whereof, We have caused this Our Proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. Witness: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Adrienne Clarkson, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611197" lims:id="611197" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>At Our Government House, in Our City of Ottawa, this twenty-sixth day of March in the year of Our Lord two thousand and four and in the fifty-third year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611198" lims:id="611198" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611199" lims:id="611199" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="16 pc"><SignatureName justification="right">JEAN-CLAUDE VILLIARD</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611200" lims:id="611200" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Agreement on Social Security Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">The Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, hereinafter referred to as “the parties”,</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">Resolved to strengthen further the relations between their two countries in the field of social security, and</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">Taking note of changes to their respective social security legislation since the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of the Netherlands was signed at The Hague on 26 February 1987,</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">Have agreed as follows:</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART I</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE I</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Definitions</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purpose of this Agreement:</Text><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>benefit</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards a Party, any cash benefit, pension or allowance for which provision is made in the legislation of that Party and includes any supplements or increases applicable to such a cash benefit, pension or allowance by virtue of the legislation specified in Article II;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards a Party, the Minister or Ministers responsible for the administration of the legislation specified in Article II with respect to that Party;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent institution</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, the competent authority; and, as regards the Netherlands, the institution charged with the implementation of the legislation specified in Article II, which is competent under the applicable legislation;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>creditable period</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards a Party, a period of contributions, insurance, employment or residence used to acquire the right to a benefit under the legislation of that Party;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>employed person</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is employed by an employer as well as any person who is deemed equivalent to an employed person by the applicable legislation;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>legislation</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards a Party, the legislation specified in Article II with respect to that Party;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>national</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, a Canadian citizen; and, as regards the Netherlands, a person of Netherlands nationality;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>previous Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of the Netherlands, signed at The Hague on 26 February 1987, as amended by the Supplementary Agreement Amending the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of the Netherlands, signed at Ottawa on 26 July 1989;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>self-employed person</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is gainfully occupied for his or her own account;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>territory</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, the territory of Canada; and, as regards the Netherlands, the territory of the Kingdom in Europe.</Text></Definition></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any term not defined in this Article has the meaning assigned to it in the applicable legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE II</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Legislation to Which the Agreement Applies</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall apply:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with respect to Canada, to:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>with respect to the Netherlands, to the national legislation on:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>invalidity insurance for employed persons,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>invalidity insurance for self-employed persons,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>old age insurance,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>survivors’ insurance,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>children’s allowances,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>for the application of Article VI(2), (3) and (4):</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>sickness insurance (cash benefits and benefits in kind) inclusive of the obligation for the employer to pay salary during the first fifty two weeks of sickness of the employed person, as laid down in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Civil Code</XRefExternal>, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>unemployment insurance.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Except as otherwise provided in paragraph 3, this Agreement shall apply also to any legislation which amends, supplements, consolidates or supersedes the legislation specified in paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>This Agreement shall not apply to laws or regulations which extend the existing legislation of a Party to a new category of beneficiaries if the competent authority of that Party notifies the competent authority of the other Party within three months from the date of the official publication or proclamation of such laws or regulations that no such extension of the Agreement is intended.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>This Agreement shall not apply to social and medical assistance schemes, to special schemes for civil servants or persons treated as such, or to benefit schemes for victims of war or its consequences.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE III</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Persons to Whom the Agreement Applies</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement, it shall apply to nationals of the Parties, to persons who are or who have been subject to the legislation of either Party, and to other persons with respect to the rights they derive from the aforementioned persons.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE IV</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Equality of Treatment</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>As regards the legislation of Canada, all persons described in Article III shall be subject to the obligations of that legislation and shall be eligible for its benefits without regard to nationality.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>As regards the legislation of the Netherlands, unless otherwise provided in this Agreement,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>nationals of Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>refugees, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention of 28 July 1951 Relating to the Status of Refugees</XRefExternal> and of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Protocol of 31 January 1967</XRefExternal> to that Convention,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>stateless persons, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention of 28 September 1954 Relating to the Status of Stateless Persons</XRefExternal>, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>other persons to the extent that they derive rights from a person described in sub-paragraph (a), (b) or (c)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>shall be subject to the obligations of that legislation and shall be eligible for its benefits under the same conditions as nationals of the Netherlands.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE V</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Export of Benefit</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement, invalidity, old age or survivors benefits acquired by a person described in Article III under the legislation of one Party, including such benefits acquired by virtue of this Agreement, shall not be subject to any reduction, modification, suspension, cancellation or confiscation by reason only of the fact that the person resides in the territory of the other Party, and they shall be paid in the territory of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement, benefits payable under this Agreement by one Party to a person who is in the territory of the other Party shall also be paid to a person who is in the territory of a third State, under the same conditions and to the same extent as to nationals of the first Party residing in that third State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART II</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning the Applicable Legislation</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE VI</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Rules Regarding Coverage</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of the following paragraphs of this Article:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an employed person who works in the territory of one Party shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of that Party; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a self-employed person who ordinarily resides in the territory of one Party and who works as such in the territory of the other Party or in the territories of both Parties shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the former Party.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>An employed person who is covered under the legislation of one Party and who is assigned to perform work in the territory of the other Party for his or her employer shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the former Party as though that work was performed in its territory and provided that such assignment does not exceed sixty months and the person concerned is not also employed in the territory of the other Party by a different employer located in that territory.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>In the application of this paragraph in regard to a person who, on the date of entry into force of this Agreement, is already on assignment in the territory of the other Party and subject to the legislation of the former Party by virtue of Article VI(2) of the previous Agreement, the reference to sixty months in sub-paragraph (a) shall be read to refer to the total period during which that person may remain subject only to the legislation of the former Party while in the territory of the other Party, inclusive of the period already completed before the entry into force of this Agreement by virtue of Article VI(2) of the previous Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>A person who is employed as a member of the crew of a ship or aircraft shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of the Party in the territory of which the employer’s principal place of business is located. However, if the person concerned ordinarily resides in the territory of the other Party, and if the employer has a place of business in the territory of that Party, that person shall be subject only to the legislation of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A person employed in the territory of one Party in a government service of the other Party shall, in respect of that employment, be subject to the legislation of the first Party only if he or she is a national thereof or ordinarily resides in its territory.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Nationals of a Party employed in a government service of that Party who are sent to the territory of the other Party shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Where the person referred to in sub-paragraph (a) is subject to the legislation of the first Party, the employer in question shall observe the obligations which that legislation imposes on employers.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the two Parties may, by common agreement, modify the application of the provisions of this Article with respect to any persons or categories of persons.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE VII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Definition of Certain Periods of Residence with Respect to the Legislation of Canada</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purpose of calculating the amount of benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if a person is subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during any period of presence or residence in the territory of the Netherlands, that period shall be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person as well as for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with him or her and who are not subject to the legislation of the Netherlands by reason of employment or self-employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if a person is obligatorily subject to the legislation of the Netherlands during any period of presence or residence in the territory of Canada, that period shall not be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person and for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with him or her and who are not subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada by reason of employment or self-employment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the application of paragraph 1:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person shall be considered to be subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during a period of presence or residence in the territory of the Netherlands only if that person makes contributions pursuant to the plan concerned during that period by reason of employment or self-employment; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person shall be considered to be obligatorily subject to the legislation of the Netherlands during a period of presence or residence in the territory of Canada only if that person makes compulsory contributions pursuant to that legislation during that period by reason of employment or self-employment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE VIII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Definition of Certain Periods of Residence with Respect to the Legislation of the Netherlands</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of the legislation of the Netherlands, a person who is subject to the Netherlands legislation in accordance with the provisions of this Part shall be considered as residing in the Netherlands.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The provision of paragraph 1 shall apply by analogy to the spouse and children accompanying a person described in paragraph 2 or 4(b) of Article VI from the territory of one Party to the territory of the other Party, unless they themselves take up a gainful occupation or are receiving a pension or a cash benefit under the legislation of the latter Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART III</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">Chapter 1</Emphasis></Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Benefits under the Legislation of Canada</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE IX</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Totalizing of Creditable Periods</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>If a person is not eligible for a benefit on the basis of the periods creditable under the legislation of Canada, the eligibility of that person for that benefit shall be determined by totalizing these periods and those specified in sub-paragraph (b), provided that the periods do not overlap.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>In the application of this paragraph:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for the purposes of determining eligibility for a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, a creditable period under the Netherlands legislation on old age insurance shall be considered as a period of residence in the territory of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for the purposes of determining eligibility for a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, a calendar year including at least thirteen weeks which are creditable under the Netherlands legislation regarding invalidity or survivors’ insurance shall be considered as a year which is creditable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>If a person is not eligible for a benefit under the legislation of Canada on the basis of the periods creditable under the legislation of the Parties, totalized as provided in paragraph 1, the eligibility of that person for that benefit shall be determined by totalizing these periods and periods creditable under the laws of a third State with which both Parties are bound by international social security instruments which provide for totalizing of periods.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE X</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is eligible for an Old Age Security pension or an allowance solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Article IX, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of the pension or allowance payable to that person in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> governing the payment of a partial pension or allowance, exclusively on the basis of the periods of residence in Canada which may be considered under that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 1 shall also apply to a person outside Canada who would be entitled to the payment of a full pension in Canada but who has not resided in Canada for the minimum period required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for entitlement to the payment of a pension outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an Old Age Security pension shall be paid, through the application of the totalizing provisions of Article IX, to a person who is outside Canada only if</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that person has resided in Canada within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for a period of at least one year after 31 December 1956, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that person’s creditable periods, when totalized as provided in Article IX, are at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for entitlement to the payment of a pension outside Canada;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an allowance and a guaranteed income supplement shall be paid to a person who is outside Canada only to the extent permitted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE XI</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>If a person is eligible for a benefit solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Article IX, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of benefit payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the earnings-related portion of the benefit shall be determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, exclusively on the basis of the pensionable earnings under that Plan; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the flat-rate portion of the benefit shall be determined by multiplying:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the benefit determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>by</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the fraction which represents the ratio of the periods of contributions under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in relation to the minimum qualifying period required under that Plan to establish entitlement to that benefit, but in no case shall that fraction exceed the value of one.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">Chapter 2</Emphasis></Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Benefits under the Legislation of the Netherlands</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE XII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Benefits under the Invalidity Acts</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>When a national of one Party or a person described in paragraph 2(b) or (c) of Article IV, at the time when incapacity for work followed by invalidity occurred, had previously completed a total creditable period of at least twelve months under the Netherlands legislation on invalidity insurance, that person shall, subject to the provisions of paragraph 2, be entitled to a benefit determined in accordance with the latter legislation and calculated according to the provisions of Article XIII.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The preceding paragraph shall apply provided there is entitlement to a disability pension under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, where appropriate through the application of Article IX, or provided there is entitlement to a benefit due to disability under the workers’ compensation plan of a province or territory of Canada.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE XIII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Amount of Benefits</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>If entitlement to a benefit is established through the application of Article XII, the amount of the benefit payable shall be calculated in proportion to the ratio of the total length of the creditable periods completed by the person concerned under the Netherlands legislation after reaching the age of fifteen to the period between the date on which the person reached the age of fifteen and the date of incapacity for work followed by invalidity.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>If, at the time when incapacity for work followed by invalidity occurred, the person concerned was an employed person, the benefit payable shall be determined according to the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Incapacity Insurance Act</XRefExternal> of 18 February 1966 (WAO). In any other case, the benefit payable shall be determined according to the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Self Employed Persons Disablement Benefits Act</XRefExternal> of 24 April 1997 (WAZ).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The following creditable periods completed under the Netherlands legislation shall be taken into consideration:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>creditable periods during employment completed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Incapacity Insurance Act</XRefExternal> of 18 February 1966 (WAO);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>creditable periods completed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Incapacity Insurance Act</XRefExternal> of 11 December 1975 (AAW);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>creditable periods completed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Self-Employed Persons Disablement Benefits Act</XRefExternal> of 24 April 1997 (WAZ); and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>periods of employment, and periods treated as such, completed in the Netherlands before 1 July 1967.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>In the application of the first sentence of paragraph 2, when a creditable period completed under the WAO coincides with a creditable period completed under the AAW and/or WAZ, only the period completed under the WAO shall be taken into account.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>In the application of the second sentence of paragraph 2, when a creditable period completed under the AAW and/or WAZ coincides with a creditable period completed under the WAO, only the period completed under the AAW and/or WAZ shall be taken into account.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE XIV</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Old Age Pensions Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Netherlands competent institution shall determine the old age pension directly and exclusively on the basis of the creditable periods completed under the Netherlands <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Old Age Pensions Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 3, periods before 1 January 1957 during which a national of one Party or a person described in paragraph 2(b) or (c) of Article IV resided in the territory of the Netherlands after reaching the age of fifteen or during which, while residing in another country, the person was gainfully employed in the Netherlands shall also be considered as creditable periods if the person does not satisfy the conditions of the Netherlands legislation permitting such periods to be treated for that person as creditable periods.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The periods referred to in paragraph 2 shall be taken into consideration in the calculation of the old age pension only if the person has been insured within the meaning of Article 6 of the Netherlands <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Old Age Pensions Act</XRefExternal> and the person has resided for at least six years in the territory of one or both Parties after reaching the age of fifty-nine and only while the person is residing in the territory of either Party. However, these periods shall not be taken into consideration if they coincide with periods taken into consideration in the calculation of an old age pension under the legislation of a country other than the Netherlands.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE XV</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Survivors’ Benefits Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>When a national of one Party or a person described in paragraph 2(b) or (c) of Article IV was, at the time of death, subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or in receipt of a benefit under that Plan and had previously completed a total creditable period of at least twelve months under the Netherlands legislation on survivors’ insurance, the survivors shall be entitled to a benefit determined in accordance with the latter legislation and calculated according to the provisions of Article XVI.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the application of paragraph 1, a person shall be considered to have been subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> at the time of death if the death occurs during a calendar year which is a creditable period under that Plan in regard to the person concerned or if the calendar year immediately prior to the calendar year in which the death occurs was a creditable period under that Plan in regard to the person concerned.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>A person, or a child, receiving or qualified to receive benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Survivors Benefit Act</XRefExternal> shall be entitled to receive the payment of that benefit while he or she, or the child, resides in the territory of Canada.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE XVI</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Amount of Benefits</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>If entitlement to a benefit is established through the application of Article XV, the amount of the benefit payable shall be calculated in proportion to the ratio of the total length of the creditable periods completed by the deceased under the Netherlands legislation before reaching the age of sixty-five to the period between the date on which the deceased reached the age of fifteen and the date of death, but at the latest the date on which the deceased reached the age of sixty-five.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE XVII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Child Benefits Act</XRefExternal></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Netherlands competent institution shall determine the children’s allowances directly and exclusively on the basis of the Netherlands <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Child Benefits Act</XRefExternal>. A person receiving or qualified to receive Netherlands children’s allowances shall be entitled to receive the payment of that allowance while he or she, or the child, resides in the territory of Canada.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">Chapter 3</Emphasis></Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Income-Related Benefits for Spouses and Partners</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE XVIII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Amount of Benefits</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Chapter:</Text><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>income-related benefits</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, a guaranteed income supplement and an allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>; and, as regards the Netherlands, a supplementary allowance;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>partner</DefinedTermEn> means a person defined as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Old Age Pensions Act</XRefExternal> of the Netherlands;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>pensioner</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, a person entitled to the payment of a pension under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>; and, as regards the Netherlands, a person entitled to the payment of a pension under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Old Age Pensions Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition><Definition generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>spouse/common-law partner</DefinedTermEn> means a person entitled to the payment of an allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> of Canada by virtue of the fact that he or she is the spouse or common-law partner of a pensioner.</Text></Definition></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 4, if a person is both a spouse/common-law partner and a partner of a pensioner, the competent institutions of Canada and the Netherlands shall determine the amount of income-related benefits payable to that person and the pensioner as follows:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The competent institution of Canada shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>calculate the combined income of the pensioner and spouse/common-law partner in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, disregarding in the calculation the amount of any supplementary allowance payable under the legislation of the Netherlands to the pensioner in respect of the partner;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>determine, on the basis of the income so calculated, the amount of guaranteed income supplement and allowance payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> to the pensioner and spouse/common-law partner respectively;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>communicate to the competent institution of the Netherlands the amount of the allowance payable to the spouse/common-law partner.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The competent institution of the Netherlands shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>calculate the theoretical amount of the supplementary allowance which, but for the following sub-paragraph, would be payable to the pensioner in respect of the partner under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">General Old Age Pensions Act</XRefExternal>, disregarding in the calculation the amount of the allowance payable under the legislation of Canada to the spouse/common-law partner;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>determine the actual amount of supplementary allowance payable to the pensioner in respect of the partner by reducing the theoretical amount by the full amount of the allowance payable by the competent institution of Canada to the spouse/common-law partner.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>In the application of sub-paragraph 2(b)(ii), the competent institution of the Netherlands shall use the following exchange rates for converting the amount of the allowance into the currency of the Netherlands:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in regard to the first twelve-month period following the date on which the most recent of the two income-related benefits becomes payable, the exchange rate in effect on that date; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in regard to any subsequent twelve-month period, the exchange rate in effect on the anniversary of the date on which the most recent of the two income-related benefits became payable.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Agreement, this Chapter shall not apply to a person who is a spouse/common-law partner on the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART IV</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Administrative and Miscellaneous Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XIX</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Exchange of Information and Mutual Assistance</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities and institutions responsible for the application of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>shall, to the extent permitted by the legislation which they administer, communicate to each other any information necessary for the application of this Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shall lend their good offices and furnish assistance to one another with regard to the determination of entitlement to, or payment of, any benefit under this Agreement, or the legislation to which this Agreement applies, as if the matter involved the application of their own legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>shall communicate to each other, as soon as possible, all information about the measures taken by them for the application of this Agreement or about changes in their respective legislation insofar as these changes affect the application of this Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The assistance referred to in sub-paragraph l(b) shall be provided free of charge, subject to any agreement reached between the competent authorities of the Parties for the reimbursement of certain types of expenses.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Unless disclosure is required under the laws of a Party, any information about an individual which is transmitted in accordance with this Agreement to an authority or an institution of that Party by an authority or an institution of the other Party is confidential and shall be used only for purposes of implementing this Agreement and the legislation to which this Agreement applies.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XX</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Administrative Arrangement</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Parties shall establish, by means of an administrative arrangement, the measures necessary for the application of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The liaison agencies of the Parties shall be designated in that arrangement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXI</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Exemption or Reduction of Taxes, Dues, Fees or Charges</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any exemption from or reduction of taxes, legal dues, consular fees or administrative charges for which provision is made in the legislation of one Party in connection with the issuing of any certificate or document required to be produced for the application of that legislation shall be extended to certificates or documents required to be produced for the application of the legislation of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any acts or documents of an official nature required to be produced for the application of this Agreement shall be exempt from any authentication by diplomatic or consular authorities or similar formality.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Language of Communication</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the application of this Agreement, the competent authorities and institutions of the Parties may communicate directly with one another in any of the official languages of either Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The authorities, institutions and tribunals of a Party may not reject claims or other documents submitted to them by reason of the fact that they are written in a foreign language, provided they are in an official language of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXIII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Submitting Claims, Notices or Appeals</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any claim, notice or appeal concerning the determination of eligibility for, or payment of, a benefit under the legislation of one Party which should, for the purposes of that legislation, have been presented within a prescribed period to a competent authority, institution or tribunal of that Party, but which is presented within the same period to a competent authority, institution or tribunal of the other Party, shall be treated as if it had been presented to the authority, institution or tribunal of the first Party. The date on which such a claim, notice or appeal was submitted to the authority, institution or tribunal of the first Party shall be considered as the date of its submission to the authority, institution or tribunal of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>A claim for a benefit payable under the legislation of one Party made after the date of entry into force of the previous Agreement shall be deemed to be a claim for the corresponding benefit under the legislation of the other Party, provided that the applicant at the time of application:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>requests that it be considered an application under the legislation of the other Party, or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provides information indicating that creditable periods have been completed under the legislation of the other Party.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>In any case to which paragraph 1 or 2 applies, the authority, institution or tribunal to which the claim, notice or appeal has been submitted shall transmit it without delay to the authority, institution or tribunal of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXIV</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Payment of Benefits</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The institution or authority of a Party shall discharge its obligations under this Agreement in the currency of that Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Benefits shall be paid to beneficiaries free from deductions for administrative expense that may be incurred in paying the benefits.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXV</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Resolution of Difficulties</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Parties shall resolve, to the extent possible, any dispute which arises in interpreting or applying this Agreement according to its spirit and fundamental principles.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>If the dispute has not been settled within six months, it shall be submitted to an arbitration tribunal whose composition and procedure shall be agreed upon by the Parties. The arbitration tribunal shall settle the dispute in accordance with the spirit and fundamental principles of this Agreement. The arbitration shall be final and binding for the Parties.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXVI</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Understandings with a Province of Canada</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The relevant authority of the Netherlands and a province of Canada may conclude understandings concerning any social security matter within provincial jurisdiction in Canada insofar as those understandings are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">PART V</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Transitional and Final Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXVII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Transitional Provisions</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any creditable period completed before the date of entry into force of this Agreement shall be taken into account for the purpose of determining the right to a benefit under this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>No provision of this Agreement shall confer any right to receive payment of a benefit for a period before the date of entry into force of the previous Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 2, a benefit, other than a lump sum payment, shall, on application, be payable under this Agreement in respect of events which happened before the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXVIII</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Cessation of the Previous Agreement</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 2, on the entry into force of this Agreement, it shall supersede the previous Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>If, after the date of entry into force of the previous Agreement but before the date of entry into force of this Agreement, a person submits an application for a benefit under the legislation of a Party, and if, on the date of entry into force of this Agreement, the competent institution of that Party has not yet reached a decision on that application, that competent institution shall apply the provisions of the previous Agreement when determining that person’s entitlement to that benefit.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Benefits awarded through the application of the previous Agreement may be recalculated by the competent institutions, either directly or on request by the beneficiary, taking into account the provisions of this Agreement. In no case, however, shall the amount of a benefit be reduced as a result of such a recalculation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXIX</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Duration and Termination</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall remain in force without any limitation on its duration. It may be terminated at any time by either Party giving twelve months’ notice in writing to the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the event of the termination of this Agreement, any right acquired by a person in accordance with its provisions or the provisions of the previous Agreement shall be maintained and negotiations shall take place for the settlement of any rights then in course of acquisition by virtue of those provisions.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE XXX</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Entry into Force</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The Parties shall notify each other in writing of the completion of their respective requirements for the entry into force of this Agreement. Subject to paragraph (2), this Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month after the date of the last notification.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Article XVII shall enter into force retroactively as of 1 January 2000.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis> the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in two copies at Brantford, this 27<Sup>th</Sup> day of June 2001, in the English, French and Dutch languages, each text being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="4"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="230.57*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="237.43*" /><tbody><row><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" hyphenation="no" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" hyphenation="no" justification="left"><Text>Jane Stewart</Text></Provision></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" hyphenation="no" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF THE KINGDOM OF THE NETHERLANDS</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" hyphenation="no" justification="left"><Text>Dirk Jan Van Houten</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="611201" lims:id="611201" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Protocol on Mutual Assistance Pursuant to the Agreement on Social Security Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM OF THE NETHERLANDS,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">WITH THE PURPOSE</Emphasis> of improving the administrative efficiency, cost effectiveness and integrity of their social security systems as they apply to benefits payable under the legislation specified in Article II of the Agreement on Social Security between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, signed at Brantford on June 27, 2001 (hereinafter referred to as “the Agreement”),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">TAKING INTO ACCOUNT</Emphasis> the provisions regarding mutual assistance found in Article XIX of the Agreement,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="underline">Definitions</Emphasis></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Terms used in this Protocol have the same meaning as in the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="underline">Mutual Assistance</Emphasis></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>In accordance with the procedures to be outlined in one or more Administrative Understandings, the competent institutions and liaison agencies of the two Parties shall assist each other in administering the legislation specified in Article II of the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In no case shall a competent institution or liaison agency of a Party be expected to:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>carry out administrative measures at variance with the statutes or the administrative practice of that Party;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>furnish information which is not obtainable under the legislation of that Party.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="underline">Management</Emphasis></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The program of mutual assistance shall be under the general direction of a Management Committee, whose function shall be to undertake an ongoing review of policy and procedures relating to the program. The Committee shall consist of four members, of which the competent institution and liaison agency of each Party shall designate two.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Management Committee shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>be responsible for the co-ordination, and any modification, of the program of mutual assistance to be set out later in one or more Administrative Understandings. The Committee shall review the various timeframes for the performance of functions set out in the Understandings in order to ensure that these standards are met to the extent possible or to modify the timeframes where appropriate;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>be responsible for exchanging statistics and other information regarding workloads and other administrative matters associated with the program of mutual assistance. The content and form of the statistics and information to be exchanged shall be agreed upon by the Management Committee;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>meet, as required, to review progress and establish program guidance and priorities.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="underline">Expenses</Emphasis></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The competent institution and liaison agency of each Party shall furnish mutual assistance in accordance with Article II of this Protocol without charge. The Management Committee shall periodically review the expenses involved in furnishing assistance under this Protocol with a view toward balancing the costs incurred.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="underline">Interpretation and Application</Emphasis></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Notwithstanding Article XXV of the Agreement, any disagreement regarding the interpretation or application of this Protocol or its Administrative Understandings shall be resolved by the Management Committee.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="underline">Duration and Termination of the Protocol</Emphasis></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Protocol shall remain in force for an indefinite period. Either Party may terminate it at any time by giving six months’ notice in writing to the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="underline">Entry into Force</Emphasis></Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Protocol shall enter into force on the same date as the Agreement and shall form an integral part of the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis>, the undersigned, duly authorised thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in two copies at Brantford this 27<Sup>th</Sup> day of June 2001, in the English, French and Dutch languages, each text being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="4"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" /><colspec colname="col2" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no"><Text>Jane Stewart</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM OF THE NETHERLANDS</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" hyphenation="no"><Text>Dirk Jan Van Houten</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>