<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2021-02-02" lims:lastAmendedDate="2021-02-02" lims:current-date="2024-12-23" lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283968" lims:id="1283968" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283969" lims:id="1283969"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2021-5</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate><Date><YYYY>2024</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283970" lims:id="1283970"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">CRIMINAL CODE</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283971" lims:id="1283971">Order Accepting the Recommendation of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness that Each Listed Entity Remain a Listed Entity</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2021-30</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>2</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283972" lims:id="1283972"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283973" lims:id="1283973" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 83.05(8.1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28010">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28011">b</FootnoteRef>, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness has completed a review of each entity set out in the annexed schedule and listed in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2002-284">Regulations Establishing a List of Entities</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28089">c</FootnoteRef>, made pursuant to subsection 83.05(1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28012">d</FootnoteRef> of that Act, and has determined that there are still reasonable grounds, as set out in subsection 83.05(1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28012">d</FootnoteRef>, for each entity to remain a listed entity;</Text><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28010" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2019, c. 13, s. 141(4)</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28011" placement="page" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>R.S., c. C-46</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28089" placement="page" status="official"><Label>c</Label><Text>SOR/2002-284</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28012" placement="page" status="official"><Label>d</Label><Text>S.C. 2019, c. 13, s. 141(1)</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283974" lims:id="1283974" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>And whereas, pursuant to subsection 83.05(1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28012">d</FootnoteRef> of that Act, the Administrator in Council is satisfied, on the recommendation of that Minister, that there are reasonable grounds to believe that each listed entity set out in the annexed schedule is an entity that has knowingly carried out, attempted to carry out, participated in or facilitated a terrorist activity or that has knowingly acted on behalf of, at the direction of or in association with such an entity;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283975" lims:id="1283975" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Therefore, His Excellency the Administrator of the Government of Canada in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness made pursuant to subsection 83.05(8.1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28010">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4367_hq_28011">b</FootnoteRef>, accepts the recommendation that each listed entity set out in the annexed schedule remain a listed entity.</Text></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:lastAmendedDate="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283976" lims:id="1283976"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283977" lims:id="1283977"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><TitleText>Listed Entities Reviewed by the Minister</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283978" lims:id="1283978" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Hay’at Tahrir al-Sham (also known among other names as Jabhat al-Nusra (JN), Jabhat Fateh al-Sham, Jabhat Fatah al-Sham, Fath al-Sham Front, al-Jabha, Fath al-Sham, Tanzim al-Qaeda fi Bilad al-Sham, Al-Qaeda in the Levant, Conquest for al-Sham Front, Conquest of the Levant Front, Fatah al-Sham Front, Fateh al-Sham Front, Front for the Conquest of Syria, Front for the Conquest of Syria/The Levant, Jabhat Fath al-Sham, Jabhat Fath al Sham, Jabhat Fathah al-Sham, Hayat Tahrir al-Sham, Tahrir al-Sham Assembly, Liberation of Syria Assembly, Liberation of the Levant Organisation, Liberation of the Levant Committee, Liberation of al-Sham Commission, Assembly for the Liberation of the Levant, Hay’et Tahrir al-Sham, Tahrir al-Sham, Liwa al-Haqq, the Al-Haqq Brigade, Liwa al-Haq, the Brigade of the Right, the Truth Brigade, Lewa’ al-Haq, the al-Haq Battalion, Jabhat Ansar al-Din, Ansar al-Din Front, Supporters/Partisans of the Religion Front, Jaish al-Sunnah, Jaysh al-Sunnah, Jaish al-Sunna, Jaysh al-Sunna, Jabhet al-Nusra, The Victory Front, Al-Nusrah Front for the People of the Levant, Jabhat Al-Nusra li-Ahl min Mujahedi al-Sham fi Sahat al-Jihad (The Support Front for the People of the Levant by the Levantine Mujahedin on the Battlefields of Jihad), the Front for the Defense of the Syrian People and the Front for the Support of the Syrian People)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283979" lims:id="1283979" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Al-Ashtar Brigades (AAB) (also known among other names as Saraya al-Ashtar, Al Ashtar Brigades, The Ashtar Brigades, Saraya Waad Allah, Wa’ad Allah Brigades, Islamic Allah Brigades, Imam al-Mahdi Brigades and al-Haydariyah Brigades)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283980" lims:id="1283980" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Fatemiyoun Division (FD) (also known among other names as Fatemioun Brigade, Fatemioun Military Division, Fatemiyoun, Fatemiyoun Battalion, Fatemiyoun Force, Fatemiyyun, Liwa Fatemiyoun, Liwa al-Fatemiyon, Fatemiyon Brigade, Fatemiyon Division and Fatemiyoun Brigade)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283981" lims:id="1283981" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Islamic State – Khorasan Province (ISKP) (also known among other names as Islamic State in the Khorasan Province, Islamic State Khorasan, Islamic State – Khorasan, IS Khorasan, Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant – Khorasan (ISIL-K), Islamic State of Iraq and Syria – Khorasan (ISIS-K), Islamic State of Iraq and al-Sham – Khorasan (ISIS-K), Wilayat Khorasan, Daesh Khorasan, ISIL’s South Asia Branch, ISIS Wilayat Khorasan, Islamic State’s Khorasan Province, South Asian chapter of ISIL, ISIL Khorasan (ISIL-K), Khorasan Chapter of the Islamic State, Islamic State Wilayat Khorasan (ISWK) and Khorasan branch of ISIS)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283982" lims:id="1283982" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Al Qaida in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP) (also known among other names as Ansar al-Shari’a (AAS), Al-Qaida of Jihad Organization in the Arabian Peninsula, Tanzim Qa’idat al-Jihad fi Jazirat al-Arab, Al-Quaida Organization in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP), Al-Quaida in the South Arabian Peninsula and Al-Qaida in Yemen (AQY))</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283983" lims:id="1283983" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Al Qaida in the Indian Subcontinent (AQIS) (also known among other names as Qaedat al-Jihad in the Indian Subcontinent, and Jamaat Qaidat al Jihad fi Shibh al Qarrah al Hindiyah (Organisation of the Base of Jihad in the Indian Subcontinent))</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-02-02" lims:enacted-date="2021-02-02" lims:fid="1283984" lims:id="1283984" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Al Shabaab (also known as Harakat Shabaab al-Mujahidin, al-Shabab, Shabaab, the Youth, Mujahidin al Shabaab Movement, Mujahideen Youth Movement, MYM, Mujahidin Youth, Hizbul Shabaab, Hisb’ul Shabaab, al-Shabaab al-Islamiya, Youth Wing, al Shabaab al-Islam, al-Shabaab al-Jihad, the Unity of Islamic Youth and the Popular Resistance Movement in the Land of the Two Migrations)</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>