<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613766" lims:id="613766" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613767" lims:id="613767"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2008-148</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2008</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613769" lims:id="613769"><OtherAuthority>OTHER THAN STATUTORY AUTHORITY</OtherAuthority></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613770" lims:id="613770">Order Governing the Grant of the Memorial Cross</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2008-1924</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2008</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613771" lims:id="613771"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613772" lims:id="613772" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of National Defence and the Minister of Veterans Affairs, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-2008-148">Order Governing the Grant of the Memorial Cross</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613773" lims:id="613773"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613774" lims:id="613774" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613775" lims:id="613775"><Label>1</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Order.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613776" lims:id="613776" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>1950 Order</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Order Governing the Grant of the Memorial Cross to Mothers and Widows</XRefExternal>, made by Order in Council P.C. 5812 of December 5, 1950. (<DefinedTermFr>décret de 1950</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613777" lims:id="613777" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>2006 Order</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-2006-141">Order Governing the Grant of the Memorial Cross (Canadian Forces)</XRefExternal>, made by Order in Council P.C. 2006-1449 of November 30, 2006 and registered as SI/2006-141. (<DefinedTermFr>décret de 2006</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613778" lims:id="613778" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>member</DefinedTermEn> means an officer or non-commissioned member. (<DefinedTermFr>militaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613779" lims:id="613779" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>representative of the estate or succession</DefinedTermEn> means the person who acts as executor or administrator of the estate, or liquidator of the succession, of a member or former member or the person who was acting in that capacity when the estate was settled. (<DefinedTermFr>représentant de la succession</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613780" lims:id="613780" level="1"><TitleText>Description</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613781" lims:id="613781"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Memorial Cross is a cross <Emphasis style="italic">pattée</Emphasis> in silver placed on a wreath of laurel, suspended from a brooch bar in the form of the lateral arms of the Cross; at the end of the upright, the Royal Crown, at the foot and at the end of either arm, a maple leaf; and in the centre, the Royal Cypher of the reigning monarch. The reverse of the Cross is engraved with the service number, rank, initials and surname of the member or former member who is commemorated.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613782" lims:id="613782" level="1"><TitleText>Service Before October 7, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613783" lims:id="613783"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Memorial Cross shall be granted as a memento of personal loss and sacrifice in respect of the death of a member or former member, to recipients designated under section 4 or 5 who survive the member or former member, if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613784" lims:id="613784"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a member of the Supplementary Reserve, the member did not serve in or with the Regular Force, Primary Reserve, Cadet Instructors Cadre or Canadian Rangers on or after October 7, 2001;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613785" lims:id="613785"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a former member of the Canadian Forces, Royal Canadian Navy, Canadian Army or Royal Canadian Air Force, the former member served before October 7, 2001;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613786" lims:id="613786"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the death is attributable to military service in an area of hostilities outside Canada in consequence of any action undertaken by Canada under the Charter of the United Nations, the North Atlantic Treaty or any other instrument for collective defence entered into by Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613787" lims:id="613787"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the death occurs on or after the day on which this Order comes into force.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613788" lims:id="613788"><Label>4</Label><Text>The member or former member may designate, in a form approved by the Minister of Veterans Affairs, a maximum of two recipients of the Memorial Cross.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613789" lims:id="613789"><Label>5</Label><Text>The representative of the estate or succession may designate recipients of the Memorial Cross, of which the number shall not exceed, as applicable,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613790" lims:id="613790"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>two, if the designation of recipients referred to in section 4 has not been made, a completed form cannot be found or no designated recipients survive the member or former member; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613791" lims:id="613791"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>one, if only one Memorial Cross is granted to a recipient designated under section 4.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613792" lims:id="613792" level="1"><TitleText>Service on or After October 7, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613793" lims:id="613793"><Label>6</Label><Text>The Memorial Cross shall be granted as a memento of personal loss and sacrifice in respect of the death of a member or former member, to recipients designated under section 7, 8 or 9 who survive the member or former member, if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613794" lims:id="613794"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a member or former member of the Regular Force, Primary Reserve, Cadet Instructors Cadre or Canadian Rangers, the member or former member served on or after October 7, 2001; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613795" lims:id="613795"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a member or former member of the Supplementary Reserve, the member or former member served in or with the Regular Force, Primary Reserve, Cadet Instructors Cadre or Canadian Rangers on or after October 7, 2001; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613796" lims:id="613796"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the death is attributable to an injury or disease related to military service.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613797" lims:id="613797"><Label>7</Label><Text>The member or former member may designate, in a form approved by the Chief of the Defence Staff, a maximum of three recipients of the Memorial Cross.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613798" lims:id="613798"><Label>8</Label><Text>Subject to section 9, the representative of the estate or succession may designate recipients of the Memorial Cross, of which the number shall not exceed, as applicable,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613799" lims:id="613799"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>three, if the designation of recipients referred to in section 7 has not been made, a completed form cannot be found or no designated recipients survive the member or former member;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613800" lims:id="613800"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two, if only one Memorial Cross is granted to a recipient designated under section 7; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613801" lims:id="613801"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>one, if two Memorial Crosses are granted to recipients designated under section 7.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613802" lims:id="613802"><Label>9</Label><Text>If the death of a member or former member who served during the period beginning on or after October 7, 2001 and ending on December 31, 2006 has occurred before the day on which this Order comes into force, the representative of the estate or succession may designate recipients of the Memorial Cross, of which the number shall not exceed, as applicable,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613803" lims:id="613803"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>three, if no Memorial Crosses were granted under the 1950 Order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613804" lims:id="613804"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two, if only one Memorial Cross was granted under the 1950 Order; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613805" lims:id="613805"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>one, if two Memorial Crosses were granted under the 1950 Order.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613806" lims:id="613806" level="1"><TitleText>Responsible Ministers</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613807" lims:id="613807"><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613808" lims:id="613808"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of National Defence is responsible for the grant of the Memorial Cross if a member dies while serving in or with the Regular Force, Primary Reserve, Cadet Instructors Cadre or Canadian Rangers.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613809" lims:id="613809"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Veterans Affairs is responsible for the grant of the Memorial Cross if a former member of the Canadian Forces, Royal Canadian Navy, Canadian Army or Royal Canadian Air Force dies, or a member of the Supplementary Reserve dies while not serving with the Regular Force, Primary Reserve, Cadet Instructors Cadre or Canadian Rangers.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613810" lims:id="613810" level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613811" lims:id="613811"><Label>11</Label><Text>If a member or former member has, before the coming into force of section 14, designated recipients, in a form approved by the Chief of the Defence Staff for the purpose of section 6 of the 2006 Order, the designation is deemed to have been made in the form approved under section 7 of this Order.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613812" lims:id="613812"><Label>12</Label><Text>A recipient to whom the Memorial Cross has been granted under the 1950 Order or the 2006 Order shall not be granted a Memorial Cross under section 6 of this Order.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613813" lims:id="613813" level="1"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613814" lims:id="613814"><Label>13</Label><Text>[Repeal]</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-12-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-12-24" lims:fid="613815" lims:id="613815"><Label>14</Label><Text>[Repeal]</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>