<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2009-06-18" lims:lastAmendedDate="2009-06-18" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614692" lims:id="614692" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614693" lims:id="614693"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2009-61</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2009</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614695" lims:id="614695"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-9">DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE AND AGRI-FOOD ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614696" lims:id="614696">Certificates of Age and Origin for Distilled Spirits Produced or Packaged in Canada Order</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614697" lims:id="614697"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614698" lims:id="614698" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to section 4<FootnoteRef idref="fn_612046-E_hq_7341">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-9">Department of Agriculture and Agri-Food Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_612046-E_hq_7342">b</FootnoteRef>, the powers, duties and functions of the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food extend to and include all matters over which Parliament has jurisdiction, not by law assigned to any other department, board or agency of the Government of Canada, relating to, among other things, agriculture and products derived from agriculture;</Text><Footnote id="fn_612046-E_hq_7341" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1994, c. 38, s. 5</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_612046-E_hq_7342" placement="page" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>R.S., c. A-9; S.C. 1994, c. 38, s. 2</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614699" lims:id="614699" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas distilled spirits are produced from botanical substances or products derived from them and, as such, constitute products derived from agriculture;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614700" lims:id="614700" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas certain of Canada’s trading partners require as a condition to the importation of distilled spirits from Canada that the distilled spirits be accompanied by a certificate issued by a duly authorized official of the Government of Canada attesting to the age and origin of the distilled spirits;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614701" lims:id="614701" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food, pursuant to section 4<FootnoteRef idref="fn_612046-E_hq_7341">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-9">Department of Agriculture and Agri-Food Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_612046-E_hq_7342">b</FootnoteRef>, hereby authorizes inspectors designated pursuant to section 5.01<FootnoteRef idref="fn_612046-E_hq_7343">c</FootnoteRef> of that Act to issue certificates in accordance with the terms and conditions set out in the annexed schedule attesting to the age and origin of distilled spirits that are produced or packaged in Canada in accordance with the requirements of Division 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._870">Food and Drug Regulations</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_612046-E_hq_7344">d</FootnoteRef>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_612046-E_hq_7343" placement="page" status="official"><Label>c</Label><Text>S.C. 1994, c. 38, s. 6</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_612046-E_hq_7344" placement="page" status="official"><Label>d</Label><Text>C.R.C., c. 870</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614702" lims:id="614702" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Ottawa, June 18, 2009</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614703" lims:id="614703" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="right">GERRY RITZ</SignatureName><SignatureName justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food</Emphasis></SignatureName></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:lastAmendedDate="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614704" lims:id="614704" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614705" lims:id="614705"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><TitleText>Terms and Conditions for the Issuance of Certificates of Age and Origin for Distilled Spirits Produced or Packaged in Canada</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><RegulationPiece lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614706" lims:id="614706"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:lastAmendedDate="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614707" lims:id="614707"><Label>1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614708" lims:id="614708"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No certificate attesting to the age and origin of distilled spirits (“spirits”) that are produced or packaged in Canada (“Certificate of Age and Origin”) shall be issued by an inspector designated by the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food (“Inspector”) unless</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614709" lims:id="614709"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the information set out in the certificate can be verified from the records of the producer or packager; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614710" lims:id="614710"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>all casks, barrels and drums that are used by a producer or packager for the storage or delivery of spirits are clearly and legibly marked with the month and year of original warehousing.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614711" lims:id="614711"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An Inspector shall not accept a certificate attesting to the age of any spirits brought into the facilities of a producer or packager unless the certificate has been endorsed by a government official of the country of origin of the spirits.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:lastAmendedDate="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614712" lims:id="614712"><Label>2</Label><Text>If whisky that is to be exported is a blend containing more than 9.090 per cent imported spirits, a Certificate of Age and Origin shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614713" lims:id="614713"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>specify the percentage of domestic and imported spirits contained in the whisky; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614714" lims:id="614714"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>not refer to the whisky as Rye Whisky, Canadian Whisky or Canadian Rye Whisky.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:lastAmendedDate="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614715" lims:id="614715"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614716" lims:id="614716"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), for the purpose of issuing a Certificate of Age and Origin in respect of spirits flavoured by blending into the spirits additional domestic or imported spirits or wine, the resultant product of the blended spirits is deemed to have been warehoused for a period equal to the period of warehousing of the most recently warehoused spirits contained in the resultant product.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614717" lims:id="614717"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the absolute ethyl alcohol content of the spirits or wine that are added as flavouring does not exceed 9.090 per cent of the total quantity of absolute ethyl alcohol contained in the resultant product of the blended spirits, that resultant product is deemed to have been warehoused for a period equal to the period of warehousing of the spirits to which were added the spirits or wine for blending purposes.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:lastAmendedDate="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614718" lims:id="614718"><Label>4</Label><Text>A Certificate of Age and Origin shall only be issued for Canadian brandy blended by the addition of domestic or imported brandies if at least 75 per cent of the absolute ethyl alcohol content of the resultant product is derived from Canadian brandy.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2009-06-18" lims:lastAmendedDate="2009-06-18" lims:fid="614719" lims:id="614719"><Label>5</Label><Text>A Certificate of Age and Origin shall not be issued in respect of spirits bottled for export that bear a label containing any reference to Canada, including the word “Canadian” in the trade name, to designate the type of spirits unless at least 75 per cent of the absolute ethyl alcohol content of those bottled spirits is derived from domestic spirits.</Text></Section></RegulationPiece></Schedule></Regulation>