<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2010-02-08" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-02-08" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614905" lims:id="614905" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614906" lims:id="614906"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2010-13</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2010</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>17</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614908" lims:id="614908"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614909" lims:id="614909">Proclamation Giving Notice that the Convention on Social Security Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of Morocco comes into Force on March 1, 2010</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614910" lims:id="614910"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614911" lims:id="614911" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>MICHAËLLE JEAN</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614912" lims:id="614912" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614913" lims:id="614913" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614914" lims:id="614914" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614915" lims:id="614915" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>TO ALL TO WHOM these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614916" lims:id="614916" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614917" lims:id="614917" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="left">JOHN H. SIMS</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614918" lims:id="614918" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614919" lims:id="614919" level="1"><TitleText>A Proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614920" lims:id="614920" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1998-1805 of October 8, 1998, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article 27 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention on Social Security between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of Morocco</XRefExternal>, signed on July 1, 1998, the Convention shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received from the other Party written notification that it has complied with all statutory requirements for the entry into force of the Convention;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614921" lims:id="614921" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas that Order in Council was laid before the House of Commons on October 23, 1998 and before the Senate on October 27, 1998, pursuant to subsection 42(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614922" lims:id="614922" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the 20th sitting day after the Order was laid before Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614923" lims:id="614923" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the 30th sitting day after it was laid before Parliament, being February 3, 1999;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614924" lims:id="614924" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the exchange of the written notifications was completed in November 2009;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614925" lims:id="614925" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Convention shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received from the other Party written notification that it has complied with all statutory requirements for the entry into force of that Convention, being March 1, 2010;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614926" lims:id="614926" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2010-113 of February 2, 2010, the Governor in Council directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention on Social Security between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of Morocco</XRefExternal> enters into force on March 1, 2010;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614927" lims:id="614927" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our Proclamation, give notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention on Social Security between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of Morocco</XRefExternal>, signed on July 1, 1998, a copy of which is annexed to this Proclamation, enters into force on March 1, 2010.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614928" lims:id="614928" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>OF ALL WHICH Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614929" lims:id="614929" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN TESTIMONY WHEREOF, We have caused this Our Proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. WITNESS: The Honourable Marie Deschamps, a Puisne Judge of the Supreme Court of Canada and Deputy of Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Michaëlle Jean, Chancellor and Principal Companion of our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614930" lims:id="614930" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>AT OTTAWA, this eighth day of February in the year of Our Lord two thousand and ten and in the fifty-ninth year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614931" lims:id="614931" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By command,</Text><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="right" topmarginspacing="4">RICHARD G. SHAW</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614932" lims:id="614932" format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="no"><Text>GOD SAVE THE QUEEN</Text></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2010-02-08" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-02-08" lims:fid="614933" lims:id="614933" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Convention on Social Security Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Kingdom of Morocco</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="italic">THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="italic">AND</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="italic">THE GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM OF MOROCCO,</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">hereinafter referred to as “the Parties”,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">RESOLVED</Emphasis> to co-operate in the field of Social Security,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">AGREEING</Emphasis> on the principle of equal treatment of persons who are or have been subject to the legislation of either States as regards the application of the Social Security legislation of each State,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">DESIRING</Emphasis> to uphold the rights acquired or in course of being acquired by insured persons of both States in regard to old age, disability, survivors and death insurance,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE DECIDED</Emphasis> to conclude a Convention to coordinate the application of the Social Security legislation of both Canada and the Kingdom of Morocco on behalf of insured persons of both States, and</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="italic">FOR THIS PURPOSE, HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Convention:</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, the Minister or Ministers responsible for the application of the legislation of Canada; and, as regards the Kingdom of Morocco, the Minister responsible for the application of the Moroccan legislation;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent institution</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, the competent authority; and, as regards the Kingdom of Morocco, the National Social Security Fund (Caisse Nationale de Sécurité Sociale) as the managing body of the General Social Security Scheme and as the representative of the other competent institutions of Morocco;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>legislation</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards a Party, the laws and regulations specified in Article 2 (1) with respect to that Party;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>insurance period</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards a Party, a period of contributions, employment, insurance or residence used to acquire the right to a benefit under the legislation of that Party; as regards Canada, it also means a period during which a disability pension is payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>; and, as regards the Kingdom of Morocco, equivalent or assimilated periods;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>benefit</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards a Party, any cash benefit, pension or allowance for which provision is made in the legislation of either Party and includes any supplements or increases applicable to such a cash benefit, pension or allowance;</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>residence</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, residence as defined by the legislation of Canada; and, as regards the Kingdom of Morocco, ordinary residence as in the legal meaning of the term.</Text></Definition></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any term not defined in this Article has the meaning assigned to it in the applicable legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label><TitleText>Legislation to Which the Convention Applies</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall apply to the following legislation:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with respect to Canada:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="4" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="6"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder, and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="4" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="6"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>with respect to the Kingdom of Morocco:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="4" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="6"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the legislation relating to the Social Security Scheme as modified or completed, limited to long term benefits and to the death allowance payable to the survivors of an insured person or of a beneficiary of an old age pension, or a disability pension or benefit,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="4" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="6"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the legislation relating to work accident and professional illnesses (provisions relating to benefits),</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="4" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="6"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the legislation, regulation or statutory provisions agreed upon by the public authority relating to special social security schemes in so far as they provide coverage of salaried workers or those considered as such, and related to current risks and benefits as provided for by the legislation of social security schemes.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 3, this Convention shall also apply to laws and regulations which amend, supplement, consolidate or supersede the legislation specified in paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>3</Label><Text>This Convention shall apply to laws and regulations which extend the legislation of a Party to new categories of beneficiaries or to new benefits unless an objection on the part of that Party has been communicated to the other Party no later than three months following the entry into force of such laws and regulations.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label><TitleText>Persons to Whom the Convention Applies</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Convention shall apply to:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for Canada, any person who is or who has been subject to the legislation of Canada, and to the dependants and survivors of such a person;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for the Kingdom of Morocco, any salaried person or a person considered as such who is or who has been subject to the legislation of Morocco and to the beneficiaries of such a person.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label><TitleText>Equality of Treatment</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>For the application of the legislation of a Party, any person described in Article 3 shall be subject to the obligations of the legislation of the other Party and shall be eligible for the benefits of that legislation under the same conditions as citizens or nationals of the latter Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label><TitleText>Export of Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Convention, benefits payable under the legislation of a Party to any person described in Article 3, including benefits acquired by virtue of this Convention, shall not be subject to any reduction, modification, suspension, cancellation or confiscation by reason only of the fact that the person resides in the territory of the other Party, and these benefits shall be paid in the territory of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>Benefits payable under this Convention to a person who is or who has been subject to the legislation of both Parties, or to the dependants or survivors of such a person, shall be paid in the territory of a third State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning the Applicable Legislation</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label><TitleText>Provisions Regarding Coverage</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to the following provisions of this Article:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an employed person who works in the territory of a Party shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of that Party; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a self-employed person who ordinarily resides in the territory of a Party and who works for his or her own account in the territory of the other Party or in the territories of both Parties shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>An employed person who is subject to the legislation of a Party and who performs services in the territory of the other Party for the same employer shall, in respect of those services, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party as though those services were performed in its territory and for a period not exceeding thirty-six months.</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="yes"><Text>A period of detachment may be extended for more than thirtysix months up to a maximum of sixty months with the prior consent of the competent or delegated authorities of the Parties.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>3</Label><Text>A person who, but for this Convention, would be subject to the legislation of both Parties in respect of employment as a member of the crew of a ship or an aircraft shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of Canada if he or she ordinarily resides in Canada and only to the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco if he or she ordinarily resides in the Kingdom of Morocco.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>4</Label><Text>A person who is employed at a harbour of a Party for the purpose of loading or unloading, carrying out inspection or repair work, shall be subject to the legislation of the Party in whose territory the harbour is located.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>5</Label><Text>An employed person shall, in respect of the duties of a government employment performed in the territory of the other Party, be subject to the legislation of the latter Party only if he or she is a citizen thereof or ordinarily resides in its territory. In the latter case, that person may, however, elect to be subject only to the legislation of the first Party if he or she is a citizen thereof.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>6</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Parties may, by common agreement, modify the application of the provisions of this Article with respect to any person or categories of persons.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label><TitleText>Definition of Certain Periods of Residence with Respect to the Legislation of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purpose of calculating the amount of benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if a person is subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during any period of presence or residence in the Kingdom of Morocco, that period shall be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person as well as for that person’s spouse and dependants who reside with him or her and who are not subject to the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco by reason of employment or self-employment; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if a person is subject to the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco during any period of presence or residence in the territory of Canada, that period shall not be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person and for that person’s spouse and dependants who reside with him or her and who are not subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada by reason of employment or selfemployment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the application of paragraph 1:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person shall be considered to be subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during a period of presence or residence in the Kingdom of Morocco only if that person makes contributions pursuant to the plan concerned during that period by reason of employment or selfemployment; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person shall be considered to be subject to the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco during a period of presence or residence in Canada only if that person makes compulsory contributions pursuant to that legislation during that period by reason of employment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPTER 1</Label><TitleText>Totalizing Periods</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 8</Label><TitleText>Periods under the Legislation of Canada and the Kingdom of Morocco</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is not entitled to the payment of a benefit because he or she has not accumulated sufficient insurance periods under the legislation of a Party, the entitlement of that person to the payment of that benefit shall be determined by totalizing these periods and those specified in paragraphs 2 and 3 of this Article, provided that the periods do not overlap.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>2 <Leader leader="none" length="1pc" />(a)</Label><Text>For purposes of determining entitlement to the payment of a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> of Canada, any insurance period under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco shall be considered as a period of residence in the territory of Canada.</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>For purposes of determining entitlement to the payment of a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, any calendar year including at least three months or seventyeight days of insurance under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco shall be considered as a year in which contributions were paid under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>3</Label><Text>For purposes of determining entitlement to the payment of a benefit under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a calendar year which is a period of insurance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as three hundred and twelve days of contributions under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a day which is a period of insurance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> of Canada and which is not part of a period of insurance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as a day of contributions under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 9</Label><TitleText>Periods Under the Legislation of a Third State</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is not entitled to the payment of a benefit on the basis of the periods of insurance under the legislation of the Parties, totalized as provided in Article 8, the entitlement of that person to the payment of that benefit shall be determined by totalizing these periods and periods of insurance under the legislation of a third State with which both Parties are bound by social security instruments which provide for totalizing of periods of insurance.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 10</Label><TitleText>Minimum Insurance Period</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Convention, if the total duration of the periods of insurance accumulated under the legislation of Canada is less than one year and if, taking into account only those periods, no right to a benefit exists, the competent institution of Canada shall not be required to pay benefits.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Convention, if the total duration of insurance periods accumulated under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco is less than three hundred and twelve days and if, taking into account only those periods, no right to a benefit exists, the competent institution of the Kingdom of Morocco shall not be required to pay benefits.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPTER 2</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the Legislation of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 11</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is entitled to the payment of an <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security</XRefExternal> pension or a spouse’s allowance solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of the pension or spouse’s allowance payable to that person in conformity with the provisions of the Old Age Security Act governing the payment of a partial pension or a spouse’s allowance, exclusively on the basis of the periods of residence in Canada which may be considered under that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraph 1 shall also apply to a person who is outside Canada and who is entitled to the payment of a full pension in Canada but who has not resided in Canada for the minimum period required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for entitlement to the payment of a pension outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>3</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Convention:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an Old Age Security pension shall not be paid to a person who is outside Canada unless that person’s periods of residence, when totalized as provided in Chapter 1, are at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for entitlement to the payment of a pension outside Canada; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a spouse’s allowance and a guaranteed income supplement shall be paid to a person who is outside Canada only to the extent permitted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 12</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is entitled to the payment of a benefit solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of benefit payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the earnings-related portion of the benefit shall be deter mined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, exclusively on the basis of the pensionable earnings under that Plan; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the flat-rate portion of the benefit shall be determined by multiplying:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the benefit determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>by</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the fraction which represents the ratio of the periods of contributions to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in relation to the minimum qualifying period required under that Plan to establish entitlement to that benefit, but in no case shall that fraction exceed the value of one.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPTER 3</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the Legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 13</Label><TitleText>Calculating the Amount of Benefit</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>In the case of persons who have accumulated sufficient periods of insurance under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco to be entitled to a benefit without taking into account the periods of insurance accumulated under the legislation of Canada, the competent institution of the Kingdom of Morocco shall determine the amount of the benefit payable in accordance with the provisions of the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco, taking into account only the periods of insurance accumulated under that legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 14</Label><TitleText>Payment of Benefit</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Benefits to which an insured person who has been subject to the legislation of both Parties is entitled under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco, shall be calculated as follows:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the competent institution of the Kingdom of Morocco shall determine, according to its own legislation, if the insured person meets the entitlement conditions to benefits under that legislation, taking into account the totalizing of periods specified in Articles 8 and 9,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if, after applying the totalizing provisions of subparagraph (a), the claimant is entitled to an old age, disability or survivors benefit under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco, the competent institution of the Kingdom of Morocco shall determine the theoretical benefit to which the insured person would be entitled if all the periods of insurance had been completed under its own legislation,</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the benefit payable to the insured person is established by reducing the amount of the theoretical benefit specified in subparagraph (b) by prorating the periods of insurance completed under the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco in relation to the total periods of insurance totalized through the application of Articles 8 and 9.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 15</Label><TitleText>Special Schemes</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>If in the application of the legislation of the Kingdom of Morocco, the entitlement to certain benefits is subject to the condition that the periods of insurance must have been completed in a profession subject to a special scheme, or in a particular profession or employment, then the periods of insurance completed under the legislation of Canada shall be taken into account to determine the entitlement to a benefit only if these periods of insurance were completed in the same profession or employment.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>If, taking into account the periods of insurance so completed, the person concerned does not fulfill the conditions required to be entitled to those benefits, such periods of insurance shall be taken into account for the entitlement to benefits under the general scheme.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 16</Label><TitleText>Payment of a Survivors’ Pension</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a death establishing entitlement to the payment of a survivors’ pension occurs before the worker became entitled to the payment of an old age pension, the benefits payable to his or her survivors shall be determined in accordance with the conditions specified in Article 14 of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>The widow’s pension eventually is divided, equally and definitively, between the beneficiaries, according to the conditions provided by the personal statute of the insured person.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Administrative and Miscellaneous Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 17</Label><TitleText>Administrative Arrangement</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Parties shall establish, by means of an administrative arrangement, the measures necessary for the application of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>The liaison agencies of the Parties shall be designated in that arrangement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 18</Label><TitleText>Exchange of Information and Mutual Assistance</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities and institutions responsible for the application of this Convention:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>shall, to the extent permitted by the legislation which they administer, communicate to each other any information necessary for the application of this Convention;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shall lend their good offices and furnish assistance to one another with regard to the determination of entitlement to and payment of any benefit under this Convention, or the legislation to which this Convention applies, as if the matter involved the application of their own legislation; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>shall communicate to each other, as soon as possible, all information about the measures taken by them for the application of this Convention or about changes in their respective legislation in so far as these changes affect the application of this Convention.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>The assistance referred to in subparagraph 1(b) shall be provided free of charge, subject to any provision contained in an Administrative Arrangement concluded pursuant to Article 17 for the reimbursement of certain types of expenses.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>3</Label><Text>Unless disclosure is required under the laws of a Party, any information about a person which is transmitted in accordance with this Convention to that Party by the other Party is confidential and shall be used only for purposes of implementing this Convention and the legislation to which this Convention applies.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 19</Label><TitleText>Exemption or Reduction of Taxes, Dues, Fees or Charges</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any exemption from or reduction of taxes, legal dues, consular fees or administrative charges for which provision is made in the legislation of a Party in connection with the issuing of any certificate or document required to be produced for the application of that legislation shall be extended to certificates or documents required to be produced for the application of the legislation of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any certificates or documents of an official nature required to be produced for the application of this Convention shall be exempt from any authentication by diplomatic or consular authorities and similar formality.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 20</Label><TitleText>Language of Communication</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the application of this Convention, the competent authorities and institutions of the Parties may communicate directly with one another in any official language of either Party.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>The competent institution of a Party may not refuse a document only because of the fact that the document is written in one of the official languages of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 21</Label><TitleText>Submitting Claims, Notices or Appeals</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any claim, notice or appeal concerning the determination or payment of a benefit under the legislation of a Party which should, for the purposes of that legislation, have been presented within a prescribed period to a competent authority or institution of that Party, but which is presented within the same period to an authority or institution of the other Party, shall be treated as if it had been presented to the competent institution of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>Unless the applicant requests that his or her claim for a benefit under the legislation of a Party be delayed, a claim for a benefit under the legislation of a Party, made after the date of entry into force of this Convention, shall be deemed to be a claim for the corresponding benefit under the legislation of the other Party, provided that the applicant, at the time of application:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>requests that it be considered an application under the legislation of the other Party, or</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provides information indicating that periods of insurance have been completed under the legislation of the other Party.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>3</Label><Text>In any case to which paragraph 1 or 2 applies, the authority or institution to which the claim, notice or appeal has been submitted shall transmit it without delay to the competent authority or institution of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 22</Label><TitleText>Payment of Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent institution of a Party shall discharge its obligations under this Convention in the currency of that Party.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>Benefits shall be paid to beneficiaries free from any deduction for administrative expenses that may be incurred in paying the benefits.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 23</Label><TitleText>Resolution of Disputes</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any dispute between the Parties concerning the interpretation or the application of this Convention, shall be resolved by direct negotiations between the competent authorities of the Parties.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>If the dispute cannot be resolved within a period of six months following the start of direct negotiations, it shall be submitted to an arbitral tribunal whose composition and procedures shall be determined by agreement between the Governments of the Parties. The arbitral tribunal shall resolve the dispute in accordance with the fundamental principles and spirit of this Convention. The decisions of the arbitral tribunal shall be final and binding.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 24</Label><TitleText>Understandings with a Province of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The relevant competent authorities of the Kingdom of Morocco and a province of Canada may conclude understandings concerning any social security matter within provincial jurisdiction in Canada in so far as those understandings are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Transitional and Final Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 25</Label><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any period of insurance completed before the date of entry into force of this Convention shall be taken into account for the purpose of determining the right to a benefit under this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>No provision of this Convention shall confer any right to receive a benefit for a period before the date of entry into force of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 2, a benefit, other than a lump sum payment, shall be paid under this Convention even though it relates to an event which happened before the date of entry into force of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 26</Label><TitleText>Duration and Denunciation</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall remain in force without any limitation on its duration. It may be denounced at any time by either Party giving written notification to the other Party. The denunciation shall be given no more than six months before the end of a calendar year; the Convention shall then cease to be in force at the end of that year.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the event this Convention ceases to be in force, any right acquired by a person in accordance with its provisions shall be maintained and negotiations shall take place for the settlement of any rights then in course of acquisition by virtue of those provisions.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 27</Label><TitleText>Entry into Force</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Convention shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received from the other Party written notification that it has complied with all statutory requirements for the entry into force of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis>, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Convention.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in two copies at Rabat, this 1<Sup>st</Sup> day of July, 1998, in the Arabic, English and French languages, each text being equally authentic.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="6"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="right">Pierre Pettigrew</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="italic">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="6"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="right">Khalid Alioua</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="italic">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE KINGDOM OF MOROCCO</Emphasis></Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>