<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2016-04-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-04-15" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629035" lims:id="629035" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629036" lims:id="629036"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2016-21</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629038" lims:id="629038"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11">FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629039" lims:id="629039">Certain Unauthorized Payments in Respect of Travel Expenses and Other Expenses, Allowances and Benefits (Canadian Forces) Remission Order</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2016-231</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2016</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629040" lims:id="629040"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629041" lims:id="629041" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, considering that the collection of debts for certain unauthorized payments in respect of travel expenses and other expenses, allowances and benefits is unreasonable and unjust, on the recommendation of the Minister of National Defence and the Treasury Board, pursuant to subsection 23(2.1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_3708_hq_11819">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_3708_hq_11820">b</FootnoteRef>, makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-2016-21">Certain Unauthorized Payments in Respect of Travel Expenses and Other Expenses, Allowances and Benefits (Canadian Forces) Remission Order</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_3708_hq_11819" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1991, c. 24, s. 7(2)</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_3708_hq_11820" placement="page" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>R.S., c. F-11</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629042" lims:id="629042"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629043" lims:id="629043" level="1"><TitleText>Remission</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629044" lims:id="629044"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to section 2, remission is granted, in a total amount of $147,487,513 including interest, to any beneficiary of unauthorized payments in respect of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629045" lims:id="629045"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>separation expenses paid during the period beginning on September 1, 2001 and ending on January 31, 2011</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629046" lims:id="629046"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to an officer or non-commissioned member who was a member of the reserve force on Class “B” Reserve Service and who would have been entitled to separation expenses under instruction 209.997 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Compensation and Benefits Instructions for the Canadian Forces</XRefExternal> had they been a member of the reserve force on Class “C” Reserve Service during the relevant period, in respect of any category of separation expense, up to the amounts that were authorized at that time under that instruction or fixed at that time under the authority of the Chief of the Defence Staff,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629047" lims:id="629047"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to an officer or non-commissioned member, in respect of lodging, to the extent that the expenses exceeded amounts authorized at that time by instruction 209.997, up to the amounts that were fixed at that time under the authority of the Chief of the Defence Staff,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629048" lims:id="629048"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to an officer or non-commissioned member returning from temporary duty or attached posting, in respect of interim lodging and meal costs, up to the amounts that were fixed at that time under the authority of the Chief of the Defence Staff,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629049" lims:id="629049"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>to an officer or non-commissioned member, in respect of lease liability costs, furniture rental, and one-time connection fees for cable, Internet, cellular telephones and land-line telephones, up to the amounts that were fixed at that time under the authority of the Chief of the Defence Staff, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629050" lims:id="629050"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>to an officer or non-commissioned member who married another officer or non-commissioned member at a time when the two were not posted to the same location;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629051" lims:id="629051"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>travel expenses for next of kin of an ill, injured, deceased or released officer or non-commissioned member paid from the Canadian Forces Contingency Fund during the period beginning on April 1, 2007 and ending on January 31, 2011;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629052" lims:id="629052"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>transportation on leave expenses of an officer or non-commissioned member that were purported to be authorized under instruction 209.50 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Compensation and Benefits Instructions for the Canadian Forces</XRefExternal>, up to the amounts that were fixed at that time under the authority of the Chief of the Defence Staff, paid during the period beginning on February 1, 2007 and ending on January 31, 2011;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629053" lims:id="629053"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>expenses for the storage of a private motor vehicle of an officer or non-commissioned member while they were absent on duty, up to the amounts that were fixed at that time under the authority of the Chief of the Defence Staff, paid during the period beginning on April 1, 2006 and ending on January 31, 2011;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629054" lims:id="629054"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>travel expenses of a person holding an honorary appointment under article 3.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Queen’s Regulations and Orders for the Canadian Forces</XRefExternal>, paid during the period beginning on January 1, 2005 and ending on January 31, 2011;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629055" lims:id="629055"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>expenses for the maintenance and safeguarding of a vacant residence of an officer or non-commissioned member while absent on duty, up to the amounts that were fixed at that time under the authority of the Chief of the Defence Staff, paid during the period beginning on September 1, 2001 and ending on January 31, 2011;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629056" lims:id="629056"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>temporary duty travel expenses and allowances of an officer or non-commissioned member, while on an attachment, up to the amounts that were fixed at that time under the authority of the Chief of the Defence Staff, paid during the period beginning on July 1, 2006 and ending on January 31, 2011;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629057" lims:id="629057"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>financial assistance for an ill, injured or released officer or non-commissioned member, or their family members, or for the family members of a deceased officer or non-commissioned member, paid during the period beginning on April 1, 1999 and ending on January 31, 2011;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629058" lims:id="629058"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>compassionate travel assistance for an officer or non-commissioned member that was purported to be authorized under instruction 209.51 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Compensation and Benefits Instructions for the Canadian Forces</XRefExternal>, paid during the period beginning on April 1, 2006 and ending on January 31, 2011;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629059" lims:id="629059"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>recruitment allowances for an officer or non-commissioned member, or for an applicant to the Canadian Forces, that were purported to be authorized under instruction 205.525 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Compensation and Benefits Instructions for the Canadian Forces</XRefExternal>, paid during the period beginning on May 1, 2002 and ending on October 31, 2005; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629060" lims:id="629060"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>vacation travel allowances paid during the period beginning on January 1, 2004 and ending on April 30, 2010, to Brian Donohue in the amount of $20,317, to Maria Groenewege in the amount of $16,732 and to Kathreen Siberry in the amount of $9,562.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629061" lims:id="629061"><Label>2</Label><Text>Amounts that have been recovered are not remitted.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629062" lims:id="629062"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629063" lims:id="629063"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Remission is granted to any accounting officer for the unrecovered amount of any unauthorized payments referred to in section 1, including payable interest, for which the officer is responsible.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-04-15" lims:fid="629064" lims:id="629064"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>accounting officer</DefinedTermEn> means any current or former <DefinedTermEn>accounting officer</DefinedTermEn>, as defined in article 1.02 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Queen’s Regulations and Orders for the Canadian Forces</XRefExternal>, or any other person who has performed the functions of such an officer.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Regulation>