<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2017-07-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2017-07-26" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631241" lims:id="631241" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631242" lims:id="631242"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2017-41</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2017</YYYY><MM>8</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631244" lims:id="631244"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631245" lims:id="631245">Proclamation giving notice of the entry into force on August 1, 2017 of the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security and the Implementing Agreement concerning the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631246" lims:id="631246"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631247" lims:id="631247" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">Stephen Wallace</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left">Deputy of the Governor General</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631248" lims:id="631248" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="20" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631249" lims:id="631249" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631250" lims:id="631250" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631251" lims:id="631251" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left" topmarginspacing="10">Nathalie G. Drouin</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left">Deputy Attorney General</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631252" lims:id="631252" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="30" list-item="no"><Text>TO ALL TO WHOM these presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631253" lims:id="631253" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="no"><Text>GREETING:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631254" lims:id="631254" format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-next="yes" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="30" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631255" lims:id="631255" level="1"><TitleText>A Proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631256" lims:id="631256" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas by Order in Council P.C. 2013-1380 of December 12, 2013, the Governor General in Council declared that, in accordance with Article 34 of the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security, and Article 10 of the Implementing Agreement concerning the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security, signed at Ottawa, on March 14, 2013, the Agreement and the Implementing Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received from the other Party written notification that it has complied with all requirements for the entry into force of the Agreements;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631257" lims:id="631257" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas that Order in Council was laid before the House of Commons and the Senate on January 30, 2014, as required under the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631258" lims:id="631258" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order had been laid before both houses of Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631259" lims:id="631259" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it had been laid before Parliament, being April 4, 2014;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631260" lims:id="631260" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the exchange of the notifications, through diplomatic channels, was completed in April 2017;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631261" lims:id="631261" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Agreements shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received from the other Party written notification that it has complied with all requirements for the entry into force of the Agreements, being August 1, 2017;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631262" lims:id="631262" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2017-0709 of June 9, 2017, the Governor in Council, pursuant to subsection 41(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, directed that a proclamation be issued giving notice of the entry into force on August 1, 2017 of the Agreements;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631263" lims:id="631263" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our proclamation give notice of the entry into force on August 1, 2017 of the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security and the Implementing Agreement concerning the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security, copies of which are annexed to this proclamation.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631264" lims:id="631264" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of all which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these presents may concern are required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631265" lims:id="631265" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN TESTIMONY WHEREOF, We have caused this Our Proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be affixed to it.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631266" lims:id="631266" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>WITNESS:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631267" lims:id="631267" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>STEPHEN WALLACE, Deputy of Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved David Johnston, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631268" lims:id="631268" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>AT OTTAWA, this twenty-sixth day of July in the year of Our Lord two thousand and seventeen and in the sixty-sixth year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631269" lims:id="631269" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="no"><Text>BY COMMAND,</Text><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left" topmarginspacing="20">John Knubley</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2017-07-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2017-07-26" lims:fid="631270" lims:id="631270" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Agreement Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE FRENCH REPUBLIC,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>hereinafter the “Contracting States”</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">RESOLVED</Emphasis> to strengthen the relationship between the Contracting States in the field of social security and to adapt the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement between Canada and France on Social Security</XRefExternal>, done at Ottawa on 9 February 1979, to reflect changes in national legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED</Emphasis> as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Definitions and General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>territory of a Contracting State</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for France: the territory of the European and Overseas Departments of the French Republic, as well as the overseas territorial unit of Saint-Pierre and Miquelon, including the territorial sea and, beyond that, the areas within which, in accordance with international law, the French Republic has sovereign rights for the purposes of exploring and exploiting the natural resources of the seabed and its subsoil and the superjacent waters;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for Canada: the territory of Canada including its land territory, internal waters and territorial sea, and includes the air space above these areas, as well as the exclusive economic zone and the continental shelf, as determined by its domestic law, consistent with international law.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>nationals of the Contracting States</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for France: persons of French nationality;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for Canada: citizens of Canada.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>legislation of a Contracting State</DefinedTermEn> means the laws and regulations specified in Article 2 for each Contracting State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for France: the Ministers responsible for the application of the legislation specified in Article 2(1)(a), each to the extent of their responsibility;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for Canada: the Ministers responsible for the application of the legislation specified in Article 2(1)(b), each to the extent of their responsibility.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>competent institution</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for France: the institutions responsible for the application of the legislation specified in Article 2(1)(a);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for Canada: the competent authority.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>insurance period</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for France: any period recognized as such by the legislation under which it was completed as well as any period recognized as equivalent to an insurance period;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for Canada: any period of contribution or residence that confers a right to a benefit under the legislation of Canada, including any period during which a disability benefit is payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any term not defined in this Article shall have the meaning assigned to it in the applicable legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label><TitleText>Scope of Application</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall apply to the following legislation:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>For France:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>legislation establishing the structure of social security;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>legislation establishing the social insurance plan for salaried employees in nonagricultural occupations and legislation concerning social insurance for salaried employees in agricultural occupations;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>legislation on prevention of and compensation for occupational accidents and illnesses; legislation concerning insurance against occupational accidents and illnesses for unsalaried workers in agricultural occupations;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>legislation relating to family benefits;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>legislation concerning special social security plans, except as otherwise provided in this Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>legislation concerning health and maternity insurance for self-employed workers in non-agricultural occupations and legislation concerning health, maternity, and disability insurance for self-employed workers in agricultural occupations;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>legislation concerning disability, old age, and death insurance for non-agricultural self-employed workers and legislation concerning old age insurance for self-employed workers in agricultural occupations, with the exception of the provisions regarding complementary retirement, and death and disability insurance for professional occupations;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>legislation concerning various plans for self-employed and equivalent to self-employed workers, with the exception of the provisions regarding complementary retirement, death, and disability insurance.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>For Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Notwithstanding paragraph 1(a), this Agreement shall not apply to any provisions that extend the right to enrol in voluntary insurance to a person who works or has worked outside the territory of France.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>This Agreement shall apply to all laws or regulations that amend or supplement the legislation set out in paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>This Agreement shall also apply to any law or regulation that extends an existing plan to other categories of beneficiaries, unless a Contracting State objects to the extension. A Contracting State that objects to applying this Agreement to that law or regulation shall, to this effect, notify the other Contracting State of its objection within three months of the date of the communication made in accordance with Article 25(b).</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label><TitleText>Understandings with the Provinces and Territories of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent authorities of France may conclude with the competent authorities of the provinces and territories of Canada understandings concerning any social security legislation within provincial and territorial jurisdiction, in particular legislation regarding health insurance, work accidents, family benefits, and pensions, provided that those understandings are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Agreement and with the applicable federal, provincial and territorial laws, and policies on the subject.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label><TitleText>Personal Scope</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall apply to persons who are or who have been subject to the legislation of one of the Contracting States, and to the dependants and survivors of those persons within the meaning of the applicable legislation, regardless of nationality or citizenship.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the case of France, subject to Article 23, this Agreement shall not apply to civil servants and military personnel of the State or to territorial and hospital employees under the jurisdiction of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other"><Language xml:lang="fr">Caisse nationale de retraite des agents des collectivités locales</Language></XRefExternal> or to State industrial establishments workers.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label><TitleText>Equality of Treatment</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to the specific restrictive provisions of this Agreement, any person who is, or who has been, subject to the legislation of one Contracting State as specified in Article 4 and who goes to the other Contracting State, is subject to the obligations of the legislation of the other Contracting State and shall receive treatment equal to that of nationals of that Contracting State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement, pensions, benefits, allowances, and death benefits acquired under the legislation of a Contracting State shall not be subject to any reduction, modification, suspension, cancellation, or confiscation by reason only of the fact that the beneficiary stays or resides in the territory of the other Contracting State or of a third State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label><TitleText>General Provisions Regarding Coverage</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A salaried worker in the territory of one of the Contracting States shall be subject only to the legislation of that Contracting State in respect of that work.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A self-employed worker in the territory of one of the Contracting States shall, in regard to that selfemployment, be subject only to the legislation of that State and, in the case of Canada, only if that person resides in Canada.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label><TitleText>Specific Provisions Regarding Coverage</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the coverage rules set out in Article 6 and in the legislation of the Contracting States:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Detached workers who are sent by their employer to carry out specific work in the other Contracting State shall not be subject to the legislation of that State in respect of that work and shall remain subject to the legislation of the sending Contracting State, provided that the detachment does not exceed three years, including holidays.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The prior approval of the competent authorities of both Contracting States or of their designated institutions is required to maintain coverage under the legislation of the sending Contracting State if a detachment must extend beyond three years.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Any worker who is detached from Canada to France is required to have valid health care coverage for the entire period of the detachment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>The terms and conditions for the application of this paragraph shall be set out in the Implementing Agreement referred to in Article 24.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the coverage rules set out in Article 6 and in the legislation of the Contracting States:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Persons who are working for a public or private international non-maritime transport enterprise of one Contracting State as crew members in the territory of the other Contracting State shall be subject only to the legislation of the Contracting State in which the enterprise has its headquarters.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The same shall apply to workers of the enterprises identified in sub-paragraph 2(a) detached to a Contracting State, provided that the duration of the detachment does not exceed the periods set out in paragraphs 1(a) or (b) and that it complies with the provisions set out in paragraph 1(c).</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 8</Label><TitleText>Members of Diplomatic Missions and Consular Posts</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement does not affect the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</XRefExternal> of 18 April 1961, or those of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Consular Relations</XRefExternal> of 24 April 1963.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The persons employed by a Contracting State sent by the government of that Contracting State to work in the territory of the other Contracting State and who are not excluded from the application of the legislation of the other Contracting State under the Conventions specified in paragraph 1 are subject only to the legislation of the first Contracting State in respect of that employment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to paragraphs 1 and 2, the persons hired by the government of a Contracting State in the territory of the other Contracting State to work in that other Contracting State are subject only to the legislation of the other Contracting State in respect of that employment.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 9</Label><TitleText>Exceptions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States or their designated institutions may, in particular cases, grant exceptions to Articles 6, 7, and 8, in the interest of certain persons or categories of persons.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States or their designated institutions shall jointly resolve any situations of double coverage that may arise in the interest of the persons concerned.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 10</Label><TitleText>Access to Voluntary Insurance</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>To establish eligibility for continued voluntary or optional coverage in accordance with the legislation of France, insurance periods completed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall, to the extent necessary, be considered as insurance periods completed under the legislation of France.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPTER ONE</Label><TitleText>Totalization</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 11</Label><TitleText>General Rules for Totalization</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If the legislation of a Contracting State requires the completion of insurance periods in order to establish, maintain or re-establish eligibility under a plan that is not a special plan within the meaning of Article 12, the competent institution of that Contracting State shall, to the extent necessary, and provided that the insurance periods do not overlap, consider the insurance periods completed under the legislation of the other Contracting State:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for Canada, under the conditions set out in paragraphs 2 and 3(a), as if those periods were completed under the applicable legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for France, under the conditions set out in paragraph 3(b), whether completed under a general or special plan, as if those periods were completed under the applicable legislation.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>To determine eligibility for a benefit under Canada’s <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, any insurance period under the legislation of France or any period of residence in France beginning on or after 1 January 1966 and after the age at which periods of residence in Canada may be considered under that Act, shall be considered as a period of residence in Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>3</Label><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>To determine eligibility for a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, any calendar year beginning on 1 January 1966 and including at least 78 days, 13 weeks, three months, or an insurance quarter under the legislation of France shall be considered as a year of contributions under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>To determine eligibility for a benefit under the legislation of France, a calendar year that is creditable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be considered as 312 days, 52 weeks, 12 months, or four insurance quarters under the legislation of France.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 12</Label><TitleText>Special Rules for Totalization</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If the legislation of France governing special plans provides that a person is eligible for certain benefits on the condition that the insurance periods be completed in a specified profession or employment, then periods completed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be taken into account in determining that person’s eligibility for those benefits only if the periods are completed in that same profession or employment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>If, taking into account the totalization set out in paragraph 1, a person does not meet the eligibility requirements under the special plan, insurance periods completed under that plan shall be taken into account in accordance with the rules governing the general plan and subject to the conditions set out in the legislation of France.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 13</Label><TitleText>Totalization of Insurance Periods Completed in a Third State</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>With respect to France, insurance periods completed in a third State with which both Contracting States are bound by social security agreements that provide for the totalizing of insurance periods shall be taken into account to determine the amount of the old age or survivor’s benefit payable under this Agreement, insofar as they do not overlap with insurance periods completed in Canada. Only periods recognized for totalization under the agreement between France and the third State shall be taken into account.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>With respect to Canada, if insurance periods completed in the two Contracting States and totalized in accordance with Article 11 are insufficient to establish eligibility for benefits under the legislation of Canada, periods of insurance or residence completed in a third State with which both Contracting States are bound by social security agreements providing for the totalizing of insurance periods shall be taken into account, provided that they do not overlap with periods of insurance or residence completed in France. Only periods recognized for totalization under the agreement between Canada and the third State shall be taken into account.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 14</Label><TitleText>Minimum Insurance Period</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If the total duration of insurance periods completed under the legislation of a Contracting State is less than one year, the competent institution shall not be required to apply the totalization set out in Articles 11, 12 and 13 to confer a benefit. However, if those insurance periods are sufficient to establish eligibility for a benefit under that legislation, the benefit shall then be payable based only on those periods.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The periods set out in paragraph 1 may nonetheless be taken into account to establish eligibility for, and to determine the amount of a benefit under the legislation of the other Contracting State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPITRE 2</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the Legislation of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 15</Label><TitleText>Definition of Certain Periods of Residence with respect to the Legislation of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of calculating the amount of benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>If a person is subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during any period of presence or residence in France, that period shall be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person, as well as for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with that person and who are not subject to the legislation of France by reason of employment or self-employment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>If a person is subject to the legislation of France during any period of presence or residence in Canada, that period for that person, and for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with them, shall be determined according to the provisions of the legislation of Canada.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 1:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A person shall be considered to be subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during a period of presence or residence in France only if that person contributes to the plan in question during that period.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>A person shall be considered to be subject to the legislation of France during a period of presence or residence in Canada only if that person makes compulsory contributions pursuant to that legislation during that period by reason of employment and self-employment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 16</Label><TitleText>Calculation of Benefits Under the Old Age Security Act</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is eligible for a benefit or an allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter One of this Part, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of the benefit or allowance payable to that person in accordance with the provisions of that Act governing the payment of a partial benefit or allowance, exclusively on the basis of the periods of residence in Canada that may be considered under that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>If a person is entitled to a benefit in Canada without recourse to the provisions of this Agreement but has not resided in Canada for the minimum period required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> to be eligible for the benefit outside Canada, the benefit shall be paid to the person outside Canada, only if the period of insurance or residence, when totalized in accordance with Chapter One of this Part, is at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> to be entitled to the payment of a benefit outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The competent institution in Canada shall not be required to pay an Old Age Security benefit to a person who is outside Canada unless that person’s periods of insurance or residence, when totalized as provided in Chapter One of this Part, are at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of a benefit outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The allowance and the guaranteed income supplement shall be paid to a person who is outside Canada only to the extent permitted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 17</Label><TitleText>Calculation of Benefits Under the Canada Pension Plan</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For all benefits other than the disability benefit, death benefit and disabled contributor’s child’s benefit, if a person is eligible for a benefit solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter One of this Part, the competent institution of Canada shall determine the amount of the benefit payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The earnings-related portion of the benefit shall be determined in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, exclusively on the basis of the pensionable earnings under that Plan.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The flat-rate portion of the benefit shall be determined by multiplying:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the benefit determined in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>by</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the fraction that represents the ratio of the periods of contributions to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in relation to the minimum qualifying period required under that Plan to establish eligibility for that benefit, but in no case shall that fraction exceed the value of one.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>With respect to the disability benefit, disabled contributor’s child’s benefit and death benefit, if a person is eligible for a benefit solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter One of this Part, the competent institution of Canada shall determine the amount of the benefit payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>If the disability or death occurs while the person is a resident of Canada within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> or is contributing to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the earnings-related portion of the benefit shall be determined in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, exclusively on the basis of the pensionable earnings under that Plan;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the flat-rate component is payable in its entirety.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>If the disability or death occurs under any circumstances other than those set out in paragraph 2(a), the competent institution of Canada shall not make any benefit payment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>CHAPITRE 3</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the Legislation of France</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 18</Label><TitleText>Calculation of Old Age or Survivor’s Benefits – France</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person who is, or who has been, subject successively or alternately to the legislation of each Contracting State, meets the eligibility criteria for an old age or survivor’s benefit under the legislation of France, the competent institution shall determine the amount of the benefit, first, in accordance with the applicable legislation taking into account only the insurance periods completed under that legislation and, second, in accordance with paragraph 2, the most advantageous outcome for the person shall be applied.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>If a person does not meet the eligibility conditions set out under the legislation of France without the application of the totalization of insurance periods, or for the purpose of determining the most advantageous outcome in accordance with paragraph 1, the competent institution of France shall determine that person’s entitlement to the benefit as if all insurance periods completed in the other Contracting State and in one or more third States with which both Contracting States are bound by a social security agreement were completed exclusively under the legislation of France. The competent institution of France shall then reduce the amount of the benefit thus determined by a pro-rata amount based on the ratio of the length of the insurance periods completed under the applicable legislation before the date on which the contingency occurred to the total length of the insurance periods completed under the legislation of the Contracting States and one or more third States before the date on which the contingency occurred. The total length of the periods shall not exceed the maximum period that may be required under the applicable legislation for entitlement to a full benefit.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>If, in accordance with the legislation of France, the benefits payable are based on the salary or average income for all or a portion of the insurance period, the salary or average income taken into account for the calculation of the benefit by the competent institution or institutions of France shall only be based on the insurance period completed under the legislation applied by that institution.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 19</Label><TitleText>Cases of Successive Application of Legislation</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person requests the determination of their eligibility solely under the legislation of France, without the determination of eligibility under the legislation of Canada, the amount of the benefit payable under the legislation of France shall be calculated in accordance with Article 18(1) or (2), as applicable.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>If entitlement to a benefit is subsequently determined under the legislation of Canada, there is not a requirement to recalculate the entitlement previously determined under the legislation of France.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 20</Label><TitleText>Determination of a Disability Benefit – France</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>1</Label><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A disability benefit shall be determined under the legislation of France if the person is subject to that legislation at the time of the work interruption and the disability which follows.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>This determination shall be made taking into account the totalization of insurance periods in accordance with Article 11 (1), or Article 12, if totalization is required to establish eligibility for the benefit.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>In the application of the totalizing provisions, the conversion rules shall be those set out in Article 11 (3)(b), with one day being equivalent to eight hours of work.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>If the interruption of work and the disability which follows occurs while a person is subject to the legislation of Canada, any outstanding entitlement to a benefit under the legislation of France without recourse to the totalization of insurance periods, shall be determined solely in accordance with the legislation of France.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>When calculating the amount of the benefit, the competent institution of France shall apply the average annual salary that corresponds to the insurance periods completed under its legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 21</Label><TitleText>Determination of Eligibility to a Death Benefit – France</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Persons insured under the legislation of France shall be eligible for death benefits under that legislation taking into account, if applicable, periods of insurance completed in Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>When the death occurs while a person is subject to the legislation of Canada, any outstanding entitlement to a benefit under the legislation of France shall be established solely in accordance with the legislation of France, without recourse to the totalization of insurance periods.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 22</Label><TitleText>Family Benefits – France</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Workers who are detached to Canada by their employer and who are subject to the legislation of France through the application of Articles 7 and 9 shall be entitled to receive, for the children who accompany them, the family benefits identified in the general Implementing Agreement referred to in Article 24.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 23</Label><TitleText>Public Service Plans</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The provisions of this Chapter shall not be applicable to special plans of France covering State civil servants or military personnel, territorial or hospital employees under the jurisdiction of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other"><Language xml:lang="fr">Caisse nationale de retraite des agents des collectivités locales</Language></XRefExternal>, or State industrial establishments workers.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Notwithstanding paragraph 1, when determining the amount of the benefit, the special plans referred to in paragraph 1 shall take into account the insurance periods completed under the legislation of Canada in determining the duration of the insurance periods completed under one or more other mandatory basic retirement plans.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>TITRE III</Label><TitleText>Miscellaneous Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 24</Label><TitleText>Implementing Agreement</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall conclude an Implementing Agreement that establishes the terms and conditions for the application of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Implementing Agreement shall designate the liaison agencies of the Contracting States.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Implementing Agreement shall prescribe the framework for the establishment and approval of the forms and certificates required to apply this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 25</Label><TitleText>Mutual Assistance</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>communicate to each other any information necessary for the application of this Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>communicate directly to each other any information concerning amendments made to the legislation or regulations specified in Article 2, if these amendments affect the application of this Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>jointly address any technical difficulties that may arise in the application of the provisions of this Agreement or of the Implementing Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>notify each other of the entry into force of social security agreements with third States that include provisions for totalization.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 26</Label><TitleText>Exchange of Information</TitleText></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>1</Label><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>For the application of this Agreement and the legislation specified in Article 2, the competent authorities and institutions shall lend their good offices as if the matter involved the application of their own legislation.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>They shall communicate to each other any information required for the purposes of this Agreement and the legislation of the Contracting States specified in Article 2, in particular:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the personal information and supporting evidence necessary for the competent institution of a Contracting State to process a claim for a benefit submitted by the liaison agency or competent institution of the other Contracting State. The following conditions shall apply:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-3-3"><Label>(A)</Label><Text>the personal information transmitted for that purpose shall be certified by the competent institution of the other Contracting State, which shall confirm that the information is corroborated by supporting evidence. The transmission of the certified claim form shall exempt the competent institution of that State from sending the corresponding supporting evidence.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-3-3"><Label>(B)</Label><Text>the personal information to which this paragraph applies shall be jointly determined and indicated on the corresponding forms.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>on request and to the extent permitted by the applicable legislation, medical information and documentation that are available regarding the disability of an applicant or beneficiary.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Unless its disclosure is required under the legislation of a Contracting State, any information provided in accordance with paragraph 1 shall be used solely for the purposes of applying this Agreement and the legislation to which this Agreement applies. A Contracting State shall not disclose, to a third party, personal information obtained from the other Contracting State unless the other Contracting State is notified and consents to the disclosure, and the information is disclosed only for the purposes for which it was originally obtained.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 27</Label><TitleText>Exemption or Reduction of Taxes, Dues, Fees and Charges</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any exemptions or reductions of taxes, stamp fees, court fees, or registration fees prescribed by the legislation of one Contracting State for supporting evidence or other documents required to be produced to apply the legislation of that Contracting State shall extend to supporting evidence or other documents required to be produced to apply the legislation of the other Contracting State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>All acts, documents and supporting evidence that are required for the application of this Agreement shall be exempt from notarization.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 28</Label><TitleText>Languages of Communication</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>For the purposes of this Agreement, the competent authorities and institutions of the Contracting States may communicate directly with each other in their official languages.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 29</Label><TitleText>Submission of a Claim, Notice or Appeal</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Claims, notices and appeals on social security matters which are required to be submitted within a specified period to the competent authority or institution or jurisdiction of one of the Contracting States authorized to accept them, shall be acceptable if they have been presented within the same specified period to a corresponding competent authority or institution or jurisdiction of the other Contracting State. If so, the claims, notices and appeals must be sent without delay to the competent authority or institution or jurisdiction of the first State.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>2</Label><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Unless an applicant expressly indicates that their claim does not concern the other Contracting State, a claim for a benefit under the legislation of one Contracting State presented after the entry into force of this Agreement shall be considered a corresponding request for a benefit under the legislation of the other Contracting State, provided that, at the time of application, the applicant:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>requests that it be considered as such; or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>provides information indicating that periods of insurance or residence have been completed under the legislation of the other Contracting State.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Old age and disability benefits shall be considered to correspond if, at the time the applicant submits the claim for benefits, the applicant expressly indicates that the claim may be determined for disability insurance in one Contracting State and for old age insurance in the other, given the different age requirements set out under the legislation of the Contracting States.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 30</Label><TitleText>Dispute Resolution</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any disputes regarding the interpretation or application of this Agreement shall be resolved by the competent authorities of the Contracting States.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Contracting States shall consult each other without delay at the request of either Contracting State concerning matters which have not been resolved by the competent authorities in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Transitional and Final Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 31</Label><TitleText>Consideration of Periods and Events Prior to the Entry into Force of this Agreement and Other Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of paragraph 4, this Agreement shall not confer any right to the payment of benefits in respect of any period prior to the date on which this Agreement enters into force.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>All insurance periods completed under the legislation of either Contracting State prior to the entry into force of this Agreement shall be taken into account to determine the right to benefits under the provisions of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of paragraph 1, a benefit, other than a death benefit payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, shall be paid under this Agreement in respect of events that occurred prior to the entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>Claims for benefits under consideration on the date of entry into force of this Agreement and claims for benefits received after that date that relate to a past event establishing entitlement to benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement between Canada and France on Social Security</XRefExternal>, done at Ottawa on 9 February 1979, shall be determined in accordance with that agreement for rights established up to the date of entry into force of this Agreement and in accordance with this Agreement for rights arising from this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 32</Label><TitleText>Repeal of Prior Agreements and Review of Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>With the entry into force of this Agreement, the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement between Canada and France on Social Security and the Protocol between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security</XRefExternal>, done at Ottawa on 9 February 1979, shall be repealed.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>2</Label><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>At the request of a person or on the initiative of the competent institution of a Contracting State, entitlement to a benefit acquired prior to the entry into force of this Agreement may be reviewed taking into account the provisions of this Agreement. This review shall confer to these persons, from the date of entry into force of this Agreement, the same rights as though this Agreement had been in force when the benefits were paid.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>If a request for review is submitted to a competent institution within 24 months from the date of entry into force of this Agreement, the effective date of payment of the revised benefit shall be the date of entry into force of this Agreement, regardless of the provisions set out under the legislation of the Contracting States concerning the forfeiture, acquisition or expiration of rights.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>If a request for review is submitted to a competent institution after the 24-month period has expired, the effective date of payment of the revised benefit shall be the date on which the request was submitted.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>The review shall not result in a reduction in the amount of the benefit.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 33</Label><TitleText>Duration and Termination</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall remain in force for an indefinite period. A Contracting State may terminate this Agreement by giving notice, in writing, to the other Contracting State through diplomatic channels. If this Agreement is terminated, it shall cease to have effect on the first day of the twelfth month following the date of receipt of the notice.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the event of the termination of this Agreement, the Contracting Parties shall maintain any right acquired by a person in accordance with the provisions of this Agreement and shall hold negotiations to settle any right then in the course of acquisition by virtue of those provisions.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 34</Label><TitleText>Entry into Force</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Each Contracting State shall notify the other, through diplomatic channels, of the completion of its constitutional or legislative procedures necessary for the entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the date of receipt of the last notification.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis>, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective governments, have signed this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> at Ottawa, this 14th day of March 2013, in duplicate, in the English and French languages, each version being equally authentic.</Text><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" /><colspec colname="col2" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>James M. Flaherty</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Yamina Benguigui</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE FRENCH REPUBLIC</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Implementing Agreement Concerning the Agreement Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE FRENCH REPUBLIC,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>hereinafter the “Contracting States”,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN ACCORDANCE</Emphasis> with Article 24 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security</XRefExternal>, done at Ottawa on 14 March 2013.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED</Emphasis> as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Implementing Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security</XRefExternal>, at Ottawa on March 14th, 2013.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>Implementing Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means this <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Implementing Agreement concerning the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the French Republic on Social Security</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any other term has the meaning assigned to it in the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label><TitleText>Liaison Agencies</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent authorities shall designate the following as their liaison agencies, in accordance with Article 24(2) of the Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for France:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2.5" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Label>–</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="other"><Language xml:lang="fr">Centre des liaisons européennes et internationales de sécurité sociale</Language></XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the International Operations Division, Service Canada, for all matters except the application of Articles 6 to 9 of the Agreement and Part II of this Implementing Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Legislative Policy Directorate, Canada Revenue Agency, for the application of Articles 6 to 9 of the Agreement and Part II of this Implementing Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning Applicable Legislation</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label><TitleText>Detached Workers</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>In the cases referred to in Article 7(1)(a) and 7(2)(b) of the Agreement, the agencies identified below shall issue, at the employer’s request, a certificate of coverage indicating which legislation applies to a detached worker and the period for which that legislation applies.</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The certificate shall be issued:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>as regards France,</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2.5" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Label>–</Label><Text>by the fund that covers the salaried worker or, in regard to salaried employees in the general plan, by the fund for the district where the employer is located;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>as regards Canada,</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2.5" subsequent-line-indent="2.5"><Label>–</Label><Text>by the Canada Revenue Agency.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The certificate of coverage issued in accordance with the preceding paragraph is kept by the employer receiving the detached salaried worker abroad. In this case, the certificate establishes that the worker is exempt from the legislation of the Contracting State where the temporary workplace is located. Employers established in Canada that employ salaried employees detached to France are required to certify that the worker has health care coverage as set out in Article 7(1)(c) of the Agreement. Dependants who accompany the worker are also required to have this coverage unless they are subject to the legislation of France as a result of a professional activity.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>3</Label><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>If the duration of the initial detachment exceeds the period set out in Article 7(1)(a) of the Agreement, prior to the end of that period:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the employer established in Canada is required to submit to the Canada Revenue Agency the application to extend a detachment from Canada to France;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the employer established in France is required to submit to the <XRefExternal reference-type="other"><Language xml:lang="fr">Centre des liaisons européennes et internationales de sécurité sociale</Language></XRefExternal> the application to extend a detachment from France to Canada.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>If the liaison agency receiving the application deems that an extension is warranted, it shall request the consent of the liaison agency of the Contracting State that receives the detached salaried worker. The employer is notified on receipt of this consent, and a new certificate of coverage is issued by the agencies referred to in paragraph 1. The provisions of paragraph 2 shall then apply.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of Article 9 of the Agreement, a person or a category of persons can obtain an exemption from the legislation of the other Contracting State through the procedure described in paragraph 3.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>The competent institution of a Contracting State that issues the above-mentioned certificate shall then send a copy of this certificate to the liaison agency of the other Contracting State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>6</Label><Text>Salaried workers who are detached for the periods provided for in Article 7 of the Agreement are not eligible for a new detachment prior to the end of a one-year period, subject to the provisions of Article 9(1) of the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>part III</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label><TitleText>Processing a Claim</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent institution of a Contracting State that receives a claim for a benefit under the legislation of the other Contracting State shall promptly send the claim to the liaison agency or the competent institution of the other Contracting State indicating the date on which the claim was received.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The documents submitted by the competent institution of the first Contracting State pursuant to paragraph 1 shall include:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the benefit application form completed in accordance with Article 26(1)(b)(i) of the Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>all supporting evidence that the competent institution of the second Contracting State may require to determine whether an applicant is eligible for the benefit;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a liaison form indicating the insurance periods under the legislation of the first Contracting State.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The competent institution of the second Contracting State shall subsequently determine the applicant’s eligibility and notify the competent institution of the other Contracting State of any benefits granted to the applicant.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label><TitleText>Agreements with Third States</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>For the application of Article 13 of the Agreement, the Contracting States shall provide one another with a list of social security agreements concluded with third States. This list, set out in Annex 1, is updated as new agreements with third States enter into force.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label><TitleText>Family Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>For the purposes of Article 22 of the Agreement, the term <DefinedTermEn>family benefits</DefinedTermEn> includes:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>family allowances;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>birth and adoption premiums.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label><TitleText>Exchange of Statistics</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent institution for Canada and the liaison agency for France shall exchange, on an annual basis, statistics regarding the benefits paid under the Agreement. These statistics shall include data on the number of beneficiaries and the total amount of benefits paid, disaggregated by type of benefit.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Other Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 8</Label><TitleText>Forms and Detailed Procedures</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Pursuant to Article 24(3) of the Agreement, the format and content of the certificates and forms required to implement the Agreement and this Implementing Agreement shall be jointly established by the liaison agencies referred to in Article 2 of this Implementing Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The certificates and forms established in accordance with paragraph 1 are submitted for validation to the competent authorities of the Contracting States. The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall notify each other of the validated forms and certificates.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The forms established in accordance with paragraphs 1 and 2 may only be amended jointly by the competent authorities of the Contracting States. The forms specific to each Contracting State may be amended unilaterally provided that the other Contracting State is immediately notified:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for France, through the liaison agency;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for Canada, through the competent institution.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>The forms and certificates shall contain information relating to:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the applicable legislation, including the information described in Part II of this Implementing Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>all information that may be useful to the competent institutions to process a payment for invalidity, old age, or survivor’s benefits to implement the provisions of Part II of the Agreement, including: civil status, family situation, statement of insurance periods and other information about the applicant’s professional career, medical reports for assessing applications for disability benefits.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>The competent institution or liaison agency of a Contracting State may refuse to process an application for benefits that is not submitted on the prescribed form and may request that it be submitted on a form prescribed by this Implementing Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 9</Label><TitleText>Duration</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Implementing Agreement is valid for the same period as the Agreement, in accordance with Article 33(1) of the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Implementing Agreement ceases to have effect on the date that the Agreement ceases to have effect, in accordance with Article 33 of the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 10</Label><TitleText>Entry into Force</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Each Contracting State shall notify the other, through diplomatic channels, of the completion of its constitutional or legislative procedures necessary for the entry into force of this Implementing Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Implementing Agreement enters into force on the first day of the fourth month following the date of receipt of the last notification.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis>, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective governments, have signed this Implementing Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> at Ottawa, this 14th day of March 2013, in duplicate, in the English and French languages, each version being equally authentic.</Text><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec align="left" char="" charoff="50" colname="COLSPEC0" colsep="0" colwidth="1.00*" /><colspec colname="col1" colsep="0" /><tbody><row><entry><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>James M. Flaherty</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Yamina Benguigui</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE FRENCH REPUBLIC</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="8" spanlanguages="yes" topmarginspacing="10"><Caption position="over">APPENDIX 1</Caption><table><title>International Agreements on Social Security to Which Canada is a Signatory</title><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.97*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.01*" /><colspec colname="col3" colwidth="1.01*" /><thead><row><entry align="center" valign="bottom"><Emphasis style="bold">COUNTRY</Emphasis></entry><entry align="center" valign="bottom"><Emphasis style="bold">SIGNING OF AGREEMENT</Emphasis></entry><entry align="center" valign="bottom"><Emphasis style="bold">ENTRY INTO FORCE</Emphasis></entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry rowheader="yes">Antigua and Barbuda</entry><entry>September 2, 1992</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1994</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Australia</entry><entry>July 4, 1988</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">September 1, 1989</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Austria</entry><entry>February 24, 1987</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">November 1, 1987</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Barbados</entry><entry>February 11, 1985</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1986</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Belgium</entry><entry>May 10, 1984</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1987</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Brazil</entry><entry>August 8, 2011</entry><entry /></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Bulgaria</entry><entry>October 5, 2012</entry><entry /></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Chile</entry><entry>November 18, 1996</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">June 1, 1998</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Croatia</entry><entry>April 22, 1998</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">May 1, 1999</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Cyprus</entry><entry>January 24, 1990</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">May 1, 1991</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Czech Republic</entry><entry>May 24, 2001</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 2003</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Denmark</entry><entry>April 12, 1985</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1986</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Dominica</entry><entry>January 14, 1988</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1989</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Estonia</entry><entry>February 21, 2005</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">November 1, 2006</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Finland</entry><entry>October 28, 1986</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">February 1, 1988</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">France</entry><entry>February 9, 1979</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">March 1, 1981</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Germany</entry><entry>November 14, 1985</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">April 1, 1988</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Greece</entry><entry>May 7, 1981</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">May 1, 1983</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Grenada</entry><entry>January 8, 1998</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">February 1, 1999</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Hungary</entry><entry>March 4, 2002</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">October 1, 2003</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Iceland</entry><entry>June 25, 1988</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">October 1, 1989</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">India</entry><entry>November 6, 2012</entry><entry /></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Ireland</entry><entry>November 29, 1990</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1992</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Israel<FootnoteRef idref="fn_a">a</FootnoteRef></entry><entry>April 9, 2000</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">September 1, 2003</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Italy</entry><entry>November 17, 1977</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1979</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Jamaica</entry><entry>January 10, 1983</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1984</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Japan</entry><entry>February 15, 2006</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">March 1, 2008</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Jersey, Guernsey</entry><entry>February 12, 1993</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1994</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Korea</entry><entry>January 10, 1997</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">May 1, 1999</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Latvia</entry><entry>June 29, 2005</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">November 1, 2006</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Lithuania</entry><entry>July 5, 2005</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">November 1, 2006</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Luxembourg</entry><entry>May 22, 1986</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">April 1, 1990</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Macedonia</entry><entry>August 26, 2009</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">November 1, 2011</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Malta</entry><entry>April 4, 1991</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">March 1, 1992</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Mexico</entry><entry>April 27, 1995</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">May 1, 1996</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Morocco</entry><entry>July 1, 1998</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">March 1, 2010</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Netherlands</entry><entry>February 26, 1987</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">October 1, 1990</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">New Zealand</entry><entry>April 9, 1996</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">May 1, 1997</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Norway</entry><entry>November 12, 1985</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1987</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Philippines</entry><entry>September 9, 1994</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">March 1, 1997</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Poland</entry><entry>April 2, 2008</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">October 1, 2009</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Portugal</entry><entry>December 15, 1980</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">May 1, 1981</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Romania</entry><entry>November 19, 2009</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">November 1, 2011</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Saint Vincent and the Grenadines</entry><entry>January 6, 1998</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">November 1, 1998</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Slovakia</entry><entry>May 21, 2001</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 2003</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Slovenia</entry><entry>May 17, 1998</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 2001</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Spain</entry><entry>November 10, 1986</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1988</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Saint Kitts and Nevis</entry><entry>August 17, 1992</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1994</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">St. Lucia</entry><entry>January 5, 1987</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1988</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Sweden</entry><entry>April 10, 1985</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 1986</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Switzerland</entry><entry>February 24, 1994</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">October 1, 1995</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Trinidad and Tobago</entry><entry>April 9, 1997</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">July 1, 1999</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Turkey</entry><entry>June 19, 1998</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 2005</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">United Kingdom<FootnoteRef idref="fn_a">a</FootnoteRef></entry><entry>January 16, 1997</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">April 1, 1998</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">United States</entry><entry>March 11, 1981</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">August 1, 1984</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Uruguay</entry><entry>June 2, 1999</entry><entry><Emphasis style="bold">January 1, 2002</Emphasis></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><Footnote id="fn_a" placement="table" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>Limited agreement dealing only with the obligation to make contributions; does not contain provisions that provide for the totalizing of periods to assist in qualifying for benefits.</Text></Footnote></TableGroup><TableGroup pointsize="8" spanlanguages="yes" topmarginspacing="10"><table><title>International Agreements on Social Security to Which France is a Signatory</title><tgroup cols="4"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.92*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="0.99*" /><colspec colname="COLSPEC0" colwidth="1.37*" /><colspec colname="col3" colwidth="0.74*" /><thead><row><entry align="center" morerows="1" valign="bottom"><Emphasis style="bold">States Affected by Community Regulations Nos. 883/2004 and 987/2009 (since May 1, 2010)</Emphasis></entry><entry align="center" nameend="col3" namest="col2" valign="top"><Emphasis style="bold">States and entities with a Bilateral Agreement on Social Security with France</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry align="center" valign="top"><Emphasis style="bold">Signatory</Emphasis></entry><entry align="center" valign="top"><Emphasis style="bold">Signing of Agreement</Emphasis></entry><entry align="center" valign="top"><Emphasis style="bold">Entry into Force</Emphasis></entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry rowheader="yes">Austria</entry><entry>Algeria</entry><entry align="center">01.10.1980</entry><entry align="center">01.02.1982</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Belgium</entry><entry>Andorra</entry><entry align="center">12.12.2000</entry><entry align="center">01.06.2003</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Bulgaria</entry><entry>Argentina</entry><entry align="center">22.09.2008</entry><entry align="center">01.11.2012</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Cyprus</entry><entry>Benin</entry><entry align="center">06.11.1979</entry><entry align="center">01.09.1981</entry></row><row><entry morerows="1" rowheader="yes">Czech Republic</entry><entry>Bosnia and Herzegovina</entry><entry align="center"><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>03 and 04.12.2003</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(application of the bilateral convention of 5/1/1950 with the former Yugoslavia)</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="center">04.12.2003</entry></row><row><entry>Brazil</entry><entry align="center">15.12.2011</entry><entry align="center" /></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Denmark</entry><entry>Cameroon</entry><entry align="center">05.11.1990</entry><entry align="center">01.03.1992</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Estonia</entry><entry>Canada</entry><entry align="center">09.02.1979</entry><entry align="center">01.03.1981</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Finland</entry><entry>Cap Verde</entry><entry align="center">15.01.1980</entry><entry align="center">01.04.1983</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Germany</entry><entry>Chile</entry><entry align="center">25.06.1999</entry><entry align="center">01.09.2001</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Greece</entry><entry>Congo</entry><entry align="center">11.02.1987</entry><entry align="center">01.06.1988</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Hungary</entry><entry>Côte d’Ivoire</entry><entry align="center">16.01.1985</entry><entry align="center">01.01.1987</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Iceland</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(since June 1, 2012)</Text></Provision></entry><entry>Croatia</entry><entry align="center"><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>09 and 12.10.1995</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(application of the bilateral convention of 5/1/1950 with the former Yugoslavia)</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="center">12.10.1995</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Ireland</entry><entry>Gabon</entry><entry align="center">02.10.1980</entry><entry align="center">01.02.1983</entry></row><row><entry morerows="1" rowheader="yes">Italy</entry><entry>Guernsey, Alderney, Herm, Jethou</entry><entry align="center"><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>10.07.1956</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(bilateral convention of 10/7/1956 with the United Kingdom)</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="center">01.05.1958</entry></row><row><entry>India</entry><entry align="center">30.09.2008</entry><entry align="center">01.07.2011</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Latvia</entry><entry>Israel</entry><entry align="center">17.12.1965</entry><entry align="center">01.10.1966</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Liechtenstein</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(since June 1, 2012)</Text></Provision></entry><entry /><entry align="center" /><entry align="center" /></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Lithuania</entry><entry>Japan</entry><entry align="center">25.02.2005</entry><entry align="center">01.06.2007</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Luxembourg</entry><entry>Jersey</entry><entry align="center">10.07.1956</entry><entry align="center">01.05.1958</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Malta</entry><entry>Korea</entry><entry align="center">06.12.2004</entry><entry align="center">01.06.2007</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Netherlands</entry><entry>Macedonia</entry><entry align="center"><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>13 and 14.12.1995</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(application of the bilateral convention of 5/1/1950 with the former Yugoslavia)</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="center">14.12.1995</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Norway</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(since June 1, 2012)</Text></Provision></entry><entry>Madagascar</entry><entry align="center">08.05.1967</entry><entry align="center">01.03.1968</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Poland</entry><entry>Mali</entry><entry align="center">12.06.1979</entry><entry align="center">01.06.1983</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Portugal</entry><entry>Mauritania</entry><entry align="center">22.07.1965</entry><entry align="center">01.02.1967</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Romania</entry><entry>Monaco</entry><entry align="center">28.02.1952</entry><entry align="center">01.04.1954</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Slovakia</entry><entry>Montenegro</entry><entry align="center">26.03.2003</entry><entry align="center">26.03.2003</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Slovenia</entry><entry>Morocco</entry><entry align="center">22.10.2007</entry><entry align="center">01.06.2011</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Spain</entry><entry>Niger</entry><entry align="center">28.03.1973</entry><entry align="center">01.11.1974</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Sweden</entry><entry>Philippines</entry><entry align="center">07.02.1990</entry><entry align="center">01.11.1994</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Switzerland</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(since April 1, 2012)</Text></Provision></entry><entry><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Quebec</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(province of Canada)</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="center"><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>Entente 17.12.2003</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="10"><Text>Protocol 19.12.1998</Text></Provision></entry><entry align="center"><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>01.12.2006</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="10"><Text>01.07.2000 and 01.01.2001<FootnoteRef idref="fn_b">b</FootnoteRef></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry>United Kingdom</entry><entry>San Marino</entry><entry align="center">12.07.1949</entry><entry align="center">01.01.1951</entry></row><row><entry /><entry>Senegal</entry><entry align="center">29.03.1974</entry><entry align="center">01.09.1976</entry></row><row><entry /><entry>Serbia</entry><entry align="center">26.03.2003</entry><entry align="center">26.03.2003</entry></row><row><entry /><entry>Togo</entry><entry align="center">07.12.1971</entry><entry align="center">01.07.1973</entry></row><row><entry /><entry>Tunisia</entry><entry align="center">26.06.2003</entry><entry align="center">01.04.2007</entry></row><row><entry /><entry>Turkey</entry><entry align="center">20.01.1972</entry><entry align="center">01.08.1973</entry></row><row><entry /><entry>United States</entry><entry align="center">02.03.1987</entry><entry align="center">01.07.1988</entry></row><row><entry /><entry>Uruguay</entry><entry align="center">06.12.2010</entry><entry align="center" /></row></tbody></tgroup></table><Footnote id="fn_b" placement="table" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>01.07.2000 regarding the provisions concerning health care and 01.01.2001 regarding provisions concerning workers’ compensation insurance.</Text></Footnote></TableGroup><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10"><table><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="1.03*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.04*" /><colspec colname="col3" colwidth="0.93*" /><thead><row><entry align="center" nameend="col3" namest="col1" valign="top"><Emphasis style="bold">AGREEMENTS WITH OVERSEAS COLLECTIVITIES</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry valign="top" /><entry align="center" valign="top"><Emphasis style="bold">Signing of Agreement</Emphasis></entry><entry align="center" valign="top"><Emphasis style="bold">Entry into Force</Emphasis></entry></row></thead><tbody><row><entry rowheader="yes">Mayotte</entry><entry>26.08.2005</entry><entry>27.08.2005</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">New Caledonia</entry><entry>19.11.2002</entry><entry>01.12.2002</entry></row><row><entry rowheader="yes">Polynesia</entry><entry>26.12.1994</entry><entry>01.01.1995</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>