<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612093" lims:id="612093" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612094" lims:id="612094"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2005-87</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>5</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612096" lims:id="612096"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">AN ACT TO IMPLEMENT CONVENTIONS BETWEEN CANADA AND SPAIN, CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF AUSTRIA, CANADA AND ITALY, CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA, CANADA AND THE SOCIALIST REPUBLIC OF ROMANIA AND CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF INDONESIA AND AGREEMENTS BETWEEN CANADA AND MALAYSIA, CANADA AND JAMAICA AND CANADA AND BARBADOS AND A CONVENTION BETWEEN CANADA AND THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND FOR THE AVOIDANCE OF DOUBLE TAXATION WITH RESPECT TO INCOME TAX</XRefExternal><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="Z-02">AGREEMENTS AND CONVENTIONS</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612097" lims:id="612097">Proclamation Giving Notice of the Coming into Force on December 31, 2004 of the Convention Between Canada and Romania for the Avoidance of Double Taxation</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612098" lims:id="612098"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612099" lims:id="612099" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ADRIENNE CLARKSON</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612100" lims:id="612100" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612101" lims:id="612101" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Elizabeth the Second, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612102" lims:id="612102" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>To all to whom these presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612103" lims:id="612103" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612104" lims:id="612104" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">JOHN H. SIMS</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612105" lims:id="612105" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612106" lims:id="612106" level="1"><TitleText>A proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612107" lims:id="612107" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas subsection 32(4) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to implement conventions between Canada and Spain, Canada and the Republic of Austria, Canada and Italy, Canada and the Republic of Korea, Canada and the Socialist Republic of Romania and Canada and the Republic of Indonesia and agreements between Canada and Malaysia, Canada and Jamaica and Canada and Barbados and a convention between Canada and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for the avoidance of double taxation with respect to income tax</XRefExternal> (“the Act”) provides that notice of the day a supplementary convention comes into force and of the day it ceases to be effective shall be given by proclamation of the Governor in Council published, with the text of such supplementary convention, in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612108" lims:id="612108" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Convention Between Canada and Romania for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion With Respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, which was signed on April 8, 2004 and is a supplementary convention for the purpose of the Act, came into force on December 31, 2004;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612109" lims:id="612109" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas section 15 of the Act provides that notice of the day the Convention comes into force and of the day it ceases to be effective shall be given by proclamation of the Governor in Council published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612110" lims:id="612110" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2005-1513 of August 31, 2005, the Governor in Council directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice that</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612111" lims:id="612111" format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Convention Between Canada and Romania for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion With Respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, signed on April 8, 2004, came into force on December 31, 2004, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612112" lims:id="612112" format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Convention Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Socialist Republic of Romania for the Avoidance of Double Taxation With Respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, set out in Schedule V to the Act, ceased to apply in accordance with paragraph 3 of Article 29 of the Convention referred to in paragraph (a);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612113" lims:id="612113" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our proclamation give notice</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612114" lims:id="612114" format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>pursuant to subsection 32(4) of the Act, that the annexed Convention Between Canada and Romania for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion With Respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, signed on April 8, 2004, came into force on December 31, 2004, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612115" lims:id="612115" format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>pursuant to Section 15 of the Act, that the Convention Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the Socialist Republic of Romania for the Avoidance of Double Taxation With Respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, set out in Schedule V to the Act, ceased to apply in accordance with paragraph 3 of Article 29 of the Convention referred to in paragraph (a).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612116" lims:id="612116" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of all which Our loving subjects and all others whom these presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612117" lims:id="612117" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In testimony whereof, We have caused this Our proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. Witness: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Adrienne Clarkson, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612118" lims:id="612118" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>At Our Government House, in Our City of Ottawa, this twenty-second day of September in the year of Our Lord two thousand and five and in the fifty-fourth year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612119" lims:id="612119" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612120" lims:id="612120" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="right">SUZANNE HURTUBISE</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="612121" lims:id="612121" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Convention Between Canada and Romania for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with Respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada and Romania desiring to conclude a Convention for the avoidance of double taxation and the prevention of fiscal evasion with respect to taxes on income and on capital, have agreed as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 1</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Persons Covered</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Convention shall apply to persons who are residents of one or both of the Contracting States.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 2</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Taxes Covered</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall apply to taxes on income and on capital imposed on behalf of a Contracting State, irrespective of the manner in which they are levied.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>There shall be regarded as taxes on income and on capital all taxes imposed on total income, on total capital, or on elements of income or of capital, including taxes on gains from the alienation of movable or immovable property, as well as taxes on capital appreciation.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The existing taxes to which the Convention shall apply are in particular:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of Romania:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the tax on income;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the tax on profit;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the tax on agricultural income;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" list-item="no"><Text>(hereinafter referred to as “Romanian tax”); and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of Canada, the taxes imposed by the Government of Canada under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-3.3">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> (hereinafter referred to as “Canadian tax”).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Convention shall apply also to any identical or substantially similar taxes which are imposed after the date of signature of the Convention in addition to, or in place of, the existing taxes. The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall notify each other of any significant changes which have been made in their respective taxation laws.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 3</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>General Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Convention, unless the context otherwise requires:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the terms <DefinedTermEn>a Contracting State</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>the other Contracting State</DefinedTermEn> mean Romania or Canada, as the context requires;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>Romania</DefinedTermEn>, used in a geographical sense, means the State territory of Romania, including its territorial sea and air space over the territory and the territorial sea over which Romania exercises sovereignty, as well as the contiguous zone and the continental shelf and the exclusive economic zone over which Romania exercises, in accordance with its legislation and with the rules and principles of international law, sovereign rights and jurisdiction;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>Canada</DefinedTermEn>, used in a geographical sense, means the territory of Canada, including</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>any area beyond the territorial sea of Canada that, in accordance with international law and the laws of Canada, is an area in respect of which Canada may exercise rights with respect to the seabed and subsoil and their natural resources, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the sea and airspace above every area referred to in clause (i);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> includes an individual, a trust, a company, a partnership and any other body of persons;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>company</DefinedTermEn> means any body corporate or any entity that is treated as a body corporate for tax purposes;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the terms <DefinedTermEn>enterprise of a Contracting State</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>enterprise of the other Contracting State</DefinedTermEn> mean respectively an enterprise carried on by a resident of a Contracting State and an enterprise carried on by a resident of the other Contracting State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>national</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>any individual possessing the citizenship of a Contracting State, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any legal person, partnership or association deriving its status as such from the laws in force in a Contracting State;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>international traffic</DefinedTermEn> means any voyage by a ship or aircraft operated by an enterprise of a Contracting State to transport passengers or property except where the principal purpose of the voyage is to transport passengers or property between places in the other Contracting State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn> means:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of Romania, the Minister of Public Finances or the Minister’s authorized representative, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of Canada, the Minister of National Revenue or the Minister’s authorized representative.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>As regards the application of the Convention at any time by a Contracting State, any term not defined therein shall, unless the context otherwise requires, have the meaning that it has at that time under the law of that State for the purposes of the taxes to which the Convention applies, any meaning under the applicable tax laws of that State prevailing over a meaning given to the term under other laws of that State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 4</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Resident</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Convention, the term <DefinedTermEn>resident of a Contracting State</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any person who, under the laws of that State, is liable to tax therein by reason of the person’s domicile, residence, place of management or any other criterion of a similar nature but does not include any person who is liable to tax in that State in respect only of income from sources in that State; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that State or an administrative territorial unit thereof in the case of Romania, or a political subdivision or local authority thereof in the case of Canada or any agency or instrumentality of that State, unit, subdivision or authority as the case may be.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Where by reason of the provisions of paragraph 1 an individual is a resident of both Contracting States, then the individual’s status shall be determined as follows:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the individual shall be deemed to be a resident only of the State in which the individual has a permanent home available and if the individual has a permanent home available in both States, the individual shall be deemed to be a resident only of the State with which the individual’s personal and economic relations are closer (centre of vital interests);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the State in which the individual’s centre of vital interests is situated cannot be determined, or if there is not a permanent home available to the individual in either State, the individual shall be deemed to be a resident only of the State in which the individual has an habitual abode;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the individual has an habitual abode in both States or in neither of them, the individual shall be deemed to be a resident only of the State of which the individual is a national; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if the individual is a national of both States or of neither of them, the competent authorities of the Contracting States shall settle the question by mutual agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Where by reason of the provisions of paragraph 1 a person other than an individual is a resident of both Contracting States, the competent authorities of the Contracting States shall by mutual agreement endeavour to settle the question and to determine the mode of application of the Convention to such person. In the absence of such agreement, such person shall not be entitled to claim any relief or exemption from tax provided by the Convention.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 5</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Permanent Establishment</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Convention, the term <DefinedTermEn>permanent establishment</DefinedTermEn> means a fixed place of business through which the business of an enterprise is wholly or partly carried on.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>permanent establishment</DefinedTermEn> includes especially:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a place of management;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a branch;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an office;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a factory;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a shop;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a workshop, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a mine, an oil or gas well, a quarry or any other place relating to the exploration for or the exploitation of natural resources.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>A building site or construction or installation project constitutes a permanent establishment only if it lasts more than twelve months.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the preceding provisions of this Article, the term <DefinedTermEn>permanent establishment</DefinedTermEn> shall be deemed not to include:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the use of facilities solely for the purpose of storage, display or delivery of goods or merchandise belonging to the enterprise;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the maintenance of a stock of goods or merchandise belonging to the enterprise solely for the purpose of storage, display or delivery;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the maintenance of a stock of goods or merchandise belonging to the enterprise solely for the purpose of processing by another enterprise;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the maintenance of a stock of goods or merchandise belonging to the enterprise, displayed during an occasional and temporary trade fair or exhibition, and which is sold by the enterprise after the closing of the said fair or exhibition;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the maintenance of a fixed place of business solely for the purpose of purchasing goods or merchandise or of collecting information, for the enterprise;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the maintenance of a fixed place of business solely for the purpose of carrying on, for the enterprise, any other activity of a preparatory or auxiliary character;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the maintenance of a fixed place of business solely for any combination of activities mentioned in subparagraphs (a) to (f), provided that the overall activity of the fixed place of business resulting from this combination is of a preparatory or auxiliary character.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2, where a person — other than an agent of an independent status to whom paragraph 7 applies — is acting on behalf of an enterprise and has, and habitually exercises, in a Contracting State an authority to conclude contracts on behalf of the enterprise, that enterprise shall be deemed to have a permanent establishment in that State in respect of any activities which that person undertakes for the enterprise, unless the activities of such person are limited to those mentioned in paragraph 4 which, if exercised through a fixed place of business, would not make this fixed place of business a permanent establishment under the provisions of that paragraph.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the preceding provisions of this Article, an insurance company of a Contracting State shall, except in regard to reinsurance, be deemed to have a permanent establishment in the other Contracting State if it collects premiums in the territory of the other State or it insures risks situated therein through a person, other than an agent of an independent status to whom paragraph 7 applies.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text>An enterprise shall not be deemed to have a permanent establishment in a Contracting State merely because it carries on business in that State through a broker, general commission agent or any other agent of an independent status, provided that such persons are acting in the ordinary course of their business.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>8</Label><Text>The fact that a company which is a resident of a Contracting State controls or is controlled by a company which is a resident of the other Contracting State, or which carries on business in that other State (whether through a permanent establishment or otherwise), shall not of itself constitute either company a permanent establishment of the other.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 6</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Income from Immovable Property</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Income derived by a resident of a Contracting State from immovable property (including income from agriculture or forestry) situated in the other Contracting State may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Convention, the term <DefinedTermEn>immovable property</DefinedTermEn> shall have the meaning which it has for the purposes of the relevant tax law of the Contracting State in which the property in question is situated. The term shall in any case include property accessory to immovable property, livestock and equipment used in agriculture and forestry, rights to which the provisions of general law respecting landed property apply, usufruct of immovable property and rights to variable or fixed payments as consideration for the working of, or the right to work, mineral deposits, sources and other natural resources; ships and aircraft shall not be regarded as immovable property.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraph 1 shall apply to income derived from the direct use, letting, or use in any other form of immovable property and to income from the alienation of such property.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraphs 1 and 3 shall also apply to the income from immovable property of an enterprise and to income from immovable property used for the performance of independent personal services.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 7</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Business Profits</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The profits of an enterprise of a Contracting State shall be taxable only in that State unless the enterprise carries on business in the other Contracting State through a permanent establishment situated therein. If the enterprise carries on or has carried on business as aforesaid, the profits of the enterprise may be taxed in the other State but only so much of them as is attributable to that permanent establishment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of paragraph 3, where an enterprise of a Contracting State carries on business in the other Contracting State through a permanent establishment situated therein, there shall in each Contracting State be attributed to that permanent establishment the profits which it might be expected to make if it were a distinct and separate enterprise engaged in the same or similar activities under the same or similar conditions and dealing wholly independently with the enterprise of which it is a permanent establishment and with all other persons.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>In determining the profits of a permanent establishment, there shall be allowed those deductible expenses which are incurred for the purposes of the permanent establishment, including executive and general administrative expenses so incurred, whether in the State in which the permanent establishment is situated or elsewhere. This provision shall apply subject to limitations under domestic law.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>Insofar as it has been customary in a Contracting State to determine the profits to be attributed to a permanent establishment on the basis of an apportionment of the total profits of the enterprise to its various parts, nothing in paragraph 2 shall preclude that Contracting State from determining the profits to be taxed by such an apportionment as may be customary; the method of apportionment adopted shall, however, be such that the result shall be in accordance with the principles contained in this Article.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>No profits shall be attributed to a permanent establishment by reason of the mere purchase by that permanent establishment of goods or merchandise for the enterprise.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>For the purposes of the preceding paragraphs, the profits to be attributed to the permanent establishment shall be determined by the same method year by year unless there is good and sufficient reason to the contrary.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text>Where profits include items of income which are dealt with separately in other Articles of this Convention, then the provisions of those Articles shall not be affected by the provisions of this Article.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 8</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>International Traffic</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Profits derived by an enterprise of a Contracting State from the operation of ships or aircraft in international traffic shall be taxable only in that State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the provisions of Article 7, profits derived by an enterprise of a Contracting State from a voyage of a ship or aircraft where the principal purpose of the voyage is to transport passengers or property between places in the other Contracting State may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 shall also apply to profits from the participation in a pool, a joint business or an international operating agency.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Article,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>profits</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>gross receipts and revenues derived directly from the operation of ships or aircraft in international traffic, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>interest that is incidental to the operation of ships or aircraft in international traffic; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the term <DefinedTermEn>operation of ships or aircraft in international traffic</DefinedTermEn> by an enterprise, includes</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the charter or rental of ships or aircraft,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the rental of containers and related equipment,</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>by that enterprise if that charter or rental is incidental to the operation by that enterprise of ships or aircraft in international traffic.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 9</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Associated Enterprises</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Where</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an enterprise of a Contracting State participates directly or indirectly in the management, control or capital of an enterprise of the other Contracting State, or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the same persons participate directly or indirectly in the management, control or capital of an enterprise of a Contracting State and an enterprise of the other Contracting State, and in either case conditions are made or imposed between the two enterprises in their commercial or financial relations which differ from those which would be made between independent enterprises, then any profits which would, but for those conditions, have accrued to one of the enterprises, but, by reason of those conditions, have not so accrued, may be included in the profits of that enterprise and taxed accordingly.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Where a Contracting State includes in the profits of an enterprise of that State — and taxes accordingly — profits on which an enterprise of the other Contracting State has been charged to tax in that other State and the profits so included are profits which would have accrued to the enterprise of the first-mentioned State if the conditions made between the two enterprises had been those which would have been made between independent enterprises, then that other State shall make an appropriate adjustment to the amount of the tax charged therein on those profits. In determining such adjustment, due regard shall be had to the other provisions of this Convention and the competent authorities of the Contracting States shall if necessary consult each other.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>A Contracting State shall not change the profits of an enterprise in the circumstances referred to in paragraph 1 after the expiry of the time limits provided in its domestic laws and, in any case, after five years from the end of the year in which the profits that would be subject to such change would, but for the conditions referred to in paragraph 1, have been attributed to that enterprise.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraphs 2 and 3 shall not apply in the case of fraud, wilful default or neglect.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 10</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Dividends</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Dividends paid by a company which is a resident of a Contracting State to a resident of the other Contracting State may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>However, such dividends may also be taxed in the Contracting State of which the company paying the dividends is a resident and according to the laws of that State, but if the beneficial owner of the dividends is a resident of the other Contracting State, the tax so charged shall not exceed:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>except in the case of dividends paid by a non-resident-owned investment corporation that is resident of Canada, five per cent of the gross amount of the dividends if the beneficial owner is a company that controls directly or indirectly at least 10 per cent of the voting power in the company paying the dividends; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>15 per cent of the gross amount of the dividends, in all other cases.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The provisions of this paragraph shall not affect the taxation of the company in respect of the profits out of which the dividends are paid.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>dividends</DefinedTermEn> as used in this Article means income from shares, “jouissance” shares or “jouissance” rights, mining shares, founders’ shares or other rights, not being debt-claims, participating in profits, as well as income which is subjected to the same taxation treatment as income from shares by the laws of the State of which the company making the distribution is a resident.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 shall not apply if the beneficial owner of the dividends, being a resident of a Contracting State, carries on business in the other Contracting State of which the company paying the dividends is a resident, through a permanent establishment situated therein, or performs in that other State independent personal services from a fixed base situated therein, and the holding in respect of which the dividends are paid is effectively connected with such permanent establishment or fixed base. In such case, the provisions of Article 7 or Article 14, as the case may be, shall apply.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where a company which is a resident of a Contracting State derives profits or income from the other Contracting State, that other State may not impose any tax on the dividends paid by the company, except insofar as such dividends are paid to a resident of that other State or insofar as the holding in respect of which the dividends are paid is effectively connected with a permanent establishment or a fixed base situated in that other State, nor subject the company’s undistributed profits to a tax on the company’s undistributed profits, even if the dividends paid or the undistributed profits consist wholly or partly of profits or income arising in such other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>Nothing in this Convention shall be construed as preventing a Contracting State from imposing on the earnings of a company attributable to a permanent establishment in that State, or the earnings attributable to the alienation of immovable property situated in that State by a company carrying on a trade in immovable property, a tax in addition to the tax that would be chargeable on the earnings of a company that is a national of that State, except that any additional tax so imposed shall not exceed five per cent of the amount of such earnings that have not been subjected to such additional tax in previous taxation years. For the purpose of this provision, the term <DefinedTermEn>earnings</DefinedTermEn> means the earnings attributable to the alienation of such immovable property situated in a Contracting State as may be taxed by that State under the provisions of Article 6 or of paragraph 1 of Article 13, and the profits, including any gains, attributable to a permanent establishment in a Contracting State in a year and previous years, after deducting therefrom all taxes, other than the additional tax referred to herein, imposed on such profits in that State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 11</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Interest</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Interest arising in a Contracting State and paid to a resident of the other Contracting State may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>However, such interest may also be taxed in the Contracting State in which it arises and according to the laws of that State, but if the beneficial owner of the interest is a resident of the other Contracting State, the tax so charged shall not exceed 10 per cent of the gross amount of the interest.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph 2</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>interest arising in a Contracting State and paid in respect of indebtedness of the government of that State or an administrative territorial unit thereof in the case of Romania, or a political subdivision or local authority thereof in the case of Canada shall, if the interest is beneficially owned by a resident of the other Contracting State, be taxable only in that other State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>interest arising in Romania and paid to a resident of Canada shall be taxable only in Canada if it is paid in respect of a loan made, guaranteed or insured, or a credit extended, guaranteed or insured by Export Development Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>interest arising in Canada and paid to a resident of Romania shall be taxable only in Romania if it is paid in respect of a loan made, guaranteed or insured, or a credit extended, guaranteed or insured by <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Banca de Export Import a Romaniei S.A</XRefExternal>. (EXIMBANK).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>interest</DefinedTermEn> as used in this Article means income from debt-claims of every kind, whether or not secured by mortgage, and in particular, income from government securities and income from bonds or debentures, including premiums and prizes attaching to such securities, bonds or debentures, as well as income which is subjected to the same taxation treatment as income from money lent by the laws of the State in which the income arises. However, the term <DefinedTermEn>interest</DefinedTermEn> does not include income dealt with in Article 8 or Article 10.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 shall not apply if the beneficial owner of the interest, being a resident of a Contracting State, carries on business in the other Contracting State in which the interest arises, through a permanent establishment situated therein, or performs in that other State independent personal services from a fixed base situated therein, and the debt-claim in respect of which the interest is paid is effectively connected with such permanent establishment or fixed base. In such case the provisions of Article 7 or Article 14, as the case may be, shall apply.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>Interest shall be deemed to arise in a Contracting State when the payer is a resident of that State. Where, however, the person paying the interest, whether the payer is a resident of a Contracting State or not, has in a Contracting State a permanent establishment or a fixed base in connection with which the indebtedness on which the interest is paid was incurred, and such interest is borne by such permanent establishment or fixed base, then such interest shall be deemed to arise in the Contracting State in which the permanent establishment or fixed base is situated.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text>Where, by reason of a special relationship between the payer and the beneficial owner or between both of them and some other person, the amount of the interest, having regard to the debt-claim for which it is paid, exceeds the amount which would have been agreed upon by the payer and the beneficial owner in the absence of such relationship, the provisions of this Article shall apply only to the last-mentioned amount. In such case, the excess part of the payments shall remain taxable according to the laws of each Contracting State, due regard being had to the other provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 12</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Royalties</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Royalties arising in a Contracting State and paid to a resident of the other Contracting State may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>However, such royalties may also be taxed in the Contracting State in which they arise and according to the laws of that State, but if a resident of the other Contracting State is the beneficial owner of the royalties the tax so charged shall not exceed:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>5 per cent of the gross amount of the royalties if they are:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>copyright royalties and other like payments in respect of the production or reproduction of any literary, dramatic, musical or other artistic work (but not including royalties in respect of motion picture films nor royalties in respect of works on film or videotape or other means of reproduction for use in connection with television broadcasting); or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>royalties for the use of, or the right to use, computer software or any patent or for information concerning industrial, commercial or scientific experience (but not including any such royalty provided in connection with a rental or franchise agreement);</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>10 per cent of the gross amount of the royalties in all other cases.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>royalties</DefinedTermEn> as used in this Article means payments of any kind received as a consideration for the use of, or the right to use, any copyright, patent, trade mark, design or model, plan, secret formula or process or other intangible property, or for the use of, or the right to use, industrial, commercial or scientific equipment, or for information concerning industrial, commercial or scientific experience, and includes payments of any kind in respect of motion picture films and works on film, videotape or other means of reproduction for use in connection with television.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 shall not apply if the beneficial owner of the royalties, being a resident of a Contracting State, carries on business in the other Contracting State in which the royalties arise, through a permanent establishment situated therein, or performs in that other State independent personal services from a fixed base situated therein, and the right or property in respect of which the royalties are paid is effectively connected with such permanent establishment or fixed base. In such case, the provisions of Article 7 or Article 14, as the case may be, shall apply.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>Royalties shall be deemed to arise in a Contracting State when the payer is a resident of that State. Where, however, the person paying the royalties, whether the payer is a resident of a Contracting State or not, has in a Contracting State a permanent establishment or a fixed base in connection with which the obligation to pay the royalties was incurred, and such royalties are borne by such permanent establishment or fixed base, then such royalties shall be deemed to arise in the Contracting State in which the permanent establishment or fixed base is situated.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>Where, by reason of a special relationship between the payer and the beneficial owner or between both of them and some other person, the amount of the royalties, having regard to the use, right or information for which they are paid, exceeds the amount which would have been agreed upon by the payer and the beneficial owner in the absence of such relationship, the provisions of this Article shall apply only to the last-mentioned amount. In such case, the excess part of the payments shall remain taxable according to the laws of each Contracting State, due regard being had to the other provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 13</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Capital Gains</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Gains derived by a resident of a Contracting State from the alienation of immovable property situated in the other Contracting State may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Gains from the alienation of movable property forming part of the business property of a permanent establishment which an enterprise of a Contracting State has or had in the other Contracting State or of movable property pertaining to a fixed base that is or was available to a resident of a Contracting State in the other Contracting State for the purpose of performing independent personal services, including such gains from the alienation of such a permanent establishment (alone or with the whole enterprise) or of such fixed base, may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Gains derived by an enterprise of a Contracting State from the alienation of ships or aircraft operated in international traffic or movable property pertaining to the operation of such ships or aircraft shall be taxable only in that State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>Gains derived by a resident of a Contracting State from the alienation of</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>shares, the value of which is derived principally from immovable property situated in the other State; or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an interest in a partnership or trust, the value of which is derived principally from immovable property situated in that other State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>may be taxed in that other State. For the purposes of this paragraph, the term <DefinedTermEn>immovable property</DefinedTermEn> does not include any property, other than rental property, in which the business of the company, partnership or trust is carried on.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>Gains from the alienation of any property other than that referred to in paragraphs 1, 2, 3 and 4 shall be taxable only in the Contracting State of which the alienator is a resident.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraph 5 shall not affect the right of a Contracting State to levy, according to its law, a tax on gains from the alienation of any property derived by an individual who is a resident of the other Contracting State and has been a resident of the first-mentioned State at any time during the five years immediately preceding the alienation of the property.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text>Where an individual who ceases to be a resident of a Contracting State, and immediately thereafter becomes a resident of the other Contracting State, is treated for the purposes of taxation in the first-mentioned State as having alienated a property and is taxed in that State by reason thereof, the individual may elect to be treated for purposes of taxation in the other State as if the individual had, immediately before becoming a resident of that State, sold and repurchased the property for an amount equal to its fair market value at that time.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 14</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Independent Personal Services</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Income derived by an individual who is a resident of a Contracting State in respect of professional or similar services of an independent character shall be taxable only in that State unless the individual has a fixed base regularly available in the other Contracting State for the purpose of performing the services. If the individual has or had such a fixed base, the income may be taxed in the other State but only so much of it as is attributable to that fixed base.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The term <DefinedTermEn>professional services</DefinedTermEn> includes especially independent scientific, literary, artistic, educational or teaching activities as well as the independent activities of physicians, lawyers, engineers, architects, dentists and accountants.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 15</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Dependent Personal Services</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of Articles 16, 18 and 19, salaries, wages and other remuneration derived by a resident of a Contracting State in respect of an employment shall be taxable only in that State unless the employment is exercised in the other Contracting State. If the employment is so exercised, such remuneration as is derived therefrom may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph 1, remuneration derived by a resident of a Contracting State in respect of an employment exercised in the other Contracting State shall be taxable only in the first-mentioned State if:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the recipient is present in the other State for a period or periods not exceeding in the aggregate 183 days in any twelve month period commencing or ending in the calendar year concerned; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the remuneration is paid by, or on behalf of, an employer who is not a resident of the other State; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the remuneration is not borne by a permanent establishment or a fixed base which the employer has in the other State.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the preceding provisions of this Article, remuneration derived in respect of an employment exercised aboard a ship or aircraft operated in international traffic by an enterprise of a Contracting State shall be taxable only in that State unless the remuneration is derived by a resident of the other Contracting State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 16</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Directors’ Fees</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Directors’ fees and other similar payments derived by a resident of a Contracting State in the capacity as a member of the board of directors or a similar organ of a company which is a resident of the other Contracting State may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 17</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Artistes and Sportspersons</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the provisions of Articles 14 and 15, income derived by a resident of a Contracting State as an entertainer, such as a theatre, motion picture, radio or television artiste, or a musician, or as a sportsperson from that resident’s personal activities as such exercised in the other Contracting State, may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Where income in respect of personal activities exercised by an entertainer or a sportsperson in that individual’s capacity as such accrues not to the entertainer or sportsperson personally but to another person, that income may, notwithstanding the provisions of Articles 7, 14 and 15, be taxed in the Contracting State in which the activities of the entertainer or sportsperson are exercised.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2, income derived from the activities referred to in paragraph 1 within the framework of cultural or sports exchanges agreed to by the Governments of the Contracting States and carried out other than for the purpose of profit shall be exempt from tax in the Contracting State in which these activities are exercised.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 18</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Pensions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Pensions, including social security payments, arising in a Contracting State and paid to a resident of the other Contracting State may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Pensions, including social security payments, arising in a Contracting State and paid to a resident of the other Contracting State may also be taxed in the State in which they arise and according to the laws of that State, but in the case of periodic payments, the tax so charged shall not exceed 15 per cent of the gross amount of such periodic payments paid to the recipient in the calendar year concerned that exceeds twelve thousand Canadian dollars or its equivalent in Romanian currency.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 19</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Government Service</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Salaries, wages and other similar remuneration, other than a pension, paid by a Contracting State or an administrative territorial unit thereof in the case of Romania, or a political subdivision or local authority thereof in the case of Canada, to an individual in respect of services rendered to that State, subdivision, authority or unit shall be taxable only in that State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>However, such salaries, wages and other similar remuneration shall be taxable only in the other Contracting State if the services are rendered in that State and the individual is a resident of that State who</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is a national of that State, or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>did not become a resident of that State solely for the purpose of rendering the services.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraph 1 shall not apply to salaries, wages and other similar remuneration in respect of services rendered in connection with a business carried on by a Contracting State or an administrative territorial unit thereof in the case of Romania, or a political subdivision or local authority thereof in the case of Canada.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 20</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Students</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Payments which a student, apprentice or business trainee who is, or was immediately before visiting a Contracting State, a resident of the other Contracting State and who is present in the first-mentioned State solely for the purpose of that individual’s education or training receives for the purpose of that individual’s maintenance, education or training shall not be taxed in that State, provided that such payments arise from sources outside that State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 21</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Other Income</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Items of income of a resident of a Contracting State, wherever arising, not dealt with in the foregoing Articles of this Convention shall be taxable in that State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>However, if such income is derived by a resident of a Contracting State from sources in the other Contracting State, such income may also be taxed in the State in which it arises and according to the law of that State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 22</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Capital</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Capital represented by immovable property owned by a resident of a Contracting State and situated in the other Contracting State, may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Capital represented by movable property forming part of the business property of a permanent establishment which an enterprise of a Contracting State has in the other Contracting State or by movable property pertaining to a fixed base available to a resident of a Contracting State in the other Contracting State for the purpose of performing independent personal services, may be taxed in that other State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Capital represented by ships and aircraft operated by an enterprise of a Contracting State in international traffic and by movable property pertaining to the operation of such ships and aircraft shall be taxable only in that State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>All other elements of capital of a resident of a Contracting State shall be taxable only in that State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 23</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Elimination of Double Taxation</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>It is agreed that double taxation shall be avoided as follows:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of Romania, where a resident of Romania derives income or owns capital which, in accordance with the provisions of this Convention may be taxed in Canada, Romania shall allow:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>as a deduction from the tax on the income of that resident, an amount equal to the income tax paid in Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>as a deduction from the tax on the capital of that resident, an amount equal to the capital tax paid in Canada,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>such deduction in either case shall not, however, exceed that part of the income tax or capital tax, as computed before the deduction is given, which is attributable, as the case may be, to the income or the capital which may be taxed in Canada;</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subject to the existing provisions of the law of Canada regarding the deduction from tax payable in Canada of tax paid in a territory outside Canada and to any subsequent modification of those provisions — which shall not affect the general principle hereof — and unless a greater deduction or relief is provided under the laws of Canada, tax payable in Romania on profits, income or gains arising in Romania shall be deducted from any Canadian tax payable in respect of such profits, income or gains,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>where, in accordance with any provision of the Convention, income derived or capital owned by a resident of Canada is exempt from tax in Canada, Canada may nevertheless, in calculating the amount of tax on other income or capital, take into account the exempted income or capital.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Article, profits, income or gains of a resident of a Contracting State that may be taxed in the other Contracting State in accordance with this Convention shall be deemed to arise from sources in that other State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 24</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Non-Discrimination</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Nationals of a Contracting State shall not be subjected in the other Contracting State to any taxation or any requirement connected therewith that is more burdensome than the taxation and connected requirements to which nationals of that other State in the same circumstances, in particular with respect to residence, are or may be subjected.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The taxation on a permanent establishment that an enterprise of a Contracting State has in the other Contracting State shall not be less favourably levied in that other State than the taxation levied on enterprises of that other State carrying on the same activities.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Nothing in this Article shall be construed as obliging a Contracting State to grant to residents of the other Contracting State any personal allowances, reliefs and reductions for taxation purposes on account of civil status or family responsibilities that it grants to its own residents.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>Except where the provisions of paragraph 1 of Article 9, paragraph 7 of Article 11, or paragraph 6 of Article 12 apply, interest, royalties and other disbursements paid by an enterprise of a Contracting State to a resident of the other Contracting State shall, for the purpose of determining the taxable profits of such enterprise, be deductible under the same conditions as if they had been paid to a resident of the first mentioned State. Similarly, any debts of an enterprise of a Contracting State to a resident of the other Contracting State shall, for the purpose of determining the taxable capital of such enterprise, be deductible under the same conditions as if they had been contracted to a resident of the first-mentioned State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraph 4 shall not affect the operation of any provision of the taxation laws of a Contracting State:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>relating to the deductibility of interest and which is in force on the date of signature of this Convention (including any subsequent modification of such provisions that does not change the general nature thereof); or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>adopted after such date by a Contracting State and which is designed to ensure that a person who is not a resident of that State does not enjoy, under the laws of that State, a tax treatment that is more favourable than that enjoyed by residents of that State.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>Enterprises of a Contracting State, the capital of which is wholly or partly owned or controlled, directly or indirectly, by one or more residents of the other Contracting State, shall not be subjected in the first-mentioned State to any taxation or any requirement connected therewith that is more burdensome than the taxation and connected requirements to which other similar enterprises that are residents of the first-mentioned State, the capital of which is wholly or partly owned or controlled, directly or indirectly, by one or more residents of a third State, are or may be subjected.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text>The provisions of this Article shall apply only to taxes which are covered by this Convention.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 25</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Mutual Agreement Procedure</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Where a person considers that the actions of one or both of the Contracting States result or will result for that person in taxation not in accordance with the provisions of this Convention, that person may, irrespective of the remedies provided by the domestic law of those States, address to the competent authority of the Contracting State of which that person is a resident an application in writing stating the grounds for claiming the revision of such taxation. To be admissible, the said application must be submitted within two years from the first notification of the action resulting in taxation not in accordance with the provisions of the Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The competent authority shall endeavour, if the objection appears to it to be justified and if it is not itself able to arrive at a satisfactory solution, to resolve the case by mutual agreement with the competent authority of the other Contracting State, with a view to the avoidance of taxation not in accordance with the Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>A Contracting State shall not, after the expiry of the time limits provided in its domestic laws and, in any case, after five years from the end of the taxable period to which the income concerned was attributed, increase the tax base of a resident of either of the Contracting States by including therein items of income that have also been charged to tax in the other Contracting State. This paragraph shall not apply in the case of fraud, wilful default or neglect.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall endeavour to resolve by mutual agreement any difficulties or doubts arising as to the interpretation or application of the Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States may consult together for the elimination of double taxation in cases not provided for in the Convention and may communicate with each other directly for the purpose of applying the Convention.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 26</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Exchange of Information</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall exchange such information as is necessary for carrying out the provisions of this Convention or of the domestic laws of the Contracting States concerning taxes covered by the Convention insofar as the taxation thereunder is not contrary to the Convention. The exchange of information is not restricted by Article 1. Any information received by a Contracting State shall be treated as secret in the same manner as information obtained under the domestic laws of that State, and shall be disclosed only to persons or authorities (including courts and administrative bodies) concerned with the assessment or collection of, the enforcement in respect of, or the determination of appeals in relation to taxes in that State. Such persons or authorities shall use the information only for such purposes. They may disclose the information in public court proceedings or in judicial decisions.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In no case shall the provisions of paragraph 1 be construed so as to impose on a Contracting State the obligation:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to carry out administrative measures at variance with the laws and administrative practice of that or of the other Contracting State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to supply information which is not obtainable under the laws or in the normal course of the administration of that or of the other Contracting State;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to supply information which would disclose any business, industrial, commercial or professional secret or trade process, or information, the disclosure of which would be contrary to public policy (ordre public).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>If information is requested by a Contracting State in accordance with this Article, the other Contracting State shall endeavour to obtain the information to which the request relates in the same way as if its own taxation were involved, even though the other State does not, at that time, need such information. If specifically requested by the competent authority of a Contracting State, the competent authority of the other Contracting State shall endeavour to provide information under this Article in the form requested, such as copies of unaltered original documents, to the same extent such documents can be obtained under the laws and administrative practices of that other State with respect to its own taxes.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 27</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Members of Diplomatic Missions and Consular Posts</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Nothing in this Convention shall affect the fiscal privileges of members of diplomatic missions or consular posts under the general rules of international law or under the provisions of special agreements.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 28</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Miscellaneous Rules</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The provisions of this Convention shall not be construed to restrict in any manner any exemption, allowance, credit or other deduction accorded by the laws of a Contracting State in the determination of the tax imposed by that State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Nothing in the Convention shall be construed as preventing the application of the provisions of the domestic law of each Contracting State concerning the taxation of income of persons in respect to their participation in a partnership, trust, or non-resident company or concerning fiscal evasion.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Convention shall not apply to any company, trust or other entity that is a resident of a Contracting State and is beneficially owned or controlled, directly or indirectly, by one or more persons who are not residents of that State, if the amount of the tax imposed on the income or capital of the company, trust or other entity by that State is substantially lower than the amount that would be imposed by that State if all of the shares of the capital stock of the company or all of the interests in the trust or other entity, as the case may be, were beneficially owned by one or more individuals who were residents of that State.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 3 of Article XXII (Consultation) of the General Agreement on Trade in Services, the Contracting States agree that, notwithstanding that paragraph, any dispute between them as to whether a measure falls within the scope of the convention may be brought before the Council for Trade in Services, as provided by that paragraph, only with the consent of both Contracting States. Any doubt as to the interpretation of this paragraph shall be resolved under paragraph 4 of Article 25 or, failing agreement under that procedure, pursuant to any other procedure agreed to by both Contracting States.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where under any provision of the Convention any income is relieved from tax in a Contracting State and, under the law in force in the other Contracting State a person, in respect of that income, is subject to tax by reference to the amount thereof that is remitted to or received in that other Contracting State and not by reference to the full amount thereof, then the relief to be allowed under the Convention in the first-mentioned Contracting State shall apply only to so much of the income as is taxed in the other Contracting State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 29</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Entry into Force</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall enter into force on the thirtieth day following the later of the notifications through which the Contracting States shall notify to each other that the domestic requirements for the entry into force of the Convention have been complied with.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The provisions of the Convention shall have effect:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of Romania:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in respect of taxes withheld at the source to the income paid on or after the first day of January in the calendar year next following the year in which the Convention enters into force, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in respect of other taxes on income and on capital paid on or after the first day of January in the calendar year next following the year in which the Convention enters into force; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in respect of tax withheld at the source on amounts paid or credited to non-residents, on or after the first day of January in the calendar year following that in which the Convention enters into force, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in respect of other Canadian tax, for taxation years beginning on or after the first day of January in the calendar year following that in which the Convention enters into force.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The provisions of the Convention Between The Government of Canada and The Government of the Socialist Republic of Romania for the Avoidance of Double Taxation With respect to Taxes on Income and Capital signed at Ottawa on the 20th of November 1978, shall cease to have effect with respect to taxes to which this Convention applies in accordance with the provisions of paragraph 2 of this Article.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">ARTICLE 30</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Termination</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Convention shall remain in force until terminated by a Contracting State. Either Contracting State may terminate the Convention after five years from the date on which the Convention enters into force provided that at least six months prior a written notice of termination has been given through diplomatic channels. In such event, the Convention shall cease to have effect:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of Romania:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in respect of taxes withheld at the source to the income derived on or after the first day of January in the calendar year next following the year in which the notice of termination is given, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in respect of other taxes on income and on capital derived on or after the first day of January in the calendar year next following the year in which the notice of termination is given; and</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in respect of tax withheld at the source on amounts paid or credited to non-residents, after the end of that calendar year, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in respect of other Canadian tax, for taxation years beginning after the end of that calendar year.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, duly authorized to that effect, have signed this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>DONE in duplicate at Ottawa, this 8<Sup>th</Sup> day of April 2004, in the English, French and Romanian languages, each version being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="50*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="50*" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Paul Dubois</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Liviu Maior</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text>FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF ROMANIA</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>