<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2014-06-03" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-06-03" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627509" lims:id="627509" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627510" lims:id="627510"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2014-54</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>2</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627512" lims:id="627512"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">AN ACT TO IMPLEMENT CONVENTIONS BETWEEN CANADA AND SPAIN, CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF AUSTRIA, CANADA AND ITALY, CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA, CANADA AND THE SOCIALIST REPUBLIC OF ROMANIA AND CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF INDONESIA AND AGREEMENTS BETWEEN CANADA AND MALAYSIA, CANADA AND JAMAICA AND CANADA AND BARBADOS AND A CONVENTION BETWEEN CANADA AND THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND FOR THE AVOIDANCE OF DOUBLE TAXATION WITH RESPECT TO INCOME TAX</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627513" lims:id="627513">Proclamation Giving Notice that the Second Protocol Amending the Convention between Canada and the Republic of Austria for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, done at Vienna on December 9, 1976, as amended by the Protocol done at Vienna on June 15, 1999 Came into Force on October 1, 2013</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627514" lims:id="627514"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627515" lims:id="627515" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>DAVID JOHNSTON</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627516" lims:id="627516" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627517" lims:id="627517" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627518" lims:id="627518" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627519" lims:id="627519" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>TO ALL TO WHOM these presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627520" lims:id="627520" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627521" lims:id="627521" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">WILLIAM PENTNEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627522" lims:id="627522" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627523" lims:id="627523" level="1"><TitleText>A Proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627524" lims:id="627524" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2014-590 of May 15, 2014, the Governor in Council, pursuant to subsection 32(4) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to implement conventions between Canada and Spain, Canada and the Republic of Austria, Canada and Italy, Canada and the Republic of Korea, Canada and the Socialist Republic of Romania and Canada and the Republic of Indonesia and agreements between Canada and Malaysia, Canada and Jamaica and Canada and Barbados and a convention between Canada and the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland for the avoidance of double taxation with respect to income tax</XRefExternal>, directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice of the entry into force on October 1, 2013 of the attached supplementary convention, done at Vienna on 9 March 2012, that amends the Convention between Canada and the Republic of Austria for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, done at Vienna on 9 December 1976, as amended by the Protocol done at Vienna on 15 June 1999;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627525" lims:id="627525" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our proclamation give notice of the entry into force on October 1, 2013 of the attached supplementary convention, done at Vienna on 9 March 2012, that amends the Convention between Canada and the Republic of Austria for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, done at Vienna on 9 December 1976, as amended by the Protocol done at Vienna on 15 June 1999.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627526" lims:id="627526" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of all which Our loving subjects and all others whom these presents may concern are required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627527" lims:id="627527" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN TESTIMONY WHEREOF, We have caused this Our proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be affixed to it. WITNESS: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved David Johnston, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627528" lims:id="627528" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>AT OUR GOVERNMENT HOUSE, in Our City of Ottawa, this third day of June in the year of Our Lord two thousand and fourteen and in the sixty-third year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627529" lims:id="627529" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627530" lims:id="627530" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="right">JOHN KNUBLEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2014-06-03" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-06-03" lims:fid="627531" lims:id="627531" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Second Protocol Amending the Convention Between Canada and the Republic of Austria for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with Respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, Done at Vienna on 9 December 1976, as Amended by the Protocol Done at Vienna on 15 June 1999</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">CANADA AND THE REPUBLIC OF AUSTRIA;</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DESIRING</Emphasis> to amend the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Convention between Canada and the Republic of Austria for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital</XRefExternal>, done at Vienna on 9 December 1976, as amended by the Protocol done at Vienna on 15 June 1999 (“the Convention”),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED</Emphasis> as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" type="amending"><Text><Emphasis style="regular">Paragraphs 1, 2 and 3 of Article 26 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following paragraphs 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5 and paragraphs 4 and 5 shall be renumbered 6 and 7 respectively:</Emphasis></Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>“1</Label><Text>The competent authorities of the Contracting States shall exchange such information as is foreseeably relevant for carrying out the provisions of this Convention or to the administration or enforcement of the domestic laws concerning taxes of every kind and description imposed on behalf of the Contracting States, insofar as the taxation thereunder is not contrary to the Convention. The exchange of information is not restricted by Articles 1 and 2.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any information received under paragraph 1 by a Contracting State shall be treated as secret in the same manner as information obtained under the domestic laws of that State and shall be disclosed only to persons or authorities (including courts and administrative bodies) concerned with the assessment or collection of, the enforcement or prosecution in respect of, the determination of appeals in relation to taxes, or the oversight of the above. Such persons or authorities shall use the information only for such purposes. They may disclose the information in public court proceedings or in judicial decisions.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>In no case shall the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 be construed so as to impose on a Contracting State the obligation:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" subsequent-line-indent="3.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to carry out administrative measures at variance with the laws and the administrative practice of that or of the other Contracting State;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" subsequent-line-indent="3.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to supply information that is not obtainable under the laws or in the normal course of the administration of that or of the other Contracting State; or</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" subsequent-line-indent="3.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to supply information that would disclose any trade, business, industrial, commercial or professional secret or trade process, or information, the disclosure of which would be contrary to public policy (<Language xml:lang="fr">ordre public</Language>).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>If information is requested by a Contracting State in accordance with this Article, the other Contracting State shall use its information gathering measures to obtain the requested information, even though that other State may not need such information for its own tax purposes. The obligation contained in the preceding sentence is subject to the limitations of paragraph 3 but in no case shall such limitations be construed to permit a Contracting State to decline to supply information solely because it has no domestic interest in such information.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>In no case shall the provisions of paragraph 3 be construed to permit a Contracting State to decline to supply information solely because the information is held by a bank, other financial institution, nominee or person acting in an agency or a fiduciary capacity or because it relates to ownership interests in a person.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The Contracting States shall notify one another through diplomatic channels that all legal procedures for the entry into force of this Protocol have been completed. The Protocol shall enter into force on the first day of the third month following the date of the receipt of the later of the notifications. The provisions of this Protocol shall have effect with regard to taxable periods beginning on or after 1 January of the calendar year following the year of the entry into force of this Protocol. If there is no taxable period, the provisions shall have effect with regard to all charges to tax arising on or after 1 January of the calendar year following the year of the entry into force of this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis> the undersigned, duly authorised thereto, by their respective Governments, have signed this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in duplicate at Vienna, this 9th day of March 2012, in the English, French and German languages, each version being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" /><colspec colname="col2" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>JOHN BARRET</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>ANDREAS SCHIEDER</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE REPUBLIC OF AUSTRIA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretative Protocol</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>At the time of signing of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Second Protocol amending the Convention between Canada and the Republic of Austria for the Avoidance of Double Taxation and the Prevention of Fiscal Evasion with respect to Taxes on Income and on Capital, done at Vienna on 9 December 1976, as amended by the Protocol done at Vienna on 15 June 1999</XRefExternal>, the undersigned have agreed upon the following provisions which shall be an integral part of the aforementioned Convention.</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>It is understood that the competent authority of the Contracting State requesting information (the “applicant State”) shall provide the following information to the competent authority of the Contracting State requested to provide information (the “requested State”) when making a request for information under the Convention to demonstrate the foreseeable relevance of the information to the request:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the identity of the person under examination or investigation;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a statement of the information sought including its nature and the form in which the applicant State wishes to receive the information from the requested State;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the tax purpose for which the information is sought;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>grounds for believing that the information requested is held in the requested State or is in the possession or control of a person within the jurisdiction of the requested State;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>to the extent known, the name and address of any person believed to be in possession of the requested information; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="2.5" list-item="yes"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a statement that the applicant State has pursued all means available in its own territory to obtain the information, except those that would give rise to disproportionate difficulties.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>It is understood that the standard of “foreseeable relevance” is intended to provide for exchange of information in tax matters to the widest possible extent and, at the same time, to clarify that Contracting States are not at liberty to engage in “fishing expeditions” or to request information that is unlikely to be relevant to the tax affairs of a given taxpayer. While paragraph 1 of this Protocol contains important procedural requirements that are intended to ensure that fishing expeditions do not occur, subparagraphs (a) through (f) of paragraph 1 nevertheless need to be interpreted liberally in order not to frustrate effective exchange of information.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>It is understood that paragraph 5 of Article 26 of the Convention does not require the Contracting States to exchange information on a spontaneous or automatic basis.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis> the undersigned, duly authorised thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Interpretative Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in duplicate at Vienna, this 9th day of March 2012, in the English, French and German languages, each version being equally authentic.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><TableGroup pointsize="9" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" /><colspec colname="col2" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>JOHN BARRET</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>ANDREAS SCHIEDER</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE REPUBLIC OF AUSTRIA</Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>