<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2013-12-06" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-12-06" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626540" lims:id="626540" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626541" lims:id="626541"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2013-129</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2013</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626543" lims:id="626543"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626544" lims:id="626544">Proclamation Giving Notice that the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway Comes into Force on January 1, 2014</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626545" lims:id="626545"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626546" lims:id="626546" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>DAVID JOHNSTON</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626547" lims:id="626547" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626548" lims:id="626548" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626549" lims:id="626549" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626550" lims:id="626550" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>TO ALL TO WHOM these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626551" lims:id="626551" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626552" lims:id="626552" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="left">WILLIAM PENTNEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626553" lims:id="626553" format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626554" lims:id="626554" level="1"><TitleText>A Proclamation</TitleText></Heading></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626555" lims:id="626555" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas by Order in Council P.C. 2012-1606 of November 29, 2012, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway</XRefExternal>, signed at Ottawa, on June 20, 2012, the Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received from the other Party written notification that it has complied with all requirements for the entry into force of the Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626556" lims:id="626556" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Order in Council was laid before the House of Commons on November 30, 2012, and the Senate on December 4, 2012, as required under the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626557" lims:id="626557" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order had been laid before both Houses of Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626558" lims:id="626558" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it had been laid before Parliament, being March 5, 2013;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626559" lims:id="626559" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the exchange of the written notices was completed on September 16, 2013;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626560" lims:id="626560" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received from the other Party written notification that it has complied with all requirements for the entry into force of the Agreement, being January 1, 2014;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626561" lims:id="626561" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 2013-1260 of November 21, 2013, the Governor in Council directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway</XRefExternal> is in force as of January 1, 2014;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626562" lims:id="626562" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now know you that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our proclamation give notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway</XRefExternal>, a copy of which is annexed to this proclamation, is in force as of January 1, 2014.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626563" lims:id="626563" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of all which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626564" lims:id="626564" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In testimony whereof, We have caused this Our Proclamation to be published and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. WITNESS: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved David Johnston, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Merit of the Police Forces, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626565" lims:id="626565" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>AT OUR GOVERNMENT HOUSE, in Our City of Ottawa, this sixth day of December in the year of Our Lord two thousand and thirteen and in the sixty-second year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626566" lims:id="626566" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626567" lims:id="626567" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="right">JOHN KNUBLEY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626568" lims:id="626568" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Agreement on Social Security Between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">CANADA AND THE KINGDOM OF NORWAY</Emphasis>, hereinafter referred to as the “Parties”,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">NOTING</Emphasis> the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway</XRefExternal> and its Final Protocol to that Agreement, done at Oslo on 12 November 1985,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DESIRING</Emphasis> to strengthen even further the relations between them in the field of social security, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">TAKING INTO ACCOUNT</Emphasis> changes in legislation since the signing of the aforementioned Agreement,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">HAVE AGREED</Emphasis> as follows:</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>territory</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, the territory of Canada; and, as regards Norway, the territory of the Kingdom of Norway, including Svalbard and Jan Mayen;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>legislation</DefinedTermEn> means the laws and regulations specified in Article 2;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, the Minister or Ministers responsible for the application of the legislation of Canada; and, as regards Norway, the Ministry responsible for the application of the legislation of Norway;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>competent institution</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, the competent authority; and, as regards Norway, the institution which is competent according to the legislation applicable;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(e)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>creditable period</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Canada, a period of contribution used to acquire the right to a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>; a period during which a disability pension is payable under that Plan; or a period of residence used to acquire the right to a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>; and, as regards Norway, a period of insurance, residence or pension point years used to acquire the right to a benefit under the legislation of Norway; a calendar year for which pension points have been credited for the purpose of calculating a supplementary pension by virtue of employment or other gainful occupation, shall be regarded as a whole year when computing the creditable period for a basic pension;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(f)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>benefit</DefinedTermEn> means any cash benefit, pension or allowance for which provision is made in the legislation of either Party and includes any supplements or increases applicable to such a cash benefit, pension or allowance;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(g)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>survivor’s pension</DefinedTermEn> means, as regards Norway, pension and transitional benefits to a survivor as specified by the applicable legislation of Norway and a children’s pension;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(h)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>continental shelf</DefinedTermEn> means the seabed and subsoil of the submarine areas that extend beyond the territorial sea throughout the natural prolongation of the land territory to the outer edge of the continental margin, or to a distance of 200 nautical miles from the baselines from which the breadth of the territorial sea is measured where the outer edge of the continental margin does not extend up to that distance.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any term not defined in this Article has the meaning assigned to it in the applicable legislation.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label><TitleText>Legislation to which this Agreement Applies</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall apply to the following legislation:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with respect to Canada:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>with respect to Norway:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Insurance Act</XRefExternal> of 28 February 1997 and the regulations made thereunder concerning old age pensions, disability benefits, funeral grant and survivor’s pension;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Labour and Welfare Service Act</XRefExternal> of 16 June 2006 and the regulations made thereunder.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 3, this Agreement shall also apply to laws and regulations which amend, supplement, consolidate or supersede the legislation specified in paragraph 1.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>This Agreement shall further apply to laws and regulations which extend the legislation of a Party to new categories of beneficiaries or to new benefits unless an objection on the part of that Party has been communicated to the other Party not later than six months following the entry into force of such laws and regulations.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label><TitleText>Persons to whom this Agreement Applies</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Agreement shall apply to persons who are or who have been subject to the legislation of Canada or Norway and to their dependants and survivors, as specified by the applicable legislation of either Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label><TitleText>Equality of Treatment</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement, a person described in Article 3, regardless of nationality, shall be subject to the obligations of the legislation of a Party and shall be eligible for the benefits of that legislation under the same conditions as citizens of that Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label><TitleText>Export of Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement, benefits payable under the legislation of a Party to a person described in Article 3, including benefits acquired by virtue of this Agreement, shall not be subject to any reduction, modification, suspension or cancellation by reason only of the fact that the person stays or resides in the territory of the other Party, and these benefits shall be payable in the territory of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Benefits under the legislation of a Party, including benefits acquired by virtue of this Agreement, shall be payable to a person described in Article 3 who stays or resides in the territory of a third State on the same conditions and to the same extent as to a citizen of that Party who stays or resides in the territory of a third State.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning the Applicable Legislation</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label><TitleText>General Rules Regarding Coverage for Employed and Self-Employed Persons</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Subject to Articles 7 to 11:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>An employed person who works in the territory of a Party shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of that Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A self-employed person who resides in the territory of a Party and who works for his or her own account in the territory of the other Party or in the territories of both Parties shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the Party in whose territory he or she resides.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label><TitleText>Detachments</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>An employed person who is subject to the legislation of a Party and who works in the territory of the other Party for the same or related employer shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party as though that work was performed in its territory. In the case of an assignment, this coverage may not be maintained for more than 60 months without the prior consent of the competent authorities of both Parties in accordance with Article 11.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 1 shall not apply in the case of a person who is sent from the territory of Norway to the territory of Canada unless the person is on a Norwegian payroll as determined by the legislation of Norway.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purpose of applying the provisions of this Article, the period of 60 months shall be counted from the date on which the person is sent to work in the territory of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purpose of the legislation of Norway, where, according to this Article, a person is subject to the legislation of Norway while residing in the territory of Canada, the spouse and children of the person who live with him or her and who are not subject to the legislation of Canada by reason of employment or self- employment shall be deemed to be resident in the territory of Norway.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>With respect to this Article, unless otherwise provided in an understanding between the competent authority of Norway and the relevant authority of a province of Canada entered into pursuant to Article 31:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person who is sent by an employer having a place of business in the territory of Norway to the territory of Canada shall be subject to all aspects of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Insurance Act</XRefExternal> of Norway; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person who is sent by an employer having a place of business in the territory of Canada to the territory of Norway and who is subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall also be subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Insurance Act</XRefExternal> of Norway with respect to medical care benefits and cash benefits in case of sickness and maternity.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 8</Label><TitleText>Workers on the Continental Shelf</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Articles 6 and 7 shall also apply to a person who works on an installation situated in the continental shelf area of a Party in connection with the exploration of the seabed and sub-soil of that area or the exploitation of its mineral resources.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 9</Label><TitleText>Crews of Ships</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>A person who, but for this Agreement, would be subject to the legislation of both Parties in respect of employment as a member of the crew of a ship shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of Canada if he or she resides in the territory of Canada and is not a Norwegian citizen, and only to the legislation of Norway in any other case.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 10</Label><TitleText>Government Employment</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any provision of this Agreement, the provisions regarding social security of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</XRefExternal>, done at Vienna 18 April 1961 and the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Vienna Convention on Consular Relations</XRefExternal>, done at Vienna 24 April 1963 shall continue to apply.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A person engaged in government employment for a Party who is posted to work in the territory of the other Party shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to the legislation of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Except as provided in paragraphs 1 and 2, a person who resides in the territory of a Party and who is engaged therein in government employment for the other Party shall, in respect of that employment, be subject only to and insured under the legislation of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>As regards the legislation of Norway, the provisions of this Article shall apply correspondingly to the spouse and children living with the person engaged in government employment in the territory of Canada, unless they themselves are subject to the legislation of Canada by reason of employment or self-employment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>When the locally engaged person is subject to the legislation of the Party in whose territory the duties are performed, the other Party shall respect the requirements prescribed by that legislation for all employers.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 11</Label><TitleText>Exceptions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent authorities of the Parties may, by common agreement, modify the application of the provisions of Articles 6 to 10 with respect to any person or categories of persons.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 12</Label><TitleText>Definition of Certain Periods of Residence with Respect to the Legislation of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the purpose of calculating the amount of benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if a person is subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during any period of presence or residence in the territory of Norway, that period shall be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person; it shall also be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with him or her and who are not subject to the legislation of Norway by reason of employment or self-employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if a person is subject to the legislation of Norway during any period of presence or residence in the territory of Canada, that period shall not be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person; it shall also not be considered as a period of residence in Canada for that person’s spouse or common-law partner and dependants who reside with him or her and who are not subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada by reason of employment or self-employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if a person referred to in sub-paragraph 1(b) of this Article also becomes subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada, by virtue of occupying simultaneously more than one employment, that period shall not be counted as a period of residence in Canada.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the application of paragraph 1:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person shall be considered to be subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or to the comprehensive pension plan of a province of Canada during a period of presence or residence in the territory of Norway only if that person makes contributions pursuant to the plan concerned during that period by reason of employment or self-employment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person shall be considered to be subject to the legislation of Norway during a period of presence or residence in the territory of Canada only if that person makes compulsory contributions pursuant to that legislation during that period by reason of employment or self-employment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Provisions Concerning Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>Chapter 1</Label><TitleText>Totalizing of Creditable Periods</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 13</Label><TitleText>Creditable Periods Under the Legislation of Canada and Norway</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is not eligible for a benefit because he or she has not accumulated sufficient creditable periods under the legislation of a Party, the eligibility of that person for that benefit shall be determined by totalizing these periods and the corresponding periods specified in paragraph 2, provided that the periods do not overlap.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text /><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>For the purpose of determining eligibility for a benefit under the legislation of Canada, a creditable period under the legislation of Norway shall be considered as a creditable period under the legislation of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>For the purpose of determining eligibility for a pension under the legislation of Norway, a creditable period under the legislation of Canada shall be considered as a creditable period under the legislation of Norway. For the purpose of assessing whether a deceased person fulfills the conditions of being insured during the last three years prior to the date of death, periods in receipt of a retirement pension under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or a pension or allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> shall be taken into account.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 14</Label><TitleText>Minimum Period to be Totalized</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Agreement, if no right to a benefit exists under the legislation of a Party, the competent institution of a Party shall not be required to pay a benefit to that person in respect of those periods by virtue of this Agreement if:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>as regards Canada, a person’s period of residence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> is less than one year or a person’s earnings in any calendar year do not exceed the minimum required under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>as regards Norway, a person has accumulated less than one year of residence or less than one year of occupational activity under the legislation of Norway.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 15</Label><TitleText>Periods Under the Legislation of a Third State</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is not eligible for a benefit on the basis of the creditable periods completed under the legislation of the Parties, totalized as provided in Article 13, the eligibility of that person for that benefit shall be determined by totalizing these creditable periods and periods completed under the legislation of a third State with which both Parties are bound by social security instruments which provide for the totalizing of periods.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>Chapter 2</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the Legislation of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 16</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the Old Age Security Act</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a person is eligible for a pension or allowance under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of the pension or allowance payable to that person in conformity with the provisions of that Act governing the payment of a partial pension or allowance, exclusively on the basis of the periods of residence in Canada which may be considered under that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 1 shall also apply to a person outside the territory of Canada who would be eligible for a full pension in the territory of Canada but who has not resided in Canada for the minimum period required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of a pension outside the territory of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an Old Age Security pension shall be paid to a person who is outside the territory of Canada only if that person’s periods of residence, when totalized as provided in Chapter 1, are at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of a pension outside the territory of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an allowance and a guaranteed income supplement shall be paid to a person who is outside the territory of Canada only to the extent permitted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>ARTICLE 17</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the Canada Pension Plan</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is eligible for a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of benefit payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the earnings-related portion of the benefit shall be determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, exclusively on the basis of the pensionable earnings under that Plan;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the flat-rate portion of the benefit shall be determined by multiplying:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the benefit determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>by</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the fraction which represents the ratio of the periods of contributions to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in relation to the minimum qualifying period required under that Plan to establish eligibility for that benefit, but in no case shall that fraction exceed the value of one.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>Chapter 3</Label><TitleText>Benefits Under the Legislation of Norway</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><Label>SUB-CHAPTER A</Label><TitleText>Old Age Pension (alderspensjon)</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><Label>ARTICLE 18</Label><TitleText>Calculation of an Old Age Pension</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>An old age pension shall be calculated exclusively on the basis of creditable periods completed and pension points credited under the legislation of Norway.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>SUB-CHAPTER B</Label><TitleText>Disability Pension (uførepensjon)</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><Label>ARTICLE 19</Label><TitleText>Calculation of a Disability Pension</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>If entitlement to a disability pension exists under the legislation of Norway, the disability pension shall be calculated exclusively in accordance with the provisions of the legislation of Norway.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>If entitlement to a disability pension under the legislation of Norway exists only according to the provisions of this Agreement, the pension shall be computed in the following manner:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a theoretical pension amount shall be calculated as if the person’s creditable periods completed under the legislation of Canada had been periods completed under the legislation of Norway;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>this amount shall be multiplied by the ratio between the person’s actual creditable periods completed under the legislation of Norway and the sum of the person’s creditable periods completed under the legislation of both Parties;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in no case shall the person’s actual creditable periods completed under the legislation of Norway, or the sum of the creditable periods completed under the legislation of both Parties, exceed 40 years in the calculation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>A supplementary pension shall be computed on the basis of the average annual pension point figure for the years during which the person concerned has been credited with pension points under the legislation of Norway in accordance with the rules for the calculation of the final pension point figure under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Insurance Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="4"><Label>ARTICLE 20</Label><TitleText>Conversion into an Old Age Pension and Coinciding Periods</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>A disability pension shall be converted into an old age pension in accordance with the provisions of the legislation of Norway when the person concerned reaches the general retirement age.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>To the extent that future insurance periods or future pension point years taken into account for the calculation of a disability pension in accordance with paragraph 1 of Article 19 coincide with corresponding creditable periods taken into account for the calculation of a benefit under the legislation of Canada, the latter periods shall not be taken into account for the calculation of an old age pension under the legislation of Norway. However, the old age pension shall at least be equal to the pension which would have been payable if the disability pension had been determined in accordance with paragraph 2 of Article 19.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>SUB-CHAPTER C</Label><TitleText>Survivor’s Pension (etterlattepensjon)</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><Label>ARTICLE 21</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The provisions of Article 19 and paragraph 1 of Article 20 shall apply correspondingly to survivor’s pensions.</Text></Provision><Heading level="3"><Label>SUB-CHAPTER D</Label><TitleText>Special Provisions Relating to Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><Label>ARTICLE 22</Label><TitleText>Basic Benefits, Attendance Benefits, Education Benefits, Child Care Benefits, Funeral Grant, Guaranteed Minimum Supplementary Pension Benefits for Persons Becoming Disabled at Birth or at a Young Age and Pensions to Refugees and Stateless Persons</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Basic benefits (<Emphasis style="italic">grunnstønad</Emphasis>), attendance benefits (<Emphasis style="italic">hjelpestønad</Emphasis>), education benefits (<Emphasis style="italic">utdanningsstønad</Emphasis>), child care benefits (<Emphasis style="italic">stønad til barnetilsyn</Emphasis>), funeral grant (<Emphasis style="italic">gravferdsstønad</Emphasis>), guaranteed minimum supplementary pension benefits to persons becoming disabled at birth or at a young age (<Emphasis style="italic">garantert tilleggspensjon for unge uføre</Emphasis>) and pensions calculated under the special provisions governing the calculation of pensions to refugees and stateless persons (<Emphasis style="italic">pensjoner til flyktinger og statsløse</Emphasis>) shall be provided only on the conditions specified in the legislation of Norway.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraph 1 of Article 5 shall not apply to the benefits referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article. These benefits shall be payable to persons who stay or reside in the territory of Canada only on the conditions specified in the legislation of Norway.</Text></Provision><Heading level="4"><Label>ARTICLE 23</Label><TitleText>Supplementary Pensions for Persons Born before 1937</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>With regard to the reduced number of pension point years required for the calculation of a full supplementary pension for persons born before 1937, the conditions in the legislation of Norway regarding periods of residence in the territory of Norway shall continue to apply.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Administrative and Miscellaneous Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 24</Label><TitleText>Exchange of Information and Mutual Assistance</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities and institutions responsible for the application of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>shall, to the extent permitted by the legislation which they administer, communicate to each other any information necessary for the application of that legislation as if the matter were affecting the application of their own legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shall lend their good offices and furnish assistance to one another for the purpose of determining eligibility for, or the amount of, any benefit under this Agreement, or under the legislation to which this Agreement applies, as if the matter were affecting the application of their own legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>shall communicate to each other, as soon as possible, all information about the measures taken by them for the application of this Agreement or about changes in their respective legislation insofar as these changes affect the application of this Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The assistance referred to in sub-paragraph 1(b) shall be provided free of charge, subject to any provision contained in an administrative arrangement concluded pursuant to Article 25 for the reimbursement of certain types of expenses.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Unless disclosure is required under the legislation of a Party, any information about a person which is transmitted in accordance with this Agreement to that Party by the other Party is confidential and shall be used only for purposes of implementing this Agreement and the legislation to which this Agreement applies and for no other purpose.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 25</Label><TitleText>Administrative Arrangement</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The competent authorities shall conclude an administrative arrangement which establishes the measures necessary for the application of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The liaison agencies of the Parties shall be designated in that arrangement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 26</Label><TitleText>Exemption or Reduction of Taxes, Dues, Fees and Charges</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any exemption from or reduction of taxes, legal dues, consular fees and administrative charges for which provision is made in the legislation of a Party in connection with the issuing of any certificate or document required to be produced for the application of that legislation shall be extended to certificates or documents required to be produced for the application of the legislation of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any documents of an official nature required to be produced for the application of this Agreement shall be exempt from any authentication by diplomatic or consular authorities or similar formality.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 27</Label><TitleText>Language of Communication</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>For the application of this Agreement, the competent authorities and institutions of the Parties may communicate directly with one another in any official language of either Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any claim which is made to a competent authority or institution of a Party in connection with the application of this Agreement shall be dealt with even if written in an official language of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 28</Label><TitleText>Submitting a Claim, Notice or Appeal</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Claims, notices and appeals concerning eligibility for, or the amount of, a benefit under the legislation of a Party which should, for the purposes of that legislation, have been presented within a prescribed period to a competent authority or institution of that Party, but which are presented within the same period to an authority or institution of the other Party, shall be treated as if they had been presented to the competent authority or institution of the first Party. The date of presentation of claims, notices and appeals to the authority or institution of the other Party shall be deemed to be the date of their presentation to the competent authority or institution of the first Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>A claim for a benefit under the legislation of a Party made after the date of entry into force of this Agreement shall be deemed to be a claim for the corresponding benefit under the legislation of the other Party, provided that the applicant at the time of application:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>requests that it be considered an application under the legislation of the other Party, or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provides information indicating that creditable periods have been completed under the legislation of the other Party.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This paragraph shall not apply if the applicant requests that his or her claim to the benefit be delayed or not considered under the legislation of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>In any case to which paragraph 1 or 2 applies, the authority or institution to which the claim, notice or appeal has been submitted shall transmit it without delay to the authority or institution of the other Party.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 29</Label><TitleText>Payment of Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Payment of benefits under this Agreement may be made in the currency of either Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Benefits shall be paid to beneficiaries free from any deduction for administrative expenses that may be incurred in paying the benefits.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 30</Label><TitleText>Resolution of Difficulties</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent authorities of the two Parties shall resolve, to the extent possible, any difficulties which arise in interpreting or applying this Agreement according to its spirit and fundamental principles.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 31</Label><TitleText>Understandings with a Province of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The competent authority of Norway and the relevant authority of a province of Canada may conclude understandings concerning any social security matter within provincial jurisdiction in Canada insofar as those understandings are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Transitional and Final Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 32</Label><TitleText>Consideration of Previous Events and Periods and Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any creditable period completed before the date of entry into force of this Agreement shall be taken into account for the purpose of determining the right to a benefit under this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 4, no provision of this Agreement shall confer any right to receive payment of a benefit for a period before the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 2, a benefit, other than a death benefit or a funeral grant, shall be payable under this Agreement in respect of events which happened before the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text /><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Any right to a benefit acquired by a person in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway</XRefExternal>, done at Oslo 12 November 1985, shall be maintained.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Any claim to a benefit made but not finally adjudicated at the date upon which this Agreement comes into force, shall be adjudicated according to the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway</XRefExternal>, done at Oslo 12 November 1985, if this gives a more favourable result.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided in this Agreement, a benefit which has been withheld because a person is resident in the territory of the other Party shall, on application by the person concerned, be granted or re-established with effect from the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 33</Label><TitleText>Termination of the Agreement of 12 November 1985 and Recalculation of Benefits</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>With the entry into force of this Agreement, the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Kingdom of Norway</XRefExternal> and its Final Protocol, done at Oslo on 12 November 1985, shall be terminated.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text /><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>A benefit awarded through the application of the Agreement referred to in paragraph 1 shall be recalculated by the competent institution, on request by the beneficiary, taking into account the provisions of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>In no case shall the amount of a benefit be reduced as a result of such recalculation.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text /><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 4, if a request for recalculation is submitted to a competent institution within 24 months of the date of entry into force of this Agreement, the recalculation shall have effect from that date, without the provisions of the legislation of a Party regarding the expiration or prescription of entitlement being applied to the individual.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>If a request for recalculation is submitted to a competent institution later than 24 months from the date of entry into force of this Agreement, the recalculation shall have effect from the date of submission of the request in respect of rights that are neither expired nor prescribed.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>Pensions already payable prior to 1 January 1991 which do not take into account all periods of residence in the territory of Norway prior to 1967 and after 1936, shall be recalculated upon a request from a beneficiary. If the result of such recalculation is more favourable to the beneficiary, the differential amount shall be paid retroactively for 72 months prior to the entry into force of this Agreement, provided that the request is submitted within 24 months of the date of entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 34</Label><TitleText>Duration and Termination</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Agreement shall remain in force without any limitation on its duration. It may be terminated at any time by either Party giving 12 months’ notice in writing to the other Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the event of the termination of this Agreement, any right acquired by a person in accordance with its provisions shall be maintained and negotiations shall take place for the settlement of any rights then in course of acquisition by virtue of those provisions.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 35</Label><TitleText>Entry into Force</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received from the other Party written notification that it has complied with all requirements for the entry into force of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">IN WITNESS WHEREOF</Emphasis>, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">DONE</Emphasis> in duplicate at Ottawa, this 20th day of June 2012, in the English, French and Norwegian languages, each text being equally authentic.</Text></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626569" lims:id="626569" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626570" lims:id="626570" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626571" lims:id="626571" cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" /><colspec colname="col2" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2013-12-06" lims:fid="626572" lims:id="626572"><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">DIANE FINLEY</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">ELSE BERIT EIKELAND</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="bold">FOR CANADA</Emphasis></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE KINGDOM OF NORWAY</Emphasis></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule></Regulation>