<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2021-06-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2021-06-24" lims:current-date="2025-07-24" lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301851" lims:id="1301851" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301852" lims:id="1301852"><InstrumentNumber>SI/2021-38</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>7</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301853" lims:id="1301853"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">CRIMINAL CODE</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301854" lims:id="1301854">Order Accepting the Recommendation of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness that Each Listed Entity Remain a Listed Entity</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2021-631</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301855" lims:id="1301855"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301856" lims:id="1301856" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 83.05(8.1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29075">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29076">b</FootnoteRef>, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness has completed a review of each entity set out in the annexed schedule and listed in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2002-284">Regulations Establishing a List of Entities</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29077">c</FootnoteRef>, made pursuant to subsection 83.05(1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29078">d</FootnoteRef> of that Act, and has determined that there are still reasonable grounds, as set out in subsection 83.05(1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29078">d</FootnoteRef> of that Act, for each entity to remain a listed entity;</Text><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29075" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2019, c. 13, s. 141(4)</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29076" placement="page" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>R.S., c. C-46</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29077" placement="page" status="official"><Label>c</Label><Text>SOR/2002-284</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29078" placement="page" status="official"><Label>d</Label><Text>S.C. 2019, c. 13, s. 141(1)</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301857" lims:id="1301857" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>And whereas, pursuant to subsection 83.05(1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29078">d</FootnoteRef> of that Act, the Administrator in Council is satisfied, on the recommendation of that Minister, that there are reasonable grounds to believe that each listed entity set out in the annexed schedule is an entity that has knowingly carried out, attempted to carry out, participated in or facilitated a terrorist activity or that has knowingly acted on behalf of, at the direction of or in association with such an entity;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301858" lims:id="1301858" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Therefore, His Excellency the Administrator of the Government of Canada in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness made pursuant to subsection 83.05(8.1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29075">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-4537_hq_29076">b</FootnoteRef>, accepts the recommendation that each listed entity set out in the annexed schedule remain a listed entity.</Text></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:lastAmendedDate="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301859" lims:id="1301859"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301860" lims:id="1301860"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><TitleText>Listed Entities Reviewed by the Minister</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301861" lims:id="1301861" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Al Qaida (also known among other names as Al Jihad (AJ), Egyptian Islamic Jihad (EIJ), Vanguards of Conquest (VOC), Islamic Army, Islamic Salvation Foundation, The Base, Group for the Preservation of the Holy Sites, Islamic Army for the Liberation of the Holy Places, World Islamic Front for Jihad Against Jews and Crusaders, Usama Bin Ladin Network, Usama Bin Ladin Organization and Qa’idat al-Jihad)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301862" lims:id="1301862" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Asbat Al-Ansar (AAA) (“The League of Partisans”) (also known among other names as God’s Partisans, Gathering of Supporters, Partisan’s League, Osbat Al Ansar, Usbat Al Ansar, Esbat Al-Ansar, Isbat Al Ansar, Usbat-ul-Ansar, Band of Helpers, Band of Partisans and League of the Followers)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301863" lims:id="1301863" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Euskadi Ta Askatasuna (ETA) (also known among other names as Basque Homeland and Liberty, Euzkadi Ta Azkatasuna, Euzkadi Ta Askatasuna, Basque Nation and Liberty, Basque Fatherland and Liberty and Basque Homeland and Freedom)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301864" lims:id="1301864" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Hamas (Harakat Al-Muqawama Al-Islamiya) (“Islamic Resistance Movement”)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301865" lims:id="1301865" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Hizballah (also known among other names as Hizbullah, Hizbollah, Hezbollah, Hezballah, Hizbu’llah, The Party of God, Islamic Jihad (Islamic Holy War), Islamic Jihad Organization, Islamic Resistance, Islamic Jihad for the Liberation of Palestine, Ansar al-Allah (Followers of God/Partisans of God/God’s Helpers), Ansarollah (Followers of God/Partisans of God/God’s Helpers), Ansar Allah (Followers of God/Partisans of God/God’s Helpers), Al-Muqawamah al-Islamiyyah (Islamic Resistance), Organization of the Oppressed, Organization of the Oppressed on Earth, Revolutionary Justice Organization, Organization of Right Against Wrong and Followers of the Prophet Muhammed)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301866" lims:id="1301866" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Jaish-e-Mohammed (JeM) (also known among other names as Jaish-i-Mohammed (Mohammad, Muhammad, Muhammed), Jaish-e-Mohammad (Muhammed), Jaish-e-Mohammad Mujahideen E-Tanzeem, Jeish-e-Mahammed, Army of Mohammed, Mohammed’s Army, Tehrik Ul-Furqaan, National Movement for the Restoration of Pakistani Sovereignty and Army of the Prophet)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301867" lims:id="1301867" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Palestinian Islamic Jihad (PIJ) (also known among other names as Harakat al-Jihad al-Islami fi Filistin, Saraya Al-Quds (The Jerusalem Brigades), Al-Quds Brigades, Islamic Jihad, Palestine Islamic Jihad – Shaqaqi Faction, Palestinian Islamic Jihad – Shaqaqi, PIJ – Shaqaqi Faction, PIJ – Shallah Faction, Islamic Jihad of Palestine, Islamic Jihad in Palestine, Abu Ghunaym Squad of the Hizballah Bayt Al-Maqdis, Al-Quds Squads, Al-Awdah Brigades, Islamic Jihad Palestine (IJP), Islamic Jihad — Palestine Faction and Islamic Holy War)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301868" lims:id="1301868" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine (PFLP) (Al-Jibha al-Sha’biya lil-Tahrir Filistin) (also known among other names as Halhul Gang, Halhul Squad, Palestinian Popular Resistance Forces, PPRF, Red Eagle Gang, Red Eagle Group, Red Eagles and Abu Ali Mustafa Brigades)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2021-06-24" lims:enacted-date="2021-06-24" lims:fid="1301869" lims:id="1301869" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes"><Text>Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine — General Command (PFLP-GC) (Al-Jibha Sha’biya lil-Tahrir Filistin-al-Qadiya al-Ama)</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>