<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641618" lims:id="641618" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641619" lims:id="641619"><InstrumentNumber>SI/88-112</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1988</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641621" lims:id="641621"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-34">PUBLIC SERVICE REARRANGEMENT AND TRANSFER OF DUTIES ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641622" lims:id="641622">Order Transferring to the Minister of Western Economic Diversification the Powers, Duties and Functions of the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development Under Certain Acts in Relation to the Western Provinces</ShortTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1988-1363</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1988</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641623" lims:id="641623"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641624" lims:id="641624" language-align="yes" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Prime Minister, pursuant to section 2 of the Public Service Rearrangement and Transfer of Duties Act, is pleased hereby to transfer</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641625" lims:id="641625" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>from the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development to the Minister of Western Economic Diversification the powers, duties and functions under paragraph 6(b) of the Department of Regional Industrial Expansion Act, that were transferred by Order in Council P.C. 1987-1613 of August 4, 1987* in relation to entering into agreements that are made under Economic and Regional Development Agreements with any of the Governments of the Provinces of Manitoba, British Columbia, Alberta and Saskatchewan except where those agreements affect only one firm, deal with the general advancement of science and technology, deal only with a comprehensive restructuring of an industrial sector, or deal with the development of northern areas or with the tourism sector;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641626" lims:id="641626" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>from the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development to the Minister of Western Economic Diversification the powers, duties and functions under Regional Economic Expansion Vote 11a of the Appropriation Act No. 5, 1973, that were transferred by Order in Council 1987-1614 of August 4, 1987**, in relation to entering into subsidiary agreements to affect the purposes of General Development Agreements made with any of the Governments of the Provinces of Manitoba, British Columbia, Alberta and Saskatchewan except where those agreements affect only one firm, deal with the general advancement of science and technology, deal only with a comprehensive restructuring of an industrial sector, or deal with the development of northern areas or with the tourism sector;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641627" lims:id="641627" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>from the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development to the Minister of Western Economic Diversification the powers, duties and functions, that were transferred under Orders in Council P.C. 1984-2694 of July 25, 1984*** and P.C. 1987-1618 of August 4, 1987****, in relation to the Provinces of Manitoba, British Columbia, Alberta and Saskatchewan;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641628" lims:id="641628" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>from the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development to the Minister of Western Economic Diversification the powers, duties and functions of the Minister of Regional Industrial Expansion that were transferred by Order in Council P.C. 1987-1619 of August 4, 1987*****, with respect to assistance that is provided in relation to a project the eligible capital costs of which do not exceed twenty million dollars and that is in accordance with the terms and conditions of the Western Transportation Industrial Development Program established under the authority of paragraph 5.1(d) of the Department of Regional Industrial Expansion Act; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641629" lims:id="641629" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>from the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development to the Minister of Western Economic Diversification the control and supervision of that part of the public service of Canada in the Department of Regional Industrial Expansion known as the offices of the Federal Economic Development Coordinators Branch in the Provinces of Manitoba, British Columbia, Alberta and Saskatchewan, which was transferred by Order in Council P.C. 1987-1620 of August 4, 1987******.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641630" lims:id="641630" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Footnote status="official"><Label>     *</Label><Text>SI/87-166, 1987 <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> Part II, p. 3346</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641631" lims:id="641631" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Footnote status="official"><Label>    **</Label><Text>SI/87-167, 1987 <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> Part II, p. 3347</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641632" lims:id="641632" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Footnote status="official"><Label>   ***</Label><Text>SI/84-151, 1984 <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> Part II, p. 3249</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641633" lims:id="641633" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Footnote status="official"><Label>  ****</Label><Text>SI/87-171, 1987 <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> Part II, p. 3351</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641634" lims:id="641634" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Footnote status="official"><Label> *****</Label><Text>SI/87-172, 1987 <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> Part II, p. 3352</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="641635" lims:id="641635" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Footnote status="official"><Label>******</Label><Text>SI/87-173, 1987 <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> Part II, p. 3353</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order></Regulation>