<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2019-06-17" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-17" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642525" lims:id="642525" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642526" lims:id="642526"><InstrumentNumber>SI/90-155</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1990</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642528" lims:id="642528"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="W-6">WEIGHTS AND MEASURES ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642529" lims:id="642529">Metering Assemblies Incorporating Electronic ATCs Specifications</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642530" lims:id="642530">Specifications Relating to the Design, Composition, Construction and Performance of Metering Assemblies Incorporating Electronic Automatic Temperature Compensators and Relating to the Installation and Use Thereof</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642531" lims:id="642531"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642532" lims:id="642532" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to paragraph 13(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1605">Weights and Measures Regulations</XRefExternal>, C.R.C., c. 1605, a copy of proposed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-90-155">Specifications relating to the design, composition, construction and performance of metering assemblies incorporating electronic automatic temperature compensators and relating to the installation and use thereof</XRefExternal>, in the form annexed hereto, was published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> Part I on February 24, 1990;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642533" lims:id="642533" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, the Minister of Consumer and Corporate Affairs, pursuant to paragraph 10(l)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="W-6">Weights and Measures Act</XRefExternal> and sections 13<FootnoteRef idref="fn_SI-90-155_e_hq_5150">*</FootnoteRef> and 27<FootnoteRef idref="fn_SI-90-155_e_hq_5150">*</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1605">Weights and Measures Regulations</XRefExternal>, C.R.C., c. 1605, hereby establishes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-90-155">Specifications relating to the design, composition, construction and performance of metering assemblies incorporating electronic automatic temperature compensators and relating to the installation and use thereof</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642534" lims:id="642534" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Ottawa, Ontario, October 5, 1990</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642535" lims:id="642535" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="right">PIERRE BLAIS</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Minister of Consumer and Corporate Affairs</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Footnote id="fn_SI-90-155_e_hq_5150" placement="page" status="official"><Label>*</Label><Text>SOR/78-792, 1978 <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> Part II, p. 3894</Text></Footnote></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642536" lims:id="642536"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642537" lims:id="642537" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642538" lims:id="642538"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Specifications may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-90-155">Metering Assemblies Incorporating Electronic ATCs Specifications</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642539" lims:id="642539" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642540" lims:id="642540"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642541" lims:id="642541"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In these Specifications,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642542" lims:id="642542" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>ATC</DefinedTermEn> means automatic temperature compensator; (<DefinedTermFr>CAT</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642543" lims:id="642543" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>metering assembly</DefinedTermEn> means a device for use in trade for measuring liquids; (<DefinedTermFr>ensemble de mesurage</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642544" lims:id="642544" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>reference pressure</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642545" lims:id="642545"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a liquid that has an equilibrium vapour pressure of less than 101.325 kPa at measurement temperature,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642546" lims:id="642546"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in metric units, an absolute pressure equal to 101.325 kPa, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642547" lims:id="642547"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in Canadian units, an absolute pressure equal to 14.73 pounds per square inch, and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642548" lims:id="642548"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a liquid that has an equilibrium vapour pressure of 101.325 kPa or more at measurement temperature, the equilibrium vapour pressure at the temperature of the liquid as it is being measured; (<DefinedTermFr>pression de référence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642549" lims:id="642549" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Regulations</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._1605">Weights and Measures Regulations</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Règlement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642550" lims:id="642550" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>VCF</DefinedTermEn> means volume correction factor as defined in section 270 of the Regulations. (<DefinedTermFr>FCV</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642551" lims:id="642551"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All other words and expressions used in these Specifications have the same meaning as in the Regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642552" lims:id="642552" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642553" lims:id="642553"><Label>3</Label><Text>These Specifications apply in respect of all metering assemblies incorporating ATCs of the electronic type that cause the registration of volumes measured by a meter to be in units corrected to a reference temperature.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642554" lims:id="642554" level="1"><TitleText>Exception</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642555" lims:id="642555"><Label>4</Label><Text>Notwithstanding section 236 of the Regulations, in the case of liquid petroleum products, liquefied petroleum gases, butane and natural gas liquids, the meter equipped with an ATC in a metering assembly may register the volume of liquid in units corrected to a temperature of 15°C and to the reference pressure.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642556" lims:id="642556" level="1"><TitleText>Design, Composition and Construction</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642557" lims:id="642557"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642558" lims:id="642558"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A register incorporating an ATC in a metering assembly shall be designed to register the net volume and, on demand for inspection purposes, the gross volume.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642559" lims:id="642559"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A register shall be designed so that the gross volume is determined directly from the signal from the measuring element of the meter, not by calculation from net volume.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642560" lims:id="642560"><Label>6</Label><Text>A register that continuously registers both net and gross volumes and is equipped with unit price and total price displays shall be designed to calculate the total price as the product of the unit price displayed and the net volume delivered.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642561" lims:id="642561"><Label>7</Label><Text>Any means of adjusting an ATC shall be sealable and located so as to be inaccessible without the removal of a portion of the exterior housing of the device containing the ATC.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642562" lims:id="642562"><Label>8</Label><Text>A register incorporating an ATC shall be designed to register on demand for inspection purposes the temperature of the metered liquid as measured by the temperature sensor used with the ATC and to have a minimum increment of registration of temperature not exceeding 0.1°C.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642563" lims:id="642563"><Label>9</Label><Text>A temperature sensor used with an ATC shall be of the interchangeable type, so that replacing one sensor with another does not alter the temperature measurement by more than 0.3°C over the temperature range of the ATC.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642564" lims:id="642564"><Label>10</Label><Text>A temperature sensor, or an assembly comprising a temperature sensor and a thermal well, shall be sealable so that the exposure of the sensor or assembly to the liquid to be metered cannot be altered without breaking the seal.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642565" lims:id="642565"><Label>11</Label><Text>A register incorporating an ATC shall be designed so that it is inoperable if the electrical circuit for the temperature sensor is shorted or incomplete.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642566" lims:id="642566"><Label>12</Label><Text>An ATC that may be used for more than one liquid shall incorporate an interlocking mechanism that ensures that the temperature correction factors corresponding to the liquid chosen are automatically selected.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642567" lims:id="642567"><Label>13</Label><Text>A register incorporating an ATC shall be designed to indicate the density or cubical coefficient of thermal expansion per degree Celsius of the liquid for which it is designed to be used or, if it is designed to be used for more than one liquid, the range of densities or cubical coefficients of thermal expansion per degree Celsius over which it is designed to be used, and the density or cubical coefficient of thermal expansion per degree Celsius to which it is adjusted, by one or more of the following means:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642568" lims:id="642568"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>applying a permanent marking in a legible and visible manner on the name-plate of the register;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642569" lims:id="642569"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>applying a permanent marking in a legible and visible manner on a metal tag affixed to the register;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642570" lims:id="642570"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>legibly displaying or printing the data on demand;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642571" lims:id="642571"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>using codes or legends associated with switch settings or jumper locations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642572" lims:id="642572"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>using any other means of ready access that indicates the data as clearly as the means set out in paragraphs (a) to (d).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642573" lims:id="642573"><Label>14</Label><Text>In addition to showing the information required by section 27 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">Electronic Registers and Ancillary Equipment Incorporated in Metering Assemblies Specifications</XRefExternal>, an electronic printer forming part of a metering assembly that indicates the amount of a delivery from a bulk meter, receiving meter or aircraft refueller equipped with an ATC shall provide a ticket that shows the net volume and gross volume, and the density used to determine the VCF.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-17" lims:fid="642574" lims:id="642574"><Label>15</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-17" lims:enacted-date="2014-06-19" lims:fid="642575" lims:id="1145874"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the test thermal well required by section 24 shall be constructed so that the name or trademark of the manufacturer and the model number of the well are on the end fitting.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642576" lims:id="642576"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the end fitting is not large enough to accommodate the information referred to in subsection (1), the information may appear on a metal tag affixed to the test thermal well.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-17" lims:enacted-date="2014-06-19" lims:fid="1145876" lims:id="1145876">2014, c. 20, s. 366(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642577" lims:id="642577"><Label>16</Label><Text>An ATC designed for a meter that measures liquids at an ambient temperature shall correct the measurement results within the applicable limits of error set out in section 270 of the Regulations over at least the range of liquid temperature of -30°C to +40°C or, if the name-plate of the ATC indicates a wider temperature range, over at least that wider temperature range.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642578" lims:id="642578"><Label>17</Label><Text>An ATC designed for a meter that measures liquids at temperatures different from the ambient temperature shall correct the measurement results within the applicable limits of error set out in section 270 of the Regulations over the temperature range marked on the name-plate of the ATC, which range shall cover at least 50 degrees Celsius.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642579" lims:id="642579"><Label>18</Label><Text>When the temperature of a liquid is outside the temperature range of an ATC, the ATC shall be designed</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642580" lims:id="642580"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to automatically prevent further deliveries; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642581" lims:id="642581"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to remain operative where the VCF does not exceed the value corresponding to the temperature of the liquid.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642582" lims:id="642582" level="1"><TitleText>Performance</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642583" lims:id="642583"><Label>19</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642584" lims:id="642584"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where the section of pipe, or other component, containing test liquid and the temperature sensor in a metering assembly incorporating an ATC have first been stabilized at ambient temperature and where test liquid at a temperature approximately 20°C higher or lower than ambient temperature is suddenly caused to flow through the pipe section at a mean velocity of approximately 3 m/s, the temperature sensor shall respond to at least 90 per cent of the variation in the temperature of the liquid</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642585" lims:id="642585"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>within 15 seconds, in the case of motor fuel dispensers; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642586" lims:id="642586"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>within 20 seconds, in the case of any other type of meter.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642587" lims:id="642587"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), the test liquid shall be mineral spirits or any other liquid with similar physical properties.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642588" lims:id="642588"><Label>20</Label><Text>A meter equipped with an ATC shall, when inspected using the gross mode of registration, meet the performance specifications applicable to volumetric liquid meters.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642589" lims:id="642589"><Label>21</Label><Text>An ATC shall remain within the applicable limits of error set out in section 270 of the Regulations when the ATC and the sensor are tested under the conditions set out in sections 29 to 31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">Electronic Registers and Ancillary Equipment Incorporated in Metering Assemblies Specifications</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642590" lims:id="642590"><Label>22</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 270(7) of the Regulations, the test volume for an ATC shall be an amount equivalent to a normal delivery through the meter, but at no time shall the test volume be less than 2,000 times the value of the minimum increment of registration of the meter register as set out in section 20 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="standard">Electronic Registers and Ancillary Equipment Incorporated in Metering Assemblies Specifications</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642591" lims:id="642591" level="1"><TitleText>Installation and Use</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642592" lims:id="642592"><Label>23</Label><Text>A temperature sensor that is used with an ATC shall be located no more than 1 m from the meter, as measured along the piping of the meter, and shall be installed so that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642593" lims:id="642593"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the sensing end of the sensor is near the axis of the pipe carrying the liquid; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642594" lims:id="642594"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>no valves, pumps or other equipment that may alter the temperature of the liquid are located between the sensor and the meter.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642595" lims:id="642595"><Label>24</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642596" lims:id="642596"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A test thermal well that has an inside diameter of not less than 3.3 mm and not more than 4.5 mm shall be installed adjacent to the temperature sensor that is used with an ATC.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642597" lims:id="642597"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The test thermal well shall be installed so that the well retains thermal conducting fluid during a test.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642598" lims:id="642598"><Label>25</Label><Text>The temperature sensor that is used with an ATC shall be installed so as to minimize the transfer of heat from the sensing end of the sensor to the atmosphere.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642599" lims:id="642599"><Label>26</Label><Text>A register incorporating an ATC designed or, if adjustable, adjusted for a liquid of a certain density or cubical coefficient of thermal expansion may be used for another liquid if the difference in the VCFs of the two liquids is 0.25 per cent or less at a temperature of 0°C.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642600" lims:id="642600"><Label>27</Label><Text>Where one of the meters in a metering assembly used for delivering a blend of liquids is equipped with an ATC, all of the other meters in the metering assembly shall also be equipped with ATCs.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="642601" lims:id="642601"><Label>28</Label><Text>Where a meter is equipped with a means of adjustment, the means of adjustment shall be installed so that any adjustments are applied to both the net and the gross registrations.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>