<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655146" lims:id="655146" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655147" lims:id="655147"><InstrumentNumber>SI/99-99</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1999</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655149" lims:id="655149"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11">FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655150" lims:id="655150">Overpayments to Certain Members of the Canadian Forces Remission Order</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1999-1519 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY> 1999</YYYY><MM>8</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655151" lims:id="655151"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655152" lims:id="655152" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, considering that it is in the public interest to do so, on the recommendation of the Minister of National Defence and the Treasury Board, pursuant to subsection 23(2.1)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_SI-99-99_e_hq_6452">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-99-99">Overpayments to Certain Members of the Canadian Forces Remission Order</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_SI-99-99_e_hq_6452" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1991, c. 24, s. 7(2)</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655153" lims:id="655153"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655154" lims:id="655154"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655155" lims:id="655155">Pay and Allowances, Annuities and Other Benefits</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>If a member of the Canadian Forces was reclassified from the general service officer military classification to the pilot classification during the period beginning on December 1, 1977 and ending on December 31, 1994 and as a result of that classification received an amount representing pay and allowances and, in certain cases, annuities or other benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-17">Canadian Forces Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> that was in excess of the amount that would have been paid had the incentive pay of that member been calculated in accordance with the Canadian Forces Administrative Order governing transfers to the pilot military occupation, remission of the amount of the excess payment is hereby granted to that member, including any interest payable on it.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655156" lims:id="655156"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="655157" lims:id="655157">Death Benefits and Allowances</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>If a person, with respect to a member of the Canadian Forces referred to in section 1, received an amount representing death benefits or allowances under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-17">Canadian Forces Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> that was in excess of the amount that would have been paid had the incentive pay of that member been calculated in accordance with the Canadian Forces Administrative Order governing transfers to pilot military occupation, remission of the amount of the excess payment is hereby granted to that person, including any interest payable on it.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>