<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649892" lims:id="649892" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649893" lims:id="649893"><InstrumentNumber>SI/97-111</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1997</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649895" lims:id="649895"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649896" lims:id="649896">Proclamation Declaring the Second Supplementary Agreement Amending the Agreement on Social Security Between Canada and the United States of America in Force October 1, 1997</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649897" lims:id="649897"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649898" lims:id="649898" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ROMÉO LEBLANC</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649899" lims:id="649899" format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649900" lims:id="649900" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649901" lims:id="649901" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Elizabeth the Second, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649902" lims:id="649902" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>To all to whom these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649903" lims:id="649903" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649904" lims:id="649904" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">GEORGE THOMSON</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649905" lims:id="649905" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="no"><Text>A Proclamation</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649906" lims:id="649906" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1996-1561 of October 8, 1996, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article 8 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Second Supplementary Agreement amending the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United States of America with respect to Social Security</XRefExternal>, signed on May 28, 1996, the Second Supplementary Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received written notification from the other Party that it has completed the legal procedures required for the entry into force of that Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649907" lims:id="649907" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Order was laid before Parliament on November 25, 1996;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649908" lims:id="649908" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order was laid before Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649909" lims:id="649909" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it was laid before Parliament, being March 3, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649910" lims:id="649910" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas instruments of ratification were exchanged on June 25, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649911" lims:id="649911" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Second Supplementary Agreement will enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the instruments of ratification were exchanged, being October 1, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649912" lims:id="649912" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1997-1169 of August 28, 1997, the Governor in Council directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Second Supplementary Agreement amending the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United States of America with respect to Social Security</XRefExternal> is in force as of October 1, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649913" lims:id="649913" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now Know You that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our Proclamation give notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Second Supplementary Agreement amending the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United States of America with respect to Social Security</XRefExternal>, signed on May 28, 1996, a copy of which is annexed hereto, is in force as of October 1, 1997.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649914" lims:id="649914" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of All Which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649915" lims:id="649915" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Testimony Whereof, We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patent and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. Witness: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Roméo A LeBlanc, a Member of Our Privy Council for Canada, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649916" lims:id="649916" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>At Our Government House, in Our City of Ottawa, this sixteenth day of September in the year of Our Lord one thousand nine hundred and ninety-seven and in the forty-sixth year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649917" lims:id="649917" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="15pc"><SignatureLine justification="right">By Command,</SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="right" topmarginspacing="4">KEVIN G. LYNCH</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649918" lims:id="649918" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Second Supplementary Agreement Amending the Agreement Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United States of America with Respect to Social Security</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The Government of Canada</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">and</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the Government of the United States of America,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Noting the Agreement between them with respect to Social Security, signed at Ottawa on March 11, 1981, and the Supplementary Agreement amending that Agreement, signed at Ottawa on May 10, 1983, and</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Having determined the need to adjust certain provisions of the Agreement,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Have decided to conclude a second Supplementary Agreement and, to this end,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Have agreed as follows:</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>For the purposes of this Supplementary Agreement:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>the Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United States of America with respect to Social Security</XRefExternal>, signed at Ottawa on March 11, 1981, as amended by the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Supplementary Agreement Amending the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United States of America with respect to Social Security</XRefExternal>, signed at Ottawa on May 10, 1983;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other term has the meaning assigned to it in the Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Article I of the Agreement is amended as follows:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>In paragraph (1), the word “and” between the words “Guam” and “American Samoa” is replaced by a comma (“,”), and the words “and the Northern Mariana Islands” are added immediately after “American Samoa”.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>In paragraph (4), the words “Secretary of Health and Human Services” are deleted, and the words “Commissioner of Social Security” are substituted in their place.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>In paragraph (5), the words “Department of National Health and Welfare” are deleted, and the words “Department of Employment and Immigration (designated by Human Resources Development)” are substituted in their place; and the hyphen (“-”) and the word “Taxation” are deleted.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>In paragraph (9), the period (“.”) at the end thereof is deleted, and a semi-colon (“;”) is substituted in its place.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>The following new paragraphs (10) and (11) are inserted immediately after paragraph (9):</Text><AmendedText><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="5"><Label>“ (10)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Government of Canada</DefinedTermEn> means the Government in its capacity as representative of Her Majesty the Queen in right of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="5"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Any term not defined in this Article has the meaning assigned to it in the applicable laws.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Article II of the Agreement is amended as follows:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>In paragraph (1) (a) (ii), “1954” is deleted, and “1986” is substituted in its place.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Paragraph (3) is deleted, and the following new paragraphs (3) and (4) are substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>“(3)</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph (4), this Agreement shall also apply to laws which amend, supplement, consolidate or supersede the laws specified in paragraph (1).</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>This Agreement shall apply to laws which extend the laws of a Contracting State to new categories of beneficiaries unless an objection on the part of that Contracting State has been communicated to the other Contracting State not later than three months following the entry into force of such laws.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Paragraph (4) is renumbered as paragraph (5).</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Article V of the Agreement is amended as follows:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Paragraph 2(a) is revised to read as follows:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>“Where a person who is normally employed in the territory of one Contracting State and who is covered under its laws in respect of work performed for an employer having a place of business in that territory is sent by that employer to work for the same employer in the territory of the other Contracting State, the person shall be subject to the laws of only the first Contracting State in respect of that work, as if it were performed in the territory of the first Contracting State. The preceding sentence shall apply provided that the period of work in the territory of the other Contracting State is not expected to exceed 60 months. For purposes of applying this sub-paragraph, an employer and an affiliated company of that employer (as defined under the laws of the Contracting State from which the person was sent) shall be considered one and the same, provided that the employment in the other Contracting State would have been subject to the laws on compulsory coverage of the Contracting State from which the person was sent in the absence of this Agreement.”</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Paragraph (9) is deleted.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Chapter 2 of Part III of the Agreement is deleted, and the following new Chapter 2 is substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><Label><Emphasis style="bold">“CHAPTER 2</Emphasis></Label><TitleText>Provisions Applicable to Canada</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE VIII</Label></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="3"><Label>(1) (a)</Label><Text>If a person is not entitled to the payment of a benefit because he or she has not accumulated sufficient periods of residence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, or periods of coverage under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, the entitlement of that person to the payment of that benefit shall, subject to sub-paragraph (1)(b), be determined by totalizing these periods and those specified in paragraph (2), provided that the periods do not overlap.</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1.5" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="3"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>In the application of sub-paragraph (1)(a) of this Article to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="3" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="5"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>only periods of residence in Canada completed on or after January 1, 1952, including periods deemed as such under Article VI of this Agreement, shall be taken into account; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="3" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="5"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if the total duration of those periods of residence is less than one year and if, taking into account only those periods, no right to a benefit exists under that Act, the agency of Canada shall not be required to pay a benefit in respect of those periods by virtue of this Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="3"><Label>(2) (a)</Label><Text>For purposes of determining entitlement to the payment of a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, a quarter of coverage credited under United States laws on or after January 1, 1952 and after the age at which periods of residence in Canada are credited for purposes of that Act shall be considered as three months of residence in the territory of Canada.</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1.5" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="3"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>For purposes of determining entitlement to the payment of a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, a calendar year including at least one quarter of coverage credited under United States laws shall be considered as a year of coverage credited under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE IX</Label></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person is entitled to the payment of an Old Age Security pension or a spouse’s allowance solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Article VIII, the agency of Canada shall calculate the amount of the pension or spouse’s allowance payable to that person in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> governing the payment of a partial pension or a spouse’s allowance, exclusively on the basis of the periods of residence in Canada on or after January 1, 1952 which may be considered under that Act or are deemed as such under Article VI of this Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1) shall also apply to a person outside Canada who would be entitled to the payment of a full pension in Canada but who has not resided in Canada for the minimum period required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for entitlement to the payment of a pension outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Agreement:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an Old Age Security pension shall be paid to a person who is outside Canada only if that person’s periods of residence, totalized as provided in Article VIII, are at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for entitlement to the payment of a pension outside Canada; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a spouse’s allowance and a guaranteed income supplement shall be paid to a person who is outside of Canada only to the extent permitted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>ARTICLE X</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>If a person is entitled to the payment of a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Article VIII, the agency of Canada shall calculate the amount of benefit payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the earnings-related portion of the benefit shall be determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, exclusively on the basis of the pensionable earnings under that Plan; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the flat-rate portion of the benefit shall be determined by multiplying:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the benefit determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-4-4"><Text>by</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the fraction which represents the ratio of the periods of coverage under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in relation to the minimum qualifying period required under that Plan to establish entitlement to that benefit, but in no case shall that fraction exceed the value of one.”.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Article XII of the Agreement is amended as follows:</Text><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The following new sub-paragraph (b) is inserted immediately after sub-paragraph a):</Text><AmendedText><Provision first-line-indent="2" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="5"><Label>“(b)</Label><Text>To the extent permitted by the laws which they administer, and any other relevant national statutes, communicate to each other any information necessary for the application of this Agreement;”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The existing sub-paragraphs (b) and (c) are respectively redesignated as sub-paragraphs (c) and (d)</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Article XIII is amended by adding the following sentence at the end thereof:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>“In accordance with arrangements to be agreed upon pursuant to Article XII(a), the Competent Authorities and agencies may also assist each other in administering the laws to which this Agreement applies.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE 8</Label></Heading><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Contracting States shall notify each other in writing, through the diplomatic channel, of the completion of their respective legal procedures required for the entry into force of this Supplementary Agreement. This Supplementary Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month after the date of the last notification.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the entry into force of this Supplementary Agreement, any reference in the Agreement to “this Agreement” shall be taken to mean the Agreement as amended by this Supplementary Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The application of this Supplementary Agreement shall not result in any reduction in the amount of a benefit to which entitlement was established prior to its entry into force.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph (5), this Supplementary Agreement shall remain in force without any limitation on its duration.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In the event of the termination of the Agreement through the application of paragraph (1) of Article XXI thereof, this Supplementary Agreement shall also be terminated, with effect on the same day as the termination of the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Supplementary Agreement.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Done in two copies at Ottawa, this 28<Sup>th</Sup> day of May, 1996, in the English and French languages, both texts being equally authentic.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="4"><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="45.63*" /><colspec colname="3" colwidth="46.51*" /><tbody><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">DOUGLAS YOUNG</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">JAMES D. WALSH</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>