<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651651" lims:id="651651" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651652" lims:id="651652"><InstrumentNumber>SI/98-51</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1998</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651654" lims:id="651654"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651655" lims:id="651655">Proclamation Giving Notice that the Administrative Understanding on Mutual Assistance Shall be Effective Upon the Entering Into Force of the Second Supplementary Agreement Between Canada and the United States of America</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651656" lims:id="651656"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651657" lims:id="651657" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ROMÉO LEBLANC</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651658" lims:id="651658" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651659" lims:id="651659" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651660" lims:id="651660" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Elizabeth the Second, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651661" lims:id="651661" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>To All to Whom these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651662" lims:id="651662" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651663" lims:id="651663" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">RICHARD THOMPSON</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Acting/Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651664" lims:id="651664" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>A Proclamation</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651665" lims:id="651665" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1997-497 of April 8, 1997, the Governor in Council declared that the Administrative Understanding on Mutual Assistance, signed on December 4, 1996, shall be effective upon the entering into force of the Second Supplementary Agreement between Canada and the United States of America;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651666" lims:id="651666" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Order was laid before Parliament on October 2, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651667" lims:id="651667" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order was laid before Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651668" lims:id="651668" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it was laid before Parliament, being November 27, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651669" lims:id="651669" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Administrative Understanding on Mutual Assistance shall be effective upon the entering into force of the Second Supplementary Agreement, which is October 1, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651670" lims:id="651670" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1998-289 of February 26, 1998, the Governor in Council directed that a Proclamation do issue giving notice that the Administrative Understanding on Mutual Assistance shall be effective upon the entering into force of the Second Supplementary Agreement between Canada and the United States of America;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651671" lims:id="651671" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now Know You that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our Proclamation give notice that the Administrative Understanding on Mutual Assistance, signed on December 4, 1996, a copy of which is annexed hereto, shall be effective upon the entering into force of the Second Supplementary Agreement between Canada and the United States of America.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651672" lims:id="651672" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of All Which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651673" lims:id="651673" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Testimony Whereof, We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patent and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. Witness: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Roméo A. LeBlanc, a Member of Our Privy Council for Canada, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651674" lims:id="651674" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>At Our Government House, in Our City of Ottawa, this twentieth day of March in the year of Our Lord one thousand nine hundred and ninety-eight and in the forty-seventh year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651675" lims:id="651675" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651676" lims:id="651676" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="right">KEVIN G. LYNCH</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651677" lims:id="651677" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Administrative Understanding on Mutual Assistance</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Pursuant to the Agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United States of America with respect to Social Security</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Leader leader="solid" length="15pc" /></Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>SECTION I</Label></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Introduction</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The Competent Authority of the United States of America and the Competent Authority of Canada, with the purpose of improving the administrative efficiency, cost effectiveness and integrity of their Social Security programs as they apply to claimants and beneficiaries of the two countries, intend to establish a program of mutual administrative assistance.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>This Administrative Understanding (hereinafter referred to as the “Understanding”) is concluded in conformity with Article XII(a) of the Agreement between the Government of the United States of America and the Government of Canada with respect to Social Security, signed at Ottawa on March 11, 1981, as amended by the Supplementary Agreement, signed at Ottawa on May 10, 1983, and the second Supplementary Agreement, signed at Ottawa on May 28, 1996, (hereinafter referred to as the “Agreement”), as well as the Administrative Arrangement for the Implementation of the Agreement, signed at Washington on May 22, 1981 (hereinafter referred to as the “Administrative Arrangement”).</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>SECTION II</Label></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Meaning of Terms</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Terms used in this Understanding or any Appendices to be agreed upon at a later time have the same meaning as in the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>SECTION III</Label></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Administrative Assistance</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>In accordance with the procedures to be outlined in one or more Appendices to this Understanding, the Competent Authorities of the two countries, or their designees, will assist each other in administering the laws specified in Article II of the Agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>In no case will a Competent Authority of a country be expected to carry out administrative measures at variance with the statutes or the administrative practice of that or the other country.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>SECTION IV</Label></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Management</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>The program of administrative assistance will be under the general direction of a Management Committee, whose function will be to undertake an ongoing review of policy and procedures relating to the program. The Committee will consist of four members:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="2" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Text>For the United States —</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="2" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Text>The Director, Office of International Policy, Social Security Administration, or the Director’s designee(s), and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="2" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Text>The Director, Office of Disability and International Operations, Social Security Administration, or the Director’s designee(s);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="2" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Text>For Canada —</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="2" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Text>The Director General, International Benefits, Income Security Programs, Department of Human Resources Development, or the Director General’s designee(s), and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Text>The Director General, Programs, Income Security Programs, Department of Human Resources Development, or the Director General’s designee(s).</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The Management Committee will be responsible for the coordination, and any modification, of the program of assistance to be set out later in one or more Appendices to this Understanding. The Committee will review the various timeframes for the performance of functions set out in the Appendices in order to ensure that these standards are met to the extent possible or to modify the timeframes where appropriate.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Modifications to the program will be set out in writing as additional Appendices to this Understanding and signed by the members of the Management Committee, or their designees.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>The Management Committee will be responsible for exchanging statistics and other information regarding workloads and other administrative matters associated with the program of assistance. The content and form of the statistics and information to be exchanged will be agreed upon by the Management Committee.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>The Management Committee will meet, as required, to review progress and establish program guidance and priorities. It is expected that this will be not more than once every two years. Meetings of the Management Committee will normally be held alternately in the United States and Canada.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>SECTION V</Label></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Expenses</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Competent Authority of each country will furnish assistance in accordance with Section III without charge to the Competent Authority of the other country. The Management Committee will periodically review the expenses involved in furnishing assistance under this Understanding with a view toward balancing the costs incurred by each side.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>SECTION VI</Label></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Confidentiality of Information</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>In accordance with Article XVIII of the Agreement, information about an individual which a Competent Authority of one country transmits to a Competent Authority of the other country in accordance with this Understanding or its Appendices will be used exclusively for purposes of administering the laws specified in Article II of the Agreement. Such information received by a Competent Authority will be governed by the statutes applicable to that Competent Authority for the protection of privacy and confidentiality of personal data.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="yes"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>In no case will a Competent Authority of either country be expected to furnish information which is not obtainable under the laws of that or the other country.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>SECTION VII</Label></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Interpretation and Application</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any disagreement regarding the interpretation or application of this Understanding or its Appendices will be resolved by the Management Committee, and will not be referred to any international tribunal or third party for settlement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="2"><Label>SECTION VIII</Label></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">Period of Operation</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Competent Authorities of the United States and Canada will endeavour to initiate the program of assistance specified in this Understanding and to be set out later in one or more detailed Appendices as soon as possible. The Competent Authority of either the United States or Canada may terminate this program of assistance by providing written notification to the Competent Authority of the other country. Such notice of termination will not affect either country’s obligations under the Agreement or Administrative Arrangement or the provisions of Section VI of this Understanding.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">DONE in duplicate at Baltimore, this 4<Sup>th</Sup> day of December 1996 in English and French, both texts being equally authentic.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="italic">FOR THE MINISTER OF HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT CANADA</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>(Serge Rainville)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><Emphasis style="italic">FOR THE SOCIAL SECURITY ADMINISTRATION OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA</Emphasis></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>(Carolyn W. Colvin)</Text></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>