<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651623" lims:id="651623" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651624" lims:id="651624"><InstrumentNumber>SI/98-50</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1998</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651626" lims:id="651626"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651627" lims:id="651627">Proclamation Giving Notice That the Memorandum of Understanding Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland Concerning Co-operation and Mutual Assistance in the Administration of Social Security Programmes Comes Into Force April 1, 1998</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651628" lims:id="651628"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651629" lims:id="651629" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ROMÉO LEBLANC</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651630" lims:id="651630" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651631" lims:id="651631" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651632" lims:id="651632" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Elizabeth the Second, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651633" lims:id="651633" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>To All to Whom these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651634" lims:id="651634" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651635" lims:id="651635" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="left">RICHARD THOMPSON</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Acting/Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651636" lims:id="651636" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>A Proclamation</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651637" lims:id="651637" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1997-495 of April 8, 1997, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article XIV of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Memorandum of Understanding between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland concerning Co-operation and Mutual Assistance in the Administration of Social Security Programmes</XRefExternal>, signed on January 16, 1997, the Memorandum of Understanding shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received written notification from the other Party that it has complied with all statutory requirements for the entry into force of the Memorandum of Understanding;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651638" lims:id="651638" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Order was laid before Parliament on October 2, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651639" lims:id="651639" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order was laid before Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651640" lims:id="651640" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it was laid before Parliament, being November 27, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651641" lims:id="651641" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas instruments of ratification were exchanged on December 29, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651642" lims:id="651642" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Memorandum of Understanding will enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the instruments of ratification were exchanged, being April 1, 1998;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651643" lims:id="651643" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1998-288 of February 26, 1998, the Governor in Council directed that a Proclamation do issue giving notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Memorandum of Understanding between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland concerning Co-operation and Mutual Assistance in the Administration of Social Security Programmes</XRefExternal>, is in force as of April 1, 1998;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651644" lims:id="651644" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now Know You that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our Proclamation give notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Memorandum of Understanding between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland concerning Co-operation and Mutual Assistance in the Administration of Social Security Programmes</XRefExternal>, signed on January 16, 1997, a copy of which is annexed hereto, is in force as of April 1, 1998.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651645" lims:id="651645" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of All Which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651646" lims:id="651646" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Testimony Whereof, We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patent and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. Witness: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Roméo A. LeBlanc, a Member of Our Privy Council for Canada, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651647" lims:id="651647" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>At Our Government House, in Our City of Ottawa, this twentieth day of March in the year of Our Lord one thousand nine hundred and ninety-eight and in the forty-seventh year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651648" lims:id="651648" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651649" lims:id="651649" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="15pc"><SignatureName justification="right">KEVIN G. LYNCH</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651650" lims:id="651650" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Memorandum of Understanding Between the Government of Canada and the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland Concerning Co-Operation and Mutual Assistance in the Administration of Social Security Programmess</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The Government of Canada</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">and</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">(hereinafter referred to as the “Participants”),</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">With the purpose of improving the administrative efficiency, cost effectiveness and integrity of their social security systems as they apply to the determination of eligibility and the payment of benefits,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Intend to establish a programme of mutual administrative assistance, and</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Have reached the following understanding:</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Heading level="5"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">SCOPE OF CO-OPERATION AND MUTUAL ADMINISTRATIVE ASSISTANCE</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Memorandum of Understanding (hereinafter referred to as the “Memorandum”) will apply,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in relation to Canada, to:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder: and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the regulations made thereunder;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to Great Britain, to:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Social Security Administration Act 1992</XRefExternal>, <Emphasis style="italic">the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Social Security Contributions and Benefits Act 1992</XRefExternal>, <Emphasis style="italic">the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Social Security (Consequential Provisions) Act 1992</XRefExternal>, <Emphasis style="italic">the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Social Security (Incapacity for Work) Act 1994</XRefExternal>, <Emphasis style="italic">and the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Jobseekers Act 1995</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-2" language-align="no" list-item="yes"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in relation to Northern Ireland, to:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Social Security Administration (Northern Ireland) Act 1992</XRefExternal> , <Emphasis style="italic">the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Social Security Contributions and Benefits (Northern Ireland) Act 1992</XRefExternal>, <Emphasis style="italic">the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Social Security (Consequential Provisions) (Northern Ireland) Act 1992</XRefExternal> , <Emphasis style="italic">the</Emphasis><Emphasis style="italic">and the</Emphasis><XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Social Security (Incapacity for Work) (Northern Ireland) Order 1994 Jobseekers (Northern Ireland) Order 1995</XRefExternal> ;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>and the legislation which was repealed or consolidated by those Acts or Orders or repealed by legislation consolidated by them</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Memorandum, the term <DefinedTermEn>agent</DefinedTermEn> means,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in relation to Canada, the Department of Human Resources Development;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to Great Britain, the Department of Social Security; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in relation to Northern Ireland, the Department of Health and Social Services.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>In accordance with the procedures to be outlined in one or more Appendices to this Memorandum, the agents of the Participants will co-operate and assist each other in administering the legislation specified in paragraph 1. This programme of mutual administrative assistance may include both general exchanges of information and the provision of assistance with specific investigations and enquiries in accordance with the Participants’ respective domestic statutes.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>To the extent permitted by the legislation which they administer, the agents of the Participants will communicate to each other any information necessary to carry out the programme of mutual administrative assistance to which this Memorandum and its Appendices apply.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>Unless disclosure is required under the statutes of a Participant, information about an individual which the agent of one Participant transmits to an agent of the other Participant in accordance with this Memorandum or its Appendices will be used exclusively for the purpose of administering the legislation specified in paragraph 1 of this Memorandum. Such information received by the agent of a Participant will be governed by the statutes applicable to that Participant for the protection of privacy and confidentiality of personal data.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>In no case will the agent of a Participant be expected to carry out administrative measures at variance with the statutes or the administrative practice of that Participant, or to furnish information which is not obtainable under the legislation of that Participant.</Text></Provision><Heading level="5"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">MANAGEMENT</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text>The programme of mutual administrative assistance will be under the general direction of a Management Committee, whose function will be to carry out an ongoing review of policy and procedures relating to the programme. The Committee will consist of four members:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>For Canada, on behalf of the Minister of Human Resources Development:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Director General, International Benefits, Income Security Programs, Department of Human Resources Development, or his or her designee(s);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Director General, Programs, Income Security Programs, Department of Human Resources Development, or his or her designee(s);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>For the United Kingdom, on behalf of the Secretary of State for Social Security and the Department of Health and Social Services for Northern Ireland:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Head of International Relations Branch, Department of Social Security, or his or her designee(s);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Territorial Director, Benefits Agency, Department of Social Security, or his or her designee(s).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>8</Label><Text>The programme of mutual administrative assistance, and any modifications to that programme, will be set out in writing as Appendices to this Memorandum and signed by the members of the Management Committee or their designees.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Management Committee will be responsible for the co-ordination, and any modification, of the programme of mutual administrative assistance to be set out later in one or more Appendices to this Memorandum. The Committee will review the various timeframes for the performance of functions set out in the Appendices in order to ensure that the required standards are met to the extent possible, or to modify the timeframes, where appropriate.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>10</Label><Text>The Management Committee will be responsible for exchanging statistics and other information regarding workloads and other administrative matters associated with the programme of mutual administrative assistance. The content and form of the statistics and information to be exchanged will be agreed upon by the Management Committee.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>11</Label><Text>The Management Committee will meet, as required, to review progress and establish programme guidance and priorities.</Text></Provision><Heading level="5"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">EXPENSES</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>12</Label><Text>Each agent will furnish assistance in accordance with this Memorandum without charge to the other agents. The Management Committee will periodically review the expenses involved in furnishing assistance under this Memorandum with a view toward balancing the costs incurred by each side.</Text></Provision><Heading level="5"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">INTERPRETATION AND APPLICATION</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>13</Label><Text>Any dispute regarding the interpretation or application of this Memorandum or its Appendices will be resolved by the Management Committee, and will not be referred to any international tribunal or third party for settlement.</Text></Provision><Heading level="5"><TitleText><Emphasis style="bold">PERIOD OF OPERATION</Emphasis></TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>14</Label><Text>This Memorandum will come into effect on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Participant will have received from the other Participant written notification that it has complied with all requirements to give effect to this Memorandum. It will remain in operation until terminated by either Participant by giving three months’ notice in writing to the other Participant through diplomatic channels.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">SIGNED</Emphasis><Emphasis style="italic">in duplicate in the French and English languages, both texts having equal validity</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>(Pierre S. Pettigrew)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED KINGDOM OF GREAT BRITAIN AND NORTHERN IRELAND</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>(Peter Lilley)</Text></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>