<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644034" lims:id="644034" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644035" lims:id="644035"><InstrumentNumber>SI/91-65</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1991</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644037" lims:id="644037"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">PUBLIC SERVICE EMPLOYMENT ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644038" lims:id="644038">Exclusion Approval Order for certain persons and certain positions (Air Traffic Control Group), 1991</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644039" lims:id="644039">Order Approving the Exclusion by the Public Service Commission from the Operation of Section 10 and Subsection 21(1) of the Public Service Employment Act of Certain Persons and Positions</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1991-771 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY> 1991</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644040" lims:id="644040"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644041" lims:id="644041" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Public Service Commission has decided that it is not practicable nor in the best interests of the Public Service</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644042" lims:id="644042" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in relation to qualifications other than language skills, to apply section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal> to training positions in the Department of Transport to which are to be or are appointed air traffic controllers who participate in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644043" lims:id="644043" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to qualifications other than language skills, to apply section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal> to operational positions in the Department of Transport to which are to be or are appointed air traffic controllers who have successfully completed their training in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644044" lims:id="644044" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to apply subsection 21(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal> to all persons who, but for this Order, would have a right of appeal under that subsection against the appointment or proposed appointment to training positions in the Department of Transport of certain air traffic controllers who participate in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644045" lims:id="644045" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>to apply subsection 21(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal> to all persons who, but for this Order, would have a right of appeal under that subsection against the appointment or proposed appointment to operational positions in the Department of Transport of air traffic controllers who have successfully completed their training in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644046" lims:id="644046" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>to apply subsection 21(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal> to all persons who, but for this Order, would have a right of appeal under that subsection against the appointment or proposed appointment to positions in the Department of Transport of air traffic controllers who have not successfully completed or have terminated without completing their training in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program, during the period beginning on May 1, 1991 and ending on December 31, 1996.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644047" lims:id="644047" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And Whereas the Public Service Commission, pursuant to subsection 41(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, has decided that certain persons and positions should be excluded from the operation of section 10 and subsection 21(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644048" lims:id="644048" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Secretary of State, pursuant to subsection 41(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to make the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-91-65">Order approving the exclusion by the Public Service Commission from the operation of section 10 and subsection 21(1) of the Public Service Employment Act of certain persons and positions</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><HistoricalNote>SI/96-37, s. 1</HistoricalNote></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644050" lims:id="644050"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644051" lims:id="644051" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644052" lims:id="644052"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Order may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SI-91-65">Exclusion Approval Order for certain persons and certain positions (Air Traffic Control Group), 1991</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644053" lims:id="644053" level="1"><TitleText>Approval</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644054" lims:id="644054"><Label>2</Label><Text>The exclusion by the Public Service Commission, from the operation of section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, in relation to qualifications other than language skills, of training positions in the Department of Transport to which are to be or are appointed air traffic controllers who participate in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program, during the period beginning on May 1, 1991 and ending on December 31, 1996, is hereby approved.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644056" lims:id="644056">SI/96-37, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644057" lims:id="644057"><Label>3</Label><Text>The exclusion by the Public Service Commission, from the operation of section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, in relation to qualifications other than language skills, of operational positions in the Department of Transport to which are to be or are appointed air traffic controllers who have successfully completed their training in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program, during the period beginning on May 1, 1991 and ending on December 31, 1996, is hereby approved.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644059" lims:id="644059">SI/96-37, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644060" lims:id="644060"><Label>4</Label><Text>The exclusion by the Public Service Commission, from the operation of subsection 21(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, of all persons who, but for this Order, would have a right of appeal under that subsection against the appointment or proposed appointment to training positions in the Department of Transport of certain air traffic controllers who participate in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program, during the period beginning on May 1, 1991 and ending on December 31, 1996, is hereby approved.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644062" lims:id="644062">SI/96-37, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644063" lims:id="644063"><Label>5</Label><Text>The exclusion by the Public Service Commission, from the operation of subsection 21(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, of all persons who, but for this Order, would have a right of appeal under that subsection against the appointment or proposed appointment to operational positions in the Department of Transport of air traffic controllers who have successfully completed their training in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program, during the period beginning on May 1, 1991 and ending on December 31, 1996, is hereby approved.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644065" lims:id="644065">SI/96-37, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644066" lims:id="644066"><Label>6</Label><Text>The exclusion by the Public Service Commission, from the operation of subsection 21(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, of all persons who, but for this Order, would have a right of appeal under that subsection against the appointment or proposed appointment to positions in the Department of Transport of air traffic controllers who have not successfully completed or have terminated without completing their training in the Selection by Seniority Program for operational training or in the Transfer Down Program during the period beginning on May 1, 1991 and ending on December 31, 1996, is hereby approved.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="644068" lims:id="644068">SI/96-37, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>