<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649437" lims:id="649437" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649438" lims:id="649438"><InstrumentNumber>SI/96-100</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1996</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>27</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649440" lims:id="649440"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649441" lims:id="649441">Proclamation Declaring the Supplementary Agreement to the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Austria in Force on December 1, 1996</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649442" lims:id="649442"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649443" lims:id="649443" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ROMÉO LEBLANC</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649444" lims:id="649444" format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649445" lims:id="649445" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649446" lims:id="649446" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Elizabeth the Second, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649447" lims:id="649447" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>To All To Whom these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649448" lims:id="649448" format-ref="right-align" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649449" lims:id="649449" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="13 pc"><SignatureName justification="left">GEORGE THOMSON</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649450" lims:id="649450" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="no"><Text> A Proclamation</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649451" lims:id="649451" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1995-1829 of October 31, 1995, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Supplementary Agreement to the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Austria</XRefExternal>, signed at Vienna on September 12, 1995, the Supplementary Agreement shall enter into force in Canada on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received written notification from the other Party that it has complied with all statutory requirements for the entry into force of the Supplementary Agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649452" lims:id="649452" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the said Order was laid before Parliament on March 19, 1996;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649453" lims:id="649453" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order had been laid before Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649454" lims:id="649454" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it had been laid before Parliament, being May 14, 1996;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649455" lims:id="649455" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas instruments of ratification were exchanged on August 27, 1996;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649456" lims:id="649456" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas the Supplementary Agreement will enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the instruments of ratification were exchanged, being December 1, 1996;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649457" lims:id="649457" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1996-1689 of November 5, 1996, the Governor in Council directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Supplementary Agreement to the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Austria</XRefExternal> is in force as of December 1, 1996;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649458" lims:id="649458" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now Know You that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our Proclamation give notice that the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Supplementary Agreement to the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Austria</XRefExternal>, signed at Vienna on September 12, 1995, a copy of which is annexed hereto, is in force as of December 1, 1996.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649459" lims:id="649459" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of All Which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649460" lims:id="649460" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Testimony Whereof, We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patent and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. Witness: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Roméo A. LeBlanc, a Member of Our Privy Council for Canada, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649461" lims:id="649461" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>At Our Government House, in Our City of Ottawa, this fourteenth day of November in the year of Our Lord one thousand nine hundred and ninety-six and in the forty-fifth year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649462" lims:id="649462" format-ref="right-align" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="15 pc"><SignatureLine justification="right">By Command,</SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="right" topmarginspacing="6">KEVIN G. LYNCH</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="649463" lims:id="649463" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ConventionAgreementTreaty><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Supplementary Agreement</TitleText><TitleText>to the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Austria</TitleText></Heading><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="bold"><Leader leader="solid" length="15pc" /></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Canada</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">and</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The Republic of Austria</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Desiring to amend and supplement the Agreement on Social Security between the two States, signed at Vienna on 24 February 1987,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Have agreed as follows:</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE I</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>For the purposes of this Supplementary Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>the Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Agreement on Social Security between Canada and the Republic of Austria, signed at Vienna on 24 February 1987;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other term has the meaning given to it in the Agreement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE II</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>In sub-paragraph (1)(c) of Article 1 of the Agreement, the words “the Federal Minister for Social Affairs” shall be replaced by the words “the Federal Minister responsible for the administration of the legislation of Austria”.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In paragraph (2) of Article 1 of the Agreement, the words “Minister of National Health and Welfare” shall be replaced by the words “Minister of Employment and Immigration”.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Paragraph (4) of Article 4 of the Agreement shall be deleted and the following paragraph substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>“(4)</Label><Text>As regards Austrian legislation concerning the crediting of periods of war service and periods considered as equivalent, Canadian nationals who were Austrian nationals immediately before 13 March 1938 shall receive equal treatment with Austrian nationals.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph (3) of Article 5 of the Agreement shall be deleted and the following paragraph substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>“(3)</Label><Text>As regards Austrian legislation, paragraph (1) of this Article shall not apply to the compensatory supplement.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>Article 6 of the Agreement shall be deleted and the following Article substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><Label>“ARTICLE 6</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Text>Subject to the provisions of Articles 7 to 9, an employed or self-employed person who works in the territory of one Party shall, in respect of that work, be subject only to the legislation of that Party. In the case of an employed person, this shall also apply if the employer’s place of business is in the territory of the other Party.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>6</Label><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>In paragraphs (1) and (2) of Article 7 of the Agreement, the word “twenty-four” shall be replaced by the word “sixty”.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>The following paragraph (3) shall be inserted immediately after paragraph (2) of Article 7 of the Agreement:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>“(3)</Label><Text>A person who would otherwise be compulsorily covered under the legislation of both Parties with respect to self-employment and who is a resident of one Party shall be subject only to the legislation of the Party of which that person is a resident.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>7</Label><Text>Paragraph (1) of Article 9 of the Agreement shall be deleted and the following paragraph substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>“(1)</Label><Text>At the request of an employed person and his employer or of a self-employed person, the competent authorities of the two Parties may provide, by agreement with one another, exceptions in the application of Articles 6 to 8, taking into account the nature and circumstances of the work.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>8</Label><Text>Article 12 of the Agreement shall be deleted and the following Article substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><Label>“ARTICLE 12</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Text>When a person who has completed periods of coverage under the legislation of both Parties, or the survivor of such a person, claims a benefit, the competent Austrian institution shall determine, in accordance with Austrian legislation, whether the claimant is entitled to a benefit by adding together the periods of coverage, as provided in Article 11, and taking into account the following provisions:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Where Austrian legislation makes the award of certain benefits conditional upon the completion of periods of coverage in an occupation covered by special schemes or in a specified occupation or employment, only periods of coverage completed under a corresponding scheme or, failing that, in the same occupation or, where appropriate, in the same employment under the legislation of Canada shall be taken into account for the award of such benefits.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Where Austrian legislation provides that the period of payment of a pension shall prolong the reference period during which periods of coverage must be completed, periods during which a pension has been awarded under the legislation of Canada shall also prolong the aforesaid reference period.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Periods of coverage completed under the legislation of Canada shall be taken into account as follows:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a calendar year which is a period of coverage under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be accepted as twelve months of contributions under Austrian legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a calendar month which contains at least fifteen days of coverage under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> of Canada and which is not part of a period of coverage under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> shall be accepted as a month of coverage under Austrian legislation.”</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>9</Label><Text>Article 13 of the Agreement shall be deleted and the following Article substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><Label>“ARTICLE 13</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where entitlement to a benefit exists under Austrian legislation without the application of Article 11, the competent Austrian institution shall determine the amount of the benefit in accordance with Austrian legislation on the basis of periods of coverage completed exclusively under that legislation.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where entitlement to a benefit exists under Austrian legislation only with the application of Article 11, the competent Austrian institution shall determine the amount of the benefit in accordance with Austrian legislation on the basis of periods of coverage completed exclusively under that legislation and taking into account the following provisions:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Benefits or parts of benefits, the amount of which does not depend on the duration of periods of coverage completed, shall be calculated in proportion to the ratio between the duration of the periods of coverage to be taken into account for the calculation under Austrian legislation and the period of 30 years, but shall not exceed the full amount.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Where periods after the contingency arises are to be taken into account for the calculation of invalidity or survivors’ benefits, such periods shall be taken into account only in proportion to the ratio between the duration of the periods of coverage to be taken into account for the calculation under Austrian legislation and two-thirds of the number of full calendar months between the date on which the person concerned reached the age of 16 and the date on which the contingency occurred, but shall not exceed the full period.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Sub-paragraph (a) of this paragraph shall not apply to:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>benefits resulting from supplementary insurance,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>means-tested benefits designed to ensure a minimum income.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the periods of coverage to be taken into account under Austrian legislation for the calculation of the benefit are in aggregate less than twelve months and no entitlement to a benefit has been established under Austrian legislation exclusively on the basis of these periods of coverage, no benefit under that legislation shall be paid.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>10</Label><Text>Articles 14 and 15 of the Agreement shall be deleted.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>11</Label><Text>Section 2 of Part III of the Agreement shall be amended by inserting, immediately after the title thereof, the following new Article 15:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><Label>“ARTICLE 15</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person is not entitled to the payment of a benefit on the basis of the periods of coverage completed under the legislation of both Parties, added together as provided in Article 11, the entitlement of that person to the payment of that benefit shall be determined by adding together these periods and periods of coverage completed under the legislation of a third State with which Canada is bound by a social security instrument which provides for totalizing periods.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Agreement, if the total duration of the periods of coverage completed by a person under the legislation of Canada is less than twelve months and if, taking into account only those periods, no right to a benefit exists under that legislation, the competent institution of Canada shall not be required to award benefits to that person in respect of those periods by virtue of this Agreement.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>12</Label><Text>Paragraphs (2) to (4) of Article 16 of the Agreement shall be deleted and the following paragraphs substituted in their place:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>If a person is entitled to the payment of a pension or a spouse’s allowance solely through the application of the provisions of Article 11 or of paragraph (1) of Article 15, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of the pension or spouse’s allowance payable to that person in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> governing the payment of a partial pension or a spouse’s allowance, exclusively on the basis of the periods of residence in Canada which may be considered under that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (2) of this Article shall also apply to a person who is entitled to the payment of a pension in Canada but who has not resided in Canada for the minimum period required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for entitlement to the payment of a pension outside Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision of this Agreement:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an Old Age Security pension shall be paid to a person who is outside Canada only if that person’s periods of coverage, when added together as provided in Article 11 and paragraph (1) of Article 15, are at least equal to the minimum period of residence in Canada required by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> for entitlement to the payment of a pension outside Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a spouse’s allowance and a guaranteed income supplement shall be paid to a person who is outside Canada only to the extent permitted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>.”</Text></Provision></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>13</Label><Text>In sub-paragraph (2)(a) of Article 17 of the Agreement, the words “a disability pension, disabled contributor’s child’s benefit, survivor’s pension, orphan’s benefit or death benefit” shall be replaced by the words “a benefit”; and, immediately after the words “as provided in Article 11”, the words “and paragraph (1) of Article 15” shall be inserted.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>14</Label><Text>Paragraph (2) of Article 21 of the Agreement shall be deleted and the following paragraph substituted in its place:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>Any claim for a benefit under the legislation of one Party submitted after the date of entry into force of this Agreement shall be considered to be a claim for the corresponding benefit under the legislation of the other Party, provided that the claimant provides information at the time of application indicating that periods of coverage have been completed under the legislation of the other Party; this shall not apply, however, when the claimant expressly requests that the determination of an old age or retirement benefit under the legislation of the other Party be deferred.”</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Provision><Heading level="1"><Label>ARTICLE III</Label></Heading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Supplementary Agreement shall be ratified. The instruments of ratification shall be exchanged at Ottawa as soon as possible.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided, this Supplementary Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the instruments of ratification are exchanged.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Paragraph (3) of Article 5 of the Agreement, as amended by this Supplementary Agreement, shall enter into force retroactively as of 1 November 1991.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph (1) of Article 13 of the Agreement, as amended by this Supplementary Agreement, shall enter into force retroactively as of 1 January 1994.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>If, on the date of entry into force of this Supplementary Agreement, a person is compulsorily covered under the legislation of both Parties with respect to self-employment, paragraph (3) of Article 7 of the Agreement, as amended by this Supplementary Agreement, shall apply to that person only if he or she requests, in writing, that this be the case. If such a request is submitted to the competent institution of either Party within six months of the date of entry into force of this Supplementary Agreement, that provision shall apply as of the date of entry into force. In any other case, it shall apply on the first day of the calendar month following the month in which the request is submitted.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the Plenipotentiaries have signed this Supplementary Agreement.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Language xml:lang="fr">EN FOI DE QUOI, les Plénipotentiaires ont signé le présent Accord supplémentaire.</Language></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Done in two copies at Vienna, this 12<Sup>th</Sup> day of September 1995, in English, French and German, each text being equally authentic.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Language xml:lang="fr">Fait en deux exemplaires à Vienne, ce 12<Sup>e</Sup> jour de septembre 1995, dans les langues française, anglaise et allemande, chaque texte faisant également foi.</Language></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">For Canada:</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Language xml:lang="fr">Pour le Canada :</Language></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(Peter F. Walker)</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">For the Republic of Austria:</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="0"><Text><Emphasis style="italic"><Language xml:lang="fr">Pour la République d’Autriche :</Language></Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(Wolfgang Schallenberg)</Text></Provision></Provision></ConventionAgreementTreaty></Schedule></Regulation>