<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651027" lims:id="651027" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SI" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651028" lims:id="651028"><InstrumentNumber>SI/97-49</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1997</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651030" lims:id="651030"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">OLD AGE SECURITY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651031" lims:id="651031">Proclamation Amending the Agreement on Social Security Between Canada and Spain in Force May 1, 1997</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651032" lims:id="651032"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651033" lims:id="651033" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock width="16pc"><SignatureName>ROMÉO LEBLANC</SignatureName><SignatureTitle>[L.S.]</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651034" lims:id="651034" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651035" lims:id="651035" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Elizabeth the Second, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651036" lims:id="651036" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>TO All To Whom these Presents shall come or whom the same may in any way concern,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651037" lims:id="651037" justification="right" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651038" lims:id="651038" format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="right" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="16 pc"><SignatureName justification="left">GEORGE THOMSON</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="left"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651039" lims:id="651039" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>A Proclamation</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651040" lims:id="651040" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1996-305 of March 12, 1996, the Governor in Council declared that, in accordance with Article 7 of the Protocol to the Convention on Social Security between Canada and Spain, signed at Ottawa on October 19, 1995, the Protocol shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received written notification from the other Party that it has complied with all statutory requirements for the entry into force of the Protocol;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651041" lims:id="651041" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Order was laid before Parliament on April 23, 1996;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651042" lims:id="651042" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, before the twentieth sitting day after the Order had been laid before Parliament, no motion for the consideration of either House to the effect that the Order be revoked was filed with the Speaker of the appropriate House;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651043" lims:id="651043" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 42(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-9">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>, the Order came into force on the thirtieth sitting day after it had been laid before Parliament, being June 11, 1996;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651044" lims:id="651044" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas instruments of ratification were exchanged on January 15, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651045" lims:id="651045" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Protocol will enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which the instruments of ratification were exchanged, being May 1, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651046" lims:id="651046" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, by Order in Council P.C. 1997-593 of April 15, 1997, the Governor in Council directed that a proclamation do issue giving notice that the Protocol to the Convention on Social Security between Canada and Spain is in force as of May 1, 1997;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651047" lims:id="651047" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now Know You that We, by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada, do by this Our Proclamation give notice that the Protocol to the Convention on Social Security between Canada and Spain, signed at Ottawa on October 19, 1995, a copy of which is annexed hereto, is in force as of May 1, 1997.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651048" lims:id="651048" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Of All Which Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651049" lims:id="651049" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Testimony Whereof, We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patent and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. Witness: Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Roméo A. LeBlanc, a Member of Our Privy Council for Canada, Chancellor and Principal Companion of Our Order of Canada, Chancellor and Commander of Our Order of Military Merit, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651050" lims:id="651050" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>At Our Government House, in Our City of Ottawa, this twenty-third day of April in the year of Our Lord one thousand nine hundred and ninety-seven and in the forty-sixth year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651051" lims:id="651051" format-ref="" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="16 pc"><SignatureName justification="right">By Command,</SignatureName><SignatureName justification="right">KEVIN G. LYNCH</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651052" lims:id="651052" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651053" lims:id="651053"><TitleText>Protocol to the Convention on Social Security Between Canada and Spain</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651054" lims:id="651054" justification="center" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651055" lims:id="651055" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Canada</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651056" lims:id="651056" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">and</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651057" lims:id="651057" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the Kingdom of Spain,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651058" lims:id="651058" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Noting the Convention on Social Security between Canada and Spain, signed at Madrid on 10 November 1986, and</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651059" lims:id="651059" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Desiring to strengthen even further the relations between them in the field of social security,</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651060" lims:id="651060" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Have agreed as follows:</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651061" lims:id="651061" level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 1</Label></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651062" lims:id="651062" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>For the purposes of this Protocol:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651063" lims:id="651063" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Convention</DefinedTermEn> means the Convention on Social Security between Canada and Spain, signed at Madrid on 10 November 1986;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651064" lims:id="651064" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other term shall have the meaning given to it in the Convention.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651065" lims:id="651065" level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 2</Label></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651066" lims:id="651066" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Spanish non-contributory social security benefits established under Law 26/90 of 20 December 1990 shall be granted to Canadian citizens under the same conditions and subject to the same requirements as that law sets out for Spanish citizens.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651067" lims:id="651067" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Article 5 and Article 9, paragraphs 1 and 3 of the Convention shall not apply to the non-contributory benefits referred to in the preceding paragraph.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651068" lims:id="651068" level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 3</Label></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651069" lims:id="651069" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>In Article 6, paragraph 2 of the Convention, the word “twenty-four” shall be replaced by the word “sixty”.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651070" lims:id="651070" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Article 6, paragraph 4 of the Convention shall be replaced by the following text:</Text><QuotedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>“4</Label><Text>A person employed as a member of the crew of a ship who, but for this Convention, would be subject to the legislation of Spain as well as to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in respect of that work shall, in respect thereof, be subject only to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> if that person resides and is hired in Canada, and only to the legislation of Spain if that person resides and is hired in Spain. When the circumstances of the previous sentence do not apply, the person shall be subject only to the legislation of Spain if the ship flies the flag of Spain.”</Text></Provision></QuotedText></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651071" lims:id="651071" level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 4</Label></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651072" lims:id="651072" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 12 of the Convention shall be replaced by the following text:</Text><QuotedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>“If a person is entitled to the payment of a benefit under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> solely through the application of the totalizing provisions of Chapter 1 of this Part, the competent institution of Canada shall calculate the amount of benefit payable to that person in the following manner:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the earnings-related portion of the benefit shall be determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, exclusively on the basis of the pensionable earnings under that Plan; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the flat-rate portion of the benefit shall be determined by multiplying:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount of the flat-rate portion of the benefit determined in conformity with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>by</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the fraction which represents the ratio of the periods of contributions to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-8">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> in relation to the minimum qualifying period required under that Plan to establish entitlement to that benefit, but in no case shall that fraction exceed the value of one.”</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision></QuotedText></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651073" lims:id="651073" level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 5</Label></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651074" lims:id="651074" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Article 13, sub-paragraph 1(c) of the Convention shall be replaced by the following text:</Text><QuotedText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“c)</Label><Text>for purposes of determining the computation base of the benefit (la base reguladora para el cálculo de la prestación) under the provisions of this Article, when all or part of the contribution period which must be taken into account by the Spanish competent institution corresponds to insured periods completed under the legislation of Canada, that competent institution shall take into account the person’s actual contribution bases paid by that person in Spain during the years immediately preceding the date on which the last contribution was due under the Spanish social security system, and the amount of the benefit thus obtained shall be adjusted to take account of the increases and reassessments prescribed for the same category of benefits for each subsequent year until the occurrence of the contingency which gives rise to the benefit.”</Text></Provision></QuotedText></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651075" lims:id="651075" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Article 13, sub-paragraph 1(d) and paragraph 2 of the Convention shall be replaced by the following text:</Text><QuotedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>“2</Label><Text>If the legislation of Spain makes award of a benefit conditional on the fact that the person concerned must be subject to that legislation at the time of the occurrence of the contingency which gives rise to the benefit, this condition shall be deemed to be met if, at that time, that person is insured under the legislation of Canada or, if that is not the case, is in receipt of a benefit of the same kind under the legislation of Canada or a benefit of a different kind but one paid on account of the beneficiary him/herself. This same principle shall apply for the awarding of survivors’ pensions where, if required, account is taken of the fact that the person in respect of whom a benefit is being claimed was validly insured (situación de alta) or in receipt of a benefit under the legislation of Canada.”</Text></Provision></QuotedText></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651076" lims:id="651076" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>When, for purposes of award of a benefit, the legislation of Spain requires that insured periods have been completed in a specific time immediately before the occurrence of the contingency giving rise to the benefit, this condition shall be deemed to be met if the person concerned has completed those periods in the time immediately before the award of a benefit under the legislation of Canada, provided that insured periods are not credited in this situation.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651077" lims:id="651077" level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 6</Label></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651078" lims:id="651078" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>At the date of the coming into force of this Protocol, benefits which have been requested or awarded, prior to that date, through the application of the Convention may be reviewed or recalculated by the competent institution, on request by the beneficiary, taking into account the provisions of this Protocol. The change in the amount of benefit payable as a result of the recalculation shall start to be due from the first day of the month following the month in which the beneficiary requests the recalculation.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651079" lims:id="651079" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In no case shall the beneficiary, as a result of a recalculation made by virtue of the provisions of the previous paragraph, receive a benefit which is lesser in amount than that which he or she had been receiving prior to that time.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651080" lims:id="651080" level="2"><Label>ARTICLE 7</Label></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651081" lims:id="651081" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Protocol shall enter into force on the first day of the fourth month following the month in which each Party shall have received written notification from the other Party that it has complied with all statutory requirements for the entry into force of this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651082" lims:id="651082" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 3 of this Article, this Protocol shall remain in force without any limitation on its duration.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651083" lims:id="651083" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>In the event of the denunciation of the Convention through the application of Article 25, paragraph 2 thereof, this Protocol shall also be denounced, with effect on the same date as the termination of the Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651084" lims:id="651084" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Protocol.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651085" lims:id="651085" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">EN FOI DE QUOI, les soussignés, dûment autorisés à cet effet par leurs Gouvernements respectifs ont signé le présent Protocole.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651086" lims:id="651086" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Done in two copies at Ottawa, this 19th day of October, 1995, in the English, French and Spanish languages, each text being equally authentic.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651087" lims:id="651087" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Fait en deux exemplaires à Ottawa, le 19<Sup>e</Sup> jour d’octobre 1995 dans les langues française, anglaise et espagnole, chaque texte faisant également foi.</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651088" lims:id="651088" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">FOR CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651089" lims:id="651089" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">POUR LE CANADA</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651090" lims:id="651090" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">LLOYD AXWORTHY</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651091" lims:id="651091" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">FOR SPAIN</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651092" lims:id="651092" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">POUR L’ESPAGNE</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="651093" lims:id="651093" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">JOSÉ LUIS PARDOS</Emphasis></Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>