<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886190" lims:id="886190" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886191" lims:id="886191"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/85-188</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1985</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886193" lims:id="886193"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886194" lims:id="886194">Peace River Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886195" lims:id="886195">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Peace River Airport</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1985-536</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1985</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886196" lims:id="886196"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886197" lims:id="886197" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, pursuant to section 6<FootnoteRef idref="fn_1e">*</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to approve the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-85-188">Regulations respecting zoning at Peace River Airport</XRefExternal>, made by the Minister of Transport.</Text><Footnote id="fn_1e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>*</Label><Text>S.C. 1976-77, c. 28, s. 2 and 49</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886198" lims:id="886198"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886199" lims:id="886199" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886200" lims:id="886200"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-85-188">Peace River Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886201" lims:id="886201" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886202" lims:id="886202"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886203" lims:id="886203"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886204" lims:id="886204" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means the Peace River Airport, in the vicinity of Peace River, in the Province of Alberta; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886205" lims:id="886205" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886206" lims:id="886206" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means the imaginary inclined planes more particularly described in Part III of the schedule that extend upward and outward from each end of the strip associated with the runway designated 03-21 of the airport; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886207" lims:id="886207" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886208" lims:id="886208" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>outer surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary surface located above and in the immediate vicinity of the airport, which outer surface is more particularly described in Part IV of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface extérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886209" lims:id="886209" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means the rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport, including the runway, prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction, which strip is more particularly described in Part V of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886210" lims:id="886210" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from the lateral limits of a strip and its approach surfaces, which transitional surface is more particularly described in Part VI of the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886211" lims:id="886211"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the assigned elevation of the airport reference point is deemed to be 567.2 m above sea level.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886212" lims:id="886212" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886213" lims:id="886213"><Label>3</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all the lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, that consist of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886214" lims:id="886214"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the lands within, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886215" lims:id="886215"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the lands directly under that portion of an approach surface that extends beyond</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886216" lims:id="886216"><Text>the outer limits described in Part II of the schedule.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886217" lims:id="886217" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886218" lims:id="886218"><Label>4</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct, on any land to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of that point</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886219" lims:id="886219"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the approach surface;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886220" lims:id="886220"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the outer surface; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886221" lims:id="886221"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the transitional surface.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886222" lims:id="886222" level="1"><TitleText>Natural Growth</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886223" lims:id="886223"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where an object of natural growth on any land to which these Regulations apply exceeds in elevation any of the surfaces referred to in paragraphs 4(a) to (c), the Minister may direct that the owner or occupier of the land on which the object is growing remove the excessive growth.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886224" lims:id="886224" level="1"><TitleText>Disposal of Waste</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886225" lims:id="886225"><Label>6</Label><Text>No owner or occupier of any land to which these Regulations apply shall permit such land or any part of it to be used for the disposal of any waste edible by or attractive to birds.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886226" lims:id="886226" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886227" lims:id="886227"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(ss. 2 and 3)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886228" lims:id="886228" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Description of the Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886229" lims:id="886229" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The airport reference point is a point lying perpendicularly distant 91.44 m northwesterly from a point on the centre line of runway 03-21 distant northeasterly 640.14 m from the 03 end of the said runway.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886230" lims:id="886230" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of Outer Limits of Lands</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886231" lims:id="886231" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The boundary of the outer limits of lands, shown on Peace River Airport Zoning Plan No. E.1801, dated January 16, 1984, is described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886232" lims:id="886232" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Commencing at a point on the South boundary of the South West Quarter of Section Eighteen (18), Township Eighty-Three (83), Range Twenty-Two (22), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian, said point being the intersection of the South boundary of said Quarter Section and the Easterly limit of Lot 4, as shown on a plan of survey of record in the Land Titles Office for the North Alberta Land Registration District as Number 802-2831; thence Easterly along the South boundaries of Sections Eighteen (18), Seventeen (17), and the South West Quarter of Section Sixteen (16), and the production intervening road allowances, to the South East corner of said Quarter Section; thence Northerly along the East boundary of the said Quarter Section to the North East corner thereof; thence Easterly along the South boundary of the North East Quarter of Section Sixteen (16) to the South East corner thereof; thence Northerly along the East boundary of the said Quarter Section to the North East corner thereof; thence Easterly across the road allowance and along the South boundary of the South West Quarter of Section Twenty-Two (22) to the South east corner thereof; thence Northerly along the East boundary of the West half of Sections Twenty-Two (22), Twenty-Seven (27), and Thirty-Four (34), all in Township Eighty-Three (83), Range Twenty-Two (22), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian, and the South West Quarter of Section Three (3), Township Eighty-Four (84), Range Twenty-Two (22), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian and their productions across the intervening road allowances to the North East corner of said Quarter Section; thence Westerly along the North boundary of the South West Quarter of Section Three (3), the North boundary of the South East Quarter of Section Four (4), and its production across the intervening road allowance to the North West corner of said Quarter Section; thence Northerly along the East boundary of the North West Quarter of Section Four (4) to the North East corner thereof; thence Westerly along the North boundaries of the North West Quarter of Section Four (4), Section Five (5), Section Six (6) of said Township Eighty-Four (84), Range Twenty Two (22), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian, and the North East Quarter of Section One (1), Township Eighty-Four (84), Range Twenty-Three (23), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian, and the productions across the intervening road allowances to the North West corner of said Quarter Section; thence Southerly along the West boundary of the North East Quarter of Section One (1) to the South West corner thereof; thence Westerly along the North boundary of the South West Quarter of Section One (1) to the North West corner thereof; thence Southerly along the West boundary of the South West Quarter of Section One (1) and its production across the road allowance to the North West corner of Section Thirty-Six (36), Township Eighty-Three (83), Range Twenty-Three (23), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian; thence Westerly across the road allowance and along the North boundary of the North East Quarter of Section Thirty-Five (35) to the North West corner thereof; thence Southerly along the West boundary of the East half of Sections Thirty-Five (35), Twenty-Six (26), Twenty-Three (23) and across intervening road allowance to an intersection with the North limit of road, as shown on plan 609 BM; thence Easterly along the North Limit of said road and its production across the road allowance to the intersection with the West boundary of Section Twenty-Four (24); thence Southerly across road plan 609 B.M. and along the West boundary of the North West Quarter of Section Thirteen (13) to the South West corner thereof; thence Easterly along the South boundary of the North half of Section Thirteen (13) and its production across the road allowance to the South West corner of the North West Quarter of Section Eighteen (18), Township Eighty-Three (83), Range Twenty-Two (22), West of the Fifth (5th) Meridian; thence Southerly along the West boundary of said Section Eighteen (18) to the most northerly corner of Lot Two (2) as shown on registered plan 8022831; thence South Easterly along the North Easterly limits of Lots Two (2), Three (3) and Four (4) as shown on registered Plan 8022831 to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886233" lims:id="886233" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Description of the Approach Surfaces</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886234" lims:id="886234" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The approach surfaces, shown on Peace River Airport Zoning Plan No. E.1801 dated January 16, 1984, are surfaces abutting each end of the strip associated with the runway designated 03-21 and are described as inclined planes having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to imaginary horizontal lines drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip 300 m measured vertically above the elevation at the ends of the strip and 15 000 m measured horizontally from the ends of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal lines being 2 400 m from the projected centre line.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886235" lims:id="886235" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886236" lims:id="886236" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The outer surface, shown on Peace River Airport Zoning Plan No. E.1801 dated January 16, 1984, is an imaginary surface located at a common plane established at a constant elevation of 45 m above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point except where that common plane is less than 9 m above the surface of the ground, the imaginary surface is located at 9 m above the surface of the ground.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886237" lims:id="886237" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Description of the Strip</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886238" lims:id="886238" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The strip associated with runway 03-21, as shown on Peace River Airport Zoning Plan No. E.1801 dated January 16, 1984, is 300 m in width, 150 m on each side of the centre line of the runway, and 1 644 m in length.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886239" lims:id="886239" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Transitional Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="886240" lims:id="886240" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The transitional surfaces, shown on Peace River Airport Zoning Plan No. E.1801 dated January 16, 1984, are surfaces consisting of an inclined plane rising at a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 7 m measured horizontally at right angles to the centre line and centre line produced of the strip and its approach surfaces to an intersection with the outer surface.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>