<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2022-03-03" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:current-date="2022-03-07" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975438" lims:id="975438" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975439" lims:id="975439"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/95-40</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1994</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975441" lims:id="975441"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-19">EXPORT AND IMPORT PERMITS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975442" lims:id="975442">General Import Permit No. 1 — Dairy Products for Personal Use</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975443" lims:id="975443"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975444" lims:id="975444" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas dairy products have been included on the Import Control list;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975445" lims:id="975445" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And Whereas the Secretary of State for External Affairs has determined an import access quantity for dairy products pursuant to subsection 6.2(1)<FootnoteRef idref="footnote1_e">*</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-19">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal>;</Text><Footnote id="footnote1_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>*</Label><Text>S.C. 1994, c. 47, s. 106</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975446" lims:id="975446" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, the Secretary of State for External Affairs, pursuant to section 10<FootnoteRef idref="footnote2_e">**</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-19">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal>, hereby cancels the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="C.R.C.,_c._623">Import of Dairy Products for Personal Use Permit</XRefExternal>, C.R.C., c. 623, and, pursuant to subsection 8(1.1)<FootnoteRef idref="footnote3_e">***</FootnoteRef> and subsection 8.3(3)<FootnoteRef idref="footnote4_e">****</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-19">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal>, hereby issues the annexed General permit authorizing the importation of dairy products for personal use, effective on the latest of the days on which sections 74 and 106, subsection 108(1) and sections 109 and 111 of An <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Act to implement the Agreement Establishing the World Trade Organization</XRefExternal>, being chapter 47 of the Statutes of Canada, 1994, come into force.</Text><Footnote id="footnote2_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>**</Label><Text>S.C. 1994, c. 47, s. 111</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="footnote3_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>***</Label><Text>S.C. 1994, c. 47, s. 108(1)</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="footnote4_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>****</Label><Text>S.C. 1994, c. 47, s. 109</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975447" lims:id="975447" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Ottawa, Ontario, December 29, 1994</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975448" lims:id="975448" topmarginspacing="12" language-align="no" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="right">ANDRÉ OUELLET</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Secretary of State for External Affairs</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975449" lims:id="975449"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975450" lims:id="975450"><Label>1</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/97-40, s. 2]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975451" lims:id="975451" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975452" lims:id="975452"><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Permit, <DefinedTermEn>dairy products</DefinedTermEn> means the goods set out in the schedule. (<Emphasis style="italic">produits laitiers</Emphasis>)</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975453" lims:id="975453" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975454" lims:id="975454"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975455" lims:id="975455"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), any resident of Canada may, under the authority of this Permit, import into Canada for the personal use of the importer and the importer’s household dairy products not exceeding $20 in value for each importation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975456" lims:id="975456"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The $20 limit in value for each importation does not apply in respect of the dairy products set out in item 5 of the schedule.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975458" lims:id="975458">SOR/2000-41, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="975459" lims:id="975459"><Label>4</Label><Text>Where any goods imported under the authority of this Permit are required to be reported in the prescribed form under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-52.6">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, that form shall contain the statement “Imported under the authority of <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-95-40">General Import Permit No. 1 — Dairy Products for Personal Use</XRefExternal>" or “<Language xml:lang="fr">Importé en vertu de la <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="DORS-95-40">Licence générale d’importation n<Sup>o</Sup> 1 — Produits laitiers pour usage personnel</XRefExternal></Language>".</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975460" lims:id="975460" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="975461" lims:id="975461"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><RegulationPiece lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="975462" lims:id="975462"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975463" lims:id="975463"><Label>1 to 4</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/96-50, s. 1]</Repealed></Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975464" lims:id="975464"><Label>5</Label><Text>Milk and cream, neither concentrated nor containing added sugar or other sweetening matter, of a fat content, by weight, not exceeding 6 per cent, that are classified under tariff item No. 0401.10.10 or 0401.20.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975465" lims:id="975465"><Label>5.1</Label><Text>Cream, neither concentrated nor containing added sugar or other sweetening matter, of a fat content, by weight, exceeding 6 per cent, that is classified under tariff item No. 0401.40.10 or 0401.50.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975466" lims:id="975466"><Label>6</Label><Text>Milk and cream, containing added sugar or other sweetening matter, in powder, granules or other solid forms, of a fat content, by weight, not exceeding 1.5 per cent, classified under tariff item No. 0402.10.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975467" lims:id="975467"><Label>7</Label><Text>Milk and cream, in powder, granules or other solid forms, of a fat content, by weight, exceeding 1.5 per cent, not containing added sugar or other sweetening matter, classified under tariff item No. 0402.21.11 or 0402.21.21 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975468" lims:id="975468"><Label>8</Label><Text>Milk and cream, in powder, granules or other solid forms, of a fat content, by weight, exceeding 1.5 per cent, containing added sugar or other sweetening matter, classified under tariff item No. 0402.29.11 or 0402.29.21 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975469" lims:id="975469"><Label>9</Label><Text>Preparations (other than preparations classified under tariff item No. 2106.90.31 or 2106.90.32 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>) containing more than 15 per cent by weight of milk fat, but less than 50 per cent by weight of dairy content, and suitable for use as butter substitutes, not elsewhere specified or included, that are classified under tariff item No. 2106.90.33 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975470" lims:id="975470"><Label>10</Label><Text>Milk and cream, not in powder, granules or other solid forms, concentrated (whether or not containing added sugar or other sweetening matter) or not concentrated (containing added sugar or other sweetening matter), that are classified under tariff item No. 0402.91.10 or 0402.99.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975471" lims:id="975471"><Label>11</Label><Text>Powdered buttermilk, whether or not containing added sugar or other sweetening matter or flavoured or containing added fruit, nuts or cocoa, that is classified under tariff item No. 0403.90.11 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975472" lims:id="975472"><Label>12</Label><Text>Buttermilk (other than powdered buttermilk), curdled milk and cream, kephir and other fermented or acidified milk and cream, whether or not concentrated or containing added sugar or other sweetening matter or flavoured or containing added fruit, nuts or cocoa, that are classified under tariff item No. 0403.90.91 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975473" lims:id="975473"><Label>13</Label><Text>Products consisting of natural milk constituents, whether or not containing added sugar or other sweetening matter, not elsewhere specified or included, that are classified under tariff item No. 0404.90.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975474" lims:id="975474"><Label>13.1</Label><Text>Powdered whey, whether or not containing added sugar or other sweetening matter, that is classified under tariff item No. 0404.10.21 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2021-04-01" lims:enacted-date="2021-03-29" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975475" lims:id="1291091"><Label>13.2</Label><Text>Milk protein substances with a milk protein content of 85% or more by weight, calculated on a dry matter basis, that do not originate in a CUSMA country, an EU country or other CETA beneficiary, a CUKTCA beneficiary, Chile, Costa Rica or Israel and that are the subject of two commitments signed by the Government of Canada on June 12, 2008, one with the European Communities and the other with the Government of Switzerland, relating to the modification, in Canada’s schedule of concessions pursuant to the Agreement Establishing the World Trade Organization, to Canada’s concession on tariff item No. 3504.00.00 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> with regard to those substances.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975476" lims:id="975476"><Label>14</Label><Text>Mixes and doughs, for the preparation of bread, pastry, cakes, biscuits and other bakers’ wares classified under heading No. 19.05 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, containing more than 25 per cent by weight of butterfat and not put up for retail sale, that are classified under tariff item No. 1901.20.11 or 1901.20.21 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975477" lims:id="975477"><Label>15</Label><Text>Milk, cream or butter substitutes containing 50 per cent or more by weight of dairy content, not elsewhere specified or included, that are classified under tariff item No. 2106.90.31 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975478" lims:id="975478"><Label>16</Label><Text>Food preparations of goods of heading Nos. 04.01 to 04.04 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> (other than ice cream mixes or ice milk mixes), containing more than 10 per cent but less than 50 per cent on a dry weight basis of milk solids, not in retail packaging, that are classified under tariff item No. 1901.90.33 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975479" lims:id="975479"><Label>16.1</Label><Text>Food preparations of goods of heading Nos. 04.01 to 04.04 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> (other than ice cream mixes or ice milk mixes), containing 50 per cent or more on a dry weight basis of milk solids, not in retail packaging, that are classified under tariff item No. 1901.90.53 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975480" lims:id="975480"><Label>17</Label><Text>Food preparations, not elsewhere specified or included, containing 50 per cent or more by weight of dairy content, that are classified under tariff item No. 2106.90.93 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975481" lims:id="975481"><Label>18</Label><Text>Non-alcoholic beverages containing milk (other than chocolate milk) and containing 50% or more by weight of dairy content and not put up for retail sale, that are classified under tariff item No. 2202.99.32 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975482" lims:id="975482"><Label>19</Label><Text>Complete feeds and feed supplements, including concentrates, containing 50 per cent or more by weight, in the dry state, of non-fat milk solids (other than preparations classified under tariff item No. 2309.10.00, 2309.90.10 or 2309.90.20 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>), not elsewhere specified or included, that are classified under tariff item No. 2309.90.31 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975483" lims:id="975483"><Label>20</Label><Text>Chocolate ice cream mix and ice milk mix that are classified under tariff item No. 1806.20.21 or 1806.90.11 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975484" lims:id="975484"><Label>21</Label><Text>Ice cream mixes and ice milk mixes, being food preparations of goods of heading Nos. 04.01 to 04.04 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, containing more than 10 per cent but less than 50 per cent on a dry weight basis of milk solids, that are classified under tariff item No. 1901.90.31 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975485" lims:id="975485"><Label>21.1</Label><Text>Ice cream mixes and ice milk mixes, being food preparations of goods of heading Nos. 04.01 to 04.04 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, containing 50 per cent or more on a dry weight basis of milk solids, that are classified under tariff item No. 1901.90.51 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975486" lims:id="975486"><Label>22</Label><Text>Ice cream and other edible ice, whether or not containing cocoa, other than flavoured ice and ice sherbets, that are classified under tariff item No. 2105.00.91 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975487" lims:id="975487"><Label>23</Label><Text>Fresh (unripened or uncured) cheese, including whey cheese and curd, that is classified under tariff item No. 0406.10.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975488" lims:id="975488"><Label>24</Label><Text>Cheddar cheese and Cheddar types of cheese, grated or powdered, that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.20.11 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975489" lims:id="975489"><Label>25</Label><Text>Grated or powdered cheese of all kinds, other than Cheddar and Cheddar types, that is classified under tariff item No. 0406.20.91 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975490" lims:id="975490"><Label>26</Label><Text>Processed cheese, not grated or powdered, that is classified under tariff item No. 0406.30.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975491" lims:id="975491"><Label>27</Label><Text>Blue-veined cheese that is classified under tariff item No. 0406.40.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975492" lims:id="975492"><Label>28</Label><Text>Cheddar cheese and Cheddar types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.11 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975493" lims:id="975493"><Label>29</Label><Text>Camembert cheese and Camembert types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.21 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975494" lims:id="975494"><Label>30</Label><Text>Brie cheese and Brie types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.31 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975495" lims:id="975495"><Label>31</Label><Text>Gouda cheese and Gouda types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.41 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975496" lims:id="975496"><Label>32</Label><Text>Provolone cheese and Provolone types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.51 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975497" lims:id="975497"><Label>33</Label><Text>Mozzarella cheese and Mozzarella types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.61 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975498" lims:id="975498"><Label>34</Label><Text>Swiss/Emmental cheese and Swiss/Emmental types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.71 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975499" lims:id="975499"><Label>35</Label><Text>Gruyère cheese and Gruyère types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.81 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975500" lims:id="975500"><Label>36</Label><Text>Havarti cheese and Havarti types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.91 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975501" lims:id="975501"><Label>37</Label><Text>Parmesan cheese and Parmesan types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.93 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975502" lims:id="975502"><Label>38</Label><Text>Romano cheese and Romano types of cheese that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.95 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975503" lims:id="975503"><Label>39</Label><Text>All other cheeses that are classified under tariff item No. 0406.90.98 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2022-03-03" lims:enacted-date="2022-03-03" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975504" lims:id="1340639"><Label>40</Label><Text>Yogurt (other than yogurt containing chocolate, spices, coffee or coffee extracts, plants, parts of plants, cereals or bakers’ wares, provided that any added substance is not used for the purpose of replacing, in whole or in part, any milk constituent, and the product retains the essential character of yogurt) that is classified under tariff item No. 0403.20.29 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2022-03-03" lims:enacted-date="2022-03-03" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="1340640" lims:id="1340640"><Label>40.1</Label><Text>Yogurt — containing chocolate, spices, coffee or coffee extracts, plants, parts of plants, cereals or bakers’ wares, provided that any added substance is not used for the purpose of replacing, in whole or in part, any milk constituent, and the product retains the essential character of yogurt — not put up for retail sale, that is classified under tariff item No. 0403.20.21 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975505" lims:id="975505"><Label>41</Label><Text>Butter that is classified under tariff item No. 0405.10.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975506" lims:id="975506"><Label>41.1</Label><Text>Dairy spreads that are classified under tariff item No. 0405.20.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975507" lims:id="975507"><Label>42</Label><Text>Fats and oils derived from milk, other than butter or dairy spreads, that are classified under tariff item No. 0405.90.10 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-03-03" lims:fid="975508" lims:id="975508"><Label>43</Label><Text>Goods that are classified under heading No. 98.04 or 98.26 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and that are otherwise classifiable under a tariff item referred to in any of items 5 to 42 of this schedule.</Text></Section></RegulationPiece><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="975510" lims:id="975510">SOR/95-397, ss. 1 to 6; SOR/96-50, ss. 1 to 4; SOR/97-40, ss. 3, 4; SOR/97-78, ss. 1, 2; SOR/98-70, ss. 1 to 3; SOR/2008-286, s. 1; SOR/2011-305, s. 1; SOR/2017-183, ss. 1, 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2020-07-01" lims:enacted-date="2020-04-07" lims:fid="1254138" lims:id="1254138" lims:enactId="1243950">SOR/2020-78, s. 3</HistoricalNoteSubItem><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2021-04-01" lims:enacted-date="2021-03-29" lims:fid="1291090" lims:id="1291090" lims:enactId="1290788">SOR/2021-72, s. 3</HistoricalNoteSubItem><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2022-03-03" lims:enacted-date="2022-03-03" lims:fid="1340641" lims:id="1340641" lims:enactId="1340251">SOR/2022-36, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule><RecentAmendments><Amendment><AmendmentCitation>SOR/2022-36</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2022-03-03</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation>SOR/2021-72</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2021-04-01</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation>SOR/2020-78</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2020-07-01</AmendmentDate></Amendment></RecentAmendments></Regulation>