<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859342" lims:id="859342" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859343" lims:id="859343"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/49-42</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859345" lims:id="859345"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">APPROPRIATION ACT, NO. 7, 1949</XRefExternal><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="Z-01">APPROPRIATION ACTS</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859346" lims:id="859346">Regulations re school fees and transportation costs for children of certain Government employees</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859347" lims:id="859347">Regulations Governing Payment of School Fees and Transportation Costs Re Children of Certain Employees of the Government of Canada</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1954-1694</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1954</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>09</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859348" lims:id="859348"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859349" lims:id="859349" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance and pursuant to The Appropriation Act, No. 7, 1949, Vote No 938, is pleased to order as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859350" lims:id="859350" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The Regulations governing the payment of school fees and transportation costs of children of certain employees of the Government of Canada, established by Order in Council PC 3455 of 19th July, 1950, are hereby revoked; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859351" lims:id="859351" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The annexed “Regulations governing payment of school fees and transportation costs re children of certain employees of the Government of Canada” are hereby made and established in substitution for the regulations hereby revoked.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859352" lims:id="859352"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859353" lims:id="859353"><Label>1</Label><Text>In these regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859354" lims:id="859354" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>child</DefinedTermEn> does not include a person who has attained the age of eighteen years at the commencement of the school year; (<DefinedTermFr>enfant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859355" lims:id="859355" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal land</DefinedTermEn> means land owned by Her Majesty in right of Canada; (<DefinedTermFr>terrain fédéral</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859356" lims:id="859356" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn>, when used with reference to an employee, child of an employee, or land, means the Minister having the direction, control and management of the employee or land; (<DefinedTermFr>Ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859357" lims:id="859357" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>non-taxable employee</DefinedTermEn> means an employee of Her Majesty in right of Canada who, by reason of the conditions of his occupancy of federal land, is not subject to municipal taxation in respect of that land, and who applies to the Minister for financial assistance towards the cost of educating his children; (<DefinedTermFr>employé non imposable</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859358" lims:id="859358" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>school authority</DefinedTermEn> means, with reference to a school, the corporation, board or other body that, with due authority, levies taxes to meet the expenses of operating and maintaining the school. (<DefinedTermFr>autorité scolaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859359" lims:id="859359"><Label>2</Label><Text>Where a non-taxable employee resides on federal land that, in the opinion of the Minister, is within easy access of a school established by the Minister of National Defence, the Minister shall, unless the facilities are insufficient, arrange with the Minister of National Defence for the accommodation at that school of the children of the employee, while he is so resident, in accordance with the provisions of Order in Council P.C. 44/2300 of 6th May, 1950.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859360" lims:id="859360"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859361" lims:id="859361"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a child of a non-taxable employee is not accommodated at a school mentioned in section 2, the Minister may arrange for the child to be accommodated at a school in the municipality in which the employee resides, or if, in the opinion of the Minister, the school facilities in that municipality are inadequate, at a school in a municipality having adequate facilities for the purpose, but a report shall be submitted to the Treasury Board whenever attendance at a school outside the municipality in which the employee resides is authorized stating the reasons for the arrangement and the additional costs resulting, if any.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859362" lims:id="859362"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a child is accommodated at a school pursuant to an arrangement under subsection (1), the Minister may pay to the school authority, in each school year during which the child attends the school under the arrangement, an amount not exceeding the school fees ordinarily charged for the accommodation of a non-resident at the school.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859363" lims:id="859363"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The amount payable under subsection (2) may be paid to a non-taxable employee to the extent that he has paid school fees to the school authority in respect of the child, and the amount payable to the school authority shall be reduced by the amount so paid.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859364" lims:id="859364"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859365" lims:id="859365"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a child of a non-taxable employee, pursuant to an arrangement under section 3, attends a school that is not less than five miles and not more than thirty miles from the place of residence, and to attend the school uses a public transportation service approved for the purpose by the Minister, other than the service mentioned in subsection (2) or an urban public transportation service, the Minister may pay to the employee the amount by which the cost to the employee of the service that is rendered to the child exceeds three dollars a month.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859366" lims:id="859366"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the Minister of National Defence provides a transportation service that can be made available to a child for the purpose of attending a school pursuant to an arrangement under section 3, the Minister may arrange for the child to use that service on such terms and conditions as the Minister of National Defence may prescribe.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859367" lims:id="859367"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where federal land is made available for residential use, the Minister shall, except where in his opinion it is not feasible, lease the land on terms that will not deprive the municipality in which the land is situated, of its right to tax the tenant in respect of his occupancy of the land.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859368" lims:id="859368"><Label>6</Label><Text>No payment shall be made under these regulations in respect of a person who resides on federal land</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859369" lims:id="859369"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that is included in property in a municipality that receives a grant under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Municipal Grants Act</XRefExternal> (for the purpose of computing the grant); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859370" lims:id="859370"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is situated in a municipality in which he is subject to municipal taxation in respect of his occupancy of that land.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859371" lims:id="859371"><Label>7</Label><Text>Any payment or arrangement made under these regulations shall be reported to the Municipal Grants Division of the Department of Finance.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>