<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2018-11-23" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2018-11-23" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873146" lims:id="873146" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873147" lims:id="873147"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/82-263</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1982</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873149" lims:id="873149"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="N-14.01">CANADA NATIONAL PARKS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873150" lims:id="873150">National Historic Parks General Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873151" lims:id="873151">General Regulations Respecting the Control and Management of the National Historic Parks of Canada</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1982-596</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1982</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873152" lims:id="873152"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873153" lims:id="873153" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of the Environment, pursuant to section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Parks Act</XRefExternal> and section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">National Historic Parks Order</XRefExternal>, C.R.C., c. 1112, is pleased hereby to make the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-82-263">General Regulations respecting the Control and Management of the National Historic Parks of Canada</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873154" lims:id="873154"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873155" lims:id="873155" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873156" lims:id="873156"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-82-263">National Historic Parks General Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873157" lims:id="873157" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873158" lims:id="873158"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873159" lims:id="873159" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>archaeological site</DefinedTermEn> means any site or area containing historical resources buried or partially buried on land, resting on the surface of land or submerged or partially submerged beneath the surface of any watercourse or body of water in a Park; (<DefinedTermFr>site archéologique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873160" lims:id="873160" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Director</DefinedTermEn> means the Director of a Region of Parks Canada, Department of the Environment; (<DefinedTermFr>directeur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873161" lims:id="873161" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>diver’s marker</DefinedTermEn> means a floating device that incorporates a marker in the form of a red square flag with a white diagonal stripe extending from the head of the hoist; (<DefinedTermFr>indicateur de plongée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873162" lims:id="873162" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>explosive</DefinedTermEn> means any substance or device other than a firearm made, manufactured or used to produce a violent effect by explosion or pyrotechnic effect; (<DefinedTermFr>explosif</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873163" lims:id="873163" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>fauna</DefinedTermEn> means all vertebrates or invertebrates, living or dead, or parts thereof and includes the eggs or young of fauna but does not include the fossil remains of any fauna; (<DefinedTermFr>faune</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873164" lims:id="873164" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>fireplace</DefinedTermEn> means a grill or stove or other such device designed for the kindling or maintenance of fire; (<DefinedTermFr>foyer</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873165" lims:id="873165" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>flora</DefinedTermEn> means any plant matter, living or dead, and includes fungi and moulds but does not include the fossil remains of any flora; (<DefinedTermFr>flore</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873166" lims:id="873166" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>historical object</DefinedTermEn> means any historical resource of a movable nature and includes any specimen, artifact, document or work of art, or any reproduction thereof; (<DefinedTermFr>objet historique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873167" lims:id="873167" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>historical resource</DefinedTermEn> means any work of nature or of man that is primarily of interest for its palaeontological, prehistorical, historical, cultural, natural, scientific or aesthetic value including, but not limited to, a palaeontological, prehistorical, historical or natural site, structure or object or any remains, restoration or reconstruction thereof; (<DefinedTermFr>ressource historique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873168" lims:id="873168" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>kindle</DefinedTermEn> means to start, or attempt to start, a fire; (<DefinedTermFr>allumer</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873169" lims:id="873169" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>maintain</DefinedTermEn> means, with respect to a fire, to add fuel to enjoy the use of, or allow to burn; (<DefinedTermFr>alimenter</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873170" lims:id="873170" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of the Environment; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873171" lims:id="873171" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>moor</DefinedTermEn> means to make fast or tie up a watercraft to a wharf or to another watercraft or to use a space or stall at a wharf and includes to dock, beach, store or anchor a watercraft; (<DefinedTermFr>amarrer</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873172" lims:id="873172" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>natural object</DefinedTermEn> means any natural material, soil, sand, gravel, rock, mineral or other object or natural phenomenon not included within the terms <DefinedTermEn>flora</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>fauna</DefinedTermEn> that is located within a Park, but does not include the fossil remains of any flora or fauna; (<DefinedTermFr>objet naturel</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873173" lims:id="873173" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Park</DefinedTermEn> means any area set apart as a National Historic Park in accordance with Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Parks Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>parc</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873174" lims:id="873174" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Superintendent</DefinedTermEn> means the Superintendent of a Park; (<DefinedTermFr>directeur du parc</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873175" lims:id="873175" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>vessel</DefinedTermEn> includes any boat, canoe, raft, amphibious vehicle or any other structure or device, other than a seaplane, used or capable of being used for transportation on water; (<DefinedTermFr>bateau</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873176" lims:id="873176" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>wharf</DefinedTermEn> means any wharf, dock, pier, jetty, quay, landing, breakwater, mole or sea-wall or any floating structure or device that may be used to moor watercraft. (<DefinedTermFr>quai</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873177" lims:id="873177" level="1"><TitleText>Preservation of Property</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873178" lims:id="873178"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873179" lims:id="873179"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall disturb, remove, deface, damage or destroy any archaeological site or historical resource in a Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873180" lims:id="873180"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), a Director may issue a permit to any person authorizing the person to remove historical resources from a Park for management of the Park or scientific purposes or for the purpose of public display.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873181" lims:id="873181"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873182" lims:id="873182"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall remove, deface, damage or destroy flora, fauna or natural objects in a Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873183" lims:id="873183"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), a Superintendent may issue a permit to any person authorizing the person to remove, deface, damage or destroy flora, fauna or natural objects in a Park for management of the Park or scientific purposes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873184" lims:id="873184"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A permit issued by the Superintendent under subsection (2) shall specify the kind and amount of, and the location from which, flora, fauna or natural objects may be removed, defaced, damaged or destroyed, and any other conditions applicable to the permit.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873185" lims:id="873185"><Label>5</Label><Text>No person shall remove, deface, damage or destroy any public building, fence or other structure in a Park or any signboard, sign or notice placed, posted or erected in a Park.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873186" lims:id="873186"><Label>6</Label><Text>No person shall deposit any snow, leaves, rubbish or other matter in a Park except in such places, at such times and under such conditions as may be specified by the Superintendent.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873187" lims:id="873187" level="1"><TitleText>Use of Water Resources</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873188" lims:id="873188"><Label>7</Label><Text>No person shall pollute any watercourse in a Park.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873189" lims:id="873189"><Label>8</Label><Text>Subject to sections 9 to 11, no person shall obstruct, divert or otherwise interfere with any watercourse.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873190" lims:id="873190"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Superintendent of a Park may permit the taking of water from any watercourse or water supply system in the Park to a place outside the Park in the case of drought, fire, contamination of a water supply or other emergency.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873191" lims:id="873191"><Label>10</Label><Text>A Director may issue a permit to any person, for a period not exceeding 10 years, authorizing the person to take water for domestic or business water supply purposes within a Park from any watercourse, well or water supply system in the Park.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873192" lims:id="873192"><Label>11</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873193" lims:id="873193"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement with a municipality or water district adjacent to a Park for the supply of water from the Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873194" lims:id="873194"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement with persons residing on land adjacent to a Park for the supply of water from the Park for domestic purposes and for use in establishments providing tourist accommodation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873195" lims:id="873195" level="1"><TitleText>Restricted Areas and Activities</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:lastAmendedDate="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873196" lims:id="873196"><Label>12</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873197" lims:id="873197"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Superintendent of a Park shall designate any activity or area in the Park as restricted if it is necessary for the preservation, control or management of the Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873198" lims:id="873198"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the Superintendent of a Park designates any activity or area as restricted pursuant to subsection (1), he or she shall so inform the public by the posting, at all information offices or centres located in the Park, of notices describing the activity and of maps showing the area.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873199" lims:id="873199"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Superintendent of a Park may, on application to him or her by any person, authorize that person to engage in an activity in the Park or to enter an area of the Park that has been designated as restricted pursuant to subsection (1) on such terms and conditions as the Superintendent may prescribe.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873200" lims:id="873200"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Superintendent of a Park may suspend or cancel any authorization issued under subsection (3) if it is necessary to do so for the preservation, control or management of a Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873201" lims:id="873201"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person shall engage in an activity or enter an area that has been designated as restricted pursuant to subsection (1) except in accordance with the terms and conditions prescribed by the Superintendent.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873203" lims:id="873203">SOR/88-538, s. 1(F); SOR/2011-217, ss. 1(E), 4(E), 5(E); SOR/2018-250, s. 22</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873204" lims:id="873204" level="1"><TitleText>Authorization</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873205" lims:id="873205"><Label>13</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873206" lims:id="873206"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873207" lims:id="873207" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>authorization</DefinedTermEn> means a pass, licence, ticket or other form of permission, issued pursuant to subsection (4) in respect of a designated activity, authorizing the holder to carry on the designated activity; (<DefinedTermFr>autorisation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873208" lims:id="873208" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated activity</DefinedTermEn> means any activity in a Park, including travel, entry into an area of the Park and the use of any facility in the Park, that is designated pursuant to subsection (2). (<DefinedTermFr>activité désignée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873209" lims:id="873209"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Superintendent may, for the proper management of the Park, designate any activity, other than an activity referred to in section 12, that may be carried on only by the holder of an authorization issued in respect of that activity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873210" lims:id="873210"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Superintendent shall post a list of designated activities and their description at information offices or centers located in the Park or at the entrances to the Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873211" lims:id="873211"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Superintendent shall, on request, issue an authorization in respect of a designated activity if the designated activity will not result in</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873212" lims:id="873212"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any significant adverse effects on the natural and cultural resources of the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873213" lims:id="873213"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any adverse effects on the safety and health of persons using the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873214" lims:id="873214"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any significant adverse effects on the enjoyment of persons using the Park; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873215" lims:id="873215"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>any significant adverse effects on the preservation, control and management of the Park.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873216" lims:id="873216"><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>The Superintendent shall set in the authorization any terms and conditions that are necessary for the preservation, control and management of the Park or for the safety of the public.<LineBreak /></Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873217" lims:id="873217"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person shall carry on a designated activity unless the person is the holder of an authorization issued in respect of that designated activity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873218" lims:id="873218"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The holder of an authorization shall, at the request of the Superintendent or a warden or other officer of the Park, produce the authorization for inspection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873219" lims:id="873219"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Superintendent may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873220" lims:id="873220"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>suspend an authorization, where the holder fails to comply with any prescribed term or condition of it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873221" lims:id="873221"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>reinstate any authorization suspended pursuant to paragraph (a), where the failure referred to in that paragraph has been remedied; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873222" lims:id="873222"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>revoke an authorization, where the holder is convicted of a contravention of these Regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873224" lims:id="873224">SOR/95-255, s. 1; SOR/2011-217, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873225" lims:id="873225" level="1"><TitleText>Prevention of Nuisances</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:lastAmendedDate="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873226" lims:id="873226"><Label>14</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873227" lims:id="873227"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a nuisance exists on any premises in a Park, the Superintendent of the Park is authorized to order the owner, lessee, licensee or occupier of the premises to abate the nuisance and, if necessary, to clean up the premises.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873228" lims:id="873228"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the owner, lessee, licensee or occupier of any premises where a nuisance exists fails, after reasonable notice from the Superintendent, to abate the nuisance and, where necessary, clean up the premises, the Superintendent may take such steps as are necessary to abate the nuisance and clean up the premises.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873230" lims:id="873230">SOR/2018-250, s. 23</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873231" lims:id="873231" level="1"><TitleText>Camping</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873232" lims:id="873232"><Label>15</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873233" lims:id="873233"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>It is prohibited, without a permit issued for this purpose, for any person to use, occupy, reside or camp on any land in a Park or erect or use any structure in a Park or park any vehicle in a Park for the purpose of camping.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873234" lims:id="873234"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in this section prevents a person from using the facilities provided in a public picnic ground for the preparation and consumption of meals.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873236" lims:id="873236">SOR/2011-217, s. 3(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:lastAmendedDate="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873237" lims:id="873237"><Label>16</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873238" lims:id="873238"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to these Regulations, on receipt of an application, the Superintendent may issue a camping permit to the applicant for the use of an area for such period and under such conditions as the Superintendent specifies in the permit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873239" lims:id="873239"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Superintendent shall cancel a camping permit issued under subsection (1) if it is necessary for the preservation, control or management of the Park or for the safety of the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873240" lims:id="873240"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person who holds a camping permit is eligible to apply for another camping permit for the period or any part of the period for which their camping permit is valid.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873242" lims:id="873242">SOR/2011-217, ss. 4(E), 6(E); SOR/2018-250, s. 24</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873243" lims:id="873243"><Label>17</Label><Text>No person shall, for valuable consideration or for gain, permit another person to use, occupy, reside on or camp on any land in a Park or erect or use any structure in a Park or park any vehicle thereon for any purpose whatever.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873244" lims:id="873244"><Label>18</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873245" lims:id="873245"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A camping permit is not transferable and is valid only during such period as the area to which the permit applies is occupied by the holder thereof.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873246" lims:id="873246"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1) and paragraph 21(a), an area to which a camping permit applies is deemed not to be occupied where a tent or trailer or similar device has been unoccupied for a period exceeding 24 hours or has been removed from the area for a period exceeding 24 hours.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873247" lims:id="873247"><Label>19</Label><Text>A camping permit expires on the expiry date specified thereon.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:lastAmendedDate="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873248" lims:id="873248"><Label>20</Label><Text>The holder of a camping permit shall, at all times, maintain the area to which the permit applies in a satisfactory condition.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873250" lims:id="873250">SOR/2018-250, s. 25</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:lastAmendedDate="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873251" lims:id="873251"><Label>21</Label><Text>The Superintendent is authorized to cancel a camping permit if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873252" lims:id="873252"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the area to which the permit applies is not occupied;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873253" lims:id="873253"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the holder of the permit fails to maintain the area to which the permit applies in a satisfactory condition;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873254" lims:id="873254"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the holder of the permit has furnished the Superintendent with false or misleading information in order to secure the permit or maintain it in force; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873255" lims:id="873255"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the holder of the permit fails to comply with</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873256" lims:id="873256"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the conditions of the permit, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873257" lims:id="873257"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a directive, instruction or order of the Superintendent made pursuant to these Regulations or to any other Regulations that apply in the Park.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873259" lims:id="873259">SOR/2018-250, s. 26</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873260" lims:id="873260"><Label>22</Label><Text>Where a camping permit has been cancelled, the Superintendent shall give notice of the cancellation to the holder of the permit by mailing a copy of the notice to the holder or by posting a copy of the notice of cancellation in the vicinity of the entrance to any structure or vehicle used for camping in the area in respect of which the permit was issued, and the cancellation takes effect on the date the notice was so mailed or posted.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873262" lims:id="873262">SOR/88-538, s. 2(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873263" lims:id="873263"><Label>23</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873264" lims:id="873264"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The holder of a camping permit shall, before the expiration of the permit or, where the permit is cancelled, on receipt of the notice of cancellation, remove from the area in respect of which the permit was issued, any trailer or other vehicle or any structure, chattel or article that the holder placed in that area.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873265" lims:id="873265"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Superintendent may remove any trailer or other vehicle or any structure, chattel or article left in a Park in violation of subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873267" lims:id="873267">SOR/88-538, s. 3(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873268" lims:id="873268" level="1"><TitleText>Fires</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873269" lims:id="873269"><Label>24</Label><Text>No person shall, in a Park, kindle or maintain any fire except</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873270" lims:id="873270"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in a fireplace provided by the Superintendent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873271" lims:id="873271"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in a portable stove burning fuel other than wood or charcoal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873272" lims:id="873272"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in a charcoal or gas-fired barbecue.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873273" lims:id="873273"><Label>25</Label><Text>Notwithstanding section 24, the Superintendent may, by written authorization, permit a person to kindle and maintain a fire and may stipulate the terms and conditions under which the fire shall be kindled and maintained.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873274" lims:id="873274"><Label>26</Label><Text>No person shall, in a Park, be in possession of more than five gallons of gasoline or other inflammable liquid, unless the gasoline or other inflammable liquid is stored in the tank of a motor vehicle, a motor-driven boat or an aircraft or unless a permit has been obtained for possession of the gasoline or other inflammable liquid.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:lastAmendedDate="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873275" lims:id="873275"><Label>27</Label><Text>No person shall, in a Park,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873276" lims:id="873276"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>allow a fire to spread beyond the confines of the fireplace, portable stove or barbecue;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873277" lims:id="873277"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>discard a lighted cigar, cigarette, match or other burning substance, except in a receptacle provided for that purpose by the Superintendent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873278" lims:id="873278"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>discard any unused match or any article or substance that could cause the kindling of a fire, except in a receptacle provided for that purpose by the Superintendent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873279" lims:id="873279"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>operate any machine or equipment that may cause the kindling of a fire, unless reasonable precautions have been taken;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873280" lims:id="873280"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>when removing or disposing of brush or any inflammable material, allow the brush or inflammable material to be accumulated, stored, handled, transported or disposed of in an unreasonable manner; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873281" lims:id="873281"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>leave any fire unattended.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2018-11-23" lims:fid="873283" lims:id="873283">SOR/2018-250, s. 27</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873284" lims:id="873284" level="1"><TitleText>Explosives</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873285" lims:id="873285"><Label>28</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873286" lims:id="873286"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), no person shall, except in accordance with a permit issued pursuant to subsection (2), have in their possession, store or use any explosive or bring any explosive into a Park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873287" lims:id="873287"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A Superintendent may issue a permit authorizing a person described in subsection (3) to have in  their possession, store or use any explosive in a Park, where that person is authorized under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-17">Explosives Act</XRefExternal> to have in their possession, store, use, make, manufacture or sell such an explosive in any other part of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873288" lims:id="873288"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A permit referred to in subsection (2) may be issued to the following persons:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873289" lims:id="873289"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person engaged in construction or demolition work who requires the explosive for their work;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873290" lims:id="873290"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person representing an organization retained by written agreement with the Director to present a reenactment of a historic event or other program for the education or entertainment of the public; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873291" lims:id="873291"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person in the employ of Her Majesty in right of Canada whose duties include the presentation of programs for the education or entertainment of the public.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873292" lims:id="873292"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), any person may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873293" lims:id="873293"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>transport explosives through a Park in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-17">Explosives Act</XRefExternal> or any provincial regulation respecting explosives; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873294" lims:id="873294"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>possess flares or fuses for use as safety equipment for motor vehicles, trains or boats in accordance with any federal or provincial requirements.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873296" lims:id="873296">SOR/2011-217, s. 6(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873297" lims:id="873297" level="1"><TitleText>Aircraft</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873298" lims:id="873298"><Label>29</Label><Text>Except as authorized by the Superintendent for the control or management of the Park, no person shall, in a Park, take off or land or deposit persons or objects from any aircraft, sail plane, glider, body kite, hang glider or other device designed or used to carry persons or objects through the air in powerless flight.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873299" lims:id="873299" level="1"><TitleText>Vessels</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873300" lims:id="873300"><Label>30</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873301" lims:id="873301"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall operate or use, or cause to be operated or used, on or under any watercourse in a Park any type of motorized vessel, water-skiing equipment or subsurface diving equipment unless a sign or notice authorized by the Superintendent permitting such operation or use is posted on or near the watercourse.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873302" lims:id="873302"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), the Superintendent may operate or use, or cause to be operated or used, any vessel or equipment referred to in subsection (1) on or under any watercourse in the Park where such operation or use is necessary for the management of the Park or for the safety of the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873303" lims:id="873303"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall drain, dump or discharge any waste or refuse from a vessel into any watercourse in a Park.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873304" lims:id="873304"><Label>31</Label><Text>No person shall moor any vessel in the approach to or in the lee of any wharf in a Park in such a manner as to obstruct the free flow of vessels to and from the wharf.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873305" lims:id="873305"><Label>32</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873306" lims:id="873306"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall moor any vessel at any wharf or area in a Park except in accordance with a traffic control device erected by the Superintendent pursuant to subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873307" lims:id="873307"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Superintendent may designate any wharf or area in the Park or any portion thereof as a wharf or area where mooring is allowed or where mooring is allowed only</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873308" lims:id="873308"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in accordance with a permit issued by the Superintendent,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873309" lims:id="873309"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>during specified periods of time, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873310" lims:id="873310"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for particular types of vessels</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873311" lims:id="873311"><Text>and the Superintendent shall erect a traffic control device at or near the designated wharf or area to indicate such designation.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873312" lims:id="873312"><Label>33</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873313" lims:id="873313"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall undertake any underwater activities in a Park unless he or she first places a diver’s marker in the vicinity of the dive site so that the marker is clearly visible to vessel operators.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873314" lims:id="873314"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who operates a vessel in the vicinity of a diver’s marker referred to in subsection (1) shall proceed with due caution and at a slow speed.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873316" lims:id="873316">SOR/2011-217, s. 5(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873317" lims:id="873317" level="1"><TitleText>Agreements</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873318" lims:id="873318"><Label>34</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement with a province or any person for the development, operation and maintenance in a Park of telephone, telegraph, natural gas and electrical, other than hydro-electrical, services for use only in the Park.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873319" lims:id="873319" level="1"><TitleText>Advertisements</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873320" lims:id="873320"><Label>35</Label><Text>No person shall display or distribute any advertisement or handbill in a Park except under and in accordance with a permit issued by the Superintendent.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873321" lims:id="873321" level="1"><TitleText>Prohibitions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873322" lims:id="873322"><Label>36</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873323" lims:id="873323"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall, in a Park,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873324" lims:id="873324"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>cause any excessive noise;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873325" lims:id="873325"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>behave in a manner that unreasonably disturbs other persons in the Park or unreasonably interferes with their enjoyment of the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873326" lims:id="873326"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>carry out any action that unreasonably interferes with fauna or the natural beauty of the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873327" lims:id="873327"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>carry out any action that threatens the historic resources in the Park; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873328" lims:id="873328"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>create or cause any nuisance in the Park.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873329" lims:id="873329"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Superintendent may remove or have removed from a Park any person who by their disorderly conduct, behaviour or action is in violation of subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873330" lims:id="873330"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person who has been removed from a Park under subsection (2) shall enter or attempt to enter that Park for one year following the date of removal unless that person applies for and obtains permission from the Director to enter the Park.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2011-09-30" lims:fid="873332" lims:id="873332">SOR/2011-217, s. 6(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>