<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2008-05-15" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-05-15" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676125" lims:id="676125" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676126" lims:id="676126"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2001-429</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676128" lims:id="676128"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-11.8">INSURANCE COMPANIES ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676129" lims:id="676129">Specialized Financing (Life Companies) Regulations</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2001-1800 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676130" lims:id="676130"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676131" lims:id="676131" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, pursuant to sections 494<FootnoteRef idref="fna_e">a</FootnoteRef>, 501<FootnoteRef idref="fna_e">a</FootnoteRef> and 1021<FootnoteRef idref="fnb_e">b</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-11.8">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fnc_e">c</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2001-429">Specialized Financing (Life Companies) Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fna_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2001, c. 9, s. 426</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fnb_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>S.C. 2001, c. 9, s. 465</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fnc_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>c</Label><Text>S.C. 1991, c. 47</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676132" lims:id="676132"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676133" lims:id="676133" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676134" lims:id="676134"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676135" lims:id="676135">Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676136" lims:id="676136"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676137" lims:id="676137" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-11.8">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676138" lims:id="676138" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>balance sheet value</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of the shares and ownership interests held by an entity, means the value reported on its balance sheet on an unconsolidated basis. (<DefinedTermFr>valeur au bilan</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676139" lims:id="676139" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>book value</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/2008-168, s. 15]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676140" lims:id="676140" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>specialized financing entity of the life company</DefinedTermEn> means a specialized financing entity that is controlled by the life company or in which the life company holds a substantial investment. (<DefinedTermFr>entité de la société d’assurance-vie s’occupant de financement spécial</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676141" lims:id="676141" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>subsidiary</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a life company, does not include a subsidiary that is a specialized financing entity of the life company. (<DefinedTermFr>filiale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676142" lims:id="676142"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676143" lims:id="676143">Definition of <DefinedTermEn>specialized financing entity</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In these Regulations and for the purpose of the definition <DefinedTermEn>specialized financing entity</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490(1) of the Act, <DefinedTermEn>specialized financing entity</DefinedTermEn> means an entity that acquires or holds shares of, or ownership interests in, entities that a life company may acquire control of, or hold, acquire or increase a substantial investment in, under subsection 493(4) of the Act.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676145" lims:id="676145">SOR/2008-168, s. 15</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676146" lims:id="676146" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676147" lims:id="676147"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676148" lims:id="676148">Application</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to specialized financing activities under subsection 493(4) of the Act and to the ownership by a life company of shares of, or ownership interests in, a specialized financing entity under paragraph 495(2)(b) of the Act.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676149" lims:id="676149" level="1"><TitleText>Conditions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676150" lims:id="676150"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676151" lims:id="676151">Limits on investments</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>A life company shall not, by way of specialized financing activities, acquire control of, or hold, acquire or increase a substantial investment in,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676152" lims:id="676152"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an entity referred to in any of paragraphs 495(1)(a) to (j) of the Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676153" lims:id="676153"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an entity that is primarily engaged in the leasing of motor vehicles in Canada for the purpose of extending credit to a customer or financing a customer’s acquisition of a motor vehicle;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676154" lims:id="676154"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an entity that is primarily engaged in providing temporary possession of personal property, including motor vehicles, to customers in Canada for a purpose other than to finance the customer’s acquisition of the property; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676155" lims:id="676155"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an entity that acts as an insurance broker or agent in Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676156" lims:id="676156"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676157" lims:id="676157">Length of investment</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>A life company shall not, by way of specialized financing activities, hold control of, or hold a substantial investment in, an entity for more than 13 consecutive years.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676158" lims:id="676158"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676159" lims:id="676159">Maximum authorized investment</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>A life company shall not, by way of specialized financing activities, acquire control of, or hold, acquire or increase a substantial investment in, an entity if the aggregate balance sheet value of the shares and ownership interests that the life company, any subsidiary of the life company and any specialized financing entity of the life company hold or would hold in the entity is more than $250 million.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676161" lims:id="676161">SOR/2008-168, s. 16</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676162" lims:id="676162"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676163" lims:id="676163">Limit of 10% of regulatory capital</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>A life company shall not, by way of specialized financing activities, acquire control of, or hold, acquire or increase a substantial investment in, an entity if the sum of the following exceeds 10% of the life company’s regulatory capital:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676164" lims:id="676164"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the aggregate balance sheet value of the shares and ownership interests that the life company and its subsidiaries, whether individually or jointly, would acquire in the entity,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676165" lims:id="676165"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the aggregate value of outstanding loans made by the life company and its subsidiaries, whether individually or jointly, to the specialized financing entities of the life company, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676166" lims:id="676166"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the aggregate balance sheet value of the shares and ownership interests held by the life company and its subsidiaries, whether individually or jointly, in the specialized financing entities of the life company, in the entities controlled by the life company by way of specialized financing activities, and in the entities in which the life company holds a substantial investment by way of specialized financing activities.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676168" lims:id="676168">SOR/2008-168, s. 16</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676169" lims:id="676169"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676170" lims:id="676170">Limit of 25% of regulatory capital — investment in a specialized financing entity</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676171" lims:id="676171"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A life company shall not, by way of specialized financing activities, acquire control of, or hold, acquire or increase a substantial investment in, an entity controlled by a specialized financing entity of the life company or an entity in which the specialized financing entity of the life company holds a substantial investment, if the sum of the following exceeds or would exceed 25% of the life company’s regulatory capital:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676172" lims:id="676172"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the aggregate balance sheet value of the shares and ownership interests held by the life company and its subsidiaries, whether individually or jointly, in the specialized financing entity of the life company, in the entities controlled by the specialized financing entity of the life company and in the entities in which that specialized financing entity holds a substantial investment, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676173" lims:id="676173"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the aggregate value of outstanding loans that the life company and its subsidiaries, whether individually or jointly, have made to the specialized financing entity of the life company, to the entities controlled by the specialized financing entity of the life company and to the entities in which that specialized financing entity holds a substantial investment.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676174" lims:id="676174"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676175" lims:id="676175">Limit of 25% of regulatory capital — investment in an entity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A life company shall not, by way of specialized financing activities, acquire control of, or hold, acquire or increase a substantial investment in, an entity, other than by way of an investment of a specialized financing entity controlled by the life company, if the sum of the following exceeds 25% of the life company’s regulatory capital:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676176" lims:id="676176"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the aggregate balance sheet value of the shares and ownership interests that the life company and its subsidiaries, whether individually or jointly, would acquire in the entity,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676177" lims:id="676177"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the aggregate balance sheet value of the shares and ownership interests held by the life company and its subsidiaries, whether individually or jointly, in the entities controlled by the life company by way of specialized financing activities and in the entities in which the life company holds a substantial investment by way of specialized financing activities, other than entities that the life company has acquired control of, or a substantial investment in, by way of an investment of a specialized financing entity of the life company, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676178" lims:id="676178"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the aggregate value of outstanding loans that the life company and its subsidiaries, whether individually or jointly, have made to the entities controlled by the life company by way of specialized financing activities and to the entities in which the life company holds a substantial investment by way of specialized financing activities, other than entities that the life company has acquired control of, or a substantial investment in, by way of an investment of a specialized financing entity of the life company.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676180" lims:id="676180">SOR/2008-168, s. 16</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676181" lims:id="676181" level="1"><TitleText>Acquisition of Specialized Financing Entities</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676182" lims:id="676182"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676183" lims:id="676183">Definition of <DefinedTermEn>non-controlling interest</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676184" lims:id="676184"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>non-controlling interest</DefinedTermEn> means an equity interest, in a specialized financing entity of the life company controlled by a specialized financing entity, that is held by a person other than the life company or an entity controlled by the life company.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676185" lims:id="676185"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676186" lims:id="676186">Ownership restrictions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A life company shall not acquire or hold control of, or hold, acquire or increase a substantial investment in, a specialized financing entity if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676187" lims:id="676187"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the value of the outstanding debt obligations, other than those payable to the life company or to entities controlled by the life company, of the specialized financing entity and any specialized financing entity of the life company controlled by the specialized financing entity, as reported on their respective balance sheets on an unconsolidated basis, exceeds twice the value of the sum of the following, namely,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676188" lims:id="676188"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the value of the excess of assets over liabilities of the specialized financing entity as reported on its balance sheet on an unconsolidated basis, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676189" lims:id="676189"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the value of the non-controlling interests as reported on the balance sheet of the specialized financing entity on a consolidated basis;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676190" lims:id="676190"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the specialized financing entity controls or holds shares of, or ownership interests in, any of the entities referred to in paragraphs 3(a) to (d);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676191" lims:id="676191"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the aggregate balance sheet value of the shares and ownership interests, other than shares or ownership interests held by the specialized financing entity in a specialized financing entity of the life company that it controls, that the life company, the specialized financing entity, the subsidiaries of the life company and the other specialized financing entities of the life company hold, or would hold, in an entity that the specialized financing entity holds control of, or a substantial investment in, is more than $250 million;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676192" lims:id="676192"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the sum of the values under paragraphs 6(a) to (c) exceeds or would exceed 10% of the life company’s regulatory capital; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676193" lims:id="676193"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the sum of the values under paragraphs 7(1)(a) and (b) exceeds or would exceed 25% of the life company’s regulatory capital.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676194" lims:id="676194"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676195" lims:id="676195">13 year limit</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A life company shall not hold control of, or a substantial investment in, a specialized financing entity of the life company if either the specialized financing entity of the life company or the specialized financing entity of the life company and one or more of the following entities, one after another, have held control of, or a substantial investment in, an entity, other than an entity described in subsection (4), for more than 13 consecutive years:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676196" lims:id="676196"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the life company; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676197" lims:id="676197"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other specialized financing entity of the life company.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676198" lims:id="676198"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676199" lims:id="676199">Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A specialized financing entity of the life company controlled by the specialized financing entity of the life company shall not be considered for the purpose of subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676200" lims:id="676200"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676201" lims:id="676201">Prior periods not included</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If a specialized financing entity of the life company held control of, or a substantial investment in, an entity for a period before becoming the specialized financing entity of the life company, that period shall not be considered for the purpose of subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-05-15" lims:fid="676203" lims:id="676203">SOR/2008-168, s. 16</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676204" lims:id="676204"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676205" lims:id="676205">Control not required</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Subsection 495(6) of the Act does not apply to a life company’s acquisition or increase of a substantial investment in an entity by way of specialized financing activities in accordance with these Regulations.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676206" lims:id="676206"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676207" lims:id="676207">Approvals not required</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>Subsections 495(7) and (8) of the Act do not apply to a life company’s acquisition of control of, or its acquisition or increase of a substantial investment in, an entity by way of specialized financing activities in accordance with these Regulations.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676208" lims:id="676208" level="1"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676209" lims:id="676209"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676210" lims:id="676210">Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>[Repeal]</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676211" lims:id="676211" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676212" lims:id="676212" type="transitional"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="676213" lims:id="676213">Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="fn_SOR-2001-429_e_hq_4587">*</FootnoteRef>12</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on the day on which sections 494, 501 and 1021 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Insurance Companies Act,</XRefExternal> as enacted by sections 426 and 465 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.1">Financial Consumer Agency of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 9 of the Statutes of Canada, 2001, come into force.</Text><Footnote id="fn_SOR-2001-429_e_hq_4587" placement="section" status="editorial"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Regulations in force October 24, 2001, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2001-102.]</Text></Footnote></Section></Body></Regulation>