<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2019-01-15" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-01-15" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939955" lims:id="939955" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939956" lims:id="939956"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/91-84</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1990</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>31</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939958" lims:id="939958"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-15">CANADIAN DAIRY COMMISSION ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939959" lims:id="939959">EEC Aged Cheddar Cheese Export Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939960" lims:id="939960">Regulations Respecting the Allotment of Export Entitlements for the Export of Canadian Aged Cheddar Cheese to the European Economic Community at a Special Customs Tariff</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1990-2866 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY> 1990</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939961" lims:id="939961"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939962" lims:id="939962" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Agriculture, pursuant to section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-15">Canadian Dairy Commission Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to revoke the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">EEC Aged Cheddar Cheese Export Quota Regulations</XRefExternal>, 1983, made by Order in Council P.C. 1982-3920 of December 23, 1982<FootnoteRef idref="fn_SOR-91-84_e_hq_6153">*</FootnoteRef>, and the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Aged Cheddar Cheese Export Quota Regulations</XRefExternal>, made by Order in Council P.C. 1981-1704 of June 25, 1981<FootnoteRef idref="fn_SOR-91-84_e_hq_6154">**</FootnoteRef>, and to make the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-91-84">Regulations respecting the allotment of export entitlements for the export of Canadian aged cheddar cheese to the European Economic Community at a special customs tariff</XRefExternal>, in substitution therefor, effective January 1, 1991.</Text><Footnote id="fn_SOR-91-84_e_hq_6153" placement="page" status="official"><Label>*</Label><Text>SOR/83-32, 1983 <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> Part II, p. 159</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_SOR-91-84_e_hq_6154" placement="page" status="official"><Label>**</Label><Text>SOR/81-494, 1981 <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> Part II, p. 1892</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939963" lims:id="939963"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939964" lims:id="939964" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939965" lims:id="939965"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-91-84">EEC Aged Cheddar Cheese Export Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939966" lims:id="939966" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-01-15" lims:fid="939967" lims:id="939967"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2019-01-15" lims:enacted-date="2018-05-30" lims:fid="939968" lims:id="1110183"><Text><DefinedTermEn>aged cheddar cheese</DefinedTermEn> means Canadian-produced cheddar cheese that is graded Canada 1 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2018-108">Safe Food for Canadians Regulations</XRefExternal> and aged for a period of not less than nine months; (<DefinedTermFr>fromage cheddar fort</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939969" lims:id="939969" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commission</DefinedTermEn> means the Canadian Dairy Commission; (<DefinedTermFr>Commission</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939970" lims:id="939970" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>EEC</DefinedTermEn> means the European Economic Community; (<DefinedTermFr>CEE</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939971" lims:id="939971" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible exporter</DefinedTermEn> means a person to whom an export entitlement is allotted by the Commission pursuant to these Regulations and includes a person referred to in section 3; (<DefinedTermFr>exportateur admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939972" lims:id="939972" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>export entitlement</DefinedTermEn> means the portion of the export quota that is allotted to a person by the Commission pursuant to these Regulations and includes the export entitlement retained by a person pursuant to section 3; (<DefinedTermFr>contingent individuel d’exportation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939973" lims:id="939973" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>export quota</DefinedTermEn> means the quantity of aged cheddar cheese that may be exported from Canada to the EEC in a year at the special customs tariff referred to in the arrangement between Canada and the EEC concerning cheese; (<DefinedTermFr>contingent global d’exportation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939974" lims:id="939974" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> means any individual, partnership, corporation or cooperative association. (<DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-01-15" lims:enacted-date="2018-05-30" lims:fid="1110185" lims:id="1110185">SOR/2018-108, s. 378</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939975" lims:id="939975" level="1"><TitleText>Export Entitlement</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939976" lims:id="939976"><Label>3</Label><Text>A person who was, as of December 31, 1990, an eligible exporter pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Aged Cheddar Cheese Export Quota Regulations</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">EEC Aged Cheddar Cheese Export Quota Regulations, 1983</XRefExternal> is hereby confirmed as an eligible exporter as of January 1, 1991, pursuant to these Regulations, and the person shall retain the same export entitlement as that person held on December 31, 1990.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939977" lims:id="939977"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subject to subsections 7(3) and 8(3), an eligible exporter shall retain, in respect of a year, the export entitlement that the eligible exporter held on December 31 of the previous year.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939978" lims:id="939978" level="1"><TitleText>Change in Export Quota</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939979" lims:id="939979"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where the export quota, in respect of a year, is increased or decreased from that of the previous year, the Commission shall, within a reasonable period of time,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939980" lims:id="939980"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of an increase,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939981" lims:id="939981"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>calculate the amount of the share of the increase available to be allotted to each eligible exporter, prorated on the basis of the portion of the eligible exporter’s export entitlement held on December 31 of the previous year that the eligible exporter utilized in that year,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939982" lims:id="939982"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>notify each eligible exporter, in writing, of the amount of the increase and the amount of the share, calculated in accordance with subparagraph (i), of the increase available to be allotted to each eligible exporter, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939983" lims:id="939983"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>increase, by the amount of the share calculated in accordance with subparagraph (i), the export entitlement of each eligible exporter who establishes, to the satisfaction of the Commission, that the eligible exporter is able to produce or obtain aged cheddar cheese and to export it to the EEC in sufficient quantity to fully utilize any increased export entitlement that may be held by that eligible exporter; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939984" lims:id="939984"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a decrease, reduce the export entitlement of each eligible exporter by an amount prorated on the basis of the eligible exporter’s export entitlement held on December 31 of the previous year.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939985" lims:id="939985" level="1"><TitleText>Annual Report</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939986" lims:id="939986"><Label>6</Label><Text>An eligible exporter shall, no later than June 30 of each year, send to the Commission a report that establishes, to the satisfaction of the Commission, that the eligible exporter has entered into agreements with one or more EEC importers for the export of aged cheddar cheese in a total quantity at least equal to the export entitlement held by that eligible exporter for the year.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939987" lims:id="939987" level="1"><TitleText>Non-utilization of Export Entitlement</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939988" lims:id="939988"><Label>7</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939989" lims:id="939989"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When an eligible exporter becomes aware that the eligible exporter will not fully utilize the export entitlement held by that eligible exporter in respect of a year, that eligible exporter shall so notify the Commission immediately.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939990" lims:id="939990"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the Commission believes, on the basis of a notification pursuant to subsection (1) or on any other basis, that an eligible exporter will not fully utilize the export entitlement held by the eligible exporter in respect of a year, the Commission shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939991" lims:id="939991"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>decrease the export entitlement held by that eligible exporter by an amount equal to the portion that the Commission believes will not be utilized;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939992" lims:id="939992"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>calculate the amount of the share of the non-utilized portion of that export entitlement available to be allotted to the remaining eligible exporters, prorated on the basis of the portion of their respective export entitlements held on December 31 of the previous year that they utilized in that year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939993" lims:id="939993"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>notify the remaining eligible exporters, in writing, of the amount of the non-utilized portion and of the amount of the share, calculated in accordance with paragraph (b), available to be allotted to each remaining eligible exporter; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939994" lims:id="939994"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>increase, by the amount of the share calculated in accordance with paragraph (b), the export entitlement of each remaining eligible exporter who establishes, to the satisfaction of the Commission, that the eligible exporter is able to produce or obtain aged cheddar cheese and to export it to the EEC in sufficient quantity to fully utilize any increased export entitlement that may be held by the eligible exporter.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939995" lims:id="939995"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the Commission has reduced the export entitlement of an eligible exporter in respect of a year pursuant to paragraph (2)(a) and the Commission is of the opinion that the eligible exporter was unable to fully utilize the eligible exporter’s export entitlement for reasons beyond the control of the eligible exporter, the Commission shall, in respect of the following year,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939996" lims:id="939996"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>increase the export entitlement held by that eligible exporter to an amount that is equal to the export entitlement held by that eligible exporter before the reduction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939997" lims:id="939997"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>reduce the export entitlement held by any eligible exporter whose export entitlement was increased pursuant to paragraph (2)(d) to an amount that is equal to the export entitlement held by that eligible exporter before that increase; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939998" lims:id="939998"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>withdraw any export entitlement that was allotted pursuant to subsections 9(3) to (5) as a result of the reduction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="939999" lims:id="939999" level="1"><TitleText>Cancellation of Export Entitlement</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940000" lims:id="940000"><Label>8</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940001" lims:id="940001"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commission shall cancel the export entitlement of any eligible exporter who</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940002" lims:id="940002"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>becomes a subsidiary of or related to, associated with or controlled by another eligible exporter;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940003" lims:id="940003"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>does not comply with section 6 or subsection 7(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940004" lims:id="940004"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>does not comply with section 10 or 11; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940005" lims:id="940005"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>does not comply with the terms and conditions of the export assistance paid, pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Exported Dairy Products Assistance Payment Order</XRefExternal>, to the eligible exporter for exports under the export entitlement held by the eligible exporter.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940006" lims:id="940006"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In a case referred to in subsection (1), the Commission shall, within a reasonable period of time,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940007" lims:id="940007"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>calculate the amount of the share of the cancelled export entitlement available to be allotted to the remaining eligible exporters, prorated on the basis of the portion of their respective export entitlements held on December 31 of the previous year that they utilized in that year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940008" lims:id="940008"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>notify the remaining eligible exporters, in writing, of the amount of the cancelled export entitlement and of the amount of the share, calculated in accordance with paragraph (a), available to be allotted to each remaining eligible exporter; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940009" lims:id="940009"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>increase, by the amount of the share calculated in accordance with paragraph (a), the export entitlement of each remaining eligible exporter who establishes, to the satisfaction of the Commission, that the eligible exporter is able to produce or obtain aged cheddar cheese and to export it to the EEC in sufficient quantity that the eligible exporter would fully utilize any increased export entitlement that may be held by the eligible exporter.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940010" lims:id="940010"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the Commission has, in a case referred to in paragraph (1)(b), cancelled the export entitlement held by an eligible exporter in respect of a year and the Commission is of the opinion that the eligible exporter did not comply with section 6 or subsection 7(1) for reasons beyond the control of the eligible exporter, the Commission shall, in respect of the following year,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940011" lims:id="940011"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>allot to that eligible exporter the same export entitlement as that eligible exporter held before the cancellation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940012" lims:id="940012"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>reduce the export entitlement held by any eligible exporter whose export entitlement was increased pursuant to paragraph (2)(c) to an amount that is equal to the export entitlement held by that eligible exporter before the increase; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940013" lims:id="940013"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>withdraw any export entitlement that was allotted pursuant to subsections 9(3) to (5) as a result of the cancellation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940014" lims:id="940014" level="1"><TitleText>Application for Export Entitlement</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940015" lims:id="940015"><Label>9</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940016" lims:id="940016"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where, after the process set out in subparagraph 5(a)(iii) or paragraph 7(2)(d) or 8(2)(c) has been completed, a portion of the export quota still remains available to be allotted, the Commission shall invite any person, other than an eligible exporter, to submit, within such period as the Commission determines, an application for export entitlement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940017" lims:id="940017"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the expiration of the period referred to in subsection (1), the Commission shall retain the application of any person who, in the opinion of the Commission,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940018" lims:id="940018"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is involved in the production or distribution, or both, of Canadian-produced cheese;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940019" lims:id="940019"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is able to produce or obtain aged cheddar cheese and to export it to the EEC in sufficient quantity to fully utilize any export entitlement that may be held by the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940020" lims:id="940020"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>has experience in the export of dairy products; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940021" lims:id="940021"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>is not a subsidiary of or related to, associated with or controlled by an eligible exporter.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940022" lims:id="940022"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where applications are retained pursuant to paragraph (2)(a), the Commission shall draw one application, by chance, from the applications retained and allot to the person whose application is drawn an export entitlement of an amount equal to the lesser of 20 000 kg and the portion of the export quota still available to be allotted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940023" lims:id="940023"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where a portion of the export quota remains available to be allotted after the process described in subsection (3) has been completed, the Commission shall allot the portion by repeating the process described in that subsection, drawing from the remaining applications, until no applications remain.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940024" lims:id="940024"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Where a portion of the export quota remains available to be allotted after the process described in subsection (4), the Commission shall allot the portion to eligible exporters, prorated on the basis of the portion of their respective export entitlements held on December 31 of the previous year that they utilized in that year.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940025" lims:id="940025" level="1"><TitleText>Transfer of Export Entitlement</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940026" lims:id="940026"><Label>10</Label><Text>No eligible exporter shall transfer, in whole or in part, the export entitlement held by the eligible exporter unless the Commission</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940027" lims:id="940027"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is of the opinion that the proposed transferee meets the criteria set out in paragraphs 9(2)(a) to (d); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940028" lims:id="940028"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>authorizes the transfer.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940029" lims:id="940029" level="1"><TitleText>Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="940030" lims:id="940030"><Label>11</Label><Text>No eligible exporter shall export aged cheddar cheese under the export entitlement held by the eligible exporter unless that eligible exporter has title to the aged cheddar cheese.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>