<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005131" lims:id="1005131" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005132" lims:id="1005132"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/97-192</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1997</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005134" lims:id="1005134"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-9.01">BROADCASTING ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005135" lims:id="1005135">Direction to the CRTC (Ineligibility of Non-Canadians)</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1997-486</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1997</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>8</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005136" lims:id="1005136"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005137" lims:id="1005137" language-align="yes" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 26(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-9.01">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnotea_e">a</FootnoteRef>, the Minister of Canadian Heritage has consulted with the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission with regard to the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Direction to the CRTC (Ineligibility of Non-Canadians)</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005138" lims:id="1005138" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Canadian Heritage, pursuant to subsection 26(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-9.01">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnotea_e">a</FootnoteRef>, hereby issues the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Direction to the CRTC (Ineligibility of Non-Canadians)</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="footnotea_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1991, c. 11</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005139" lims:id="1005139"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005140" lims:id="1005140" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005141" lims:id="1005141"><Label>1</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in this Direction.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005142" lims:id="1005142" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>acquiring corporation</DefinedTermEn> means a corporation referred to in paragraph 17(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-94-667">Canadian Telecommunications Common Carrier Ownership and Control Regulations</XRefExternal> as they read on October 25, 1994, registered as SOR/94-667. (<DefinedTermFr>acquéreur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005143" lims:id="1005143" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>affiliate corporation</DefinedTermEn> means, in relation to a qualified successor,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005144" lims:id="1005144"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Canadian carrier referred to in subsection 16(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-3.4">Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal> or any of its subsidiary corporations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005145" lims:id="1005145"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an acquiring corporation or any of its subsidiary corporations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005146" lims:id="1005146"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a corporation that controls the corporations referred to in paragraphs (a) and (b), or any of its subsidiary corporations. (<DefinedTermFr>société affiliée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005147" lims:id="1005147" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Canadian</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005148" lims:id="1005148"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a citizen within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-29">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> who is ordinarily resident in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005149" lims:id="1005149"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration Act</XRefExternal> who is ordinarily resident in Canada and has been ordinarily resident in Canada for not more than one year after the date on which that person first became eligible to apply for Canadian citizenship;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005150" lims:id="1005150"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a Canadian government, whether federal, provincial or local, or an agency thereof, subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-85-627">Direction to the CRTC (Ineligibility to Hold Broadcasting Licences)</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005151" lims:id="1005151"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a corporation without share capital where a majority of its directors are appointed or designated, either by their personal names or by their names of office, by one or more of the following, namely,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005152" lims:id="1005152"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a federal or provincial statute or any regulation made thereunder,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005153" lims:id="1005153"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Governor in Council or the lieutenant governor in council of a province, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005154" lims:id="1005154"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a minister of the Crown in right of Canada or a province;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005155" lims:id="1005155"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a qualified corporation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005156" lims:id="1005156"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a qualified mutual insurance company;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005157" lims:id="1005157"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a qualified pension fund society;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005158" lims:id="1005158"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a qualified cooperative; or</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005159" lims:id="1005159"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a qualified successor</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005160" lims:id="1005160"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for the purpose of holding a broadcasting distribution undertaking licence, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005161" lims:id="1005161"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for the purpose of beneficially owning, directly or indirectly, 50 per cent or less of all the issued and outstanding voting shares, and 50 per cent or less of the votes, of a qualified corporation that holds a broadcasting licence for a distribution undertaking only. (<DefinedTermFr>Canadien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005162" lims:id="1005162" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>control</DefinedTermEn> means control in any manner that results in control in fact, whether directly through the ownership of securities or indirectly through a trust, an agreement or arrangement, the ownership of a corporation or otherwise. (<DefinedTermFr>contrôle</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005163" lims:id="1005163" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>director</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is a member of the board of directors of a corporation or, where the corporation has no directors, a person performing functions that are similar to the functions performed by directors. (<DefinedTermFr>administrateur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005164" lims:id="1005164" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>independent member</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is not an officer or employee of, or a contractor who provides goods or services to, a qualified successor or any of its affiliate corporations, who is not a director of any affiliate corporations of the qualified successor, and in respect of whom there are no considerations that could reasonably be anticipated to interfere with the person’s ability to act in the best interests of the qualified successor. (<DefinedTermFr>membre indépendant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005165" lims:id="1005165" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>non-Canadian</DefinedTermEn> means a person or entity that is not a Canadian. (<DefinedTermFr>non-Canadien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005166" lims:id="1005166" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualified cooperative</DefinedTermEn> means a cooperative, not less than 80 per cent of the members of which are Canadians, that is established under an Act of Parliament or under any provincial legislation that relates to the establishment of cooperatives. (<DefinedTermFr>coopérative qualifiée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005167" lims:id="1005167" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualified corporation</DefinedTermEn> means a corporation incorporated or continued under the laws of Canada or a province, where</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005168" lims:id="1005168"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the chief executive officer or, where the corporation has no chief executive officer, the person performing functions that are similar to the functions performed by a chief executive officer, and not less than 80 per cent of the directors are Canadians;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005169" lims:id="1005169"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation having share capital, Canadians beneficially own and control, directly or indirectly, in the aggregate and otherwise than by way of security only, not less than 80 per cent of all the issued and outstanding voting shares of the corporation and not less than 80 per cent of the votes; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005170" lims:id="1005170"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation that is a subsidiary corporation,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005171" lims:id="1005171"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the parent corporation is incorporated or continued under the laws of Canada or a province,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005172" lims:id="1005172"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Canadians beneficially own and control, directly or indirectly, in the aggregate and otherwise than by way of security only, not less than 66 2/3 per cent of all of the issued and outstanding voting shares of the parent corporation and not less than 66 2/3 per cent of the votes, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005173" lims:id="1005173"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the parent corporation or its directors do not exercise control or influence over any programming decisions of the subsidiary corporation where</Text><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005174" lims:id="1005174"><Label>(A)</Label><Text>Canadians beneficially own and control, directly or indirectly, in the aggregate and otherwise than by way of security only, less than 80 per cent of the issued and outstanding voting shares of the parent corporation and less than 80 per cent of the votes,</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005175" lims:id="1005175"><Label>(B)</Label><Text>the chief executive officer of the parent corporation or, where the parent corporation has no chief executive officer, the person performing functions that are similar to the functions performed by a chief executive officer is a non-Canadian, or</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005176" lims:id="1005176"><Label>(C)</Label><Text>less than 80 per cent of the directors of the parent corporation are Canadian. (<DefinedTermFr>personne morale qualifiée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005177" lims:id="1005177" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualified mutual insurance company</DefinedTermEn> means a mutual insurance company, the head office and principal place of business of which are in Canada and not less than 80 per cent of the board of directors and of each committee of the directors of which are Canadians. (<DefinedTermFr>société mutuelle d’assurance qualifiée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005178" lims:id="1005178" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualified pension fund society</DefinedTermEn> means a pension fund society, not less than 80 per cent of the board of directors of which and of each committee of the directors of which are Canadians, and that is established under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to incorporate the Guarantee and Pension Fund Society of the Dominion Bank</XRefExternal>, S.C. 1887, c. 55, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to incorporate the Pension Fund Society of the Bank of Montreal</XRefExternal>, S.C. 1885, c. 13, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-8">Pension Fund Societies Act</XRefExternal>, R.S., 1985, c. P-8, or under any provincial legislation that relates to the establishment of pension fund societies. (<DefinedTermFr>société de caisse de retraite qualifiée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005179" lims:id="1005179" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>qualified successor</DefinedTermEn> means a corporation referred to in paragraph 17(2)(b) or (c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-94-667">Canadian Telecommunications Common Carrier Ownership and Control Regulations</XRefExternal> as they read on October 25, 1994, registered as SOR/94-667, incorporated or continued under the laws of Canada or a province and directly controlled by a Canadian carrier referred to in subsection 16(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-3.4">Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal>, or by its acquiring corporation, where</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005180" lims:id="1005180"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the control of the Canadian carrier and its acquiring corporation has remained unchanged since the date of the coming into force of this Direction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005181" lims:id="1005181"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the chief executive officer of the corporation or, where the corporation has no chief executive officer, the person performing functions that are similar to the functions performed by a chief executive officer, and all its directors are Canadians;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005182" lims:id="1005182"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>all the voting shares of the corporation that are not beneficially owned and controlled by the Canadian carrier or its acquiring corporation are beneficially owned and controlled by Canadians;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005183" lims:id="1005183"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation referred to in subparagraph (i)(ii) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>Canadian</DefinedTermEn>, all the voting shares of the qualified corporation that are not beneficially owned by the corporation are beneficially owned and controlled by Canadians;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005184" lims:id="1005184"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the corporation operates only in the operating territory of the Canadian carrier;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005185" lims:id="1005185"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the corporation does not beneficially own, directly or indirectly, voting shares of a corporation that holds a broadcasting distribution undertaking licence and that operates outside of the operating territory of the Canadian carrier;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005186" lims:id="1005186"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the directors of the corporation and its officers have complete and exclusive control over all programming decisions and</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005187" lims:id="1005187"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>at least 33 1/3 per cent of the directors are independent members, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005188" lims:id="1005188"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a quorum at any meeting of the directors or of any committee of the directors must include at least one independent member; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005189" lims:id="1005189"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>no parent corporation or affiliate corporation of the corporation exercises any control or influence over any programming decisions of the corporation. (<DefinedTermFr>ayant droit qualifié</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005190" lims:id="1005190" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>subsidiary corporation</DefinedTermEn> means a corporation that is controlled by another corporation. (<DefinedTermFr>filiale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005191" lims:id="1005191" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>voting share</DefinedTermEn> means a share of any class of shares of a corporation carrying voting rights under all circumstances or by reason of any event that has occurred and is continuing or by reason of a condition that has been fulfilled, and includes</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005192" lims:id="1005192"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a security that is convertible into such a share at the time a calculation of the percentage of shares owned and controlled by Canadians is made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005193" lims:id="1005193"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an option or a right to acquire such a share, or the security referred to in paragraph (a), that is exercisable at the time the calculation referred to in that paragraph is made. (<DefinedTermFr>action avec droit de vote</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005195" lims:id="1005195">SOR/98-378, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005196" lims:id="1005196" level="1"><TitleText>Direction</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005197" lims:id="1005197"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission is hereby directed that no broadcasting licence may be issued, and no amendments or renewals thereof may be granted, to an applicant that is a non-Canadian.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005198" lims:id="1005198"><Label>3</Label><Text>Where the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission determines that an applicant is controlled by a non-Canadian, whether on the basis of personal, financial, contractual or business relations or any other considerations relevant to determining control, other than the beneficial ownership and control of the voting shares of a qualified successor by a Canadian carrier or its acquiring corporation, the applicant is deemed to be a non-Canadian.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005199" lims:id="1005199" level="1"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005200" lims:id="1005200" type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Direction to the CRTC (Ineligibility of Non-Canadians)</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnote1_e">1</FootnoteRef> is repealed.</Text><Footnote id="footnote1_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>1</Label><Text>SOR/96-192</Text></Footnote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005201" lims:id="1005201" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1005202" lims:id="1005202" type="transitional"><Label>5</Label><Text>This Direction comes into force on April 8, 1997.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>