<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2012-12-19" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-12-19" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787754" lims:id="787754" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787755" lims:id="787755"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2012-267</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>7</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787757" lims:id="787757"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-1.01">BANK ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787758" lims:id="787758">Disclosure on Continuance Regulations (Federal Credit Unions)</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2012-1626</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787759" lims:id="787759"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787760" lims:id="787760" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, pursuant to subsection 35.1(3)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_a">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-1.01">Bank Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_b">b</FootnoteRef>, makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2012-267">Disclosure on Continuance Regulations (Federal Credit Unions)</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_a" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2010, c. 12, s. 1911</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_b" placement="page" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>S.C. 1991, c. 46</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787761" lims:id="787761"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787762" lims:id="787762" level="1"><TitleText>Notice and Disclosure</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787763" lims:id="787763"><Label>1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787764" lims:id="787764"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A local cooperative credit society that intends to make an application to the Minister for letters patent continuing it as a federal credit union (the “local cooperative credit society”) must send a notice approved by the Superintendent in consultation with the Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation to the last known mailing address of every member of the local cooperative credit society at least four weeks before the members vote on a special resolution authorizing that application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787765" lims:id="787765"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person applies to become a member of the local cooperative credit society after the notice has been sent to members in accordance with subsection (1) and before the day on which the members vote against the special resolution or the day that the Minister issues letters patent continuing the local cooperative credit society as a federal credit union, the local cooperative credit society must provide that person with the notice at the time they apply to become a member.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787766" lims:id="787766"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The notice must include the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787767" lims:id="787767"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the day on which provincial deposit insurance coverage for the local cooperative credit society would end;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787768" lims:id="787768"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a description of the Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation coverage that would apply during the transitional period to the deposits of the local cooperative credit society that is continued as a federal credit union; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787769" lims:id="787769"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a description of the Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation coverage that would apply after the transitional period to the deposits of the local cooperative credit society that is continued as a federal credit union and how it differs from the pre-continuance provincial deposit insurance coverage applicable to the local cooperative credit society.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787770" lims:id="787770"><Label>2</Label><Text>The local cooperative credit society must make the notice available by way of a hyperlink on its main page and on any other pages of its website that reference deposit products four weeks before its members vote on the special resolution until the day of a negative vote or the date of continuance.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787771" lims:id="787771"><Label>3</Label><Text>The local cooperative credit society must prominently display a sign that refers customers to the notice, and indicates how customers can obtain a copy of the notice, in each branch and office where customers are served four weeks before its members vote on the special resolution until the day of a negative vote or the date of continuance.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787772" lims:id="787772"><Label>4</Label><Text>The local cooperative credit society must publish the information contained in the notice once a week in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> for the four weeks before its members vote on the special resolution.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787773" lims:id="787773"><Label>5</Label><Text>The local cooperative credit society must publish the information contained in the notice once a week in a newspaper with general circulation in the province or territory in which the local cooperative credit society transacts business for the four weeks before its members vote on the special resolution.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-19" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-12-19" lims:fid="787774" lims:id="787774"><Label>6</Label><Text>The local cooperative credit society must make a copy of the notice available to any customer conducting deposit-taking business with staff at a branch of the local cooperative credit society during the period beginning four weeks before its members vote on the special resolution and ending on the day of a negative vote or on the date of continuance.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787775" lims:id="787775" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2012-12-07" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-12-07" lims:fid="787776" lims:id="787776"><Label><FootnoteRef idref="fn_Ind87D5_hq_13723">*</FootnoteRef>7</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on the day on which section 1911 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="J-0.7">Jobs and Economic Growth Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 12 of the Statutes of Canada, 2010, comes into force or, if later, on the day on which they are registered.</Text><Footnote id="fn_Ind87D5_hq_13723" placement="section" status="editorial"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Regulations in force December 19, 2012, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2012-99.]</Text></Footnote></Section></Body></Regulation>