<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2016-06-14" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-06-14" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024921" lims:id="1024921" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024922" lims:id="1024922"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/98-52</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1997</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><LastAmendedDate><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></LastAmendedDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024924" lims:id="1024924"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-52.6">CUSTOMS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024925" lims:id="1024925">Proof of Origin of Imported Goods Regulations</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1997-2024 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1997</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024926" lims:id="1024926"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024927" lims:id="1024927" language-align="yes" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the proposed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-52">Proof of Origin of Imported Goods Regulations</XRefExternal> give effect, in part, to a public announcement made on October 27, 1997 and are therefore, by virtue of paragraph 164(4)(a.2)<FootnoteRef idref="footnotea_e">a</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-52.6">Customs Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnoteb_e">b</FootnoteRef>, not required to be published under subsection 164(3) of that Act;</Text><Footnote id="footnotea_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1992, c. 28, s. 30(3)</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="footnoteb_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024928" lims:id="1024928" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no" language-align="yes"><Text>Therefore, His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of National Revenue and the Minister of Finance, pursuant to section 35.1<FootnoteRef idref="footnotec_e">c</FootnoteRef> and paragraph 164(1)(i)<FootnoteRef idref="footnoted_e">d</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-52.6">Customs Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef>b</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-52">Proof of Origin of Imported Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="footnotec_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>c</Label><Text>S.C. 1997, c. 14, s. 37</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="footnoted_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>d</Label><Text>S.C. 1992, c. 28, s. 30(1)</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024929" lims:id="1024929"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024930" lims:id="1024930" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024931" lims:id="1024931"><Label>1</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024932" lims:id="1024932" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-52.6">Customs Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024933" lims:id="1024933" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>alteration</DefinedTermEn> means a modification, other than a repair, that does not include an operation or process that either destroys the essential characteristics of a good or creates a new or commercially different good. (<DefinedTermFr>modification</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024934" lims:id="1024934" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>casual goods</DefinedTermEn> means goods imported into Canada, other than commercial goods. (<DefinedTermFr>marchandises occasionnelles</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024935" lims:id="1024935" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>commercial goods</DefinedTermEn> means goods imported into Canada for sale or for any industrial, occupational, commercial, institutional or other like use. (<DefinedTermFr>marchandises commerciales</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024936" lims:id="1024936" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>identical goods</DefinedTermEn> means goods that are the same in all respects, including physical characteristics, quality and reputation, except for minor differences in appearance that do not affect the determination of origin of those goods. (<DefinedTermFr>marchandises identiques</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024937" lims:id="1024937" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>minor processing</DefinedTermEn> means, with respect to a good, </Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024938" lims:id="1024938"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>mere dilution with water or any other substance that does not materially alter the characteristics of the good;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024939" lims:id="1024939"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cleaning, including removal of rust, grease, paint or any other coating;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024940" lims:id="1024940"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>applying any preservative or decorative coating, including any lubricant, protective encapsulation, preservative or decorative paint, or metallic coating;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024941" lims:id="1024941"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>trimming, filing or cutting off small amounts of excess material;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024942" lims:id="1024942"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>packing or repacking of the good for transport, storage or sale;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024943" lims:id="1024943"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>packaging or repackaging the good for retail sale or relabelling of the good in one or more official languages of a Party to CIFTA; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024944" lims:id="1024944"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>repairs or alterations, washing, laundering or sterilizing. (<DefinedTermFr>traitement mineur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024945" lims:id="1024945" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>repair</DefinedTermEn> means the adjustment of a machine, instrument, electrical device or other article, including replacing or refitting of parts to restore the article to its original operating condition. (<DefinedTermFr>réparation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024946" lims:id="1024946" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>series of importations</DefinedTermEn> means two or more importations of goods that are accounted for separately under section 32 of the Act, but that are covered by one commercial invoice issued by the vendor of the goods to the purchaser of the goods. (<DefinedTermFr>série d’importations</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024947" lims:id="1024947" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>textile and apparel goods</DefinedTermEn> means goods of any of the tariff item numbers set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2013-165">General Preferential Tariff and Least Developed Country Tariff Rules of Origin Regulations</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>textiles et vêtements</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024948" lims:id="1024948" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transaction value</DefinedTermEn> means the price actually paid or payable for the good or material with respect to the transaction between the producer of the good and the buyer of the good or the seller of the material, respectively, adjusted in accordance with paragraphs 1, 3 and 4 of Article 8 of the Customs Valuation Code as defined in section 1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-97-63">CIFTA Rules of Origin Regulations</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>valeur transactionnelle</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024949" lims:id="1024949" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>United States</DefinedTermEn> means </Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024950" lims:id="1024950"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the customs territory of the United States, the 50 states of the United States, the District of Columbia and Puerto Rico;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024951" lims:id="1024951"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the foreign trade zones located in the United States and Puerto Rico; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024952" lims:id="1024952"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any areas beyond the territorial seas of the United States within which, in accordance with international law and its domestic law, the United States may exercise rights with respect to the seabed and subsoil and their natural resources. (<DefinedTermFr>États-Unis</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024954" lims:id="1024954">SOR/2005-164, s. 1; SOR/2008-78, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024955" lims:id="1024955"><Label>2</Label><Text>Wherever in these Regulations a reference is made to a particular tariff or tariff treatment, that reference shall be construed to mean that tariff or tariff treatment in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024956" lims:id="1024956"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsections 4(2) to (5) and 5(2) and (3), any person or class of persons authorized to account for goods under regulations made pursuant to paragraph 32(6)(a) of the Act is authorized to furnish proof of origin of goods under subsection 35.1(1) of the Act in lieu of the importer or owner thereof.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024957" lims:id="1024957" level="1"><TitleText>Proof of Origin of Goods from Countries that Are Beneficiaries of the General Preferential Tariff, Commonwealth Caribbean Countries Tariff or Least Developed Country Tariff</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:lastAmendedDate="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024958" lims:id="1024958"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024959" lims:id="1024959"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, <DefinedTermEn>beneficiary country</DefinedTermEn> means a country the goods of which have been extended the benefit of the General Preferential Tariff, Commonwealth Caribbean Countries Tariff or Least Developed Country Tariff.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024960" lims:id="1024960"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) to (5), where the benefit of the General Preferential Tariff, Commonwealth Caribbean Countries Tariff or Least Developed Country Tariff is claimed for goods, the importer or owner of the goods shall, for the purposes of section 35.1 of the Act, furnish to an officer, as proof of origin, at the times set out in section 13, the prescribed form completed in English or French and signed by the exporter in the beneficiary country.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024961" lims:id="1024961"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The importer and owner of goods that originate in a beneficiary country, other than textile and apparel goods that originate in a country the goods of which have been extended the benefit of the Least Developed Country Tariff, are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act, if the importer or owner</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024962" lims:id="1024962"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>furnishes to an officer, at the times set out in section 13, an exporter’s statement of origin in the form set out in the schedule, completed in English or French and signed by the exporter in the beneficiary country; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024963" lims:id="1024963"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>declares to an officer in writing, at the time set out in paragraph 13(a), that it has in its possession</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024964" lims:id="1024964"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the completed and signed prescribed form referred to in subsection (2), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024965" lims:id="1024965"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an exporter’s statement of origin referred to in paragraph (a).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024966" lims:id="1024966"><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>The importer and owner of textile and apparel goods that originate in a country the goods of which have been extended the benefit of the Least Developed Country Tariff are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the importer or owner declares to an officer in writing, at the time set out in paragraph 13(a), that it has in its possession the completed and signed prescribed form referred to in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024967" lims:id="1024967"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The importer and owner of casual goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024968" lims:id="1024968"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>there is no evidence that the goods originate in a country other than a beneficiary country;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024969" lims:id="1024969"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the goods are imported in a traveller’s baggage or consigned from an individual in the beneficiary country to an individual in Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024970" lims:id="1024970"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the goods are declared at the time of importation as not intended for resale.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024971" lims:id="1024971"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Where the benefit of the General Preferential Tariff is claimed for commercial goods that originate in the People’s Republic of China and the goods are shipped from Hong Kong on a through bill of lading to a consignee in Canada, the importer and owner of those goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the importer or owner furnishes to an officer, at the times set out in section 13, a document that is completed in English or French and signed by the exporter in Hong Kong or the producer in the People’s Republic of China, and that indicates that at least 60 per cent of the ex-factory price of the goods is attributable to production in the People’s Republic of China.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2008-03-11" lims:fid="1024973" lims:id="1024973">SOR/2005-164, s. 2; SOR/2008-78, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024974" lims:id="1024974" level="1"><TitleText>Proof of Origin of Goods from Countries that Are Beneficiaries of the Most-Favoured-Nation Tariff, Australia Tariff or New Zealand Tariff</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024975" lims:id="1024975"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024976" lims:id="1024976"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, <DefinedTermEn>beneficiary country</DefinedTermEn> means a country the goods of which have been extended the benefit of the Most-Favoured-Nation Tariff, Australia Tariff or New Zealand Tariff.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024977" lims:id="1024977"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), where the benefit of the Most-Favoured-Nation Tariff, Australia Tariff or New Zealand Tariff is claimed for goods, the importer or owner of the goods shall, for the purposes of section 35.1 of the Act, furnish to an officer, as proof of origin, at the times set out in section 13, the prescribed form, completed in English or French by the vendor or the transferee in the country of export.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024978" lims:id="1024978"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the importer or owner furnishes to an officer, at the times set out in section 13,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024979" lims:id="1024979"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Canada Customs invoice, completed in English or French by the importer or owner that indicates that the goods originate in the applicable beneficiary country;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024980" lims:id="1024980"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where the Canada Customs invoice does not indicate that the goods originate in the applicable beneficiary country, a commercial invoice, completed in English or French by the vendor or the transferee in the country of export, that indicates that the goods originate in the applicable beneficiary country; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1024981" lims:id="1024981"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any other documentation, completed in English or French, that indicates that the goods originate in the applicable beneficiary country.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024982" lims:id="1024982" level="1"><TitleText>Proof of Origin of Goods that are Entitled to the Benefit of Preferential Tariff Treatment under NAFTA, CCFTA, CCRFTA, CPFTA, CCOFTA or CPAFTA</TitleText><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024984" lims:id="1024984">SOR/2004-186, s. 1; SOR/2013-218, ss. 2, 4; SOR/2016-147, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024985" lims:id="1024985"><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024986" lims:id="1024986"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) to (5), if the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under NAFTA, CCFTA, CCRFTA, CPFTA, CCOFTA or CPAFTA is claimed for goods, the importer or owner of the goods shall, at the times set out in section 13, furnish to an officer, as proof of origin for the purposes of section 35.1 of the Act, a Certificate of Origin for the goods that is completed in English, French or Spanish.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024987" lims:id="1024987"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the importer or owner furnishes to an officer, at the time set out in paragraph 13(a), a written and signed declaration, in English or French, certifying that the goods originate in a NAFTA country, Chile, Costa Rica, Peru, Colombia or Panama, as the case may be, and that a completed Certificate of Origin is in the importer’s possession.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024988" lims:id="1024988"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under NAFTA, CCFTA, CCRFTA, CPFTA, CCOFTA or CPAFTA is claimed for casual goods, the importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the goods are entitled to preferential tariff treatment under, as the case may be,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024989" lims:id="1024989"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>NAFTA, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-93-593">NAFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024990" lims:id="1024990"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>CCFTA, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-97-323">CCFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024991" lims:id="1024991"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>CCRFTA, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2002-396">CCRFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024992" lims:id="1024992"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>CPFTA, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2009-215">CPFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024993" lims:id="1024993"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>CCOFTA, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2011-132">CCOFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024994" lims:id="1024994"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>CPAFTA, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2013-51">CPAFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024995" lims:id="1024995"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under NAFTA is claimed for commercial goods whose estimated value for duty is less than $2,500 or if the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CCFTA, CCRFTA, CPFTA, CCOFTA or CPAFTA is claimed for commercial goods whose estimated value for duty is less than $1,600, the importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024996" lims:id="1024996"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the commercial goods do not form part of a series of importations that is undertaken or arranged for the purpose of avoiding the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024997" lims:id="1024997"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the importer or owner of the commercial goods furnishes to an officer, at the times set out in section 13,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024998" lims:id="1024998"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a commercial invoice for the goods, containing a written statement, in English or French, signed by the exporter or producer of the goods, certifying that the goods originate in a NAFTA country, Chile, Costa Rica, Peru, Colombia or Panama, as the case may be, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1024999" lims:id="1024999"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a statement, in English or French, written and signed by the exporter or producer of the goods, certifying that the goods originate in a NAFTA country, Chile, Costa Rica, Peru, Colombia or Panama, as the case may be.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1025000" lims:id="1025000"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under NAFTA is claimed for locomotives classified under heading No. 86.01 or 86.02 or railway freight cars classified under heading No. 86.06 of the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act with respect to those goods if they are transported overland from the United States into Canada.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1025002" lims:id="1025002">SOR/2004-186, s. 2; SOR/2013-218, ss. 3, 5; SOR/2014-238, s. 1; SOR/2016-147, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025003" lims:id="1025003"><Label>7</Label><Text>Where the Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 6(1) is completed in Spanish, the importer or owner of the goods shall, at the request of an officer, furnish to the officer a translation of the Certificate of Origin in English or French.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025004" lims:id="1025004"><Label>8</Label><Text>The Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 6(1) may apply in respect of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025005" lims:id="1025005"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a single importation of a good; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025006" lims:id="1025006"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two or more importations of identical goods, imported by the same importer, that occur within a period not exceeding 12 months, as set out in the Certificate of Origin by the person signing it.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025007" lims:id="1025007"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 6(1) may be accepted as proof of origin for four years after the date on which it was signed.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1025008" lims:id="1025008" level="1"><TitleText>Proof of Origin of Goods that Are Entitled to the Benefit of Preferential Tariff Treatment Under CJFTA</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025009" lims:id="1025009"><Label>9.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025010" lims:id="1025010"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) to (4), if the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CJFTA is claimed for goods, the importer or the owner of the goods shall, at the times set out in section 13, furnish to an officer, as proof of origin for the purposes of section 35.1 of the Act, a Certificate of Origin for the goods that is completed in English, French or Arabic.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025011" lims:id="1025011"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The importer and the owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the importer or the owner furnishes to an officer, at the time set out in paragraph 13(a), a written and signed declaration, in English or French, certifying that the goods originate in Jordan and that a completed Certificate of Origin is in the importer’s possession.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025012" lims:id="1025012"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CJFTA is claimed for casual goods, the importer and the owner of the casual goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the casual goods are entitled to preferential tariff treatment under CJFTA in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2012-180">CJFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025013" lims:id="1025013"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CJFTA is claimed for commercial goods that have an estimated value for duty of less than $1,600, the importer and the owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025014" lims:id="1025014"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the goods do not form part of a series of importations that is undertaken or arranged for the purpose of avoiding the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025015" lims:id="1025015"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the importer or the owner of the goods furnishes to an officer, at the times set out in section 13,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025016" lims:id="1025016"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a commercial invoice for the goods, containing a written and signed statement, in English or French, from the exporter or the producer of the goods, that certifies that the goods originate in Jordan, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025017" lims:id="1025017"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a written and signed statement, in English or French, from the exporter or the producer of the goods, certifying that the goods originate in Jordan.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025019" lims:id="1025019">SOR/2014-284, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025020" lims:id="1025020"><Label>9.2</Label><Text>If the Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 9.1(1) is completed in Arabic, the importer or owner of the goods shall, at the request of an officer, furnish to the officer a translation of the Certificate of Origin in English or French.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025022" lims:id="1025022">SOR/2014-284, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025023" lims:id="1025023"><Label>9.3</Label><Text>The Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 9.1(1) may apply in respect of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025024" lims:id="1025024"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a single importation of a good; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025025" lims:id="1025025"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two or more importations of identical goods, imported by the same importer, that occur within a period not exceeding 12 months, as set out in the Certificate of Origin by the person signing it.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025027" lims:id="1025027">SOR/2014-284, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025028" lims:id="1025028"><Label>9.4</Label><Text>The Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 9.1(1) may be accepted as proof of origin for four years after the date on which it is signed.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2014-11-28" lims:fid="1025030" lims:id="1025030">SOR/2014-284, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1025031" lims:id="1025031" level="1"><TitleText>Proof of Origin of Goods that Are Entitled to the Benefit of Preferential Tariff Treatment Under CIFTA</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025032" lims:id="1025032"><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025033" lims:id="1025033"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (1.1) to (4), where the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CIFTA is claimed for goods, the importer or owner of the goods shall, for the purposes of section 35.1 of the Act, furnish to an officer, as proof of origin, at the times set out in section 13, a Certificate of Origin for the goods, completed in English, French, Hebrew or Arabic.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025034" lims:id="1025034"><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Where goods, except for goods listed in any of Chapters 50 through 63 of the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, are shipped to Canada from Israel or another CIFTA beneficiary through the United States, a Declaration of Minor Processing, as prescribed by the Minister, completed in English or French and signed by the exporter in the United States, shall accompany the Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection (1) if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025035" lims:id="1025035"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the goods do not undergo further production in the United States other than minor processing; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025036" lims:id="1025036"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any processing that occurs in the United States does not increase the transaction value of the goods by greater than 10%.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025037" lims:id="1025037"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the importer or owner furnishes to an officer, at the time set out in paragraph 13(a), a written and signed declaration, in English or French, that certifies that the goods originate in Israel or another CIFTA beneficiary and that the completed Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection (1) and, if applicable, the completed Declaration of Minor Processing referred to in subsection (1.1) are in the importer’s possession.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025038" lims:id="1025038"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CIFTA is claimed for casual goods acquired in Israel or another CIFTA beneficiary, the importer and owner of the casual goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the casual goods are entitled to preferential tariff treatment under CIFTA pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-97-65">CIFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025039" lims:id="1025039"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CIFTA is claimed for commercial goods whose estimated value for duty does not exceed $1,600, the importer and owner of the commercial goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025040" lims:id="1025040"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the commercial goods do not form part of a series of importations that is undertaken or arranged for the purpose of avoiding the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025041" lims:id="1025041"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the importer or owner of the commercial goods furnishes to an officer, at the times set out in section 13,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025042" lims:id="1025042"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a commercial invoice for the commercial goods, containing a written and signed statement by the exporter, in English or French, that certifies that the commercial goods originate in Israel or another CIFTA beneficiary, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025043" lims:id="1025043"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a written and signed statement by the exporter, in English or French, that certifies that the commercial goods originate in Israel or another CIFTA beneficiary.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025045" lims:id="1025045">SOR/2005-164, s. 3</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025046" lims:id="1025046"><Label>11</Label><Text>Where the Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 10(1) is completed in Hebrew or Arabic, the importer or owner of the goods shall, at the request of an officer, furnish to the officer a translation of the Certificate of Origin in English or French.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025047" lims:id="1025047"><Label>12</Label><Text>The Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 10(1) may apply in respect of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025048" lims:id="1025048"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a single importation of a good; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025049" lims:id="1025049"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two or more importations of identical goods, imported by the same importer, that occur within a period not exceeding 12 months, as set out in the Certificate of Origin by the exporter who signed it.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1025050" lims:id="1025050" level="1"><TitleText>Proof of Origin of Goods that Are Entitled to the Benefit of Preferential Tariff Treatment Under CEFTA</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025051" lims:id="1025051"><Label>12.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025052" lims:id="1025052"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) to (4), if the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CEFTA is claimed for goods, the importer or owner of the goods shall, at the times set out in section 13, furnish to an officer, as proof of origin for the purposes of section 35.1 of the Act, a Certificate of Origin for the goods that is completed in English or French.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025053" lims:id="1025053"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if the importer or owner furnishes to an officer, at the time set out in paragraph 13(a), a written and signed declaration in English or French certifying that the goods originate in an EFTA state and that a completed Certificate of Origin is in the importer’s possession.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025054" lims:id="1025054"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CEFTA is claimed for casual goods, the importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act when the goods are entitled to preferential tariff treatment under CEFTA in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2009-199">CEFTA Rules of Origin for Casual Goods Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025055" lims:id="1025055"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the benefit of preferential tariff treatment under CEFTA is claimed for commercial goods whose estimated value for duty is less than $1,600, the importer and owner of the goods are exempt from the requirements of subsection 35.1(1) of the Act if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025056" lims:id="1025056"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the goods do not form a part of a series of importations that is undertaken or arranged for the purpose of avoiding those requirements; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025057" lims:id="1025057"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the importer or owner furnishes to an officer, at the times set out in section 13,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025058" lims:id="1025058"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a commercial invoice for the goods, containing a written statement, in English or French, signed by the exporter or producer of the goods certifying that the goods originate in an EFTA state, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025059" lims:id="1025059"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a written statement, in English or French, signed by the exporter or producer of the goods certifying that the goods originate in an EFTA state.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025061" lims:id="1025061">SOR/2013-218, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025062" lims:id="1025062"><Label>12.2</Label><Text>The Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 12.1(1) may apply in respect of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025063" lims:id="1025063"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a single importation of a good; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025064" lims:id="1025064"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two or more importations of identical goods that are imported by the same importer and that occur within a period not exceeding 12 months as set out the Certificate of Origin completed by the exporter.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025066" lims:id="1025066">SOR/2013-218, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025067" lims:id="1025067"><Label>12.3</Label><Text>The Certificate of Origin referred to in subsection 12.1(1) is acceptable as proof of origin for four years after the day on which it is completed.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2013-11-29" lims:fid="1025069" lims:id="1025069">SOR/2013-218, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1025070" lims:id="1025070" level="1"><TitleText>Time</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025071" lims:id="1025071"><Label>13</Label><Text>Proof of origin of goods accounted for under section 32 of the Act on or after January 1, 1998 shall be furnished at the following times:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025072" lims:id="1025072"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>at any time the goods are accounted for under subsection 32(1), (3) or (5) of the Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025073" lims:id="1025073"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>at the time an application for a refund in respect of origin of the goods is made under section 74 of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025074" lims:id="1025074"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>at any time when requested by an officer.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1025075" lims:id="1025075" level="1"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025076" lims:id="1025076" type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>[Repeal]</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-06-14" lims:fid="1025077" lims:id="1025077" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025078" lims:id="1025078" type="transitional"><Label>15</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on January 1, 1998.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025079" lims:id="1025079" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025080" lims:id="1025080"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsections 4(2) and (3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Exporter’s Statement of Origin</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025081" lims:id="1025081" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>I certify that the goods described in this invoice or in the attached invoice # <Leader leader="solid" length="5pc" /> were produced in the beneficiary country of <Leader leader="solid" length="5pc" /> and that at least <Leader leader="solid" length="2pc" /> per cent of the ex-factory price of the goods originates in the beneficiary country/countries of <Leader leader="solid" length="8pc" />.</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025082" lims:id="1025082" language-align="yes" justification="center" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="yes"><Text><FormBlank width="13pc"><Emphasis style="italic">Name and title</Emphasis></FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025083" lims:id="1025083" language-align="yes" justification="center" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="yes"><Text><FormBlank width="13pc"><Emphasis style="italic">Corporation name and address</Emphasis></FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025084" lims:id="1025084" language-align="yes" justification="center" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="yes"><Text><FormBlank width="13pc"><Emphasis style="italic">Telephone and fax numbers</Emphasis></FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1025085" lims:id="1025085" language-align="yes" justification="center" topmarginspacing="10" list-item="yes"><Text><FormBlank width="13pc"><Emphasis style="italic">Signature and date (day/month/year)</Emphasis></FormBlank></Text></Provision></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>