<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963739" lims:id="963739" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963740" lims:id="963740"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/94-300</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1994</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963742" lims:id="963742"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-7">TERRITORIAL LANDS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963743" lims:id="963743">Government Employees Land Acquisition Order, 1994, No. 1</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963744" lims:id="963744">Order Authorizing Certain Employees of the Government of Canada to Acquire Interests in Territorial Lands in the Northwest Territories</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1994-558 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY> 1994</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963745" lims:id="963745"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963746" lims:id="963746" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development, pursuant to paragraph 29(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-7">Territorial Lands Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to make the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-94-300">Order authorizing certain employees of the Government of Canada to acquire interests in territorial lands in the Northwest Territories</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963747" lims:id="963747"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963748" lims:id="963748" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963749" lims:id="963749"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Order may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-94-300">Government Employees Land Acquisition Order, 1994, No. 1</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963750" lims:id="963750" level="1"><TitleText>Authorization</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963751" lims:id="963751"><Label>2</Label><Text>The employees of the Government of Canada named in the schedule are hereby authorized to acquire interests in territorial lands in the Northwest Territories as described in the schedule.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963752" lims:id="963752" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963753" lims:id="963753"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><RegulationPiece lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963754" lims:id="963754"><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963755" lims:id="963755"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963756" lims:id="963756"><Label>1</Label><Text>Charles Roger Bourque, of the Town of Fort Smith in the Northwest Territories, Craftsman, an employee of the Department of the Environment, to lease for a trapper’s cabin the whole of a parcel of land situated on the northwesterly shore of Sparks Lake in Quad numbered 75 F/4 in the Northwest Territories, as said parcel is shown outlined in red on a sketch plan on file 33-1-12 in the Land Management Division of the Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development at Ottawa, saving and excepting therefrom and reserving thereout all mines and mineral, including hydrocarbons, whether solid, liquid or gaseous and the right to work the same.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="963757" lims:id="963757"><Label>2</Label><Text>John Kyneston Laycock, Senior Technical Officer, an employee of the Department of Public Works, and Gillian Joan Belsheim-Laycock, Peace Officer, a member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, both of the City of Yellowknife in the Northwest Territories, to acquire by assignment from the current lessee the whole of Lot numbered 1003 in Quad numbered 85 J/9 in the Northwest Territories, as said lot is shown on a plan of survey of record number 65951 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, a copy of which is filed in the Land Titles Office for the Northwest Territories Land Registration District at Yellowknife under number 1328, saving and excepting therefrom and reserving thereout all mines and minerals, including hydrocarbons, whether solid, liquid or gaseous and the right to work the same.</Text></Section></Body></RegulationPiece></Schedule></Regulation>