<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888011" lims:id="888011" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888012" lims:id="888012"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/85-900</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1985</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888014" lims:id="888014"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-52">CURRENCY ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888015" lims:id="888015">Currency Exchange for Customs Valuation Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888016" lims:id="888016">Regulations Respecting the Means of Determining the Equivalent Dollar Value of Currencies of Other Countries for the Purpose of Computing the Value for Duty for Customs Purposes</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1985-2752</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1985</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888017" lims:id="888017"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888018" lims:id="888018" language-align="yes" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, pursuant to section 13.2<FootnoteRef idref="footnote1_e">*</FootnoteRef> of the Currency Act<FootnoteRef idref="footnote2_e">**</FootnoteRef>, is pleased hereby to revoke the Currency Exchange for Customs Valuation Regulations, made by Order in Council P.C. 1978-181 of 26th January, 1978<FootnoteRef idref="footnote3_e">***</FootnoteRef> and to make the annexed Regulations respecting the means of determining the equivalent dollar value of currencies of other countries for the purpose of computing the value for duty for customs purposes, in substitution therefor.</Text><Footnote id="footnote1_e" placement="section" status="official"><Label>  *</Label><Text>S.C. 1984, c. 25, s. 100</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="footnote2_e" placement="section" status="official"><Label> **</Label><Text>S.C. 1984, c. 9, s. 2</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="footnote3_e" placement="section" status="official"><Label>***</Label><Text>SOR/78-86, 1978 <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> Part II, p. 498</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888019" lims:id="888019"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888020" lims:id="888020" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888021" lims:id="888021"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-85-900">Currency Exchange for Customs Valuation Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888022" lims:id="888022" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888023" lims:id="888023"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations, <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of National Revenue.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888024" lims:id="888024" level="1"><TitleText>Determination of Exchange Rate</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888025" lims:id="888025"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-52.6">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the rate of exchange used by the Minister for determining the value in Canadian dollars of a currency other than Canada shall be the rate prevailing on the date of direct shipment to Canada of the goods whose value in Canadian currency is to be determined.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888026" lims:id="888026"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-15">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal>, the rate of exchange used by the Minister for determining the value in Canadian dollars of a currency of a country other than Canada shall be the rate prevailing on the date of sale to a Canadian importer or the date of direct shipment to Canada, whichever date is applicable according to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-84-927">Special Import Measures Regulations</XRefExternal>, of the goods whose value in Canadian currency is to be determined.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888027" lims:id="888027"><Label>5</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 3 and 4, <DefinedTermEn>rate prevailing</DefinedTermEn> on a date means, in respect of a currency of any country other than Canada, the rate of exchange for that currency, as communicated to the ports of entry by the Minister for that date.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888028" lims:id="888028"><Label>6</Label><Text>Subject to sections 7 and 8, the rate of exchange for any currency to be communicated by the Minister to the ports of entry shall be established on the basis of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888029" lims:id="888029"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the latest rate of exchange for that currency quoted to the Minister by the Bank of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888030" lims:id="888030"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if no rate of exchange is quoted as described in paragraph (a), the latest rate of exchange for that currency quoted to the Minister by any Canadian chartered bank selected by the Minister; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888031" lims:id="888031"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if no rate of exchange is quoted as described in paragraph (a) or (b), the latest rate of exchange for that currency quoted by the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Financial Times</XRefExternal> of London, Great Britain.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888032" lims:id="888032"><Label>7</Label><Text>Where more than one rate of exchange for a currency is quoted as described in paragraph 6(a), (b) or (c), excluding any rate of exchange for that currency commonly known as a tourist rate, the rate of exchange for that currency shall be established on the basis of the average of the exchange rates so quoted, excluding any tourist rate, weighted by the percentage value in terms of Canadian currency of all the goods in the same category as the goods in question that, according to the records of Statistics Canada, were imported from the country of export during the latest six month period for which such records are available prior to the establishment of that rate of exchange.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="888033" lims:id="888033"><Label>8</Label><Text>Where no rate of exchange for a currency is quoted as described in paragraph 6(a), (b) or (c), the Minister shall establish a rate of exchange for that currency on the basis of the information available to him as to the value of that currency in Canadian currency.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>