<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-12-14" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-12-14" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727425" lims:id="727425" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727426" lims:id="727426"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2006-355</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2006</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727428" lims:id="727428"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-3.4">TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727429" lims:id="727429">Order Issuing a Direction to the CRTC on Implementing the Canadian Telecommunications Policy Objectives</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2006-1534</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2006</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727430" lims:id="727430"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727431" lims:id="727431" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 10(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-3.4">Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_SOR-2006-355_e_hq_1688">a</FootnoteRef>, the Minister of Industry had a copy of the proposed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2006-355">Order Issuing a Direction to the CRTC on Implementing the Canadian Telecommunications Policy Objectives</XRefExternal> published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>, Part I, on June 17, 2006, substantially in the annexed form, and a reasonable opportunity was thereby given to interested persons to make representations to the Minister with respect to the proposed Order;</Text><Footnote id="fn_SOR-2006-355_e_hq_1688" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1993, c. 38</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727432" lims:id="727432" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 10(1) of that Act, the Minister laid the proposed Order before each House of Parliament and forty sitting days of Parliament have elapsed since the proposed Order was tabled in both Houses;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727433" lims:id="727433" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to subsection 10(2) of that Act, the Minister consulted the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission with respect to the proposed Order before it was published and laid and consulted the Commission again with respect to the proposed Order in its definitive form;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727434" lims:id="727434" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas, pursuant to section 13 of that Act, the Minister, before making his recommendation to the Governor in Council for the purposes of this Order, notified the minister designated by the government of each province of his intention to make the recommendation and provided an opportunity for each of them to consult with the Minister;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727435" lims:id="727435" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Industry, pursuant to section 8 of the Telecommunications Act<FootnoteRef idref="fn_SOR-2006-355_e_hq_1691">a</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2006-355">Order Issuing a Direction to the CRTC on Implementing the Canadian Telecommunications Policy Objectives</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_SOR-2006-355_e_hq_1691" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1993, c. 38</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727436" lims:id="727436"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727437" lims:id="727437" level="1"><TitleText>Direction</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727438" lims:id="727438"><Label>1</Label><Text>In exercising its powers and performing its duties under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-3.4">Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal>, the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission (the “Commission”) shall implement the Canadian telecommunications policy objectives set out in section 7 of that Act, in accordance with the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727439" lims:id="727439"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Commission should</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727440" lims:id="727440"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>rely on market forces to the maximum extent feasible as the means of achieving the telecommunications policy objectives, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727441" lims:id="727441"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>when relying on regulation, use measures that are efficient and proportionate to their purpose and that interfere with the operation of competitive market forces to the minimum extent necessary to meet the policy objectives;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727442" lims:id="727442"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Commission, when relying on regulation, should use measures that satisfy the following criteria, namely, those that</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727443" lims:id="727443"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>specify the telecommunications policy objective that is advanced by those measures and demonstrate their compliance with this Order,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727444" lims:id="727444"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if they are of an economic nature, neither deter economically efficient competitive entry into the market nor promote economically inefficient entry,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727445" lims:id="727445"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>if they are not of an economic nature, to the greatest extent possible, are implemented in a symmetrical and competitively neutral manner, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727446" lims:id="727446"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>if they relate to network interconnection arrangements or regimes for access to networks, buildings, in-building wiring or support structures, ensure the technological and competitive neutrality of those arrangements or regimes, to the greatest extent possible, to enable competition from new technologies and not to artificially favour either Canadian carriers or resellers; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727447" lims:id="727447"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Commission, to enable it to act in a more efficient, informed and timely manner, should adopt the following practices, namely,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727448" lims:id="727448"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to use only tariff approval mechanisms that are as minimally intrusive and as minimally onerous as possible,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727449" lims:id="727449"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>with a view to increasing incentives for innovation and investment in and construction of competing telecommunications network facilities, to complete a review of its regulatory framework regarding mandated access to wholesale services, to determine the extent to which mandated access to wholesale services that are not essential services should be phased out and to determine the appropriate pricing of mandated services, which review should take into account the principles of technological and competitive neutrality, the potential for incumbents to exercise market power in the wholesale and retail markets for the service in the absence of mandated access to wholesale services, and the impediments faced by new and existing carriers seeking to develop competing network facilities,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727450" lims:id="727450"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to publish and maintain performance standards for its various processes, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727451" lims:id="727451"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>to continue to explore and implement new approaches for streamlining its processes.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727452" lims:id="727452" level="1"><TitleText>Effect of Order</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727453" lims:id="727453"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Order is binding on the Commission beginning on the day on which it comes into force and applies in respect of matters pending before the Commission on that day.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727454" lims:id="727454" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-12-14" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-12-14" lims:fid="727455" lims:id="727455"><Label>3</Label><Text>This Order comes into force on the day on which it is registered.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>