<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2015-01-15" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2015-01-15" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789658" lims:id="789658" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789659" lims:id="789659"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2012-36</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>7</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789661" lims:id="789661"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-1.6">AN ACT TO PROMOTE THE EFFICIENCY AND ADAPTABILITY OF THE CANADIAN ECONOMY BY REGULATING CERTAIN ACTIVITIES THAT DISCOURAGE RELIANCE ON ELECTRONIC MEANS OF CARRYING OUT COMMERCIAL ACTIVITIES, AND TO AMEND THE CANADIAN RADIO-TELEVISION AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS COMMISSION ACT, THE COMPETITION ACT, THE PERSONAL INFORMATION PROTECTION AND ELECTRONIC DOCUMENTS ACT AND THE TELECOMMUNICATIONS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789662" lims:id="789662">Electronic Commerce Protection Regulations (CRTC)</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789663" lims:id="789663"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789664" lims:id="789664" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission, pursuant to subsection 64(2) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-1.6">An Act to promote the efficiency and adaptability of the Canadian economy by regulating certain activities that discourage reliance on electronic means of carrying out commercial activities, and to amend the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission Act, the Competition Act, the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act and the Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-801.e_hq_10858">a</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2012-36">Electronic Commerce Protection Regulations (CRTC)</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-801.e_hq_10858" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2010, c. 23</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789665" lims:id="789665" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Gatineau, Quebec, March 5, 2012</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789666" lims:id="789666" language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="12" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="20pc"><SignatureName justification="right">JOHN TRAVERSY</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Secretary General</Emphasis></SignatureTitle><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Canadian Radio-television and</Emphasis></SignatureTitle><SignatureTitle justification="right"><Emphasis style="italic">Telecommunications Commission</Emphasis></SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789667" lims:id="789667"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789668" lims:id="789668" level="1"><TitleText>Definition</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789669" lims:id="789669"><Label>1</Label><Text>In these Regulations, <DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-1.6">An Act to promote the efficiency and adaptability of the Canadian economy by regulating certain activities that discourage reliance on electronic means of carrying out commercial activities, and to amend the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission Act, the Competition Act, the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act and the Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789670" lims:id="789670" level="1"><TitleText>Information to Be Included in Commercial Electronic Messages</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789671" lims:id="789671"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789672" lims:id="789672"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 6(2) of the Act, the following information must be set out in any commercial electronic message:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789673" lims:id="789673"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name by which the person sending the message carries on business, if different from their name, if not, the name of the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789674" lims:id="789674"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the message is sent on behalf of another person, the name by which the person on whose behalf the message is sent carries on business, if different from their name, if not, the name of the person on whose behalf the message is sent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789675" lims:id="789675"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the message is sent on behalf of another person, a statement indicating which person is sending the message and which person on whose behalf the message is sent; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789676" lims:id="789676"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the mailing address, and either a telephone number providing access to an agent or a voice messaging system, an email address or a web address of the person sending the message or, if different, the person on whose behalf the message is sent.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789677" lims:id="789677"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If it is not practicable to include the information referred to in subsection (1) and the unsubscribe mechanism referred to in paragraph 6(2)(c) of the Act in a commercial electronic message, that information may be posted on a page on the World Wide Web that is readily accessible by the person to whom the message is sent at no cost to them by means of a link that is clearly and prominently set out in the message.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789678" lims:id="789678" level="1"><TitleText>Form of Commercial Electronic Messages</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789679" lims:id="789679"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789680" lims:id="789680"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The information referred to in section 2 and the unsubscribe mechanism referred to in paragraph 6(2)(c) of the Act must be set out clearly and prominently.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789681" lims:id="789681"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The unsubscribe mechanism referred to in paragraph 6(2)(c) of the Act must be able to be readily performed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789682" lims:id="789682" level="1"><TitleText>Information to Be Included in a Request for Consent</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789683" lims:id="789683"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsections 10(1) and (3) of the Act, a request for consent may be obtained orally or in writing and must be sought separately for each act described in sections 6 to 8 of the Act and must include</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789684" lims:id="789684"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name by which the person seeking consent carries on business, if different from their name, if not, the name of the person seeking consent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789685" lims:id="789685"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the consent is sought on behalf of another person, the name by which the person on whose behalf consent is sought carries on business, if different from their name, if not, the name of the person on whose behalf consent is sought;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789686" lims:id="789686"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if consent is sought on behalf of another person, a statement indicating which person is seeking consent and which person on whose behalf consent is sought; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789687" lims:id="789687"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the mailing address, and either a telephone number providing access to an agent or a voice messaging system, an email address or a web address of the person seeking consent or, if different, the person on whose behalf consent is sought; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-07-01" lims:fid="789688" lims:id="789688"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a statement indicating that the person whose consent is sought can withdraw their consent.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789689" lims:id="789689" level="1"><TitleText>Specified Functions of Computer Programs</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2015-01-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2015-01-15" lims:fid="789690" lims:id="789690"><Label>5</Label><Text>A computer program’s material elements that perform one or more of the functions listed in subsection 10(5) of the Act must be brought to the attention of the person from whom consent is being sought separately from any other information provided in a request for consent and the person seeking consent must obtain an acknowledgement in writing from the person from whom consent is being sought that they understand and agree that the program performs the specified functions.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2012-03-07" lims:fid="789691" lims:id="789691" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-05-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-05-28" lims:fid="789692" lims:id="789692"><Label><FootnoteRef idref="fn_Ind263B_hq_12183">*</FootnoteRef>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-05-28" lims:fid="789693" lims:id="789693"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>These Regulations, except section 5, come into force on the day on which sections 6, 7 and 9 to 11 and subsection 64(2) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-1.6">An Act to promote the efficiency and adaptability of the Canadian economy by regulating certain activities that discourage reliance on electronic means of carrying out commercial activities, and to amend the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission Act, the Competition Act, the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act and the Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 23 of the Statutes of Canada, 2010, come into force, but if they are registered after that day, they come into force on the day on which they are registered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2014-05-28" lims:fid="789694" lims:id="789694"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 5 comes into force on the day on which section 8 of the Act, referred to in subsection (1), comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Footnote id="fn_Ind263B_hq_12183" placement="section" status="editorial"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Regulations, except section 5, in force July 1, 2014, section 5 in force January 15, 2015, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2013-127.]</Text></Footnote><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2014-05-28" lims:fid="789696" lims:id="789696">SOR/2014-130, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>