<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722428" lims:id="722428" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722429" lims:id="722429"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2005-73</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722431" lims:id="722431"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-6.7">CANADA MARINE ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722432" lims:id="722432">Natural and Man-made Harbour Navigation and Use Regulations</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2005-400</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722433" lims:id="722433"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722434" lims:id="722434" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, pursuant to subsection 104(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-6.7">Canada Marine Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnotea_e">a</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Natural and Man-made Harbour Navigation and Use Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="footnotea_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1998, c. 10</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722435" lims:id="722435"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722436" lims:id="722436" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722437" lims:id="722437"><Label>1</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722438" lims:id="722438" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-6.7">Canada Marine Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722439" lims:id="722439" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>dangerous goods</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-19.01">Transportation of Dangerous Goods Act, 1992</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>marchandises dangereuses</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722440" lims:id="722440" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>floating structure</DefinedTermEn> means any type of floathome, houseboat, ship, work or other type of floating craft that is used for residential or commercial purposes. (<DefinedTermFr>construction flottante</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722441" lims:id="722441" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>harbour</DefinedTermEn> means the navigable waters of a natural or man-made harbour that have been designated by the Governor in Council under subsection 104(2) of the Act. (<DefinedTermFr>port</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722442" lims:id="722442" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>harbour official</DefinedTermEn>, with respect to a harbour, means a traffic control official designated by the Minister under section 106 of the Act or an enforcement officer designated by the Minister under subsection 108(1) of the Act. (<DefinedTermFr>responsable de port</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722443" lims:id="722443" level="1"><TitleText>Binding on Her Majesty</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722444" lims:id="722444"><Label>2</Label><Text>These Regulations are binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722445" lims:id="722445" level="1"><TitleText>Safety of Persons and Ships in Harbours</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722446" lims:id="722446" level="2"><TitleText>Prohibitions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722447" lims:id="722447"><Label>3</Label><Text>Unless otherwise authorized under these Regulations, no person shall, by act or omission, adversely affect the use of a harbour, interfere with navigation in a harbour or jeopardize the safety of persons or ships in a harbour by doing anything or permitting anything to be done that has or is likely to have any of the following results in the harbour:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722448" lims:id="722448"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to obstruct or threaten any part of the harbour;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722449" lims:id="722449"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to interfere with an authorized activity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722450" lims:id="722450"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to divert the flow of a river or stream, cause or affect currents, cause silting or the accumulation of material or otherwise reduce the depth of the waters;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722451" lims:id="722451"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>to cause a nuisance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722452" lims:id="722452"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>to cause injury to persons or damage to ships; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722453" lims:id="722453"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>to adversely affect sediment or water quality.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722454" lims:id="722454" level="2"><TitleText>Removal from Waters</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722455" lims:id="722455"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722456" lims:id="722456"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Unless otherwise authorized under these Regulations, a person who, adversely affects the use of a harbour, interferes with navigation in a harbour or jeopardizes the safety of persons or ships in a harbour by dropping, depositing, discharging or spilling refuse, a substance that pollutes, cargo, ship’s gear or any other object must</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722457" lims:id="722457"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>immediately make every technically feasible and reasonable effort to remove it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722458" lims:id="722458"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>notify a harbour official of the incident without delay and provide a description of what was dropped, deposited, discharged or spilled and its approximate location, and of the efforts made by the person to remove it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722459" lims:id="722459"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>as soon as possible, provide to the harbour official a detailed written report containing the information mentioned in paragraph (b).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722460" lims:id="722460"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the person does not remove the refuse, polluting substance, cargo, ship’s gear or object immediately, the harbour official may have it done.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722461" lims:id="722461" level="2"><TitleText>Fire Protection</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722462" lims:id="722462"><Label>5</Label><Text>Every person in a harbour must follow the fire protection and prevention measures established for the safety of persons and ships in the harbour, taking into account the activities in the harbour.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722463" lims:id="722463" level="2"><TitleText>Dangerous Situations</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722464" lims:id="722464"><Label>6</Label><Text>Every person who, by act or omission, causes a dangerous situation in a harbour must immediately take appropriate precautionary measures to prevent injury to persons or damage to ships and notify a harbour official without delay as to the nature of the dangerous situation and the precautions that have been taken and their location.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722465" lims:id="722465" level="2"><TitleText>Emergencies</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722466" lims:id="722466"><Label>7</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of these Regulations, a person may, in a harbour, conduct an activity set out in column 1 of the schedule without having a contract or lease with, or a licence granted by, the Minister of National Defence or an authorization from a harbour official or without complying with the conditions of an authorization for the duration of an emergency situation if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722467" lims:id="722467"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the activity is required as a result of an emergency situation that jeopardizes the safety of persons or ships;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722468" lims:id="722468"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the person conducting the activity makes every effort to notify a harbour official of the activity and the emergency situation, if practicable; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722469" lims:id="722469"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the person conducting the activity submits a detailed written report to the harbour official without delay describing the activity and explaining why the situation was regarded as an emergency.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722470" lims:id="722470"><Label>8</Label><Text>If an activity in a harbour causes or is likely to cause an emergency situation that jeopardizes the safety of persons or ships, the person conducting the activity and, in the case of an activity conducted under a contract, lease, licence or authorization, the person authorized to conduct the activity must</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722471" lims:id="722471"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>notify a harbour official without delay of the emergency situation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722472" lims:id="722472"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>submit a detailed written report of the emergency situation to the harbour official as soon as possible after the situation ceases to exist; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722473" lims:id="722473"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>at the request of the harbour official, submit with the report to the harbour official a copy of each report of the emergency situation that the person makes to municipal, provincial and federal authorities.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722474" lims:id="722474" level="2"><TitleText>Accidents and Incidents</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722475" lims:id="722475"><Label>9</Label><Text>A person who does anything in a harbour that results in an incident involving injury to persons or damage to ships, including an explosion, fire, accident, grounding, or stranding must</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722476" lims:id="722476"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>notify a harbour official of the incident without delay; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722477" lims:id="722477"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>submit a detailed written report of the incident to the harbour official as soon as possible after the incident occurs.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722478" lims:id="722478" level="2"><TitleText>Precautionary Measures</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722479" lims:id="722479"><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722480" lims:id="722480"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in a harbour, a person conducts an activity, other than an activity set out in the schedule, that is likely to have any of the results prohibited under section 3, a harbour official may instruct the person conducting the activity to cease the activity or authorize the person to conduct the activity on condition that the person takes measures reasonably necessary to mitigate or prevent the result.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722481" lims:id="722481"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The person must immediately comply with the instructions of the harbour official.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722482" lims:id="722482" level="1"><TitleText>Authorizations and Instructions for Activities in a Harbour</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722483" lims:id="722483" level="2"><TitleText>Activities under Contracts, Leases and Licences</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722484" lims:id="722484"><Label>11</Label><Text>A person may, in a harbour, conduct an activity set out in column 1 of the schedule if authorized to do so in writing expressly or by necessary implication under a contract or lease entered into with, or a licence granted by, the Minister of National Defence.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722485" lims:id="722485"><Label>12</Label><Text>If, by entering into a contract or lease or granting a licence, the Minister of National Defence authorizes an activity set out in column 1 of the schedule that has or is likely to have any of the results prohibited under section 3, that Minister may stipulate as a condition of the contract, lease or licence that the person with whom the contract or lease is made or to whom the licence is granted must take measures reasonably necessary to mitigate or prevent the result.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722486" lims:id="722486" level="2"><TitleText>Authorizations by Posted Signs, Nautical Charts, Maps or Forms</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722487" lims:id="722487"><Label>13</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722488" lims:id="722488"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3), a harbour official may, by such means as posted signs, nautical charts, maps or forms, give an authorization under this section to conduct, in a harbour, an activity set out in column 1 of the schedule if an “X” is set out in column 2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722489" lims:id="722489"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the conduct of the activity is not likely to have a result prohibited under section 3, the harbour official may give the authorization without conditions to persons wanting to conduct the activity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722490" lims:id="722490"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the conduct of the activity is likely to have a result prohibited under section 3, the harbour official may give the authorization for the activity only if the harbour official</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722491" lims:id="722491"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>establishes conditions designed to mitigate or prevent the result; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722492" lims:id="722492"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>communicates the conditions by posting them in a prominent place clearly visible to persons wanting to conduct the activity or setting them out on forms that are readily available to persons wanting to conduct the activity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722493" lims:id="722493"><Label>14</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722494" lims:id="722494"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall conduct an activity set out in column 1 of the schedule if an “X” is set out in column 2, unless the person complies with the conditions, if any, for conducting the activity that are posted or set out on forms.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722495" lims:id="722495"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a condition for conducting the activity is to complete a checklist, the person conducting the activity must keep the checklist readily available for inspection.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722496" lims:id="722496" level="2"><TitleText>Authorization to a Person</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722497" lims:id="722497"><Label>15</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722498" lims:id="722498"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A harbour official may give an authorization under this section to a person to conduct, in a harbour, an activity set out in column 1 of the schedule if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722499" lims:id="722499"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an “X” is set out in column 3; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722500" lims:id="722500"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an “X” is set out in column 2 and the person or any person who would be covered by the authorization is unable to comply with the conditions posted or set out on forms under section 13 for the conduct of the activity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722501" lims:id="722501"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request for an authorization and the information required under subsection 16(2), the harbour official must</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722502" lims:id="722502"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>give their authorization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722503" lims:id="722503"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the results of the conduct of the activity are uncertain or if the conduct of the activity is likely to have any of the results prohibited under section 3,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722504" lims:id="722504"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>refuse to give their authorization, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722505" lims:id="722505"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>give their authorization subject to conditions designed to mitigate or prevent the results; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722506" lims:id="722506"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the harbour official required that the person obtain insurance coverage, performance security or damage security in respect of the conduct of the activity and none is obtained or that which is obtained is inadequate, refuse to give their authorization.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722507" lims:id="722507"><Label>16</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722508" lims:id="722508"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall, in a harbour, conduct an activity set out in column 1 of the schedule if an “X” is set out in column 3 unless the person</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722509" lims:id="722509"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>obtains an authorization under section 15 or is covered by an authorization given under that section; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722510" lims:id="722510"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>complies with the conditions, if any, of the authorization.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722511" lims:id="722511"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who seeks an authorization from a harbour official to conduct an activity in a harbour must provide to the harbour official</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722512" lims:id="722512"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name and address of the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722513" lims:id="722513"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>information relevant to the proposed activity and required by the harbour official to assess the likelihood of the occurrence of any of the results prohibited under section 3;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722514" lims:id="722514"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if required by the harbour official, proof that the person seeking the authorization has an insurance policy that provides adequate coverage for the activity, names Her Majesty in right of Canada as an additional insured and provides for the insurer to notify the harbour official in the event that the policy is amended or cancelled; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722515" lims:id="722515"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if required by the harbour official, performance security and damage security in respect of the conduct of the activity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722516" lims:id="722516"><Label>17</Label><Text>A harbour official may cancel an authorization given under section 15 or change the conditions to which an authorization is subject if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722517" lims:id="722517"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the conduct of the activity has a result prohibited under section 3 or, because of a change in circumstances, becomes likely to have such a result or the result of the activity becomes uncertain;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722518" lims:id="722518"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the authorization was based on incorrect or misleading information; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722519" lims:id="722519"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the person to whom the authorization is given or any person covered by the authorization does not comply with a condition of the authorization.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722520" lims:id="722520"><Label>18</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722521" lims:id="722521"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an authorization given under section 15 is cancelled, the harbour official must give notice of the cancellation to the person to whom the authorization was given.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722522" lims:id="722522"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The cancellation is effective at the earliest of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722523" lims:id="722523"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the end of the fifth business day after the notice of cancellation is sent by registered mail to the address provided in the application for the authorization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722524" lims:id="722524"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two hours after a facsimile or electronic transmission of the notice of cancellation is sent to the address provided in the application for the authorization; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722525" lims:id="722525"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>immediately on service of the notice of cancellation at the address provided in the application for the authorization.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722526" lims:id="722526" level="2"><TitleText>Instructions to Cease, Remove, Return and Restore</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722527" lims:id="722527"><Label>19</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722528" lims:id="722528"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A harbour official may instruct a person to take any of the actions referred to in subsection (2) if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722529" lims:id="722529"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person conducts an activity for which an authorization is required under section 15 without first obtaining the authorization or without being covered by one;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722530" lims:id="722530"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the person, or any person covered by the authorization, fails to comply with a condition of the authorization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722531" lims:id="722531"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the authorization to conduct the activity is cancelled under section 17; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722532" lims:id="722532"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case of an activity for which no authorization is required under these Regulations, the conduct of the activity has a result prohibited under section 3.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722533" lims:id="722533"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The actions are</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722534" lims:id="722534"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to cease the activity or comply with the conditions for conducting the activity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722535" lims:id="722535"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the person is instructed to cease the activity,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722536" lims:id="722536"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to remove anything brought into the harbour in connection with the activity,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722537" lims:id="722537"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to return to the harbour anything that was removed from it in connection with the activity, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722538" lims:id="722538"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to restore the property affected by the activity to its former state.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722539" lims:id="722539"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The person must comply immediately with the instructions of the harbour official.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722540" lims:id="722540"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the person fails to remove the thing or to restore the property immediately, the harbour official may conduct the removal or restoration and may store the thing.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722541" lims:id="722541" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722542" lims:id="722542"><Label>20</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on the day on which they are registered.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722543" lims:id="722543" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722544" lims:id="722544"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 7 and 11 to 16)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722545" lims:id="722545" pointsize="7" topmarginspacing="4" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><Caption lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722546" lims:id="722546" position="over">ACTIVITY LIST</Caption><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722547" lims:id="722547" frame="topbot"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722548" lims:id="722548" cols="4"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="12.52*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="37.12*" /><colspec colname="3" colwidth="26.47*" align="center" /><colspec colname="4" colwidth="23.92*" align="center" /><thead lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722549" lims:id="722549"><row rowsep="1" topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Column 1</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="left" valign="top">Column 2</entry><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" align="left">Column 3</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Item</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Activity</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Authorization by posted signs, nautical charts, maps or forms<Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(section 13)</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" align="left" valign="bottom">Authorization to a person<Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(section 15)</Text></Provision></entry></row></thead><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="722550" lims:id="722550"><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">1</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Conducting a diving operation</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">2</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Conducting a salvage operation</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">3</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Transporting, loading, unloading or transhipping explosives or other dangerous goods, industrial waste or pollutants</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">4</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Bunkering or fuelling</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">5</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Carrying out an oil transfer operation, a chemical transfer operation or a liquefied gas transfer operation</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">6</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Conducting a dredging operation</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">7</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Excavating or removing any material or substance</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">8</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Building, placing, rebuilding, repairing, altering, moving or removing any structure or work</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">9</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Placing or operating a light or day marker</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">10</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Casting adrift a ship, log or other object</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">11</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Conducting a race, regatta, trial, demonstration, organized event or similar activity</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">12</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Causing a fire or explosion, conducting blasting or setting off fireworks, including setting off a flare or other signalling device</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">13</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Placing a placard, bill, sign or device</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">X</entry><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">14</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Swimming</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">X</entry><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">15</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Venturing out onto ice</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">16</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Launching a ship by slipway or crane</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">X</entry><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">17</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Conducting the take-off or landing of a sea-plane</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">18</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Laying up a ship</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">19</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Placing, altering, removing or relocating an aid to navigation, buoy, mooring, float, picket, mark or sign</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">20</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Mooring or anchoring a floating structure</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">21</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Mooring log booms</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">X</entry><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom" /></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">22</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Fishing or crabbing</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="4"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">23</entry><entry rowheader="yes" colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">Conducting aquacultural research or operations</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top" /><entry colname="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom">X</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule></Regulation>