<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2020-06-25" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2020-06-25" lims:current-date="2025-07-24" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964007" lims:id="964007" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964008" lims:id="964008"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/94-42</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1994</YYYY><MM>1</MM><DD>13</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964010" lims:id="964010"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-10.4">CANADA TRANSPORTATION ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964011" lims:id="964011">Personnel Training for the Assistance of Persons with Disabilities Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964012" lims:id="964012">Regulations Respecting the Training of Personnel Employed in Transportation-Related Facilities or Premises or by Carriers, to Assist Persons with Disabilities Travelling Within the Transportation Network</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1994-21 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY> 1994</YYYY><MM>1</MM><DD>13</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964013" lims:id="964013"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964014" lims:id="964014" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, pursuant to paragraph 63.1(1)(b)<FootnoteRef idref="fn_SOR-94-42_e_hq_5253">*</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Transportation Act, 1987</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_SOR-94-42_e_hq_5254">**</FootnoteRef>, is pleased hereby to approve the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Regulations respecting the training of personnel employed in transportation-related facilities or premises or by carriers, to assist persons with disabilities travelling within the transportation network</XRefExternal>, made by the National Transportation Agency on October 28, 1993, effective on the first anniversary of the date of their publication in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> Part II.</Text><Footnote id="fn_SOR-94-42_e_hq_5253" placement="page" status="official"><Label>*</Label><Text>R.S., c. 19 (4th Supp.), s. 2</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_SOR-94-42_e_hq_5254" placement="page" status="official"><Label>**</Label><Text>R.S., c. 28 (3rd Supp.)</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964015" lims:id="964015"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964016" lims:id="964016" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964017" lims:id="964017"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-94-42">Personnel Training for the Assistance of Persons with Disabilities Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964018" lims:id="964018" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964019" lims:id="964019"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964020" lims:id="964020" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-10.4">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964021" lims:id="964021" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>attendant</DefinedTermEn> means a person who travels with a person with a disability to provide a service related to a disability that is not usually provided by a carrier; (<DefinedTermFr>accompagnateur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964022" lims:id="964022" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>carrier</DefinedTermEn> means a Canadian citizen or a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration Act</XRefExternal>, a government in Canada or an agent thereof, or any other person or entity that is controlled in fact by Canadians and, where applicable, of which at least 75 per cent of the voting interests are held and controlled by Canadians, that operates a passenger transportation service within or from Canada; (<DefinedTermFr>transporteur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964023" lims:id="964023" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>commuter rail service</DefinedTermEn> means a passenger-train service that accommodates principally persons who commute between points on the railway of the company that provides the service; (<DefinedTermFr>service ferroviaire de banlieue</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964024" lims:id="964024" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>contractor</DefinedTermEn> means any person, or employee of that person, who performs services pursuant to a contract or an arrangement with a carrier or a terminal operator, and who is not an employee of the carrier or the terminal operator, but does not include a travel agency; (<DefinedTermFr>entrepreneur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964025" lims:id="964025" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>disability</DefinedTermEn> means a physical, sensory, developmental, mental health or medical functional limitation or restriction that affects a person in such a manner that the person is a person with a disability; (<DefinedTermFr>déficience</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964026" lims:id="964026" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>lodge operation</DefinedTermEn> means an operation that involves a commercial air service of a small aeroplane, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Air Carriers Using Small Aeroplanes Order</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>hôtel pavillonnaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964027" lims:id="964027" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>mobility aid</DefinedTermEn> includes wheelchairs, scooters, transfer chairs, walkers, canes, crutches and braces; (<DefinedTermFr>aide à la mobilité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964028" lims:id="964028" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>person with a disability</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is, has been or will be a passenger on a service operated by a carrier and who, because of a disability, requires services that are not usually extended to other passengers, including assistance</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964029" lims:id="964029"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>when making travel arrangements,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964030" lims:id="964030"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>when embarking and disembarking,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964031" lims:id="964031"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>on board a vehicle, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964032" lims:id="964032"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>during any movements between facilities inside or outside the terminal buildings that involve transportation-related services; (<DefinedTermFr>personne ayant une déficience</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964033" lims:id="964033" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>service animal</DefinedTermEn> means an animal that is required by a person with a disability for assistance and is certified, in writing, as having been trained to assist a person with a disability by a professional service animal institution; (<DefinedTermFr>animal aidant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964034" lims:id="964034" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>terminal operator</DefinedTermEn> means the owner, operator or lessee of facilities or premises related to the transport of passengers within the transportation network governed by the Act; (<DefinedTermFr>exploitant de terminal</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964035" lims:id="964035" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transportation-related services</DefinedTermEn> includes passenger security screening, baggage handling, vehicle rental, public parking and, in the case of air terminals, all ground transportation from the terminal. (<DefinedTermFr>services liés au transport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964037" lims:id="964037">SOR/94-700, s. 3; SOR/98-197, s. 13</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964038" lims:id="964038" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964039" lims:id="964039"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964040" lims:id="964040"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to every carrier except</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964041" lims:id="964041"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an air carrier</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964042" lims:id="964042"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that provides service only to air terminals where there were less than 10,000 enplaned and deplaned passengers in each of the two preceding calendar years,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964043" lims:id="964043"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>whose gross annual revenue was less than $500,000 in either of the two preceding calendar years, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964044" lims:id="964044"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>whose operations are limited to serving the needs of a lodge operation;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964045" lims:id="964045"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a rail carrier in respect of commuter rail services provided by that carrier; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964046" lims:id="964046"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a carrier that operates an extra-provincial bus undertaking.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964047" lims:id="964047"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to every terminal operator except</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964048" lims:id="964048"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an air terminal operator at whose terminal there were less than 10,000 enplaned and deplaned passengers in each of the two preceding calendar years; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964049" lims:id="964049"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an extra-provincial bus terminal operator.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964051" lims:id="964051">SOR/98-197, s. 14</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:lastAmendedDate="2020-06-25" lims:fid="1251549" lims:id="1251549"><Label>3.1</Label><Text>Despite section 3, these Regulations do not apply to any carrier or terminal operator that is subject to Part 1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2019-244">Accessible Transportation for Persons with Disabilities Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1251551" lims:id="1251551" lims:enactId="1177251">SOR/2019-244, s. 242</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964052" lims:id="964052" level="1"><TitleText>Employees and Contractors Who Interact with the Public</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964053" lims:id="964053"><Label>4</Label><Text>Every carrier and terminal operator shall ensure that, consistent with its type of operation, all employees and contractors of the carrier or terminal operator who provide transportation-related services and who may be required to interact with the public or to make decisions in respect of the carriage of persons with disabilities receive a level of training appropriate to the requirements of their function in the following areas:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964054" lims:id="964054"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the policies and procedures of the carrier or terminal operator with respect to persons with disabilities, including relevant regulatory requirements;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964055" lims:id="964055"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the needs of those persons with disabilities most likely to require additional services, recognition of those needs, and the responsibilities of the carrier or terminal operator in relation to those persons, including the level of assistance, methods of communication and aids or devices generally required by persons with disabilities; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964056" lims:id="964056"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the necessary skills for providing assistance to persons with disabilities, including the role of the attendant, and the needs of persons with disabilities travelling with a service animal, including the role and the needs of that animal.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964057" lims:id="964057" level="1"><TitleText>Employees and Contractors Who Provide Physical Assistance</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964058" lims:id="964058"><Label>5</Label><Text>Every carrier shall ensure that, consistent with its type of operation, all employees and contractors of the carrier who may be required to provide physical assistance to a person with a disability receive the training described in section 4 and a level of training appropriate to the requirements of their function in the following areas:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964059" lims:id="964059"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>assisting with mobility aids through doors and on irregular and multi-level surfaces, steps, curbs and elevators;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964060" lims:id="964060"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>transferring a person with a disability between the person’s own mobility aid and a mobility aid provided by a carrier and between a mobility aid and the person’s passenger seat, including</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964061" lims:id="964061"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>seeking information from a person with a disability with respect to the person’s preferred method of transfer and information with respect to any other special measures required to ensure the safety and comfort of the person with a disability, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964062" lims:id="964062"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>performing appropriate lifting techniques to</Text><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964063" lims:id="964063"><Label>(A)</Label><Text>execute various types of transfer with maximum consideration for the dignity, safety and comfort of the person with a disability, and</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964064" lims:id="964064"><Label>(B)</Label><Text>avoid injury to the employee or contractor making the transfer;</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964065" lims:id="964065"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>guiding and orienting a person who is blind or whose visual impairment affects that person’s mobility; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964066" lims:id="964066"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>assisting a person who has limitations in balance, agility or coordination that affect that person’s mobility.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964067" lims:id="964067" level="1"><TitleText>Employees and Contractors Who Handle Mobility Aids</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964068" lims:id="964068"><Label>6</Label><Text>Every carrier shall ensure that, consistent with its type of operation, all employees and contractors of the carrier who may be required to handle mobility aids receive the training described in section 4 and a level of training appropriate to the requirements of their function in the following areas:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964069" lims:id="964069"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>different types of mobility aids;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964070" lims:id="964070"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>requirements, limitations and procedures for securing, carrying and stowing mobility aids in the passenger compartment of a vehicle; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964071" lims:id="964071"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>proper methods of carrying and stowing mobility aids in the baggage compartment of a vehicle, including the disassembling, packaging, unpackaging and assembling of the mobility aids.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964072" lims:id="964072" level="1"><TitleText>Employees and Contractors Who Assist with Special Equipment or Aids</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964073" lims:id="964073"><Label>7</Label><Text>Every carrier shall ensure that, consistent with its type of operation, all employees and contractors of the carrier who may be required to assist with special equipment or aids receive the training described in section 4 and a level of training appropriate to the requirements of their function in the following areas:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964074" lims:id="964074"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>telephone devices for persons who are deaf or hard of hearing, electronic signage, and audio or video equipment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964075" lims:id="964075"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>mechanical lifts, ramps and other level-change devices; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964076" lims:id="964076"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>on-board oxygen, on-board electrical supply, connection of auxiliary respirator systems and installation of stretchers.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964077" lims:id="964077" level="1"><TitleText>Time Limit for Completion of Training</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964078" lims:id="964078"><Label>8</Label><Text>Every carrier and terminal operator shall ensure that all employees and contractors of the carrier or terminal operator who are required by these Regulations to receive training complete their initial training within 60 days after the commencement of their duties.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964079" lims:id="964079"><Label>9</Label><Text>Every carrier and terminal operator shall ensure that all employees and contractors of the carrier or terminal operator receive periodic refresher training sessions appropriate to the requirements of their function.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964080" lims:id="964080"><Label>10</Label><Text>Every carrier and terminal operator shall keep its training program current by incorporating, at the earliest opportunity, any new information on procedures and services offered or any specific technologies introduced by the carrier or terminal operator to assist persons with disabilities.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964081" lims:id="964081" level="1"><TitleText>Training Program Description</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964082" lims:id="964082"><Label>11</Label><Text>Every carrier and terminal operator shall keep available for inspection by the Agency and the general public a copy of its current training program prepared in the form set out in the schedule and containing the information required therein.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964083" lims:id="964083" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964084" lims:id="964084"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 11)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Description of Training Program</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964085" lims:id="964085" language-align="yes" justification="center" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Corporate name, address and nature of business of carrier or terminal operator</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964086" lims:id="964086" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Date:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964087" lims:id="964087" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Name and title of person responsible for managing the training program within the organization.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964088" lims:id="964088" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Target group of the training program (specify):</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964089" lims:id="964089" format-ref="indent-3-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>employees and contractors who interact with the public;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964090" lims:id="964090" format-ref="indent-3-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>employees and contractors who provide physical assistance;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964091" lims:id="964091" format-ref="indent-3-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>employees and contractors who handle mobility aids;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964092" lims:id="964092" format-ref="indent-3-3" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>employees and contractors who assist with special equipment or aids.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964093" lims:id="964093" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>List of the occupational categories of the organization’s employees and contractors required to receive training.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964094" lims:id="964094" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subject matter covered in the training program.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964095" lims:id="964095" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>Principal teaching methods and types of educational and support materials used in the training program.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964096" lims:id="964096" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>6</Label><Text>Number of hours of training provided in the initial training program.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964097" lims:id="964097" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>7</Label><Text>Average period between the beginning of employment and the initial training.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964098" lims:id="964098" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>8</Label><Text>Frequency, nature and number of hours of refresher training sessions required.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964099" lims:id="964099" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>9</Label><Text>Qualifications and title of the person who provides the initial training and refresher training sessions.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964100" lims:id="964100" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>10</Label><Text>Where a person with a disability is involved in the training program, the nature of the involvement.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964101" lims:id="964101" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>11</Label><Text>Means used by the organization to ensure that employees receive a level of training appropriate to the requirements of their function.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964102" lims:id="964102" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>12</Label><Text>The recording and monitoring of the completion of the initial training and each refresher training session.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="964103" lims:id="964103" language-align="yes" first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="3" list-item="yes"><Label>13</Label><Text>Where the organization uses contractors, the means used to ensure that the contractors receive a level of training appropriate to the requirements of their function.</Text></Provision><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="20pc"><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="15pt"><Leader leader="solid" length="20pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureTitle justification="left" topmarginspacing="0">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature, name and title of authorized officer or agent</Emphasis>)</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Schedule><RecentAmendments><Amendment><AmendmentCitation>SOR/2019-244</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2020-06-25</AmendmentDate></Amendment></RecentAmendments></Regulation>