<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859890" lims:id="859890" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859891" lims:id="859891"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/56-290</InstrumentNumber><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859893" lims:id="859893"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-44.6">CORRECTIONS AND CONDITIONAL RELEASE ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859894" lims:id="859894">Saskatchewan Penitentiary proclaimed a penitentiary for Alberta and Saskatchewan</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859895" lims:id="859895">Saskatchewan Penitentiary proclaimed a penitentiary for Alberta and Saskatchewan</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859896" lims:id="859896"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859897" lims:id="859897" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName>GÉRALD FAUTEUX,</SignatureName><SignatureTitle><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Governor General</Emphasis>.</SignatureTitle><SignatureTitle>[L.S.]</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859898" lims:id="859898" format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>CANADA</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859899" lims:id="859899" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>ELIZABETH THE SECOND, by the Grace of God of the United Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories QUEEN, Head of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859900" lims:id="859900" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">To All To Whom</Emphasis> these Presents shall come or whom the same may in anywise concern, — <Emphasis style="smallcaps">Greeting</Emphasis>:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859901" lims:id="859901" format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>A PROCLAMATION</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859902" lims:id="859902" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><SignatureBlock justification="left" width="15pc"><SignatureName>F. P. VARCOE,</SignatureName><SignatureTitle><Emphasis style="italic">Deputy Attorney General</Emphasis>,</SignatureTitle><SignatureTitle>Canada.</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859903" lims:id="859903" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Whereas</Emphasis> in and by section twenty-two of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Penitentiary Act</XRefExternal>, Chapter 206 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1952, it is among other things enacted that Our Governor in Council may declare from time to time by proclamation that any tract of land within Canada of which the boundaries shall be described in such proclamation is a penitentiary and is to be so held within the meaning of the said Act, and by such proclamation may declare for what part of Canada the same shall be a penitentiary.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859904" lims:id="859904" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">And Whereas</Emphasis> Our Governor in Council by Order bearing date the nineteenth day of July, in the year of Our Lord one thousand nine hundred and fifty-six, has directed that a Proclamation do issue declaring the following lands to be a penitentiary, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Penitentiary Act</XRefExternal>, for the Provinces of Alberta and Saskatchewan, namely:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859905" lims:id="859905" format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Description of Saskatchewan Penitentiary Reserve</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859906" lims:id="859906" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Firstly</Emphasis>:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859907" lims:id="859907" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>All those five parcels of land in the Province of Saskatchewan shown lettered severally A, C, D, E, and F, on a plan of subdivision of River Lots numbers 52 to 60 inclusive, and part of River Lot number 61, Prince Albert Settlement Registered plan No. A.W. 1216 and fractional southeast quarter of section 7, township 48, range 26, west of the Second Meridian, signed by William Christie, Saskatchewan Land Surveyor, on the 24th day of October, A.D. 1937, and registered in the Land Titles Office at Prince Albert under number B.Q. 2506; and all that portion of the government road allowance between Prince Albert Settlement and fractional section 7 in the said township, lying outside the right of way of the Canadian National Railway, the said parcels and portion of road allowance containing together an area of one thousand seven hundred and eighty-four acres and seventy-one hundredths of an acre, more or less, and being more particularly described as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859908" lims:id="859908" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Parcel A</Emphasis> bounded on the north by North Saskatchewan river; on the west by the easterly limit of a government road allowance along the east boundary of river lot 51 of Prince Albert Settlement; on the south by the north limit of a government road leading westward from the City of Prince Albert and on the east by the westerly limit of Twentieth Avenue West of the said city of Prince Albert, comprising an area of two hundred and sixty acres and nine-tenths of an acre, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859909" lims:id="859909" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Parcel C</Emphasis> bounded on the west by the easterly limit of a government road allowance along the east boundary of the said river lot 51 and along the east boundary of the southeast quarter of section 12, township 49, range 27, west of the Second Meridian; on the south by the northerly limit of the government road allowance between Prince Albert Settlement and fractional section 7, township 48, range 26, west Second Meridian; on the east by the westerly limit of the right of way of the Canadian National Railway shown on Parcel H on the aforementioned plan and by the westerly limit of Twentieth Avenue West of the said city of Prince Albert; on the north by southerly limit of the aforementioned road leading westward from the said city and by the cemetery of the Anglican Synod of the Diocese of Saskatchewan, shown as parcel B on the aforementioned plan, the land herein described comprising an area of nine hundred and forty-four acres and seventy-nine hundredths of an acre, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859910" lims:id="859910" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Parcel D</Emphasis> bounded on the north and west by the easterly limit of the right of way of the said railway; on the south by the northerly limit of the government road allowance between Prince Albert Settlement and the fractional southeast quarter of section 7, township 48, range 26, west Second Meridian; on the east by the westerly limit of Twentieth Avenue West of the said city of Prince Albert; comprising an area of four hundred and eighty-eight acres and fifty-six hundredths of an acre, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859911" lims:id="859911" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Parcel E</Emphasis> being all that portion of the fractional southeast quarter of section 7, township 48, range 26, west Second Meridian which lies to the West of the Westerly limit of the right of way of the said railway (shown as parcel G on the aforementioned plan) the said parcel E comprising an area of seven acres and thirty-four hundredths of an acre, more or less.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859912" lims:id="859912" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Parcel F</Emphasis> being all that portion of the fractional southeast quarter of section 7, township 48, range 26, west Second Meridian which lies to the east of the easterly limit of the right of way of the said railway comprising an area of sixty-nine acres and seventy-two hundredths of an acre, more or less.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859913" lims:id="859913" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Secondly</Emphasis>:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859914" lims:id="859914" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>All that said portion of the Government road allowance between Prince Albert Settlement and fractional section 7, township 48, range 26, west Second Meridian, lying outside the right of way of the Canadian National Railway, the said portion comprising the whole of said road allowance saving and excepting thereout and therefrom, that part lying between Parcel G and Parcel H of the said right of way, all as shown on the aforementioned plan. The portion hereby described containing an area of thirteen acres and forty hundredths of an acre, more or less.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859915" lims:id="859915" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Thirdly</Emphasis>:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859916" lims:id="859916" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Legal Subdivision 1 of Section 14, Township 49, Range 27, west of the Second Meridian, in the Province of Saskatchewan.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859917" lims:id="859917" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Now Know Ye</Emphasis> that by and with the advice of Our Privy Council for Canada We do hereby proclaim and declare that from and after the date hereof the lands above described shall henceforth be a penitentiary, to be known as the Saskatchewan Penitentiary, for the Provinces of Alberta and Saskatchewan.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859918" lims:id="859918" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Of All Which</Emphasis> Our Loving Subjects and all others whom these Presents may concern are hereby required to take notice and to govern themselves accordingly.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859919" lims:id="859919" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">In Testimony Whereof</Emphasis> We have caused these Our Letters to be made Patent and the Great Seal of Canada to be hereunto affixed. <Emphasis style="smallcaps">Witness</Emphasis>: The Honourable <Emphasis style="smallcaps">Gérald Fauteux</Emphasis>, Puisne Judge of the Supreme Court of Canada and Deputy of Our Right Trusty and Well-beloved Counsellor, <Emphasis style="smallcaps">Vincent Massey</Emphasis>, Member of Our Order of the Companions of Honour, Governor General and Commander-in-Chief of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859920" lims:id="859920" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">At Ottawa</Emphasis>, this Nineteenth day of July in the year of Our Lord One thousand nine hundred and fifty-six and in the Fifth year of Our Reign.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="859921" lims:id="859921" format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>By Command,</Text><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="12pc"><SignatureName justification="center" topmarginspacing="8">H. W. DOYLE,</SignatureName><SignatureTitle justification="center"><Emphasis style="italic">Acting Under Secretary of State</Emphasis>.</SignatureTitle></SignatureBlock></Provision></Order></Regulation>