<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2011-06-01" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-06-01" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765566" lims:id="765566" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765567" lims:id="765567"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2010-234</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2010</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765569" lims:id="765569"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-11.8">INSURANCE COMPANIES ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765570" lims:id="765570">Policyholders Disclosure Regulations</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2010-1331</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2010</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765571" lims:id="765571"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765572" lims:id="765572" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, pursuant to sections 165<FootnoteRef idref="fn_1a">a</FootnoteRef>, 331<FootnoteRef idref="fn_1b">b</FootnoteRef>, 464.1<FootnoteRef idref="fn_1c">c</FootnoteRef> and 1021<FootnoteRef idref="fn_1d">d</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-11.8">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_1e">e</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2010-234">Policyholders Disclosure Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_1a" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2005, c. 54, s. 244</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_1b" placement="page" status="official"><Label>b</Label><Text>S.C. 2005, c. 54, s. 284</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_1c" placement="page" status="official"><Label>c</Label><Text>S.C. 2005, c. 54, s. 297</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_1d" placement="page" status="official"><Label>d</Label><Text>S.C. 2005, c. 54, s. 364</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="fn_1e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>e</Label><Text>S.C. 1991, c. 47</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765573" lims:id="765573"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765574" lims:id="765574" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765575" lims:id="765575"><Label>1</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765576" lims:id="765576" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Insurance Companies Act.</XRefExternal> (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765577" lims:id="765577" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>closed block</DefinedTermEn> means an account or sub-account that was created by a company as part of a conversion under section 237 of the Act and is closed to new business and maintained exclusively with respect to participating policies of eligible policyholders. (<DefinedTermFr>bloc fermé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765578" lims:id="765578" level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>Participating Policies Disclosure</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765579" lims:id="765579" level="2"><TitleText>Content of Policy Respecting Participating Policy Dividends and Bonuses</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765580" lims:id="765580"><Label>2</Label><Text>A policy respecting participating policy dividends and bonuses established under paragraph 165(2)(e) of the Act shall include the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765581" lims:id="765581"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a statement indicating</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765582" lims:id="765582"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that the dividends or bonuses are declared at the discretion of the board of directors of the company, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765583" lims:id="765583"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that the company’s policy respecting participating policy dividends and bonuses may be amended from time to time at the discretion of the board of directors of the company;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765584" lims:id="765584"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the frequency with which experience and dividend and bonus scales are examined and, if necessary, adjusted, and the principal factors that, in the opinion of the board of directors of the company, would be expected to affect the amount of the dividends and bonuses declared under section 464 of the Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765585" lims:id="765585"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the principal factors that might cause the board of directors of the company to review its policy respecting participating policy dividends and bonuses;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765586" lims:id="765586"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a description of the basis upon which dividends and bonuses are allocated among different classes of participating policies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765587" lims:id="765587"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a description of the principal sources of income considered for the purpose of declaring dividends and bonuses and, in the case of a mutual company, if income other than income derived from the participating business of the company is not considered, the use to which that other income is put; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765588" lims:id="765588"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a description of how specific policyholder behaviour is reflected in the dividend or bonus scale.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765589" lims:id="765589" level="2"><TitleText>Content of Management Policy</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765590" lims:id="765590"><Label>3</Label><Text>A participating account management policy established under paragraph 165(2)(e.1) of the Act shall include the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765591" lims:id="765591"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a description of the participating account and its associated policies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765592" lims:id="765592"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a description of the investment policy for the participating account;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765593" lims:id="765593"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a description of the method, under section 457 of the Act, for allocating investment income to the participating account;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765594" lims:id="765594"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a description of the method, under section 458 of the Act, for allocating expenses, including taxes, to the participating account;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765595" lims:id="765595"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a description of the company’s approach in respect of managing and using the surplus, if any, in the participating account;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765596" lims:id="765596"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the principal factors that might cause the board of directors of the company to change the policy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765597" lims:id="765597"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>if the company does not accept new business in the participating account, information on how the company would manage and dispose of the surplus, if any, in the participating account;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765598" lims:id="765598"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>in the case of a converted company under section 237 of the Act, the measures taken by the company to ensure fairness to participating policyholders whose policies form part of a closed block; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765599" lims:id="765599"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the percentage that the amount that the company intends to transfer to shareholders or a shareholder account of the company out of the company’s participating accounts in a financial year in accordance with section 461 of the Act represents of the total amount that the company intends to transfer to shareholders or a shareholder account of the company and participating policyholders from those participating accounts in that year in accordance with that section.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765600" lims:id="765600" level="2"><TitleText>Information Required to Be Provided at Annual Meeting</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765601" lims:id="765601"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purpose of paragraph 331(1)(a.1) of the Act, a company that has participating policyholders must provide the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765602" lims:id="765602"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a summary of all the information required under sections 2 and 3;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765603" lims:id="765603"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a statement of changes for each participating account for the two financial years immediately preceding the annual meeting, showing such information and particulars as in the opinion of the directors of the company are necessary to present fairly, in accordance with the accounting principles referred to in subsection 331(4) of the Act, the financial position of the account as at the end of each financial year to which the statement relates and the results of the operations and changes in the financial position of the account for each financial year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765604" lims:id="765604"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the surplus in each participating account of the company for the two financial years immediately preceding the annual meeting;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765605" lims:id="765605"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case of a converted company under section 237 of the Act, the amount by which the value of the assets in a closed block exceeds the amount of the policy liabilities in that closed block;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765606" lims:id="765606"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the amounts from each participating account that are invested in segregated funds of the company or its subsidiaries, and the performance of those funds for the two financial years immediately preceding the annual meeting, if applicable;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765607" lims:id="765607"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the actual amounts that have been transferred to shareholders or a shareholder account of the company out of the company’s participating accounts in accordance with section 461 of the Act in the two financial years immediately preceding the annual meeting;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765608" lims:id="765608"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the percentage that the amounts referred to in paragraph (f) represent of the total amount paid to shareholders or a shareholder account of the company and participating policyholders from the company’s participating accounts in accordance with section 461 of the Act, which, in the case of a converted company under section 237 of the Act, shall be calculated without taking into account any amounts paid out of a closed block, in the corresponding financial year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765609" lims:id="765609"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a statement that the company’s policies referred to in sections 2 and 3 are available on request to a shareholder or participating policyholder and, on payment of a reasonable fee, to any other person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765610" lims:id="765610"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>information on the manner in which the company’s policies referred to in sections 2 and 3 may be obtained from the company.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765611" lims:id="765611" level="2"><TitleText>Additional Information Included with the Annual Financial Statement</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765612" lims:id="765612"><Label>5</Label><Text>If a company sends to participating policyholders the information required under section 4 it must include, with its annual financial statement to shareholders, a notice indicating how to proceed if the shareholder wishes to obtain a copy of the information from the company.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765613" lims:id="765613" level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>Adjustable Policies Disclosure</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765614" lims:id="765614" level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765615" lims:id="765615"><Label>6</Label><Text>For the purpose of the definition <DefinedTermEn>adjustable policy</DefinedTermEn> in subection 2(1) of the Act, that term means an individual life insurance policy, other than a participating policy, that is issued by a life company and for which the company may at its sole discretion directly or indirectly change the premium or charge for insurance, the amount of insurance or the policy’s surrender value, but does not include</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765616" lims:id="765616"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a policy under which the premium or charge for insurance, amounts of insurance and surrender values are stated in the policy or a schedule to the policy, or can be determined under the terms of the policy or a schedule to the policy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765617" lims:id="765617"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a group insurance policy including a creditor’s group insurance policy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765618" lims:id="765618"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an annuity contract, including a deferred annuity or a savings, investment or capital accumulation plan under which the life company has undertaken to provide an annuity; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765619" lims:id="765619"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a reinsurance policy.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765620" lims:id="765620" level="2"><TitleText>Information to the Policyholder</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765621" lims:id="765621"><Label>7</Label><Text>For the purpose of subsection 464.1(2) of the Act, where a change has been made in an adjustable policy in the preceding 12 months, the company shall, no later than the end of the 30-day period following the policy anniversary that falls immediately after that 12-month period, send a notice to the policyholder containing a brief summary of the change.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2011-06-01" lims:fid="765622" lims:id="765622" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-10-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-10-28" lims:fid="765623" lims:id="765623"><Label>8</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on June 1, 2011.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>