<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="884695" lims:id="884695" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="884696" lims:id="884696"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/84-764</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1984</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="884698" lims:id="884698"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-14">ATLANTIC FISHERIES RESTRUCTURING ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="884699" lims:id="884699">Order Authorizing the Minister of Regional Industrial Expansion to Exercise the Powers of the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans under Subsection 6(1) of the Act with Respect to Certain Companies</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1984-3183</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1984</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="884700" lims:id="884700"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="884701" lims:id="884701" language-align="yes" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Prime Minister, pursuant to section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-14">Atlantic Fisheries Restructuring Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to authorize the Minister of Regional Industrial Expansion to exercise in respect of 125459 Canada Ltd., The Lake Group Ltd., John Penny and Sons Ltd., Caribou Fisheries Inc., Caribou Food Industries Inc., Fishery Products Ltd., Fishery Products (St. Anthony) Ltd., Fishery Products (Harbour Breton) Ltd., St. Anthony Fisheries Ltd., Fishery Products Inc., North Atlantic Fisheries Ltd., T.J. Hardy Co. Ltd., Fishery Products International Ltd., Great Harbour Deep Seafoods Ltd., or any company formed by the amalgamation of two or more of the aforesaid fishery enterprises, the powers given to the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans pursuant to subsection 6(1) of the Act.</Text></Provision></Order></Regulation>