<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:current-date="2025-07-24" lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392196" lims:id="1392196" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392197" lims:id="1392197"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2023-29</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>02</MM><DD>17</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392198" lims:id="1392198"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-21.5">EXPUNGEMENT OF HISTORICALLY UNJUST CONVICTIONS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392199" lims:id="1392199">Order Establishing Criteria Related to Certain Offences Listed in the Schedule to the Expungement of Historically Unjust Convictions Act</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2023-170</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>02</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392200" lims:id="1392200"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392201" lims:id="1392201" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, pursuant to section 24 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-21.5">Expungement of Historically Unjust Convictions Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-3754_hq_24304">a</FootnoteRef>, makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2023-29">Order Establishing Criteria Related to Certain Offences Listed in the Schedule to the Expungement of Historically Unjust Convictions Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-3754_hq_24304" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2018, c. 11</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392202" lims:id="1392202"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392203" lims:id="1392203" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392204" lims:id="1392204"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392205" lims:id="1392205">Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>In this Order, <DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-21.5">Expungement of Historically Unjust Convictions Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392206" lims:id="1392206" level="1"><TitleText>Criteria</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392207" lims:id="1392207"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392208" lims:id="1392208">Offences listed in item 7 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>An application for an expungement order for a conviction in respect of the offences that are listed in item 7 of the schedule to the Act must include evidence that the following criteria are satisfied:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392209" lims:id="1392209"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the conviction related to the convicted person’s association with a bawdy-house kept for the practice of acts of indecency and not for the purpose of prostitution, where consensual sexual activity was viewed or engaged in; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392210" lims:id="1392210"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the person who was convicted did not exchange money for the provision or receipt of sexual services in that bawdy-house.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392211" lims:id="1392211"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392212" lims:id="1392212">Offences listed in item 8 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>An application for an expungement order for a conviction in respect of the offences that are listed in item 8 of the schedule to the Act must include evidence that the conviction was related to a bawdy-house kept for the practice of acts of indecency and not for the purpose of prostitution, where consensual sexual activity was viewed or engaged in.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392213" lims:id="1392213"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392214" lims:id="1392214">Offences listed in items 9 to 13 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>An application for an expungement order for a conviction in respect of the offences that are listed in items 9 to 13 of the schedule to the Act must include evidence that the following criteria are satisfied:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392215" lims:id="1392215"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the activity for which the person was convicted took place in a bawdy-house in which acts of indecency are practiced and not a place kept for the purpose of prostitution, where consensual sexual activity was viewed or engaged in; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392216" lims:id="1392216"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the person who was convicted did not exchange money for the provision or receipt of sexual services in that bawdy-house.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392217" lims:id="1392217"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392218" lims:id="1392218">Offence listed in item 14 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>In the case of a person who has been convicted of the offence of procuring a woman or female person’s miscarriage that is listed in item 14 of the schedule to the Act, if the convicted person used or assisted in the use of the means to procure a miscarriage, the application for an expungement order for that conviction must include evidence that the following criteria are satisfied:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392219" lims:id="1392219"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the convicted person at the time of the offence was a medical doctor, nurse or midwife; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392220" lims:id="1392220"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the convicted person acted with the consent of the woman or female person.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392221" lims:id="1392221"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392222" lims:id="1392222">Offence listed in item 14 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>In the case of a person who has been convicted of the offence of procuring a woman or female person’s miscarriage that is listed in item 14 of the schedule to the Act, if the convicted person assisted the woman or female person access the means to procure a miscarriage, the application for an expungement order for that conviction must include evidence that the convicted person acted at the request of the woman or female person.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392223" lims:id="1392223"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392224" lims:id="1392224">Offence listed in item 15 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>In the case of a person who has been convicted of the offence of a pregnant woman or female person procuring her own miscarriage that is listed in item 15 of the schedule to the Act, if the convicted person assisted in accessing the means to carry out the miscarriage, the application for an expungement order for that conviction must include evidence that the convicted person acted at the request of the pregnant woman or female person.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392225" lims:id="1392225"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392226" lims:id="1392226">Offence listed in item 15 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>In the case of a person who has been convicted of the offence of a pregnant woman or female person procuring her own miscarriage that is listed in item 15 of the schedule to the Act, if the convicted person used the means with the intention of procuring her own miscarriage, the application for an expungement order for that conviction must include evidence that the convicted person was the pregnant woman or female person.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392227" lims:id="1392227"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392228" lims:id="1392228">Offence listed in item 17 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>In the case of a person who has been convicted of the offence of supplying or procuring a drug or other noxious thing, instrument or thing for the purpose of procuring a miscarriage of a woman or female person that is listed in item 17 of the schedule to the Act, if the convicted person was acting in the capacity of a medical doctor, nurse or midwife, the application for an expungement order for that conviction must include evidence that the following criteria are satisfied:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392229" lims:id="1392229"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the convicted person was at the time of the offence a medical doctor, nurse or midwife; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392230" lims:id="1392230"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the convicted person acted with the consent of the woman or female person.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392231" lims:id="1392231"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392232" lims:id="1392232">Offence listed in item 17 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>In the case of a person who has been convicted of the offence of supplying or procuring a drug or other noxious thing, instrument or thing for the purpose of procuring a miscarriage of a woman or female person that is listed in item 17 of the schedule to the Act, if the convicted person assisted the woman or female person procure the drug or other noxious thing, instrument or thing knowing that it was intended to be used to procure a miscarriage, the application for an expungement order for a conviction in respect of must include evidence that the convicted person acted at the request of the woman or female person.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392233" lims:id="1392233"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392234" lims:id="1392234">Offence listed in item 17 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>In the case of a person who has been convicted of the offence of supplying or procuring a drug or other noxious thing, an instrument or thing for the purpose of procuring the miscarriage of a woman or female person that is listed in item 17 of the schedule to the Act, if the convicted person procured the drug or other noxious thing, the instrument or thing knowing that it was intended to be used to procure her own miscarriage, the application for an expungement order must include evidence that the convicted person was the woman or female person .</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392235" lims:id="1392235"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392236" lims:id="1392236">Offence listed in item 18 of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>An application for an expungement order for a conviction in respect of an offence that is listed in item 18 of the schedule to the Act must include evidence that any of the criteria set out in sections 2 to 11 that apply to the offence are satisfied.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392237" lims:id="1392237" level="1" type="normal"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392238" lims:id="1392238" type="CIFnobold"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2023-02-17" lims:enacted-date="2023-02-17" lims:fid="1392239" lims:id="1392239">Registration</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>This Order comes into force on the day on which it is registered.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>