<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021197" lims:id="1021197" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021198" lims:id="1021198"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/98-261</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1998</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021200" lims:id="1021200"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-7">TERRITORIAL LANDS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021201" lims:id="1021201">Order authorizing certain employees of the Government of Canada to acquire interests in territorial lands in the Northwest Territories (Order No. 1, 1998)</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1998-672 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY> 1998</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021202" lims:id="1021202"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021203" lims:id="1021203" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development, pursuant to paragraph 29(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="T-7">Territorial Lands Act</XRefExternal>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-261">Order authorizing certain employees of the Government of Canada to acquire interests in territorial lands in the Northwest Territories (Order No. 1, 1998)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021204" lims:id="1021204"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021205" lims:id="1021205" level="1"><TitleText>Authorization</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021206" lims:id="1021206"><Label>1</Label><Text>The employees of the Government of Canada named in the schedule are hereby authorized to acquire interests in territorial lands in the Northwest Territories as described in the schedule.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021207" lims:id="1021207" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021208" lims:id="1021208"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Order comes into force on April 23, 1998.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021209" lims:id="1021209" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021210" lims:id="1021210"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 1)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><RegulationPiece lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021211" lims:id="1021211"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021212" lims:id="1021212"><Label>1</Label><Text>To Raymond Wayne Halwas, of the City of Yellowknife in the Northwest Territories, Peace Officer, a member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, to acquire by assignment from the current lessee the whole of Lot numbered 1015 in Quad numbered 85 J/9, Prelude Lake, in the Northwest Territories, as said lot is shown on a plan of survey of record number 67302 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, a copy of which is filed in the Land Titles Office for the Northwest Territories Land Registration District at Yellowknife under number 1410, saving and excepting therefrom and reserving thereout all mines and minerals, including hydrocarbons, whether solid, liquid or gaseous and the right to work them.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021213" lims:id="1021213"><Label>2</Label><Text>To Linda Christine Zachariassen, of the City of Yellowknife in the Northwest Territories, GST Auditor, an employee of the Department of National Revenue, to acquire by assignment from the current lessee the whole of Lot numbered 1063 in Quad numbered 85 I/12, Prelude Lake, in the Northwest Territories, as said lot is shown on a plan of survey of record number 66282 in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, a copy of which is filed in the Land Titles Office for the Northwest Territories Land Registration District at Yellowknife under number 1337, saving and excepting therefrom and reserving thereout all mines and minerals, including hydrocarbons, whether solid, liquid or gaseous and the right to work them.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1021214" lims:id="1021214"><Label>3</Label><Text>To Stephen William Deschene, of the Town of Norman Wells in the Northwest Territories, Resource Management Officer, an employee of the Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development, to lease, for a hunting and fishing cabin, the whole of a parcel of land situated on the northerly shore of Twentyfive Mile Lake, at approximately 65°00′ North Latitude and 127°00′ West Longitude, in Quad numbered 96 E/3 in the Northwest Territories, as said parcel is shown outlined in red on a sketch plan on file 33-1-12 in the Land and Water Management Division of the Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development at Ottawa, saving and excepting therefrom and reserving thereout all mines and minerals, including hydrocarbons, whether solid, liquid or gaseous and the right to work them.</Text></Section></RegulationPiece></Schedule></Regulation>