<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868601" lims:id="868601" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868602" lims:id="868602"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/80-182</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1980</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868604" lims:id="868604"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-11.2">ANIMAL PEDIGREE ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868605" lims:id="868605">Livestock Pedigree Associations Winding-up Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868606" lims:id="868606">Regulations Respecting the Winding-Up of Associations Incorporated Under the Livestock Pedigree Act</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868607" lims:id="868607"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868608" lims:id="868608" language-align="yes" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no"><Text>The Minister of Agriculture, pursuant to subsection 12(6) of the Livestock Pedigree Act, is pleased hereby to make the annexed Regulations respecting the winding-up of associations incorporated under the Livestock Pedigree Act.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868609" lims:id="868609" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated at Ottawa, Ontario, this 17th day of March, 1980</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868610" lims:id="868610"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868611" lims:id="868611" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868612" lims:id="868612"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-80-182">Livestock Pedigree Associations Winding-up Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868613" lims:id="868613" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868614" lims:id="868614"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868615" lims:id="868615"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868616" lims:id="868616" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Livestock Pedigree Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868617" lims:id="868617" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>association</DefinedTermEn> means an association incorporated under the Act or any other Act mentioned in the definition <DefinedTermEn>association</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act, the corporate powers of which have been declared by the Minister, pursuant to the Act, to be at an end; (<DefinedTermFr>association</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868618" lims:id="868618" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>court</DefinedTermEn> means a court having jurisdiction in the place where the association has its head office; (<DefinedTermFr>tribunal</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868619" lims:id="868619" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>director</DefinedTermEn> means, in respect of an association, a person who was a director of the association on the date on which the Minister declared the corporate powers of the association to be at an end; (<DefinedTermFr>dirigeant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868620" lims:id="868620" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>member</DefinedTermEn> means, in respect of an association, a person who was a member of the association on the date on which the Minister declared the corporate powers of the association to be at an end; (<DefinedTermFr>membre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868621" lims:id="868621" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>officer</DefinedTermEn> means, in respect of an association, a person who was an officer of the association on the date on which the Minister declared the corporate powers of the association to be at an end. (<DefinedTermFr>administrateur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868622" lims:id="868622" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868623" lims:id="868623"><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868624" lims:id="868624"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>These Regulations do not apply to an association that, on the date on which the Minister declares the corporate powers of the association to be at an end or thereafter, is insolvent within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-3">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> or is a bankrupt within the meaning of that Act and the affairs of such an association shall be wound up in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-3">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868625" lims:id="868625"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any proceedings taken under these Regulations to wind up the affairs of an association shall be stayed if the association is at any time found, in a proceeding under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-3">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal>, to be insolvent within the meaning of that Act.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868627" lims:id="868627">1992, c. 27, s. 90</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868628" lims:id="868628" level="1"><TitleText>Winding-Up</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868629" lims:id="868629"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868630" lims:id="868630"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where the directors of an association or a majority of the members thereof provide proof, to the satisfaction of the Minister, that the association has no property and no liabilities, the affairs of the association shall be wound up.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868631" lims:id="868631"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When the Minister is satisfied that an association has no property and no liabilities, he shall terminate the winding-up of the affairs of the association and shall issue a certificate certifying that the winding-up of the affairs of the association is terminated.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868632" lims:id="868632"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The winding-up of the affairs of an association under this section is terminated on the date on which the certificate is issued pursuant to subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868633" lims:id="868633"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868634" lims:id="868634"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The directors of any member of an association may make a proposal for the voluntary winding-up of the affairs of the association.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868635" lims:id="868635"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a proposal referred to in subsection (1) is approved,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868636" lims:id="868636"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>at a meeting of the members of the association called and held in accordance with</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868637" lims:id="868637"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a notice thereof that sets out the purpose of the meeting and the terms of the proposal, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868638" lims:id="868638"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the by-laws of the association,</Text></Subparagraph><ContinuedParagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868639" lims:id="868639"><Text>by a majority of not less than two-thirds of the votes cast by the members present and entitled to vote who voted in respect of the proposal, or</Text></ContinuedParagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868640" lims:id="868640"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in writing and signed by all the members entitled to vote in respect of the proposal,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868641" lims:id="868641"><Text>the affairs of the association shall be wound up in accordance with subsection (3).</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868642" lims:id="868642"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After a proposal for the voluntary winding-up of the affairs of an association is approved in accordance with subsection (2), the association shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868643" lims:id="868643"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>immediately cause notice that its corporate powers are at an end and that its affairs are being wound up to be mailed or delivered to each known creditor of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868644" lims:id="868644"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>forthwith publish notice that its corporate powers are at an end and that its affairs are being wound up once a week for four consecutive weeks in a newspaper published or distributed in the place where the association has its head office and take reasonable steps to give notice thereof in each province in Canada where the association was carrying on its affairs on the date on which the Minister declared its corporate powers at an end;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868645" lims:id="868645"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>proceed to collect its property, to dispose of properties that are not to be distributed in accordance with section 15, to discharge all its obligations and to do all other acts required to wind up its affairs; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868646" lims:id="868646"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>after giving the notice required under paragraphs (a) and (b) and paying or adequately providing for the payment or discharge of all its obligations, distribute its remaining property, either in money or in kind, in accordance with section 15.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868647" lims:id="868647"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister or any member or creditor of an association or any interested person may, at any time during the winding-up of the affairs of the association under this section, apply to a court for an order that the winding-up be continued under the supervision of the court as provided in these Regulations, and on such application the court may so order and make any further order it thinks fit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868648" lims:id="868648"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An applicant under subsection (4), other than the Minister, shall give the Minister not less than ten days notice of the application and the Minister is entitled to appear and be heard in person or by counsel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868649" lims:id="868649"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>When the Minister is satisfied that subsections (2) and (3) have been complied with in respect of an association and an order has not been made by a court pursuant to subsection (4), he shall terminate the winding-up of the affairs of the association and shall issue a certificate certifying that the winding-up of the affairs of the association is terminated.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868650" lims:id="868650"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The winding-up of the affairs of an association under this section is terminated on the date on which the certificate is issued pursuant to subsection (6).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868651" lims:id="868651"><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868652" lims:id="868652"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, within thirty days of the date on which the Minister declares the corporate powers of an association to be at an end,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868653" lims:id="868653"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the proof required by section 4 has not been provided to the Minister or the Minister has not issued a certificate pursuant to subsection 4(2), or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868654" lims:id="868654"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subsections 5(2) and (3) have not been complied with in respect of an association or the Minister has not issued a certificate pursuant to subsection 5(6),</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868655" lims:id="868655"><Text>the Minister, any member or creditor of the association or any interested person may apply to a court for an order that the affairs of the association be wound up.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868656" lims:id="868656"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An applicant under this section, other than the Minister, shall give the Minister not less than ten days notice of the application and the Minister is entitled to appear and be heard in person or by counsel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868657" lims:id="868657"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On an application under this section, the court may order that the affairs of the association be wound up and may make any further order it thinks fit.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868658" lims:id="868658"><Label>7</Label><Text>The Minister shall publish notice in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> of an order made by a court pursuant to subsection 5(4) or 6(3).</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868659" lims:id="868659"><Label>8</Label><Text>An application to a court to supervise the winding-up of the affairs of an association under subsection 5(4) or an application to a court to wind up the affairs of an association under subsection 6(1) by a member or creditor of the association or any interested party shall state the reasons, verified by an affidavit of the applicant, why the court should so supervise or order the winding-up of the affairs of the association.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868660" lims:id="868660"><Label>9</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868661" lims:id="868661"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a court makes an order under subsection 5(4) or 6(3), the winding-up of the affairs of the association shall continue or be carried out, as the case may be, under the supervision of the court in accordance with these Regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868662" lims:id="868662"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On an application under subsection 5(4) or 6(1), the court may order the directors and officers of the association to furnish to the court all material information known to or reasonably ascertainable by them, including</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868663" lims:id="868663"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>financial statements of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868664" lims:id="868664"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the name and address of each member of the association; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868665" lims:id="868665"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the name and address of each creditor or claimant, including any creditor or claimant with unliquidated, future or contingent claims, and any person with whom the association has a contract.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868666" lims:id="868666"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On an application under subsection 5(4) or 6(1), the court may, if it is satisfied that the association is able to pay or adequately provide for the payment or discharge of all its obligations, make any order it thinks fit including, without limiting the generality of the foregoing</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868667" lims:id="868667"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an order that the affairs of the association be wound up or that the winding-up of the affairs of the association be continued under the supervision of the court, as the case may be;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868668" lims:id="868668"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an order appointing a liquidator, with or without security, fixing his remuneration and replacing a liquidator;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868669" lims:id="868669"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an order appointing inspectors or referees, specifying their powers and fixing their remuneration and replacing inspectors or referees;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868670" lims:id="868670"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an order determining the notice to be given to any interested person, or dispensing with notice to any person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868671" lims:id="868671"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>an order determining the validity of any claims made against the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868672" lims:id="868672"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>an order, at any stage of the proceedings, restraining the directors and officers of the association from,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868673" lims:id="868673"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>exercising any of their powers, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868674" lims:id="868674"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>collecting or receiving any debt or other property of the association, and from paying out or transferring any property of the association, except as permitted by the court;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868675" lims:id="868675"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>an order determining and enforcing the duty or liability of any director, officer or member of the association or any person who was a director, officer or member of the association prior to the date on which the Minister declared the corporate powers of the association to be at an end</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868676" lims:id="868676"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to the association, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868677" lims:id="868677"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for an obligation of the association;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868678" lims:id="868678"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>an order approving the payment, satisfaction or compromise of claims against the association and the retention of assets for such purposes, and determining the adequacy of provisions for the payment or discharge of obligations of the association, whether liquidated, unliquidated, future or contingent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868679" lims:id="868679"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an order in respect of the disposition or destruction of the documents and records of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868680" lims:id="868680"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>on the application of a creditor, the inspectors or the liquidator, an order giving directions on any matter arising in the winding-up;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868681" lims:id="868681"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>after notice has been given to all interested parties, an order relieving the liquidator from any omission or default on such terms as the court thinks fit and confirming any act of the liquidator;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868682" lims:id="868682"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>an order directing meetings of the members of the association to be called, held and conducted in such manner as the court thinks fit for the purpose of ascertaining their wishes, and appointing a person to act as chairman of any such meeting and to report the result of it to the court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868683" lims:id="868683"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>an order requiring any member, director, officer, employee or agent of the association to pay, deliver, convey, surrender or transfer forthwith, or within such time as the court directs, to the liquidator all documents, records, moneys and property that are in his hands and to which the association is entitled;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868684" lims:id="868684"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>an order for the inspection of the documents and records of the association by its creditors and members;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868685" lims:id="868685"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>subject to section 14, an order approving any proposed distribution of the association’s remaining property, in money or in kind, in accordance with section 15 or an order directing the distribution of the association’s remaining property in such other manner as the court thinks fit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868686" lims:id="868686"><Label>(p)</Label><Text>an order in respect of the disposition of any property belonging to creditors or members of the association who cannot be found; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868687" lims:id="868687"><Label>(q)</Label><Text>on the application of any director, officer member, security holder, creditor or the liquidator,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868688" lims:id="868688"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an order staying the winding-up on such terms and conditions as the court thinks fit,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868689" lims:id="868689"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an order continuing or discontinuing the winding-up proceedings, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868690" lims:id="868690"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>an order to the liquidator to restore to the association all its remaining property.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868691" lims:id="868691"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where a court makes an order for the winding-up of the affairs of an association, the winding-up of the affairs of the association commences when the court makes the order therefor.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868692" lims:id="868692"><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868693" lims:id="868693"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When making an order for the winding-up of the affairs of an association or the supervision of the winding-up of the affairs of an association, as the case may be, or at any time thereafter, the court may appoint any person, including a director, an officer or a member of the association or any other association, as liquidator of the association.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868694" lims:id="868694"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an order for the winding-up of the affairs of an association or the supervision of the winding-up of the affairs of an association, as the case may be, has been made and the office of liquidator is or becomes vacant, the property of the association is under the control of the court until the office of liquidator is filled.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868695" lims:id="868695"><Label>11</Label><Text>Where an order for the winding-up of the affairs of an association or the supervision of the winding-up of the affairs of an association, as the case may be, has been made, the property and rights of the association wherever situated vest in the liquidator on his appointment for the benefit of the claimants, creditors and the persons to whom distribution of the property of the association is to be made pursuant to paragraph 14(5)(a) and section 15.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868696" lims:id="868696"><Label>12</Label><Text>A liquidator shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868697" lims:id="868697"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>forthwith after his appointment give notice thereof to the Minister and to each claimant and creditor known to the liquidator;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868698" lims:id="868698"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>forthwith publish notice in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> and by insertion once a week for two consecutive weeks in a newspaper published or distributed in the place where the association has its head office and take reasonable steps to give notice thereof in each province in Canada where the association was carrying on its affairs on the date on which the Minister declared its corporate powers at an end, requiring any person,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868699" lims:id="868699"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>indebted to the association, to render an account and pay to the liquidator at the time and place specified any amount owing,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868700" lims:id="868700"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>possessing property of the association, to deliver it to the liquidator at the time and place specified, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868701" lims:id="868701"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>having a claim against the association, whether liquidated, unliquidated, future or contingent, to present particulars thereof in writing to the liquidator not later than two months after the first publication of the notice;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868702" lims:id="868702"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>take into his custody and control the property of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868703" lims:id="868703"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>open and maintain a trust account for the moneys of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868704" lims:id="868704"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>apply the property of the association in satisfaction of all its obligations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868705" lims:id="868705"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>keep accounts of the moneys of the association received and paid out by him;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868706" lims:id="868706"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>maintain separate lists of the members, creditors and other persons having claims against the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868707" lims:id="868707"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>if at any time the liquidator determines that the association is unable to pay or adequately provide for the discharge of its obligations, apply to the court for directions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868708" lims:id="868708"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>deliver to the court and to the Minister, at least once in every twelve month period after his appointment or more often as the court may require, financial statements of the association in such form as the liquidator may think proper or as the court may require; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868709" lims:id="868709"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>after his final accounts are approved by the court, distribute any remaining property of the association in accordance with an order of the court made pursuant to paragraph 14(5)(a).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868710" lims:id="868710"><Label>13</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868711" lims:id="868711"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A liquidator may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868712" lims:id="868712"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>retain legal counsel, accountants and other professional advisers;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868713" lims:id="868713"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>bring, defend or take part in any civil, criminal or administrative action or proceeding in the name and on behalf of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868714" lims:id="868714"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>carry on the affairs of the association as required for an orderly winding-up of the affairs of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868715" lims:id="868715"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>sell by public auction or private sale any property of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868716" lims:id="868716"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>do all acts and execute any documents in the name and on behalf of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868717" lims:id="868717"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>borrow money on the security of the property of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868718" lims:id="868718"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>settle or compromise any claims by or against the association; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868719" lims:id="868719"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>do all other things necessary for the winding-up of the affairs of the association and distribution of its property.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868720" lims:id="868720"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a liquidator has reason to believe that any person has in his possession or under his control or has concealed, withheld or misappropriated any property of the association, he may apply to the court for an order requiring that person to appear before the court at the time and place designated in the order and to be examined.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868721" lims:id="868721"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the examination referred to in subsection (2) discloses that a person has concealed, withheld or misappropriated property of the association, the court may order him to restore it or pay compensation to the liquidator.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868722" lims:id="868722"><Label>14</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868723" lims:id="868723"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A liquidator shall pay the costs of the winding-up of the property of the association and shall pay or make adequate provision for all claims against the association.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868724" lims:id="868724"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within one year after his appointment, and after paying or making adequate provision for all claims against the association, the liquidator shall apply to the court</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868725" lims:id="868725"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for approval of his final accounts and for an order permitting him to distribute in money or in kind the remaining property of the association in accordance with section 15 or in such other manner as the court may direct; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868726" lims:id="868726"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for an extension of time, setting out the reasons therefor.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868727" lims:id="868727"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a liquidator fails to make the application required by subsection (2), a member of the association or the Minister may apply to the court for an order for the liquidator to show cause why a final accounting and distribution should not be made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868728" lims:id="868728"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A liquidator shall give not less than ten days notice of his intention to make an application under subsection (2) to the Minister, each inspector appointed under subsection 9(3), each member of the association and any person who provided a security or fidelity bond for the winding-up of the affairs of the association, and he shall publish the notice in a newspaper published or distributed in the place where the association has its head office or as otherwise directed by the court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868729" lims:id="868729"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court approves the final accounts rendered by a liquidator, the court shall make an order</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868730" lims:id="868730"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>directing the distribution of the property of the association remaining after paying or adequately providing for the payment or discharge of all its obligations in accordance with section 15 or in such other manner as the court thinks fit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868731" lims:id="868731"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>directing the custody or disposal of the documents and records of the association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868732" lims:id="868732"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (6), discharging the liquidator; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868733" lims:id="868733"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>directing the Minister to issue a certificate certifying that the winding-up of the affairs of the association is terminated when the Minister is satisfied that the order of the court made pursuant to paragraphs (a) and (b) has been complied with.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868734" lims:id="868734"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The liquidator shall forthwith send or deliver a certified copy of the court order referred to in subsection (5) to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868735" lims:id="868735"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>When the Minister receives the court order referred to in subsection (5) and is satisfied that the order of the court made pursuant to paragraphs 5(a) and (b) has been complied with, the Minister shall issue a certificate certifying that the winding-up of the affairs of the association is terminated.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868736" lims:id="868736"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The winding-up of the affairs of the association is terminated on the date on which the certificate is issued pursuant to subsection (7).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868737" lims:id="868737"><Label>15</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868738" lims:id="868738"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of a court order made pursuant to paragraph 14(5)(a), after the payment or adequate provision for the payment or discharge of all the obligations of the association has been made, the remaining property of the association shall be transferred, conveyed or distributed in accordance with this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868739" lims:id="868739"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a person has transferred property to an association subject to the condition that it be returned to him on the termination of the existence of the association, that property shall be transferred to that person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868740" lims:id="868740"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The remaining property of an association, other than property referred to in subsection (2), shall be transferred in accordance with its application for incorporation, endorsed with a certificate of approval, or its by-laws, whichever are applicable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868741" lims:id="868741"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where the application for incorporation, endorsed with a certificate of approval, or the by-laws of an association do not provide for the transfer of any remaining property of the association referred to in subsection (3) on the termination of the existence of the association, the remaining property of the association referred to in subsection (3) shall be</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868742" lims:id="868742"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>divided in equal shares according to the number of members of the association, which shares shall be distributed rateably among the members; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868743" lims:id="868743"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>distributed</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868744" lims:id="868744"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to one or more associations with similar or cognate objects, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868745" lims:id="868745"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in such other manner</Text><ContinuedSubparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868746" lims:id="868746"><Text>as may be determined by</Text></ContinuedSubparagraph><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868747" lims:id="868747"><Label>(A)</Label><Text>the approval, at a meeting of the members of the association called and held in accordance with a notice thereof that sets out the purpose of the meeting and in accordance with the by-laws of the association, of a majority of not less than two-thirds of the votes cast by the members present and entitled to vote who voted in respect of the matter, or</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868748" lims:id="868748"><Label>(B)</Label><Text>the approval, in writing, of all the members of the association entitled to vote in respect of the matter.</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868749" lims:id="868749"><Label>16</Label><Text>A person who has been granted custody of the documents and records of an association remains liable to produce such documents and records for six years following the date of the termination of the winding-up of the affairs of the association or until the expiry of such other shorter period as may be ordered under subsection 14(5).</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868750" lims:id="868750"><Label>17</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868751" lims:id="868751"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the winding-up of the affairs of an association, the portion of the property distributable to a creditor or member who cannot be found shall be converted into money and paid to the Receiver General.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868752" lims:id="868752"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If at any time a person establishes that he is entitled to any moneys paid to the Receiver General pursuant to this section, the Receiver General shall pay an equivalent amount to him out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="868753" lims:id="868753"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subject to section 17, property of an association that has not been disposed of at the date of the termination of the winding-up of the affairs of the association vests in Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>