<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2022-11-28" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="863883" lims:id="863883" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="863884" lims:id="863884"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/78-68</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1978</YYYY><MM>1</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="863886" lims:id="863886"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">CRIMINAL CODE</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="863887" lims:id="863887">Rules of the Court of Appeals for the Northwest Territories as to A. Criminal Appeals B. Bail on Appeals</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="863888" lims:id="863888">Rules Respecting Criminal Appeals Under Sections 678-689 of the Criminal Code and Bail Rules on Appeals to the Court of Appeal for the Northwest Territories</LongTitle></Identification><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="863889" lims:id="863889" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863890" lims:id="863890" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Under the authority of section 438 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> the Judges of the Court of Appeal for the Northwest Territories hereby make the following Rules respecting Criminal Appeals and Bail Applications pending appeal.</Text></Provision><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863891" lims:id="863891" pointsize="8" rowbreak="yes" topmarginspacing="10" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863892" lims:id="863892" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863893" lims:id="863893" cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="0.57*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="1.43*" /><thead lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863894" lims:id="863894"><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><Emphasis style="italic">CODE REF.</Emphasis></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /></row></thead><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863895" lims:id="863895"><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>1</Label><Text>In these Rules, unless the context otherwise requires:</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(1)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Appellant</DefinedTermEn> means any person entitled to appeal to the Court under Part XXI of the Code, or Section 839 of the Code, or otherwise under any statute or ordinance giving a right of appeal to the Court of Appeal in summary conviction matters and includes the Attorney-General.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Appellate judge</DefinedTermEn> means a judge of the Court of Appeal of the Northwest Territories, and includes an <Language xml:lang="la">ex officio</Language> judge thereof.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>S. 2</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>S. 605</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Attorney-General</DefinedTermEn> means the Attorney-General as defined in s. 2 of the Code and includes counsel instructed by him for the purpose of an appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Code</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(5)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Court</DefinedTermEn> means the Court of Appeal for the Northwest Territories.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(6)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Prisoner appeal</DefinedTermEn> means an appeal by a person who at the time the notice of appeal is given, is in custody and not represented by counsel.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(7)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Registrar</DefinedTermEn> means the Registrar of the Court of Appeal for the Northwest Territories, Court House, Yellowknife, Northwest Territories, and includes a Deputy, Assistant or Acting Registrar. The Registrar shall also maintain a record of all appeals at an office so designated at the Law Courts in Edmonton, Alberta.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(8)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Respondent</DefinedTermEn> means the Attorney-General in the case of a person who appeals against a conviction or sentence or against a finding or verdict that he is unfit to stand trial, or from a finding of “not guilty” by reason of insanity; and in the case of the Attorney-General who appeals against sentence or acquittal, or a finding of “not guilty” by reason of insanity, or a finding or verdict that the Accused is unfit to stand trial, means the person accused.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(9)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Sentence appeal</DefinedTermEn> means an appeal where only the question of sentence is involved.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(10)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Trial disposition</DefinedTermEn> means a conviction, a sentence, an acquittal, or an order from which there is an appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(11)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Trial judge</DefinedTermEn> means the judge who presided at the trial and includes a judge or deputy judge of the Territorial Court of the Northwest Territories and a judge or deputy judge or <Language xml:lang="la">ex officio</Language> judge of the Supreme Court of the Northwest Territories.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(12)</Label><Text><DefinedTermEn>Warden</DefinedTermEn> means the person in charge of any custodial institution, including a remand centre, a gaol, a penitentiary, or a mental hospital.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">GENERAL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>2 (1)</Label><Text>These Rules shall apply to appeals to the Court under:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>Part XXI of the Code, or section 839 of the Code, or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Any statute or ordinance giving a right of appeal to the Court of Appeal in summary conviction matters.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Numbers preceded by the letter “s” are references to sections of the Code.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In all matters not provided for by these Rules, the Rules of Court respecting civil appeals shall apply, <Language xml:lang="la">mutatis mutandis</Language>, save that there shall be no cross-appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Non-compliance with the Rules shall not render any proceedings void, but the same may be amended, set aside, or otherwise dealt with as may be just by an Appellate judge or the Court.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 678(2)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(5) (i)</Label><Text>Any time prescribed by these Rules within which an appeal is to be taken may be extended by an Appellate judge or the Court before or after the expiration thereof, and any other time may similarly be extended or shortened.</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Two clear days’ notice in writing of an application to extend or shorten time shall be given to the opposite party unless such application is made on consent, or unless otherwise ordered by an Appellate judge.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>An appeal to the Court may be taken from the dismissal by an Appellate judge of an application to extend or shorten time by filing a notice in writing with the registrar within seven (7) days of such dismissal.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An appeal may be dismissed if the appellant fails to appear when the case is called for hearing, but such order dismissing an appeal may for special reasons be vacated on application to the Court.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the appellant or respondent obtains leave of the Court to call further evidence upon the hearing of the appeal, the attendance of any witness or the production of any document may be obtained in the same way as that provided for by the Rules of the Supreme Court in civil matters, and all the provisions of such Rules so far as they are applicable, shall apply to the production of evidence upon an appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(8) (i)</Label><Text>The registrar shall, following the pronouncement of judgment by the Court in every criminal appeal, promptly enter a formal judgment.</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Any clerical errors or omissions may be corrected by a single member of the Court pronouncing the judgment.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">METHOD OF APPEALING</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 678(1)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>3</Label><Text>An appeal or an application for leave to appeal under the Code shall be made by filing and serving a notice of appeal in the manner and within the time as hereinafter directed.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>4</Label><Text>An appeal under any statute or ordinance giving a right of appeal in summary conviction matters shall be made by the filing and serving of a notice of appeal in the manner and within such time as is hereinafter directed, provided that there shall be due compliance with any appeals provision in any such statute or ordinance.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">TIME FOR APPEAL AND SERVICE</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 678(1)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>5 (1)</Label><Text>A notice of appeal from conviction, or conviction and sentence, or sentence only, shall be filed and served within sixty (60) days from the date of sentence.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice of appeal from acquittal shall be filed and served within sixty (60) days from the date of acquittal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 675(2)(b)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A notice of appeal from a finding of “not guilty” by reason of insanity by an accused person pursuant to s. 675(3) shall be filed and served within sixty (60) days from the date of such finding.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>S. 675(3)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>S. 676(3)</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A notice of appeal from a finding or verdict that an accused person is unfit to stand trial by reason of insanity by either such accused person or the Attorney-General, pursuant to s. 675(3) or 676(3) shall be filed and served within sixty (60) days from such finding or verdict.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>6 (1)</Label><Text>The filing and serving of a notice of appeal shall be effected:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in a prisoner appeal, by serving three (3) copies of the notice of appeal on the warden or the designate of the warden of the institution in which the appellant is in custody. Such officer shall endorse on the copies the date he received them, and shall forthwith return one (1) copy to the appellant, and forthwith forward one (1) copy to the registrar, and shall retain one (1) copy;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in any other appeal by a convicted person, by filing in the office of the registrar or by mailing to him by registered mail three (3) copies of a notice of appeal;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in an appeal by the Attorney-General, by filing two (2) copies of the notice of appeal with the registrar and by personal service on the person in respect of whose trial disposition the appeal is brought, unless otherwise ordered by an Appellate judge; PROVIDED that where substitutional service is ordered, no appeal shall be argued without leave of the Court, and on such application for leave, the Court may give further directions as to service.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Upon receipt of a notice of appeal other than an appeal by the Attorney-General or prosecutor, the registrar shall forthwith forward a copy to the Attorney-General or his counsel at trial, or the prosecutor or his counsel at trial.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In cases tried before a judge or deputy judge of the Territorial Court of the Northwest Territories, the Registrar shall immediately forward a copy of the notice of appeal to the judge or deputy judge.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In all other cases, the Registrar shall immediately forward a copy to the clerk of the court in which the trial took place.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">CONTENT OF NOTICE OF APPEAL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 678(1)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>7 (1)</Label><Text>In appeals where the appellant is not represented by counsel, a notice of appeal and application for leave to appeal shall be in Form “A” or to like effect.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In all other appeals and applications for leave to appeal, the notice of appeal shall be in Form “B” or to like effect.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where an appeal or an application for leave to appeal is commenced by an appellant not represented by counsel, and the appellant subsequently retains counsel, the latter shall immediately notify the registrar and the respondent. Thereafter, all relevant Rules relating to appeals which are not appeals by persons not represented by counsel shall apply.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>8</Label><Text>Every notice of appeal and every application for leave to appeal, shall set out the grounds for appeal or application, and shall be signed by the appellant or counsel.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>9 (1)</Label><Text>No time or place for the hearing shall be stated in the notice of appeal. The registrar shall forthwith after receipt of the notice, other than a notice of an application to an Appellate judge for leave to appeal, enter the case on the lists of appeal for the next ensuing sittings of the Court, and all necessary directions as to the hearing of the appeal or application may be given by the Court or any judge thereof.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In appeals by the Attorney-General, the Attorney-General shall take all reasonable steps to notify a respondent of the time and place for the hearing of the appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">PLACE OF HEARING</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>10</Label><Text>Unless otherwise ordered by the Court or a Judge thereof, all appeals and applications to the Court or a judge thereof for leave to appeal from any trial disposition made in the Northwest Territories shall be heard at Yellowknife, or at such place within the Northwest Territories or the Province of Alberta as may be ordered by the Court or Chief Justice thereof.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">DISPENSING WITH ORAL ARGUMENT</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>10.1 (1)</Label><Text>Where</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the appeal does not raise complex issues of fact or law,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the issues on the appeal require the application of established law or procedure, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the parties to the appeal consent,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>the Court may, on such terms as it considers just, direct that argument on an appeal be presented in writing without oral argument.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the parties seek to have an appeal entertained in writing only, they must apply to the Registrar jointly in writing setting out the reasons why the appeal is suitable for such procedure and acknowledging their agreement to this procedure.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Registrar will direct the application to the panel assigned to the appeal which will decide whether or not to accept the application.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The panel hearing the appeal may, at any time, direct that there be full or partial oral argument, with the personal attendance of the parties or their counsel, or direct that further argument in writing be submitted.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">APPEALS WHERE LEAVE REQUIRED</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>11 (1)</Label><Text>Applications for leave to appeal may be made to the Court or to an Appellate judge.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application for leave to appeal to the Court shall be made by the filing of a notice of appeal, pursuant to these Rules, and no further notice is required.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the Court grants leave to appeal, it may at once determine the appeal on its merits or it may direct that the appeal be heard at a later time.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An application for leave to appeal to an Appellate judge shall be made by filing a notice of appeal pursuant to these Rules, and by filing with the registrar contemporaneously, or thereafter, a notice of motion. Such notice of motion shall be served on the respondent not less than two (2) clear days before the return of the motion, unless otherwise ordered.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 675(1)(a)(ii)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If an appellate judge refuses leave to appeal against a conviction in respect of an application brought pursuant to s. 675(1)(a)(ii), the applicant may, by filing a notice in writing with the registrar within seven (7) days of such refusal, have the application for leave to appeal determined by the Court.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>S. 675(1)(b)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>S. 675(3)</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If an Appellate judge refuses leave to appeal from sentence in respect of an application brought pursuant to s. 675(1)(b), such determination is final, and no appeal from such order lies.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 675(1)(a)(ii)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>12 (1)</Label><Text>An application to a trial judge for a certificate under s. 675(1)(a)(ii) shall be made within thirty (30) days from the date of sentence, and may be made <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language>, or if the trial judge requires, on at lest two (2) clear days’ notice to the Attorney-General.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a trial judge requires notice of the application:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the notice may be returnable before or after the expiration of the thirty (30) days mentioned above;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a copy of the notice shall be mailed to or filed with the registrar;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>if the certificate is granted, the notice of appeal shall be mailed or filed within thirty (30) days from the date of sentence, or within two (2) clear days after the certificate is granted, whichever is the later.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">SENTENCE APPEALS WITH COUNSEL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>13 (1)</Label><Text>In an appeal against sentence, where the appellant is represented by counsel, unless otherwise ordered by the Court or a judge thereof, there shall be filed by the appellant with the registrar six (6) copies of a group of documents entitled “Sentence Material”, and a further copy shall forthwith be served upon the respondent.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Sentence Material shall be filed with the registrar at least fourteen (14) days before the opening of the Court.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Sentence Material shall include the following:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Information or Indictment and sentence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a Statement of Facts as related to the trial judge;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any pre-sentence or post-sentence reports;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>a transcript of the Reasons for Judgment and for sentence given by the trial judge; the criminal record, if any, of the convicted person, as disclosed to the trial judge.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where an appeal book has been filed, the Sentence Material need not include any material already contained in the Appeal Book.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Six (6) copies of written material to be used in support of a respondent’s argument shall be filed with the registrar seven (7) days before the opening of the Court, unless the Court otherwise orders, and a further copy shall be forthwith served upon the appellant.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">SENTENCE APPEALS WITHOUT COUNSEL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>14 (1)</Label><Text>In an appeal against sentence, where the appellant is not represented by counsel, he may present his argument orally or in writing, but in order to do so orally, he must signify in his notice of appeal his desire to be present, if he is in custody.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any argument in writing shall be filed with the registrar prior to the day fixed for the hearing.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">SENTENCE APPEALS GENERALLY</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 614</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>15 (1)</Label><Text>In an appeal against sentence by a convicted person, the Attorney-General, if he intends upon the hearing of the appeal to contend that the sentence should be increased or varied, shall, not less than three (3) days before the commencement of the sittings of the Court at which the appeal comes to be heard, give notice of such intention in writing to the appellant or his counsel.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In any appeal against sentence by either a convicted person or the Attorney-General, the Court of its own motion may treat the whole matter of sentence as open, and on an appeal by a convicted person, may increase or vary the sentence, and on an appeal by the Attorney-General, decrease or vary the sentence, PROVIDED that notice that such increase or variation is to be considered, is given by the Court so that the convicted person or the Attorney-General may be heard on such disposition.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">APPEALS OTHER THAN SENTENCE APPEALS</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>16 (1)</Label><Text>Except in sentence appeals, or unless otherwise ordered, the appellant shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>file six (6) copies of an appeal book with the registrar;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>deliver one (1) copy of the appeal book to the respondent.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The appeal book shall be furnished to the appellant upon payment of the fees from time to time authorized by the tariff of fees payable to the office of the court reporters.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Unless otherwise ordered by the Court or a judge thereof, the Appeal Book shall contain:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Information or Indictment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the transcript of the evidence, including exhibits;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>Counsels’ addresses;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>Charge to the jury and verdict of the jury;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>Reasons for Judgment;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>Formal certificate of conviction (or acquittal);</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>Notice of appeal (or notice of application for leave to appeal).</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>17</Label><Text>Except in sentence appeals, or unless otherwise ordered,</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>when an appellant is represented by counsel, the appellant shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>file six (6) copies of a factum with the registrar;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>deliver one (1) copy of a factum to the respondent twenty-eight (28) days before the date of commencement of the sittings at which the appeal is to be heard.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>when a respondent is represented by counsel, the respondent shall:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>file six (6) copies of a factum with the registrar;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>deliver one (1) copy of a factum to the appellant fourteen (14) days before the date of commencement of the sittings at which the appeal is to be heard.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">FURNISHING CERTIFIED COPIES</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 438(2)(v)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>18</Label><Text>The magistrate or deputy magistrate before whom a trial took place, or the clerk of the Court shall, upon request, forward to the Attorney-General and the counsel who acted for the Attorney-General at the trial, certified copies of the documents, exhibits and things connected with the proceedings which are in his custody and control, and which are required for the purposes of an appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">REPORT OF A TRIAL JUDGE</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 609(1)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>19 (1)</Label><Text>Where an appeal is taken or an application for leave to appeal is made, the trial judge shall, at the request of the Court or a judge thereof, furnish to the registrar a report on the case or on any matter relating to the case which is specified in the request.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Forthwith after the registrar receives the report, he shall mail a copy of it to the appellant and to the respondent, or to their counsel.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">DISPOSITION OF DOCUMENTS AND EXHIBITS</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>20 (1)</Label><Text>Subject to the other subsections of this Rule, all documents, exhibits and things connected with a trial shall be retained by the trial judge or by the clerk of the Court for eighty (80) days after sentence or acquittal, as the case may be.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>At any time after a trial, the trial judge or an Appellate judge may make such order as to the custody or conditional release of any document, exhibit or thing as the special circumstances of the case may require.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Upon the filing of written consents by the accused or his counsel, and by the Attorney-General or his counsel, the trial judge or the clerk of the Court shall deliver any document, exhibit or thing in accordance with such consents.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Upon receipt of a copy of a notice of appeal, the trial judge or the clerk of the Court shall forward to the registrar all documents, exhibits and things connected with the proceedings at the trial, other than such as may already have been released pursuant to subsections (2) and (3) hereof.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">VERIFICATION OF TRANSCRIPTS AND DEPOSITIONS AT TRIAL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>S. 487</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>S. 540</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>S. 575</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>21 (1)</Label><Text>A transcript of the evidence of proceedings taken in shorthand at a trial and certified by the court reporter who made or extended the transcript shall be <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> proof of such evidence and proceedings.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the evidence and proceedings are not taken by a court reporter, but by a sound-recording apparatus, as authorized under legislation, a transcript of such recording, certified by a court recorder, shall be <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> proof of such evidence and proceedings.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the evidence and proceedings are not taken by a court reporter, and are not taken by a sound-recording apparatus, as authorized under legislation, then depositions taken in accordance with s. 540 shall be <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> proof of such evidence and proceedings.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">COMPENSATION OR RESTITUTION OF PROPERTY</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>S. 689</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>S. 738</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>S. 739</Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>22</Label><Text>An order for the restitution of property under ss. 738 or 739 shall provide for securing the safe custody of the property referred to in the order, for the period during which its operation is suspended by virtue of s. 689.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">RELEASE FROM CUSTODY PENDING APPEAL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 608(1)(a)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>23 (1)</Label><Text>All applications for release from custody pending the determination of an appeal to the Court shall be made to an Appellate judge. No application for release from custody pending the determination of an appeal shall be entertained unless the applicant has filed with the registrar a notice of appeal or an application for leave to appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 608(1)(b)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No application for release from custody pending the determination of an appeal from sentence only shall be granted unless the appellant has been granted leave to appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An application for leave to appeal may be combined and heard with an application for release from custody pending appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">S. 608(1)(c)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No application for release pending the determination of an appeal or motion for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court of Canada shall be entertained unless the applicant has filed and served his notice of appeal, or, where leave is required, his application for leave to appeal.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>24 (1)</Label><Text>Where an applicant applies for release from custody pending determination of appeal, he shall give written notice of such application to the prosecutor. Such notice shall be two (2) clear days’ notice, unless both parties attend upon an Appellate judge or the judge otherwise orders.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application shall be supported:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>A</Label><Text>by an affidavit stating:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>his place of abode in the three years preceding his conviction, and where he proposes to reside if released;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>his employment, if any, prior to conviction, and whether he expects to be employed if released;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>his criminal record, if any, including convictions outside Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>whether criminal charges are, at the time of the application, pending against him, either in Canada or elsewhere.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>B</Label><Text>by his undertaking to surrender himself into custody in accordance with the terms of any order granted.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An Appellate Court judge may dispense with the filing of the affidavit referred to above, and may act upon a statement of facts conveyed to him by counsel for the applicant and for the Attorney-General, which statements of fact the judge may require each counsel to put in writing and file with the registrar.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A judge of the Court which orders a new trial may forthwith entertain an application for interim release pending the new trial.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order for release of an appellant pending the determination of an appeal shall be in Form “C” and shall specify the terms and conditions of release and when it is to take effect.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">ABANDONMENT OF APPEALS</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>25 (1)</Label><Text>An appellant who desires to abandon an appeal may do so at any time before the hearing of the appeal commences by completing a Notice of Abandonment in Form “D”, or to like effect, and by filing or sending the same to the registrar. Form “D” shall be signed by the appellant, or by his solicitor of record in the appeal. In the former case, the signature of the appellant shall be verified by affidavit or witnessed by a solicitor or by an officer of the institution in which the appellant is confined.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1) of this Rule, the appellant may be given leave by the Court to an appeal after the commencement of argument.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An appeal which is abandoned shall be as if no appeal had been taken.</Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">DISSEMINATION OF RULES</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Label>26</Label><Text>A sufficient number of copies of these Rules shall be prepared by the registrar at Yellowknife and sent to every keeper of a Gaol or Correctional Institute in the Northwest Territories and to the wardens of the Penitentiary at Prince Albert, and the Penitentiary at Drumheller, and such other penal institutions as may be operated by the Government of Canada to which prisoners from the Northwest Territories are confined, and the registrar shall also send to the said keepers and wardens a copy of Sections 675, 678, 683 and 685 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> for any convicted person in his custody who requests the same.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>These Rules shall come into force on the 30th day of June, A.D. 1978, on which date the Rules respecting criminal appeals to the Court of Appeal for the Northwest Territories heretofore in force cease to be in force, without prejudice to any proceedings under the said Rules which may have been taken prior to the 30th June, 1978.</Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863897" lims:id="863897">SOR/2000-232, ss. 2 to 13, 16(F)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote><PageBreak /><FormGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863898" lims:id="863898"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863899" lims:id="863899"><Label>FORM “A”</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863900" lims:id="863900" pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863901" lims:id="863901" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863902" lims:id="863902" cols="4"><colspec colname="COLSPEC2" colwidth="180.02*" /><colspec colname="1" colwidth="599.17*" /><colspec colname="COLSPEC1" colwidth="529.53*" /><colspec colname="COLSPEC0" colwidth="594.31*" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863903" lims:id="863903"><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">TO BE USED WHEN APPELLANT IS NOT REPRESENTED BY COUNSEL — RULE 7(1)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">IN THE COURT OF APPEAL FOR THE NORTHWEST TERRITORIES</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /> APPELLANT</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">(Fill in Full Name)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">-v-</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /> RESPONDENT</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">TO:</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="1" rowsep="0">THE REGISTRAR,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="1" rowsep="0">Court of Appeal for the</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="1" rowsep="0">Northwest Territories,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="1" rowsep="0">Court House,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="1" rowsep="0">YELLOWKNIFE, N.W.T.</entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">NOTICE OF APPEAL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>On the <Leader leader="solid" length="3pc" /> day of <Leader leader="solid" length="3pc" /> 19<Leader leader="none" length="1pc" /> at <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Northwest Territories, I was convicted on charges of <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">in the Magistrate’s ☐ Court</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Supreme ☐ Court</entry><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0">and was</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">sentenced to <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">At trial I pleaded <Leader length="1pc" /> GUILTY ☐ <Leader length="2pc" /> NOT GUILTY ☐</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>My address is: <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">I, the above appellant, hereby give notice that I desire to appeal and if necessary for me to do so, to apply for leave to appeal against Conviction Only <Leader length="1pc" /> Sentence Only <Leader length="1pc" /> or both Conviction and Sentence for the following reasons: (Set out reasons.) (If the space is insufficient, put additional grounds on the reverse side of this form.)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">I wish<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />do not wish<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />to be present at the hearing of the appeal. (S. 688)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">If a new trial is ordered and I have a right to trial by judge and jury, I wish<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />do not wish<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />trial by judge and jury.</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">DATED this <Leader length="2pc" /> day of <Leader length="5pc" />, 19<Leader length="1pc" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>SIGNED: <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text><Provision format-ref="right-align" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text>(APPELLANT)</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>(IF APPELLANT IS IN CUSTODY)</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes"><Text>3 copies of this Notice of Appeal are to be served upon the Warden or designate of the Warden of the Institution in which the Appellant is imprisoned within sixty (60) days of the sentence being imposed upon him.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="COLSPEC0" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>(IF APPELLANT IS NOT IN CUSTODY)</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes"><Text>3 copies of this Notice of Appeal are to be filed in the office of the Registrar or mailed to him by registered mail within sixty (60) days from the date of the sentence imposed upon him.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863905" lims:id="863905">SOR/2000-232, ss. 14, 16(F)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></FormGroup><PageBreak /><FormGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863906" lims:id="863906"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863907" lims:id="863907"><Label>FORM “B”</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863908" lims:id="863908" pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863909" lims:id="863909" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863910" lims:id="863910" cols="3"><colspec colname="COLSPEC3" colwidth="106.03*" /><colspec colname="COLSPEC2" colwidth="63.26*" /><colspec colname="1" colwidth="827.91*" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863911" lims:id="863911"><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0">TO BE USED WHERE NOTICE IS FILED BY COUNSEL FOR AN APPELLANT OR ON BEHALF OF THE ATTORNEY-GENERAL — RULE 7(2)</entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0">IN THE COURT OF APPEAL FOR THE NORTHWEST TERRITORIES</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><FormBlank width="9pc">APPELLANT</FormBlank><Leader length="2pc" /><FormBlank width="9pc">RESPONDENT</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">TO:</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">The Registrar,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Court of Appeal for the</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Northwest Territories,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Court House,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">YELLOWKNIFE, N.W.T.</entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">NOTICE OF APPEAL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">PARTICULARS</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" morerows="2" rowsep="0">1</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">The Appeal is in respect of indictable offence, or by way of further Appeal from the Magistrate’s Court in respect of a summary conviction offence.</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">(INDICTABLE OFFENCE<Leader leader="none" length="1pc" /> ☐</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">SUMMARY CONVICTION<Leader leader="none" length="0.4pc" /> ☐)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">2</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Place of Trial <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">3</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Name of Judge <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">4</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Name of Court <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">5</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Name of Crown Prosecutor at Trial <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">6</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Name of Defence Counsel at Trial <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">7</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Offences of which Appellant convicted or acquitted <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">8</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Sections of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Statutes under which Appellant convicted <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">9</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Plea at Trial <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">10</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Sentence imposed <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">11</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">Date of Sentence or Acquittal <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" morerows="6" rowsep="0">12</entry><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>If Appellant in custody, place of incarceration <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC2" rowsep="0">TAKE NOTICE that the Appellant: (mark with an “x” which of the following are applicable)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">(1)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">appeals against conviction (or acquittal) on grounds involving a question of law alone;<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">(2)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">applies for Leave to Appeal his conviction on grounds involving a question of fact alone or a question of mixed law and fact, and if Leave be granted, hereby appeals against the said conviction; ☐</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" morerows="2" rowsep="0">(3)</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">applies for Leave to Appeal against sentence, and if Leave be granted, hereby appeals against the sentence.<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">The grounds of Appeal are annexed hereto.</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>The relief sought is <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" keep-with-previous="yes" topmarginspacing="4"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0">(The Appellant wishes<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />does not wish<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />to be present at the hearing of the Appeal.)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0">If a new Trial is ordered and the Appellant has a right to a Trial by Judge and Jury, the Appellant wishes<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />does not wish<Leader leader="none" length="0.5pc" />☐ the new Trial to be by Judge and Jury.</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0">The Appellant’s address for service is <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0">DATED at <Leader leader="solid" length="5pc" /> Northwest Territories this <Leader length="3pc" /> day of <Leader length="3pc" />, 19<Leader length="1pc" />.</entry></row><row><entry align="right" colsep="0" nameend="1" namest="COLSPEC3" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="right-align"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">Counsel for the Appellant</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863913" lims:id="863913">SOR/2000-232, s. 16(F)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></FormGroup><PageBreak /><FormGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863914" lims:id="863914"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863915" lims:id="863915"><Label>FORM “C”</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863916" lims:id="863916" pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863917" lims:id="863917" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863918" lims:id="863918" cols="2"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="260.66*" /><colspec colname="2" colwidth="243.34*" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863919" lims:id="863919"><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">IN THE COURT OF APPEAL FOR THE NORTHWEST TERRITORIES</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">BETWEEN:</entry></row><row><entry align="right" colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">Appellant</entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">- and -</entry></row><row><entry align="right" colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">Respondent</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Before His Lordship</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Leader leader="solid" length="3pc" />day the<LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" />day</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">The Honourable Mr. Justice<Leader leader="none" length="1pc" />}</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">of <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" /><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">A.D. 19<Leader leader="none" length="1pc" /> at <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">In Chambers</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">ORDER</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">UPON the application of the above-named appellant <Leader leader="solid" length="7pc" /> for an order releasing him pending the determination of his appeal herein, notice of which appeal has been given (or leave to appeal sentence having been granted as the case may be);</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>AND UPON hearing <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /> of</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="4"><Text>Counsel for the Appellant and <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /> of</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="4"><Text>Counsel for the Crown (Respondent);</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">AND UPON reading the said Notice of Appeal and the Notice of Application for Bail and the Affidavit of the Appellant;</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">IT IS HEREBY ORDERED THAT the Appellant be released from custody pending the determination of his appeal upon (set forth the terms and conditions directed under Section 679(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>).</entry></row><row><entry align="right" colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="right-align"><Text><FormBlank width="9pc">Registrar or Judge</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">ENTERED this <Leader length="3pc" /> day of <Leader length="3pc" /> A.D. 19<Leader length="1pc" />.</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><FormBlank width="9pc">Registrar</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" nameend="2" namest="1" rowsep="0">(Where an Order has been obtained releasing the Appellant pursuant to Subsection 679(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> it should be noted that Subsection 679(9) provides that an undertaking in this section may be in Form 12 and a Recognizance may be in Form 32.)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863921" lims:id="863921">SOR/2000-232, ss. 15, 16(F)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></FormGroup><PageBreak /><FormGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863922" lims:id="863922"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863923" lims:id="863923"><Label>FORM “D” — RULE 25(1)</Label></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863924" lims:id="863924" pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863925" lims:id="863925" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863926" lims:id="863926" cols="1"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="468.0*" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863927" lims:id="863927"><row valign="top"><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0">IN THE COURT OF APPEAL FOR THE NORTHWEST TERRITORIES</entry></row><row><entry align="center" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Emphasis style="italic">NOTICE OF ABANDONMENT OF APPEAL</Emphasis></entry></row><row><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="right-align"><Text><FormBlank width="8pc">APPELLANT</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry align="right" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="right-align"><Text><FormBlank width="8pc">RESPONDENT</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">The Registrar,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Court of Appeal for the</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Northwest Territories,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Court House,</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="4"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">YELLOWKNIFE, N.W.T.</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>I, <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /> of</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /> give notice that I abandon my Appeal.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>DATED at <LeaderRightJustified leader="solid" /></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="4"><Text>the<Leader leader="solid" length="3pc" /> day of<Leader leader="solid" length="3pc" /> 19<Leader leader="none" length="1pc" />.</Text></Provision></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">THIS NOTICE WAS SIGNED IN THE PRESENCE OF:</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><FormBlank width="6pc">WITNESS</FormBlank><Leader length="2pc" /><FormBlank width="12pc">(APPELLANT) (OR HIS SOLICITOR, AS THE CASE MAY BE)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">NOTE: If this notice of abandonment of Appeal is signed by the Appellant personally, Rule 25(1) requires that his signature <Emphasis style="italic">must</Emphasis> be verified by affidavit or witnessed by a solicitor, or by an officer of the institution in which he may be confined.</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863929" lims:id="863929">SOR/2000-232, s. 16(F)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></FormGroup><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:inforce-end-date="2019-09-18" lims:fid="863930" lims:id="863930" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>THE RULES RELATING TO CRIMINAL APPEALS ABOVE SET OUT AND ATTESTED BY THE MEMBERS OF THE COURT OF APPEAL FOR THE NORTHWEST TERRITORIES HAVE BEEN MADE BY THE COURT OF APPEAL FOR THE NORTHWEST TERRITORIES WITH THE CONCURRENCE OF ALL JUDGES THEREOF PRESENT AT A MEETING CALLED FOR THE PURPOSE HELD AT CALGARY, ALBERTA, ON THE 16th DAY OF JANUARY A.D. 1978, PURSUANT TO SECTION 438 OF THE <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">CRIMINAL CODE</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><SignatureBlock justification="right" width="10pc"><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="16"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">McGILLIVRAY, C.J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">McDERMID, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">MADDISON, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">SINCLAIR, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">CLEMENT, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">LIEBERMAN, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">PROWSE, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">MOIR, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">HADDAD, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">MORROW, J.A.</SignatureName><SignatureLine justification="left" topmarginspacing="8"><Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" /></SignatureLine><SignatureName justification="left">TALLIS, J.A.</SignatureName></SignatureBlock></Schedule></Regulation>