<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2015-05-15" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2015-05-15" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784946" lims:id="784946" gazette-part="II" in-force="yes" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784947" lims:id="784947"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2012-231</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784949" lims:id="784949"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-25.7">PROTECTION OF RESIDENTIAL MORTGAGE OR HYPOTHECARY INSURANCE ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784950" lims:id="784950">Protection of Residential Mortgage or Hypothecary Insurance Regulations</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2012-1450</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784951" lims:id="784951"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784952" lims:id="784952" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, pursuant to paragraphs 41(b) to (e) and (h) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-25.7">Protection of Residential Mortgage or Hypothecary Insurance Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_81000-2-987-E_hq_11076">a</FootnoteRef>, makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2012-231">Protection of Residential Mortgage or Hypothecary Insurance Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_81000-2-987-E_hq_11076" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2011, c. 15, s. 20</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784953" lims:id="784953"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784954" lims:id="784954" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784955" lims:id="784955"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784956" lims:id="784956">Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784957" lims:id="784957" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-25.7">Protection of Residential Mortgage or Hypothecary Insurance Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784958" lims:id="784958" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>beneficial ownership</DefinedTermEn> includes ownership through one or more trustees, legal representatives, agents or other intermediaries. (<DefinedTermFr>propriété effective</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784959" lims:id="784959" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>voting share</DefinedTermEn> means a share of any class of shares of a corporation carrying voting rights under all circumstances or because of an event that has occurred and is continuing or because of a condition that has been fulfilled. (<DefinedTermFr>action avec droit de vote</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784960" lims:id="784960" level="1"><TitleText>Designation of Qualified Mortgage Lenders</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784961" lims:id="784961"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784962" lims:id="784962">Designation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>To be designated as a qualified mortgage lender, a mortgage or hypothecary lender must meet the criteria set out in subsection 3(1) and, as applicable, subsections 3(2) and (3).</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784963" lims:id="784963"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784964" lims:id="784964">General criteria</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784965" lims:id="784965"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The mortgage or hypothecary lender must be</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784966" lims:id="784966"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a corporation whose articles do not restrict its powers to lend in the jurisdictions in which it operates; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784967" lims:id="784967"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>one of the following:</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784968" lims:id="784968"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a financially sound institution with at least $3,000,000 of unencumbered paid-up capital that is incorporated by or under an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784969" lims:id="784969"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a federal financial institution or an authorized foreign bank within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="B-1.01">Bank Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784970" lims:id="784970"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a trust, loan or insurance corporation that is incorporated and regulated by or under an Act of the legislature of a province, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784971" lims:id="784971"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>a cooperative credit society that is incorporated and regulated by or under an Act of the legislature of a province.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784972" lims:id="784972"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784973" lims:id="784973">Criteria for underwriting</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>To underwrite mortgage or hypothecary loans, the mortgage or hypothecary lender must, in addition to meeting the criteria set out in subsection (1),</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784974" lims:id="784974"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>have at least three years’ experience underwriting residential mortgage or hypothecary loans in Canada and the capability and resources to underwrite such loans and make loan commitments;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784975" lims:id="784975"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>be a subsidiary of a parent corporation that is a qualified mortgage lender and that meets the criteria set out in paragraph (a), if the parent corporation undertakes to fulfil the task of underwriting residential mortgage and hypothecary loans in Canada for the subsidiary and to be accountable to the approved mortgage insurer for the subsidiary’s performance in relation to those loans; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784976" lims:id="784976"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>have paid-up capital of at least $5,000,000 and employ at least two mortgage officers who each have a minimum of ten years’ residential mortgage or hypothecary underwriting experience and who are responsible for underwriting the lender’s residential mortgage and hypothecary loans in Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784977" lims:id="784977"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784978" lims:id="784978">Criteria for administering</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>To administer mortgage or hypothecary loans, the mortgage or hypothecary lender must, in addition to meeting the criteria set out in subsection (1),</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784979" lims:id="784979"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>have at least three years’ experience administering residential mortgage or hypothecary loans in Canada and the capability and resources to administer such loans and meet all insurance conditions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784980" lims:id="784980"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>be a subsidiary of a parent corporation that is a qualified mortgage lender and that meets the criteria set out in paragraph (a), if the parent corporation undertakes to fulfil the task of administering residential mortgage and hypothecary loans in Canada for the subsidiary and to be accountable to the approved mortgage insurer for the subsidiary’s performance in relation to those loans; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784981" lims:id="784981"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>have paid-up capital of at least $5,000,000 and employ at least two mortgage officers who each have a minimum of ten years’ residential mortgage or hypothecary administration experience and who are responsible for administering the lender’s residential mortgage and hypothecary loans in Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784982" lims:id="784982"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784983" lims:id="784983">Exception — designated cooperative credit societies</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A cooperative credit society referred to in subparagraph (1)(b)(iv) need not meet the criteria set out in subsection (2) to underwrite mortgage or hypothecary loans or in subsection (3) to administer them if, before the coming into force of these Regulations, it was designated as a qualified mortgage lender under an agreement as defined in section 43 of the Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784984" lims:id="784984" level="1"><TitleText>Reinsurance</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784985" lims:id="784985"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784986" lims:id="784986">Exceptions to reinsurance restrictions</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 11(2) of the Act, an approved mortgage insurer may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784987" lims:id="784987"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>cause itself to be reinsured against any risk that it has undertaken under its policies only if the reinsurer is also an approved mortgage insurer; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="784988" lims:id="784988"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>reinsure any risk that another insurer has undertaken under that insurer’s contracts of insurance only if those contracts of insurance are, or could be deemed under section 19 of the Act to be, policies.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784989" lims:id="784989" level="1"><TitleText>Conditions on Approved Mortgage Insurers</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784990" lims:id="784990"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784991" lims:id="784991">Restriction — substitution</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784992" lims:id="784992"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An approved mortgage insurer must not replace an insured mortgage or hypothecary loan with another mortgage or hypothecary loan under the same insurance coverage unless</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784993" lims:id="784993"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>both loans are made to the same borrower and the purpose of the new loan is to discharge the outstanding balance of the loan being replaced; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784994" lims:id="784994"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the new loan is made in relation to a loan workout whose purpose is to reduce or avoid losses on a real or potential mortgage or hypothecary insurance claim in respect of the outstanding loan being replaced.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784995" lims:id="784995"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784996" lims:id="784996">Restriction — portfolio insurance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An approved mortgage insurer that makes a commitment to insure a portfolio of mortgage or hypothecary loans up to a specified total value must not insure a mortgage or hypothecary loan in accordance with that commitment later than one year after the day on which the commitment is made.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784998" lims:id="784998">SOR/2015-108, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="784999" lims:id="784999" level="1"><TitleText>Persons or Entities in Prescribed Relationship</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785000" lims:id="785000"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785001" lims:id="785001">Nature of relationship</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 13(1)(c) of the Act, a person or entity is in a prescribed relationship with an approved mortgage insurer if that person or entity is a qualified mortgage lender and</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785002" lims:id="785002"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the mortgage insurer and any entities controlled by that mortgage insurer within the meaning of section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-11.8">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal> beneficially own in total more than 20 per cent of the outstanding shares of any class of the qualified mortgage lender’s voting shares; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785003" lims:id="785003"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>another person or entity and any entities controlled by that other person or entity within the meaning of section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="I-11.8">Insurance Companies Act</XRefExternal> beneficially own in total</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785004" lims:id="785004"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>more than 20 per cent of the outstanding shares of any class of the qualified mortgage lender’s voting shares, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785005" lims:id="785005"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>more than 20 per cent of the outstanding shares of any class of the approved mortgage insurer’s voting shares.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785006" lims:id="785006"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785007" lims:id="785007">Acting in concert</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785008" lims:id="785008"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 5, two or more persons or entities are deemed to be a single person or entity that beneficially owns the total number of shares or ownership interests that are beneficially owned by them if they have agreed, under any agreement, commitment or understanding, whether formal or informal, verbal or written, to act jointly or in concert in respect of any</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785009" lims:id="785009"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>shares of a qualified mortgage lender or of an approved mortgage insurer that they beneficially own;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785010" lims:id="785010"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shares or ownership interests that they beneficially own of any entity that beneficially owns shares of a qualified mortgage lender or approved mortgage insurer; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785011" lims:id="785011"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>shares or ownership interests that they beneficially own of any entity that controls any entity that beneficially owns shares of a qualified mortgage lender or approved mortgage insurer.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785012" lims:id="785012"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785013" lims:id="785013">Veto or consent</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of subsection (1), two or more persons or entities are deemed, for the purposes of section 5, to be a single person or entity that beneficially owns the total number of shares or ownership interests that are beneficially owned by them if they have entered into an agreement, commitment or understanding</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785014" lims:id="785014"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>by which any of them or their nominees may veto any proposal put before the board of directors of the qualified mortgage lender or approved mortgage insurer, as the case may be; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785015" lims:id="785015"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>under which no proposal put before the board of directors of the qualified mortgage lender or approved mortgage insurer, as the case may be, may be approved except with the consent of any of them or their nominees.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785016" lims:id="785016"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785017" lims:id="785017">Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Persons or entities are not presumed to have agreed to act jointly or in concert solely because</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785018" lims:id="785018"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>one is the proxyholder of one or more of the others in respect of shares or ownership interests referred to in subsection (1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785019" lims:id="785019"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>they exercise the voting rights attached to shares or ownership interests referred to in subsection (1) in the same manner.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785020" lims:id="785020"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785021" lims:id="785021">Prohibited policies — exception</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 14 of the Act, an approved mortgage insurer may be a party to a policy under which the beneficiary is a person or entity referred to in paragraph 13(1)(c) of the Act if, at least 60 days before that occurs, the Minister has been notified that the insurer is or expects to be in a prescribed relationship with that person or entity.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785022" lims:id="785022" level="1"><TitleText>Fees for Risk Exposure</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785023" lims:id="785023"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785024" lims:id="785024">Method of calculating</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785025" lims:id="785025"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The fees that an approved mortgage insurer must pay under section 9 of the Act with respect to a given calendar year are to be determined in accordance with the formula</Text><FormulaGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785026" lims:id="785026"><Formula lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785027" lims:id="785027"><FormulaText>A × 2.25%</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector><FormulaDefinition lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785028" lims:id="785028"><FormulaTerm>A</FormulaTerm><Text>is the total amount of direct premiums written by the approved mortgage insurer in respect of policies that it entered into during that calendar year.</Text></FormulaDefinition></FormulaGroup></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785029" lims:id="785029"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785030" lims:id="785030">Fees due and recoverable</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The fees are due and payable on March 1 of the following year and may be recovered as a debt due to Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785031" lims:id="785031" level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785032" lims:id="785032"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785033" lims:id="785033">Reduced capital requirement</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>For a period of one year beginning on the day on which these Regulations come into force, the amount of unencumbered paid-up capital required under subparagraph 3(1)(b)(i) is at least $1,000,000.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785034" lims:id="785034"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2013-01-01" lims:fid="785035" lims:id="785035">Reinsurance by company</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>An approved mortgage insurer that caused itself, before the day on which these Regulations come into force, to be reinsured by a company within the meaning of section 2 of the Act against a risk that it had undertaken under its contracts of insurance may, despite paragraph 4(a), continue to be reinsured against that risk by that company for a period of no more than three years beginning on the day on which these Regulations come into force.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:lastAmendedDate="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785036" lims:id="785036"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785037" lims:id="785037">Existing portfolio commitment</MarginalNote><Label>10.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785038" lims:id="785038"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 4.1(1) does not apply in respect of insurance coverage resulting from a commitment to insure a portfolio of mortgage or hypothecary loans up to a specified total value that is made before that subsection comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785039" lims:id="785039"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785040" lims:id="785040">Existing portfolio commitment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 4.1(2) does not apply in respect of a commitment that is made before that subsection comes into force.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785042" lims:id="785042">SOR/2015-108, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2015-05-15" lims:fid="785043" lims:id="785043" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2012-11-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2012-11-01" lims:fid="785044" lims:id="785044"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2012-11-01" lims:fid="785045" lims:id="785045"><HistoricalNote>S.C. 2011, c. 15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="fn_Ind4D13_hq_13581">*</FootnoteRef>11</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on the day on which section 20 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-25.5">Supporting Vulnerable Seniors and Strengthening Canada’s Economy Act</XRefExternal> comes into force, but if they are registered after that day, they come into force on the day on which they are registered.</Text><Footnote id="fn_Ind4D13_hq_13581" placement="section" status="editorial"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Regulations in force January 1, 2013, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2012-87.]</Text></Footnote></Section></Body></Regulation>