<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866466" lims:id="866466" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866467" lims:id="866467"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/79-817</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1979</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866469" lims:id="866469"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-10.4">CANADA TRANSPORTATION ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866470" lims:id="866470">By-laws Nos. 6 and 8 of VIA Rail Canada Inc.</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866471" lims:id="866471">By-Laws Nos. 6 and 8 of Via Rail Canada Inc.</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1979-2992</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1979</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866472" lims:id="866472"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866473" lims:id="866473" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Canadian Transport Commission, pursuant to section 233 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to sanction <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-79-817">By-laws Nos. 6 and 8 of VIA Rail Canada Inc.</XRefExternal> annexed hereto.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866474" lims:id="866474"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866475" lims:id="866475" level="1"><TitleText>Traffic Rules and Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866476" lims:id="866476"><Label>1</Label><Text>No person shall travel in any of the Company’s trains without having obtained from the Company, or from some other company or person duly authorized in that behalf by the Company, a ticket entitling him to travel therein.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866477" lims:id="866477"><Label>2</Label><Text>Every passenger shall show his ticket or his ticket receipt, when and so often as he shall be required to do so, to the conductor or any duly authorized servant or agent of the Company, and shall also, when required to do so, either deliver up his ticket or pay the fare demandable for his passage.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866478" lims:id="866478"><Label>3</Label><Text>Every passenger who refuses to pay his fare or produce and deliver up his ticket upon the request of the conductor may, by the conductor of the train and the train servants or agents of the Company, be expelled from and put out of the train with his baggage at any usual stopping place; provided that the conductor shall first stop the train and use no unnecessary force.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866479" lims:id="866479"><Label>4</Label><Text>No person shall alter or deface any ticket after it has been issued and while it is available for use or attempt to use any ticket which shall have been altered or defaced.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866480" lims:id="866480"><Label>5</Label><Text>No person, except a servant or agent of the Company in the performance of his duty, shall open any vestibule door or stand upon the steps or platform of any car while it is in motion, or entrain on or detrain from, or attempt to entrain or detrain from any such car while it is in motion; and no person shall, without authorization, travel or be in any baggage car or other car not intended for the conveyance of passengers.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866481" lims:id="866481"><Label>6</Label><Text>Passengers and all other persons using the trains, stations or other premises occupied by the Company, shall obey the reasonable requests of the Station Master, Conductor or other officer or agent of the Company, with a view to maintaining order and decorum therein and thereon.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866482" lims:id="866482"><Label>7</Label><Text>No passenger in a car shall occupy more seat space than is sufficient for one person or place his feet on a seat or place baggage or articles of any kind upon a seat to the exclusion or inconvenience of other passengers or in the aisles or vestibules, or place any unreasonably bulky or heavy parcel in a parcel rack.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866483" lims:id="866483"><Label>8</Label><Text>Except by permission of a duly authorized officer or agent of the Company, and under such conditions as such officer or agent shall impose, no person suffering or apparently suffering from any infectious or contagious disease or disorder shall enter or remain, and no person having the custody, care or charge of any such person shall cause of permit such person to enter or remain in or upon any train, station or other premises occupied by the Company.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866484" lims:id="866484"><Label>9</Label><Text>No person in a state of intoxication or in an unfit or improper condition to be a passenger shall enter or remain in or upon any train, station or other premises occupied by the Company, and any person violating this regulation may, in addition to any other liability thereby incurred, be forthwith removed from such train, station or other premises occupied by the Company.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866485" lims:id="866485"><Label>10</Label><Text>No person shall at any time while in or upon trains, stations or other premises occupied by the Company, use any threatening, abusive, indecent, profane or offensive language or gestures or behave in an abusive, disorderly, indecent or offensive manner, or commit any nuisance, or molest or otherwise interfere with the comfort or convenience of any person upon the Company’s premises, and any person violating this regulation may, in addition to any liability thereby incurred, be forthwith removed from such train, station or other premises occupied by the Company.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866486" lims:id="866486"><Label>11</Label><Text>No person shall take into a car, train, station or other property of the Company any article which may cause inconvenience or annoyance to other persons or damage to the property of the Company or that of other persons. No person shall take any dog, bird, reptile or any other animal into a car, train, station or other property of the Company without the permission of an employee or agent of the Company acting in the course of his duty.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866487" lims:id="866487"><Label>12</Label><Text>No person shall, without proper authority, take into any station or any car or vehicle upon the railway any loaded firearm, or any inflammable, corrosive or offensive article, substance or matter, or any article, substance or matter liable to explode or which may become dangerous to any passenger or property.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866488" lims:id="866488"><Label>13</Label><Text>No person shall smoke in a station or car or in any part of a station or car not provided for smoking or in or upon a part of the Company’s property where smoking is expressly prohibited by the Company or in or about a place where persons are requested by an employee or agent of the Company, acting in the course of his duty, to refrain from smoking.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866489" lims:id="866489"><Label>14</Label><Text>No person shall throw or let fall from a train or car any litter or article nor thing liable to cause a fire or injure, damage or endanger persons or property.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866490" lims:id="866490"><Label>15</Label><Text>No person shall write obscene or offensive words or make signs or pictures on the walls or any part of a car, train, station, platform or other property of the Company or commit a nuisance thereon, or damage, mark, deface a car, train, station, platform or other property of the Company or any part thereof.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866491" lims:id="866491"><Label>16</Label><Text>Except by permission of an officer or agent of the Company acting in the course of his duty, no person shall, while in or upon a car, train, station or other property of the Company, advertise, sell or expose or offer for sale any article or goods or distribute advertising or other literature or carry on, advertise, solicit or canvass for any business, trade, occupation, calling or employment, or solicit alms, reward or charity for himself or any other person.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866492" lims:id="866492"><Label>17</Label><Text>No person shall spit upon the floor or upon any part of any car or vehicle upon the railway, or upon the platform of any station or upon the floor or walls of any room or passage in any station.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866493" lims:id="866493"><Label>18</Label><Text>The parking of private or public vehicles on station and other premises of the Company is prohibited except at such places and under such conditions as may from time to time be designated by an employee or agent of the Company acting in the course of his duty. Every person in charge of any such vehicle shall obey the parking directions given by employees or agents of the Company acting in the course of their duty.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866494" lims:id="866494"><Label>19</Label><Text>Every person violating any of the foregoing rules and regulations shall be liable for every such offence to a penalty enforceable on summary conviction not exceeding Forty ($40) Dollars. If the violation or non-observance of any by-law, rule or regulation is attended with danger or annoyance to the public, or hindrance to the Company in the lawful use of the railway, the Company may, pursuant to section 236 of the Railway Act, summarily intervene, using reasonable force, if necessary, to prevent violation of any of the said rules or regulations, or to enforce observance, without prejudice to any penalty incurred in respect thereof.</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866495" lims:id="866495" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>PASSED AND ADOPTED as a By-Law of VIA Rail Canada Inc. this 20th day of September 1978.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866496" lims:id="866496" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[L.S.]</Text></Provision><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="866498" lims:id="866498">SOR/79-817 (By-law no. 8)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>