<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2023-08-17" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-08-17" lims:current-date="2023-08-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946224" lims:id="946224" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946225" lims:id="946225"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/92-48</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1991</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>8</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946227" lims:id="946227"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-3.01">OFFICIAL LANGUAGES ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946228" lims:id="946228">Official Languages (Communications with and Services to the Public) Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946229" lims:id="946229">Regulations Respecting Communications with and Services to the Public in Either Official Language</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1991-2541 </OrderNumber><Date><YYYY> 1991</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946230" lims:id="946230"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946231" lims:id="946231" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to section 84 of the Official Languages Act<FootnoteRef idref="fnstar1_e">*</FootnoteRef>, the President of the Treasury Board has sought the views of members of the English and French linguistic minority communities and members of the public generally on the proposed Regulations concerning communications with and services to the public in either official language;</Text><Footnote id="fnstar1_e" placement="page"><Label>*</Label><Text>R.S., c. 31 (4th Supp.)</Text></Footnote></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946232" lims:id="946232" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to section 85 of the said Act, the President of the Treasury Board has laid a draft of the proposed Regulations before the House of Commons on November 8, 1990, which date is at least thirty days before a copy of the proposed Regulations was published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> under section 86 of the said Act;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946233" lims:id="946233" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And Whereas, pursuant to section 86 of the said Act, the proposed Regulations were published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> on March 23, 1991, which date is at least thirty days before the proposed effective date thereof, and a reasonable opportunity was thereby afforded to interested persons to make representations to the President of the Treasury Board with respect thereto;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946234" lims:id="946234" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Treasury Board, pursuant to section 32 of the Official Languages Act<FootnoteRef idref="fnstar1_e">*</FootnoteRef>, is pleased hereby to make the annexed Regulations respecting communications with and services to the public in either official language.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946235" lims:id="946235"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946236" lims:id="946236" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946237" lims:id="946237"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-92-48">Official Languages (Communications with and Services to the Public) Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946238" lims:id="946238" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-08-17" lims:fid="946239" lims:id="946239"><Label>2</Label><Text lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1183976" lims:id="1185803">The following definitions apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946240" lims:id="946240" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-3.01">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946241" lims:id="1185805"><Text><DefinedTermEn>CMA</DefinedTermEn> means a census metropolitan area, excluding Ottawa-Gatineau, as used by Statistics Canada for the purposes of the most recent decennial census of population. (<DefinedTermFr>région métropolitaine de recensement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946242" lims:id="1185806"><Text><DefinedTermEn>CSD</DefinedTermEn> means a census subdivision, excluding any census subdivision or any part of a census subdivision within the National Capital Region, as used by Statistics Canada for the purposes of the most recent decennial census of population. (<DefinedTermFr>subdivision de recensement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946243" lims:id="1374344"><Text><DefinedTermEn>immigration services</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/2019-242, s. 1]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946244" lims:id="1374345"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Method I</DefinedTermEn><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/2019-242, s. 1]</Repealed></Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374346" lims:id="1374346"><Text><DefinedTermEn>regional economic development agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Atlantic Canada Opportunities Agency, the Economic Development Agency of Canada for the Regions of Quebec, the Canadian Northern Economic Development Agency, the Federal Economic Development Agency for Southern Ontario, the Federal Economic Development Initiative for Northern Ontario and the Department of Western Economic Diversification. (<DefinedTermFr>organisme de développement économique régional</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946245" lims:id="946245" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>route</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946246" lims:id="946246"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for the purposes of paragraphs 7(4)(c) and (d), a route on which a federal institution provides the travelling public with a transportation service by aircraft or train that is carried out by a single conveyance, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946247" lims:id="946247"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for the purposes of subsection 7(2) and paragraph 7(4)(e), a route on which a federal institution provides the travelling public with a two-way transportation service by aircraft, train or ferry between the starting and finishing points of a flight, train run or ferry crossing that is carried out by a single conveyance between those two points, with or without intermediate stops. (<DefinedTermFr>trajet</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946249" lims:id="946249">2001, c. 27, s. 273</HistoricalNoteSubItem><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185807" lims:id="1185807" lims:enactId="1179768">SOR/2019-242, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-08-17" lims:fid="1374347" lims:id="1374347"><Label>2.1</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 32(2)(a) of the Act and these Regulations, <DefinedTermEn>English or French linguistic minority population</DefinedTermEn> means all persons, in a province in which an office or facility of a federal institution is located, for whom the first language, or one of the first languages, learned at home in childhood and still understood, is the minority official language and those who speak the minority official language at home, as determined by Statistics Canada based on the published data from the most recent decennial census of population.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374349" lims:id="1374349" lims:enactId="1179776">SOR/2019-242, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946250" lims:id="946250" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Significant Demand</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-08-17" lims:fid="946252" lims:id="1374350"><Label>3</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/2019-242, s. 3]</Repealed></Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946257" lims:id="946257" level="2"><TitleText>Calculation of Population Numbers</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-08-17" lims:fid="946258" lims:id="1374352"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Part, the number of persons of the English or French linguistic minority population in a province, CMA, CSD or service area is equal to the total number of the persons for whom the first language, or one of the first languages, learned at home in childhood and still understood, is the minority official language and those who speak the minority official language at home, as determined by Statistics Canada based on the published data from the most recent decennial census of population.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374354" lims:id="1374354" lims:enactId="1179779">SOR/2019-242, s. 4</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946261" lims:id="946261" level="2"><TitleText>General Circumstances</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-08-17" lims:fid="946262" lims:id="946262"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946263" lims:id="946263"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 22(b) of the Act, there is significant demand for communications with and services from an office or facility of a federal institution in both official languages where</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946264" lims:id="946264"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located in a CMA that has at least 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population and is the only office or facility of the institution in the CMA that provides a certain service;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946265" lims:id="946265"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located in a CMA that has at least 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the office or facility is one of two or more offices or facilities of the institution in the CMA that provide the same services and those services are not available in both official languages at a proportion of those offices or facilities that is at least equal to the proportion of that population in the CMA to the total population in the CMA or, if the number representing that proportion of offices is equal to less than one, at at least one of those offices or facilities, the choice of which depends on</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946266" lims:id="1185808"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the distribution of the English or French linguistic minority population within the CMA,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946267" lims:id="1185809"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the mandate of the offices or facilities that provide those services, their clientele and their location within the CMA, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185810" lims:id="1185810"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the advice received after consultation with the English or French linguistic minority population that is served by those offices or facilities;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946268" lims:id="946268"><Label>(c)</Label><Text lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1183977" lims:id="1374355">the office or facility is located in a CMA that has a population of at least 1,000,000 persons, the office or facility is one of two or more offices or facilities of the institution in the CMA that provide any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (f)(i) to (viii) and those services are not available in both official languages at a number of offices or facilities equal to one plus a proportion of those offices or facilities that is at least equal to the proportion of the English or French linguistic minority population in the CMA, the choice of which offices or facilities depends on<LineBreak /></Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946269" lims:id="1185811"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the distribution of the English or French linguistic minority population within the CMA,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946270" lims:id="1185812"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the mandate of the offices or facilities that provide those services, their clientele and their location within the CMA, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185813" lims:id="1185813"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the advice received after consultation with the English or French linguistic minority population that is served by those offices or facilities;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946271" lims:id="1374356"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located in a CMA that has fewer than 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population and does not provide any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (f)(i) to (viii), and at that office or facility during a year at least 5% of the demand from the public for services is in the official language of that population;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374357" lims:id="1374357"><Label>(d.1)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located in a CMA that has fewer than 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population and the service area of the office or facility has at least one minority language primary or secondary public educational facility;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946272" lims:id="946272"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located in a CMA that has fewer than 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population and the service area of the office or facility has at least 5,000 persons of the linguistic minority population;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946273" lims:id="946273"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located in a CMA that has fewer than 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population and is the only office or facility of the institution in the CMA that provides</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946274" lims:id="1374358"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>services of a Service Canada Centre of the Department of Employment and Social Development,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946275" lims:id="1374359"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>services of a passport point of service,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946276" lims:id="1374360"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>services of a post office,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946277" lims:id="1374361"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>services of an office of the Business Development Bank of Canada,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946278" lims:id="1374362"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>services of an office of the Canada Revenue Agency,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946279" lims:id="1374363"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>services of an office of the Department of Canadian Heritage,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374364" lims:id="1374364"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>services of an office of the Public Service Commission, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374365" lims:id="1374365"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>services of a regional economic development agency;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946280" lims:id="946280"><Label>(g)</Label><Text lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1183978" lims:id="1374366">the office or facility is located in a CMA that has fewer than 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the office or facility is one of two or more offices or facilities of the institution in the CMA that provide any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (f)(i) to (viii) and those services are not available in both official languages at a proportion of those offices or facilities that is at least equal to the proportion of that population in the CMA to the total population in the CMA or, if the number representing that proportion of offices or facilities is less than one, at at least one of those offices or facilities, the choice of which depends on</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946281" lims:id="1185814"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the distribution of the English or French linguistic minority population within the CMA,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946282" lims:id="1185815"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the mandate of the offices or facilities that provide those services, their clientele and their location within the CMA, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185816" lims:id="1185816"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the advice received after consultation with the English or French linguistic minority population that is served by those offices or facilities;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946283" lims:id="946283"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD and</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946284" lims:id="946284"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the service area of the office or facility has at least 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population and the number of those persons is equal to at least 5 per cent of the total population of that service area,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946285" lims:id="946285"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the service area of the office or facility has at least 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946286" lims:id="946286"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the office or facility serves the CSD and is the only office or facility of the institution in the CSD that provides a certain service, the CSD has at least 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population and the number of those persons is equal to at least 5 per cent of the total population in the CSD, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946287" lims:id="946287"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the service area of the office or facility includes all or part of two or more provinces in which the languages of the English or French linguistic minority populations are not the same;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374367" lims:id="1374367"><Label>(h.1)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD and the service area of the office or facility has at least one minority language primary or secondary public educational facility;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946288" lims:id="946288"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has at least 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to at least 5 per cent and less than 30 per cent of the total population in the CSD, the office or facility is one of two or more offices or facilities of the institution in the CSD that provide the same services and those services are not available in both official languages at a proportion of those offices or facilities that is at least equal to the proportion of that population in the CSD to the total population in the CSD or, if the number representing that proportion of offices is equal to less than one, at at least one of those offices or facilities, the choice of which depends on</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946289" lims:id="1185817"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the distribution of the English or French linguistic minority population within the CSD,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946290" lims:id="1185818"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the mandate of the offices or facilities that provide those services, their clientele and their location within the CSD, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185819" lims:id="1185819"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the advice received after consultation with the English or French linguistic minority population that is served by those offices or facilities;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946291" lims:id="946291"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has at least 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to at least 30 per cent of the total population in the CSD and the office or facility is one of two or more offices or facilities of the institution in the CSD that provide the same services;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946292" lims:id="1374368"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has at least 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to less than 5% of the total population in the CSD, the office or facility does not provide any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (l)(i) to (ix) and at that office or facility during a year at least 5% of the demand from the public for services is in the official language of the English or French linguistic minority population;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946293" lims:id="946293"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has at least 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to less than 5 per cent of the total population in the CSD and the office or facility is the only office or facility of the institution in the CSD that provides</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946294" lims:id="1374369"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>services of a Service Canada Centre of the Department of Employment and Social Development,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946295" lims:id="1374370"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>services of a passport point of service,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946296" lims:id="1374371"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>services of a post office,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946297" lims:id="1374372"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>services of an office of the Business Development Bank of Canada,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946298" lims:id="1374373"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>services of an office of the Canada Revenue Agency,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946299" lims:id="1374374"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>services of an office of the Department of Canadian Heritage,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946300" lims:id="1374375"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>services of a detachment of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374376" lims:id="1374376"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>services of an office of the Public Service Commission, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374377" lims:id="1374377"><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>services of a regional economic development agency;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946301" lims:id="946301"><Label>(m)</Label><Text lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1183979" lims:id="1374378">the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has at least 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to less than 5% of the total population in the CSD, the office or facility is one of two or more offices or facilities of the institution in the CSD that provide any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (l)(i) to (ix) and those services are not available in both official languages at a proportion of those offices or facilities that is at least equal to the proportion of that population in the CSD to the total population in the CSD or, if the number representing that proportion of offices or facilities is less than one, at at least one of those offices or facilities, the choice of which depends on</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946302" lims:id="1185820"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the distribution of the English or French linguistic minority population within the CSD,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946303" lims:id="1185821"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the mandate of the offices or facilities that provide those services, their clientele and their location within the CSD, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185822" lims:id="1185822"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the advice received after consultation with the English or French linguistic minority population that is served by those offices or facilities;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946304" lims:id="1374379"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has at least 200 but fewer than 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to at least 5% of the total population in the CSD, the office or facility does not provide any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (l)(i) to (ix) and at that office or facility during a year at least 5% of the demand from the public for services is in the official language of the English or French linguistic minority population;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946305" lims:id="1374380"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has at least 200 but fewer than 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to at least 5% of the total population in the CSD, the office or facility is the only office or facility of the institution in the CSD that provides any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (l)(i) to (ix);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946306" lims:id="1374381"><Label>(p)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has at least 200 persons but fewer than 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to at least 5% of the total population in the CSD, the office or facility is one of two or more offices or facilities of the institution in the CSD that provides any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (l)(i) to (ix) and those services are not available in both official languages at a proportion of those offices or facilities that is at least equal to the proportion of that population in the CSD to the total population in the CSD or, if the number representing that proportion of offices is less than one, at least one of those offices or facilities, the choice of which depends on</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374382" lims:id="1374382"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the distribution of the English or French linguistic minority population within the CSD,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374383" lims:id="1374383"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the mandate of the offices or facilities that provide those services, their clientele and their location within the CSD, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374384" lims:id="1374384"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the advice received after consultation with the English or French linguistic minority population that is served by those offices or facilities;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946307" lims:id="1374385"><Label>(q)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the CSD has fewer than 200 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, the number of those persons is equal to at least 30% of the total population in the CSD and the office or facility provides any of the services referred to in subparagraphs (l)(i) to (ix);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946308" lims:id="1374386"><Label>(r)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that it serves, the number of persons of the English or French linguistic minority population in the CSD has not been determined by Statistics Canada, or cannot be disclosed by it for reasons of confidentiality, and at that office or facility during a year at least 5% of the demand from the public for services is in the official language of that population;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374387" lims:id="1374387"><Label>(s)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located outside a CMA and within a CSD, the number of persons of the English or French linguistic minority population in the service area of the office or facility cannot be determined by Statistics Canada because of the nature of the service area or cannot be disclosed by Statistics Canada for reasons of confidentiality, and at that office or facility during a year at least 5% of the demand from the public for services is in the official language of that population; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374388" lims:id="1374388"><Label>(t)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located on an island that is accessible only by boat or by plane and the English or French linguistic minority population is equal to at least 30% of the total population of the island.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946309" lims:id="946309"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 22(b) of the Act, there is significant demand for communications with and services from an office or facility of a federal institution in the official language that is not the official language of the English or French linguistic minority population where the office or facility is located in Canada and is not an office or facility at which there is significant demand in both official languages under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946310" lims:id="946310"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 22(b) of the Act, there is significant demand for communications with and services from an office or facility of a federal institution in an official language where the office or facility is located outside Canada and at that office or facility over a year at least 5 per cent of the demand from the public for services is in that language.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2023-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1420450" lims:id="1420450"><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraphs (1)(b), (c), (g), (h), (i), (j), (l), (m), (o), (p) and (q), there is significant demand for communications with and services from an office or facility of a federal institution in both official languages if there is currently a significant demand for communications with and services from the office or facility in both official languages under one of those paragraphs and the English or French linguistic minority population referred to in that paragraph has remained the same or has increased based on data from the most recent decennial census of population.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946311" lims:id="1251540"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections (1), (2) and (3) do not apply in respect of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1251541" lims:id="1251541"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>services described in paragraph 6(1)(a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1251542" lims:id="1251542"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an office or facility described in any of paragraphs 6(1)(b) and (e) and subsections 6(2) and 7(2) to (4).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185824" lims:id="1185824" lims:enactId="1179781">SOR/2019-242, s. 5</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946314" lims:id="946314" level="2"><TitleText>Specific Circumstances</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-08-17" lims:fid="946315" lims:id="946315"><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946316" lims:id="946316"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 22(b) of the Act, there is significant demand for communications with and services from an office or facility of a federal institution in an official language where</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946317" lims:id="946317"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the services provided by the office or facility are provided to a restricted clientele, the members of which are identifiable, those services are specifically intended for that clientele and at that office or facility over a year at least 5 per cent of the demand from that clientele for those services is in that language;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946318" lims:id="946318"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the office or facility provides ship-to-shore communications services, including coast radio station services and vessel traffic services, and at that office or facility over a year at least 5 per cent of the demand from the public for those services is in that language;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946319" lims:id="1374389"><Label>(c)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/2019-242, s. 6]</Repealed></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946320" lims:id="1374390"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located at a point of entry into Canada, other than an airport or a ferry terminal, in Ontario, Quebec or New Brunswick, and at that office or facility during a year at least 5% of the demand from the public for services is in the minority official language;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946321" lims:id="946321"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the office or facility provides search and rescue services from a vessel that has long-range capabilities or from an aircraft, the vessel or aircraft from which the service is provided is distinctively marked by the Department of National Defence or the Canadian Coast Guard as a search and rescue vessel or aircraft or is crewed by the Department of National Defence with personnel specially trained for search and rescue operations, and at that office or facility over a year at least 5 per cent of the demand from the public for those services is in that language; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946322" lims:id="946322"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the office or facility is a Royal Canadian Mounted Police detachment that provides services in a province to sections of the Trans-Canada Highway where there is a point of entry to another province that is officially bilingual, and over a year at least 5 per cent of the demand from the public for those services is in that language.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946323" lims:id="946323"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 22(b) of the Act, there is significant demand for communications with and services from an office or facility of a federal institution in both official languages where</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946324" lims:id="946324"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the office or facility provides ship-to-shore communications services, including coast radio station services and vessel traffic services, and the service area of the office or facility includes all or a portion of the Bay of Fundy, the St. Lawrence River or the Gulf of St. Lawrence up to the innermost limit of Cabot Strait, but not including Cabot Strait, and up to the southern limit of the Strait of Belle Isle, but not including the Strait of Belle Isle;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946325" lims:id="1185825"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the office or facility provides air traffic control services and related advisory services in circumstances in which either official language may be used in accordance with sections 602.133 and 602.134 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-96-433">Canadian Aviation Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946326" lims:id="1374391"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the office or facility is located at a point of entry into Canada, other than an airport or ferry terminal, in Ontario, Quebec or New Brunswick, and at that point of entry at least 500,000 persons come into Canada during a year; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946327" lims:id="946327"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the office or facility provides search and rescue services from a vessel that has long-range capabilities or from an aircraft, the vessel or aircraft from which the service is provided is distinctively marked by the Department of National Defence or the Canadian Coast Guard as a search and rescue vessel or aircraft or is crewed by the Department of National Defence with personnel specially trained for search and rescue operations, and the office or facility provides those services</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946328" lims:id="1185826"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in or over Ontario, Quebec or New Brunswick,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946329" lims:id="946329"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in or over Hudson Bay, Hudson Strait or James Bay, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946330" lims:id="946330"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in or over an area that falls within the boundaries of the Halifax Search and Rescue Region as set out in Annex 3B of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">National Search and Rescue Manual</XRefExternal>, published by the Department of National Defence and the Canadian Coast Guard, as amended from time to time.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2007-07-31" lims:fid="946332" lims:id="946332">SOR/2007-172, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185827" lims:id="1185827" lims:enactId="1179824">SOR/2019-242, s. 6</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2020-06-25" lims:fid="946333" lims:id="946333"><Label>7</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946334" lims:id="1251543"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 23(1) of the Act, there is significant demand for services to the travelling public, other than air traffic control services and related advisory services, from an office or facility of a federal institution in both official languages if the facility is an airport, railway station or ferry terminal or the office is located at an airport, railway station or ferry terminal and at that airport, railway station or ferry terminal over a year at least 5% of the demand from the public for services is in the minority official language.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946335" lims:id="946335"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 23(1) of the Act, there is significant demand for services to the travelling public from an office or facility of a federal institution in an official language where the office or facility provides those services on a route and on that route over a year at least 5 per cent of the demand from the travelling public for services is in that language.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946336" lims:id="946336"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 23(1) of the Act, there is significant demand for services to the travelling public, other than air traffic control services and related advisory services, from an office or facility of a federal institution in both official languages where the facility is an airport or the office is located in an airport and over a year the total number of emplaned and deplaned passengers at that airport is at least 1,000,000.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946337" lims:id="946337"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 23(1) of the Act, there is significant demand for services to the travelling public from an office or facility of a federal institution in both official languages where</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946338" lims:id="946338"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the facility is a railway station that serves the travelling public and</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946339" lims:id="946339"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is located in a CMA that has at least 5,000 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946340" lims:id="946340"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is located outside a CMA and within a CSD that has at least 500 persons of the English or French linguistic minority population and the number of those persons is equal to at least 5 per cent of the total population of the CSD;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946341" lims:id="946341"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the facility is a ferry terminal located in Canada and over a year the total number of arriving and departing passengers at that ferry terminal is at least 100,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946342" lims:id="946342"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the office or facility provides those services on board an aircraft</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946343" lims:id="946343"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>on a route that starts, has an intermediate stop or finishes at an airport located in the National Capital Region, the CMA of Montreal or the City of Moncton or in such proximity to that Region, CMA or City that it primarily serves that Region, CMA or City,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946344" lims:id="1185828"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>on a route that starts and finishes at airports both of which are located in Ontario, Quebec or New Brunswick, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946345" lims:id="1185829"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>on a route that starts and finishes at airports that are located in two of those provinces;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946346" lims:id="946346"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the office or facility provides those services on board a train</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946347" lims:id="1185830"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>on an interprovincial route that starts in, finishes in or passes through Ontario, Quebec or New Brunswick, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946348" lims:id="1185831"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>on a route that starts and finishes at railway stations both of which are located in Ontario, Quebec or New Brunswick; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946349" lims:id="946349"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the office or facility provides those services on board a ferry on a route on which over a year there are at least 100,000 passengers.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1251544" lims:id="1251544"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 23(1) of the Act, there is significant demand for services to the travelling public, other than air traffic control services and related advisory services, from an office or facility of a federal institution in both official languages if the office or facility is a train station or airport and is located in a provincial or territorial capital or the office or facility is located in an airport that is located in a provincial or territorial capital.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185833" lims:id="1185833" lims:enactId="1179833">SOR/2019-242, s. 7</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946350" lims:id="946350" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Nature of the Office</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946351" lims:id="946351" level="2"><TitleText>Health, Safety and Security of the Public</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946352" lims:id="946352"><Label>8</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 24(1)(a) of the Act, the circumstances that relate to the health, safety or security of members of the public are the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946353" lims:id="946353"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>where an office or facility of a federal institution provides emergency services, including first aid services, in a clinic or health care unit at an airport, railway station or ferry terminal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946354" lims:id="946354"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where an office or facility of a federal institution uses signage that includes words or standardized public announcements regarding health, safety or security in respect of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946355" lims:id="946355"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>passengers on aircraft, trains or ferries,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946356" lims:id="946356"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>members of the public at airports, railway stations or ferry terminals, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946357" lims:id="946357"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>members of the public in or on the grounds of federal buildings; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946358" lims:id="946358"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where an office or facility of a federal institution uses written notices or signage that includes words for alerting the public to hazards of a radioactive, explosive, chemical, biological or environmental nature or to other hazards of a similar nature.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185835" lims:id="1185835" lims:enactId="1179842">SOR/2019-242, s. 8(F)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946359" lims:id="946359" level="2"><TitleText>Location of the Office</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-08-17" lims:fid="946360" lims:id="946360"><Label>9</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 24(1)(a) of the Act, the circumstances that relate to the location of an office or facility of a federal institution are the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946361" lims:id="1185836"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>where the office or facility is located in a <DefinitionRef>park</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="N-14.01">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> or on land set aside as a national historic site under section 42 of that Act and the office or facility does not provide the services referred to in paragraph (b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946362" lims:id="946362"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where the office or facility is located in a park or on land referred to in paragraph (a), the office or facility is one of two or more offices or facilities in the park or on the land that provide the services of a post office and those services are not available in both official languages at at least one of those offices or facilities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946363" lims:id="946363"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where the office or facility is located in such proximity to a park or land referred to in paragraph (a) that it provides specific services for visitors to the park or land and those services are not available in that park or on that land;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946364" lims:id="1374392"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>where the office or facility is located in the Yukon Territory, serves the public generally and, of all offices or facilities of the institution in the Yukon Territory, is the office or facility at which over a year there is the greatest number of persons using the French language to request services;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946365" lims:id="1374393"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>where the office or facility is located in the Northwest Territories, serves the public generally and, of all offices or facilities of the institution in the Northwest Territories, is the office or facility at which over a year there is the greatest number of persons using the French language to request services; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1374394" lims:id="1374394"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>where the office or facility is located in Nunavut, serves the public generally and, of all offices or facilities of the institution in Nunavut, is the office or facility at which during a year there is the greatest number of persons using the French language to request services.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185838" lims:id="1185838" lims:enactId="1179844">SOR/2019-242, s. 9</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946366" lims:id="946366" level="2"><TitleText>National or International Mandate of the Office</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2022-08-17" lims:fid="946367" lims:id="946367"><Label>10</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 24(1)(a) of the Act, the circumstances that relate to the national or international mandate of an office of a federal institution are the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946368" lims:id="1251545"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>where the office is a diplomatic mission or consular post or an office of the Department of Citizenship and Immigration that is located in a diplomatic mission or consular post;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946369" lims:id="946369"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where the office is responsible for organizing or hosting an exposition, fair, exhibition, competition or game of national or international scope that is open to the public;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946370" lims:id="1374395"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where the office participates in an event referred to in paragraph (b); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946371" lims:id="1374396"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>where the office is located in a province at a point of entry into Canada, other than an airport, and which, among those points of entry into Canada for the same province, has the greatest number of persons coming into Canada during a year.</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2022-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946372" lims:id="1374397"><Label>(e)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, SOR/2019-242, s. 10]</Repealed></Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2020-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185840" lims:id="1251546" lims:enactId="1179851">SOR/2019-242, s. 10</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946373" lims:id="946373" level="2"><TitleText>Other Circumstances</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2023-08-17" lims:fid="946374" lims:id="946374"><Label>11</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 24(1)(b) of the Act, the circumstances in which it is reasonable that communications with and services from an office or facility of a federal institution be available in both official languages are the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946375" lims:id="946375"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>where the office or facility serves one or more entire provinces and those services are</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946376" lims:id="946376"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>correspondence services,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946377" lims:id="1420445"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>offered by means of toll-free long-distance telephone services, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946378" lims:id="1420446"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>offered by means of local telephone services, if the office or facility provides the same services by means of toll-free long-distance telephone services;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946379" lims:id="1420447"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where those communications and services are made available by the office or facility through an automated system accessible to the public and the communications and services are directly related to the operation of the system or consist of providing material or information that originated with the institution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946380" lims:id="1420448"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where those communications and services are the provision in an airport, railway station or ferry terminal of signage, including information display systems with respect to aircraft, train or ferry transportation services or baggage pick-up; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2023-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1420449" lims:id="1420449"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>where those communications and services are offered by the office or facility by means of video conferencing services.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2023-08-17" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1420452" lims:id="1420452" lims:enactId="1179858">SOR/2019-242, s. 11</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946381" lims:id="946381" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Contract for Services to the Travelling Public</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946382" lims:id="946382"><Label>12</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946383" lims:id="946383"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection 23(2) of the Act, services to the travelling public are the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946384" lims:id="946384"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>restaurant, cafeteria, car rental, travel insurance, ground transportation dispatch, foreign exchange, duty free shop and hotel services;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946385" lims:id="946385"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>self-service equipment, including automated banking machines and vending machines, and the provision of instructions for the use of public telephones and electronic games; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946386" lims:id="946386"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>passenger screening and boarding services, public announcements and the provision of other information to the public, and carrier services, including counter services for tickets and check-in but excluding carrier services in respect of buses provided at railway stations or ferry terminals.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946387" lims:id="946387"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a service referred to in subsection (1) is provided by means of printed or pre-recorded material, such as signs, notices and menus, car rental contracts and travel insurance policies for the travelling public, the material shall be provided in both official languages.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="946388" lims:id="946388"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where a service referred to in subsection (1) is provided by means other than those referred to in subsection (2), the service shall be offered to the travelling public by such means as will enable any member of that public to obtain those services in the official language of his or her choice.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185842" lims:id="1185842" lims:enactId="1179863">SOR/2019-242, s. 12(F)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946389" lims:id="1185843" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Ten-Year Review</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-25" lims:fid="946390" lims:id="1185844"><Label>13</Label><Text>The Minister must ensure that a review of these Regulations and their administration and operation is conducted 10 years after this section comes into force and every 10 years after that, and must cause a report on the review to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 30 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-25" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-25" lims:fid="1185846" lims:id="1185846" lims:enactId="1179865">SOR/2019-242, s. 13</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body><RecentAmendments><Amendment><AmendmentCitation>SOR/2019-242</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2023-08-17</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation>SOR/2019-242</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2022-08-17</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation>SOR/2019-242</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2020-06-25</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation>SOR/2019-242</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2019-06-25</AmendmentDate></Amendment></RecentAmendments></Regulation>