<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871507" lims:id="871507" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871508" lims:id="871508"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/81-568</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1981</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>10</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871510" lims:id="871510"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871511" lims:id="871511">Villeneuve Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871512" lims:id="871512">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Villeneuve Airport</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1981-1893</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1981</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871513" lims:id="871513"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871514" lims:id="871514" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, pursuant to section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to approve the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-81-568">Regulations respecting Zoning at Villeneuve Airport</XRefExternal> made by the Minister of Transport.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871515" lims:id="871515"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871516" lims:id="871516" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871517" lims:id="871517"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-81-568">Villeneuve Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871518" lims:id="871518" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871519" lims:id="871519"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871520" lims:id="871520"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871521" lims:id="871521" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means the Villeneuve Airport, in township 54, range 27, west of the Fourth Meridian, in the Province of Alberta; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871522" lims:id="871522" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871523" lims:id="871523" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from each end of a strip, which approach surface is more particularly described in Part III of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871524" lims:id="871524" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871525" lims:id="871525" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>outer surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary surface located above and in the immediate vicinity of the airport, which outer surface is more particularly described in Part IV of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface extérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871526" lims:id="871526" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means the rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport including the runway prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction, which strip is more particularly described in Part V of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871527" lims:id="871527" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from the lateral limits of a strip and its approach surfaces, which transitional surface is more particularly described in Part VI of the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871528" lims:id="871528"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the assigned elevation of the airport reference point is 2,227 feet above sea level.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871529" lims:id="871529" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871530" lims:id="871530"><Label>3</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all the lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, that are within the outer limits described in Part II of the schedule.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871531" lims:id="871531" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871532" lims:id="871532"><Label>4</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct on any land to which these Regulations apply any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of that point, any</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871533" lims:id="871533"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>approach surface;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871534" lims:id="871534"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>outer surface; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871535" lims:id="871535"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>transitional surface.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871536" lims:id="871536" level="1"><TitleText>Natural Growth</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871537" lims:id="871537"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where an object of natural growth on any land to which these Regulations apply exceeds in elevation any of the surfaces referred to in section 4, the Minister may make a direction that the owner or occupier of the land on which that object is growing remove the excessive growth.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871538" lims:id="871538" level="1"><TitleText>Disposal of Waste</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871539" lims:id="871539"><Label>6</Label><Text>No owner or occupier of any land to which these Regulations apply shall permit that land or any Part of it to be used for the disposal or accumulation of any waste, material or substance edible by or attractive to birds.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871540" lims:id="871540" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871541" lims:id="871541"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(ss. 2 and 3)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871542" lims:id="871542" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Description of the Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871543" lims:id="871543" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The airport reference point is a point commencing at the end of the centre line of runway 26L; THENCE westerly along the said centre line of runway 08R-26L for a distance of 1,752 feet, THENCE southerly and perpendicular to the said centre line of runway 08R-26L a distance of 2,050 feet to a point being the airport reference point.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871544" lims:id="871544" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Limits of Lands</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871545" lims:id="871545" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The following described boundaries are the outer limits of lands:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871546" lims:id="871546" format-ref="indent-2-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Commencing at the South-East corner of Section Thirty-six (36), Township Fifty-four (54), Range Twenty-seven (27), West of the Fourth Meridian; THENCE Northerly along the East boundary of said section to the North-East corner of the South-East quarter thereof; THENCE Westerly along the North boundaries to the South halves of Sections Thirty-six (36) and Thirty-five (35) and their productions across the intervening road allowance to the North-West corner of the South-West quarter of said Section Thirty-five (35); THENCE Southerly along the West boundary of the said quarter to the South-West corner thereof; THENCE Westerly along the North boundary of the North-East quarter of Section Twenty-seven (27) of said Township and Range and its production across the intervening road allowance to the North-West corner of said quarter; THENCE Southerly along the West boundary of said quarter of the South-West corner thereof; THENCE Westerly along the North boundary of the South-East quarter of said Section Twenty-seven (27) to the North-East corner thereof; THENCE Southerly along the West boundary of the said quarter and its production across the intervening road allowance to the North-West corner of Section Twenty-two (22) of said Township and Range; THENCE Westerly along the North boundary of the North-East quarter of Section Twenty-one (21) of said Township and Range and its production across the intervening road allowance to the North-West corner of said quarter; THENCE Southerly along the West boundaries of the East halves of Sections Twenty-one (21) and Sixteen (16) of said Township and Range to the South-East corner of the South-East quarter of said Sections Sixteen (16); THENCE Easterly along the south boundary of said quarter and its production across the intervening road allowance to the South-West corner of Section Fifteen (15) of said Township and Range; THENCE Southerly along the West boundary of Section Ten (10) of said Township and Range and its production across the intervening road allowance to the South-West corner thereof; THENCE Easterly along the North boundary of the North-West quarter of Section Three (3) of said Township and Range to the North-East corner of said quarter; THENCE Southerly along the East boundary of said quarter to the South-East corner thereof; THENCE Easterly along the North boundary of the South-East quarter of said Section Three (3) and its production across the intervening road allowance to the North-West corner of the South-West quarter of Section Two (2) of said Township and Range; THENCE Southerly along the West boundary of the said South-West quarter to the South-West corner thereof; THENCE Easterly along the South boundaries of said Section Two (2) and Section One (1) of said Township and Range and their productions across the intervening road allowances to the South-West corner of Section Six (6), Township Fifty-four (54), Range Twenty-Six (26), West of the Fourth Meridian and continuing Easterly along the South boundary of said Section Six (6) to intersect the Western limit of the road allowance along East boundary of the former Michel Indian Reserve No. 132 as shown on a plan of record in the Land Titles for the North Alberta Land Registration District as No. 1321 E.U.; THENCE Northerly along the said Western limit of said road allowance to intersect the North boundary of the South half of said Section Six (6); THENCE Easterly along the North boundary of the South half of said Section Six (6) and its production across the intervening road allowance to intersect the West limit of the highway as shown on a plan of record in the said Land Titles Office as No. 350 T.R.; THENCE Northerly along the said West limit to the North boundary of said Section Six (6); THENCE Easterly along the North boundary of the North-West quarter of Section Five (5) of said Township and Range and its production across the highway as shown on said Plan 350 T.R. to the North-East corner of the said North-West quarter; THENCE Northerly along the West boundary to the East half of Section Eight (8) of said Township and Range and its production across the intervening road allowance to the South-West corner of the South-East quarter of Section Seventeen (17) of said Township and Range; THENCE Easterly along the South boundary of the said South-East quarter to the South-East corner thereof; THENCE Northerly along the East boundaries of said Section Seventeen (17) and the South-East quarter of Section Twenty (20) of said Township and Range to the North-East corner of the South-East quarter of said Section Twenty (20); THENCE Westerly along the North boundary of the said quarter to the North-West corner thereof; THENCE Northerly along the East boundary of the North-West quarter of said Section Twenty (20) to the North-East corner thereof; THENCE Westerly along the North boundary of the said quarter and its production across the highway as shown on said Plan 7821436 to the West boundary thereof; THENCE Northerly along said West boundary of road Plan 7821436 and its production across the intervening road allowance to intersect the East boundary of the South-East quarter of Section Thirty (30); THENCE Northerly along the East boundary of said quarter to its intersection with the West boundary of road Plan 3949 T.R.; THENCE Northerly along the West boundary of said road Plan 3949 T.R. to intersect the North boundary of Section Thirty (30) of said Township and Range; THENCE Westerly along the North boundary of said Section Thirty (30) and to its production across the intervening road allowance to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871547" lims:id="871547" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Description of the Approach Surfaces</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871548" lims:id="871548" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The approach surfaces, shown on Department of Public Works Plan No. E1455 dated June 21, 1978, are surfaces abutting each end of the strips associated with the runways designated 08L-26R, 08R-26L, 16L-34R and 16R-34L and are described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871549" lims:id="871549" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 08L,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871550" lims:id="871550" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 26R,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871551" lims:id="871551" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 08R,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871552" lims:id="871552" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a surface abutting each end of the strip associated with runway approach 26L,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871553" lims:id="871553" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a surface abutting each end of the strip associated with runway approach 16L,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871554" lims:id="871554" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a surface abutting each end of the strip associated with runway approach 34R,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871555" lims:id="871555" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a surface abutting each end of the strip associated with runway approach 16R, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871556" lims:id="871556" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a surface abutting each end of the strip associated with runway approach 34L,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871557" lims:id="871557" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one foot measured vertically to 50 feet measured horizontally rising to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, 200 feet measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip, except at the end of runway approach 26L where 600 feet is measured vertically above the elevation at the end of the strip and 10,000 feet measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of each imaginary horizontal line being 1,250 feet from the projected centre line.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871558" lims:id="871558" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871559" lims:id="871559" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The outer surface, shown on Department of Public Works Plan No. E1455 dated June 21, 1978, is an imaginary surface located at a common plane established at a constant elevation of 150 feet above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point, except where that common plane is less than 30 feet above the surface of the ground, the imaginary surface is located at 30 feet above the surface of the ground.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871560" lims:id="871560" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Description of the Strips</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871561" lims:id="871561" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The strips, shown on Department of Public Works Plan No. E1455 dated June 21, 1978, are described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871562" lims:id="871562" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 08L-26R is 500 feet in width, 250 feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway and 4,400 feet in length, 200 feet extending beyond each end of the runway;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871563" lims:id="871563" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 08R-26L is 500 feet in width, 250 feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway and 4,300 feet in length, 200 feet extending beyond the end of runway approach 08R and 600 feet extending beyond the end of runway approach 28L;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871564" lims:id="871564" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 16L-34R is 500 feet in width, 250 feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway and 3,900 feet in length, 200 feet extending beyond each end of the runway; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871565" lims:id="871565" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 16R-34L is 500 feet in width, 250 feet being on each side of the centre line of the runway and 4,400 feet in length, 200 feet extending beyond each end of the runway.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871566" lims:id="871566" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Transitional Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="871567" lims:id="871567" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Each transitional surface, shown on Department of Public Works Plan No. E1455 dated June 21, 1978, is a surface consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of one foot measured vertically to seven feet measured horizontally at right angles to the centre line and centre line produced of each strip and extending upward from the lateral limits of each strip and its approach surface to an intersection with the outer surface or another transitional surface of an adjoining strip.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>