<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873700" lims:id="873700" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873701" lims:id="873701"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/82-468</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1982</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873703" lims:id="873703"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873704" lims:id="873704">Fort St. John Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873705" lims:id="873705">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Fort St. John Airport</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1982-1316</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1982</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873706" lims:id="873706"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873707" lims:id="873707" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, pursuant to section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to approve the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Regulations respecting Zoning at Fort St. John Airport</XRefExternal> made by the Minister of Transport.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873708" lims:id="873708"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873709" lims:id="873709" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873710" lims:id="873710"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-82-468">Fort St. John Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873711" lims:id="873711" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873712" lims:id="873712"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873713" lims:id="873713"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873714" lims:id="873714" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means Fort St. John Airport, in Townships 83 and 84, Range 18, West of the sixth Meridian, in the Province of British Columbia; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873715" lims:id="873715" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873716" lims:id="873716" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from each end of a strip, which approach surface is more particularly described in Part III of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873717" lims:id="873717" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873718" lims:id="873718" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>outer surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary surface located above and in the immediate vicinity of the airport, which outer surface is more particularly described in Part IV of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface extérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873719" lims:id="873719" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means the rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport, including the runway prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction, which strip is more particularly described in Part V of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873720" lims:id="873720" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from the lateral limits of a strip and its approach surfaces, which transitional surface is more particularly described in Part VI of the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873721" lims:id="873721"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the assigned elevation of the airport reference point is deemed to be 684.5 m above sea level.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873722" lims:id="873722" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873723" lims:id="873723"><Label>3</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all the lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, that consist of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873724" lims:id="873724"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the lands within, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873725" lims:id="873725"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the lands directly under that portion of an approach surface that extends beyond</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873726" lims:id="873726"><Text>the outer limits described in Part II of the schedule.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873727" lims:id="873727" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873728" lims:id="873728"><Label>4</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct on any land to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of that point, any</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873729" lims:id="873729"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>approach surface;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873730" lims:id="873730"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>outer surface; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873731" lims:id="873731"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>transitional surface.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873732" lims:id="873732" level="1"><TitleText>Natural Growth</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873733" lims:id="873733"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where an object of natural growth on any land to which these Regulations apply exceeds in elevation any of the surfaces referred to in section 4, the Minister may make a direction that the owner or occupier of the land on which that object is growing remove the excessive growth.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873734" lims:id="873734" level="1"><TitleText>Disposal of Waste</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873735" lims:id="873735"><Label>6</Label><Text>No owner or occupier of any land to which these Regulations apply shall permit that land or any part of it to be used for the disposal of any waste that is edible by or attractive to birds.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873736" lims:id="873736" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873737" lims:id="873737"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(ss. 2 and 3)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873738" lims:id="873738" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Description of the Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873739" lims:id="873739" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The airport reference point that is marked by a brass monument set in concrete is a point distant 121.894 m measured northeasterly from and perpendicular to the centreline of Runway 11-29 from a point thereon distant 1 083.078 m measured southeasterly along the said centreline from airport control monument 403, located on said centreline of approach 11, which said distances are ground level distances.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873740" lims:id="873740" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Limits of Lands</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873741" lims:id="873741" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The following described boundaries are the outer limits of lands:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873742" lims:id="873742" format-ref="indent-2-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the South East corner of Section 22, TWP. 83, RGE. 18, W6M; THENCE, Westerly along the Southerly limit of the said Section 22 to the south one quarter point of the said Section 22; THENCE, North Westerly to a point in the Westerly limit of the road allowance between the said Section 22 and Section 21, both of TWP. 83, RGE. 18, W6M radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, North Westerly to the intersection of the South Easterly limit of the approach surface to Runway 02 with East-West dividing line between the North East Quarter and South East Quarter of the said Section 21, TWP. 83, RGE. 18, W6M; THENCE, North Westerly on a grid bearing of 313°10′06″ to a point in the North Westerly limit of the said approach surface to Runway 02; THENCE, North Easterly on a grid bearing of 51°41′57″ along the said North Westerly limit of the approach surface to Runway 02 to the most South Westerly limit of the transitional surface; THENCE, North Easterly on a grid bearing of 43°44′58″ along the North Westerly limit of the said transitional surface on Runway 02 to the Northerly limit of the Alaska Highway; THENCE, Westerly along the said Northerly limit of the Alaska Highway to the South West corner of the remainder of the South West Quarter of Sec. 28, TWP. 83, RGE. 18, W6M; THENCE, Northerly along the West boundary of the said remainder of the South West Quarter, to the South East corner of Lot 3, Plan 22611; THENCE, Westerly along the said Northerly limit of the Alaska Highway to the South West corner of Lot 1, Plan 12565; THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly limit of Road No. 146 to the North West corner of Lot A, Plan 24272; THENCE, Westerly to the North East corner of Lot 1, Plan 22313; THENCE, Westerly along the Northerly limit of the said Lot 1, Plan 22313 to a point radially distant 4 000 m from airport reference point; THENCE, North Westerly to the South West corner of Block 24, Plan 12116 which point is in the Easterly limit of 75th Street; THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly limit of the said 75th Street and limit produced to intersection with the Northerly limit of 93rd Avenue; THENCE, North Easterly to the South East corner of the remainder of Lot 1, Plan 24424; THENCE, Northerly along the most Easterly limit of said remainder of Lot 1, Plan 24424 to the most Easterly North East corner of the said remainder of Lot 1, Plan 24424; THENCE, North Easterly to the East one quarter point of Section 5, TWP. 84, RGE. 18, W6M; THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly limit of the said Section 5, to the North East corner of the said Section 5; THENCE, Northerly along the Easterly limit of Section 8, TWP. 84, RGE. 18, W6M to intersection with the South Westerly limit of the approach surface to Runway 11; THENCE, North Easterly on a grid bearing of 43°10′46″ to a point in the North Easterly limit of the said approach surface to Runway 11; THENCE, North Westerly on a grid bearing of 321°42′37″ along the said North Easterly limit of the approach surface to Runway 11 to intersection with the East-West dividing line between the North West Quarter and South West Quarter of Section 9, TWP. 84, RGE. 18, W6M; THENCE, Easterly along the said dividing line in the said Section 9 to the centre of the said Section 9; THENCE, North Easterly to a point in the Westerly limit of Road No. 259 radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, North Easterly to a point in the North-South dividing line between the North West Quarter and North East Quarter of Section 10, TWP. 84, RGE. 18, W6M radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, Easterly to a point in the North-South dividing line between the North West Quarter and North East Quarter of Section 11, TWP. 84, RGE. 18, W6M radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, South Easterly to a point in the Westerly limit of Section 12, radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, South Easterly to the centre of Section 12, TWP. 84, RGE. 18, W6M; THENCE, Southerly along the North-South dividing line between the South West Quarter and South East Quarter of the said Section 12 to intersection with a line drawn from a point in the Westerly limit of Section 6, TWP. 84, RGE. 17, W6M at intersection with the South Easterly limit of approach surface to Runway 20, at a grid bearing of 313°10′06″; THENCE, South Easterly along the previously described line of grid bearing 313°10′06″ to the previously described point in the Westerly limit of Section 6, TWP. 84, RGE. 17, W6M; THENCE, South Easterly to a point in the East-West dividing line between the North West Quarter and South West Quarter of the said Section 6, radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, South Easterly to 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, South Easterly to a point in the Northerly limit of Section 31, TWP. 83, RGE. 17, W6M radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, Easterly along the said Northerly limit of the said Section 31 to the North One Quarter point of the said Section 31; THENCE, Southerly along the North-South dividing line between the East One Half and West One Half of the said Section 31 to the South One Quarter point of the said Section 31; THENCE, Southerly along the North-South dividing line between the North West Quarter and North East Quarter of Section 30, TWP. 83, RGE. 17, W6M to the centre of the said Section 30; THENCE, Westerly along the East-West dividing line between the North West Quarter and the South West Quarter of the said Section 30 to a point radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, South Westerly to the North East corner of Lot 7, Plan 3083; THENCE, Southerly along the Easterly limits of the said Lot , Plan 3083, and Parcel A (C. of T. # P38260) to the South East corner of the said Parcel A; THENCE, Westerly along the Southerly limit of the said Parcel A to the South West corner of the said Parcel A; THENCE, Southerly to the North West corner of Section 19, TWP. 83, RGE. 17, W6M; THENCE, Southerly along the Westerly limit of the said Section 19 to an intersection with the North Easterly limit of approach surface to Runway 29; THENCE, South Easterly on a grid bearing of 124°38′56″ along the said North Easterly limit of approach surface to Runway 29 to a point which lies at a grid bearing of 43°10′46″ from the South East corner of Lot 5, Plan 2913; THENCE, South Westerly along the previously described line of grid bearing 43°10′46″ to a point in the South Westerly limit of the said approach surface to Runway 29; THENCE, North Westerly on a grid bearing of 321°42′37″ along the said South Westerly limit of approach surface to Runway 29 to a point radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, South Westerly to a point in the Westerly limit of the road allowance between Section 23 and Section 24 both of TWP. 83, RGE. 18, W6M radially distant 4 000 m from the airport reference point; THENCE, Southerly along the said Westerly limit of the road allowance between the said Section 23 and Section 24 to the South East corner of said Section 23; THENCE, Westerly along the Southerly limit of the said Section 23 to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873743" lims:id="873743" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Description of the Approach Surfaces</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873744" lims:id="873744" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The approach surfaces, shown on Department of Transport Fort St. John Airport Zoning Plan No. (Z) B.C. 1427 dated January 20, 1981, are surfaces abutting each end of the strips associated with runways designated 02-20 and 11-29 and are described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873745" lims:id="873745" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 02 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; THENCE, such approach surface shall be contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and passing through the intersection of the East-West dividing line between the North East and South East Quarters of Section 21, TWP. 83, RGE. 18, W6M with the South Easterly limit of approach surface to Runway 02; THENCE, said approach surface shall slope upward at the above-specified slope of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and distant 15 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 2 400 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 298.68 m, measured vertically, above the elevation at the end of the strip;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873746" lims:id="873746" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 20 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; THENCE, such approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and passing through the intersection of the Easterly limit of road allowance between Section 1, TWP. 84, RGE. 18, W6M and Section 6, TWP. 84, RGE. 17, W6M with the South Easterly limit of approach surface to Runway 20; THENCE, said approach surface shall slope upward at the above-specified slope of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and distant 15 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 2 400 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 281.11 m, measured vertically, above the elevation at the end of the strip;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873747" lims:id="873747" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 11 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; THENCE, such approach shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and passing through the intersection of the Easterly limit of Section 8, TWP. 84, RGE. 18, W6M with the South Westerly limit of the approach surface to Runway 11; THENCE, said approach surface shall slope upward at the above-specified slope of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and distant 15 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 2 400 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 291.55 m, measured vertically, above the elevation at the end of the strip; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873748" lims:id="873748" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 29 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; THENCE, such approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and passing through the South East corner of Lot 5, North East Quarter Section 24, TWP. 83, RGE. 18, W6M, Peace River District, Plan 2913; THENCE, said approach surface shall slope upward at the above-specified slope of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and distant 15 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 2 400 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 285.15 m, measured vertically, above the elevation at the end of the strip.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873749" lims:id="873749" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873750" lims:id="873750" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The outer surface, shown on Department of Transport Fort St. John Airport Zoning Plan (Z) B.C. 1427 dated January 20, 1981, is an imaginary surface located at a common plane established at a constant elevation of 45 m above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point, except that, where that common plane is less than 9 m above the surface of the ground, the imaginary surface is located at 9 m above the surface of the ground.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873751" lims:id="873751" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Description of the Strips</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873752" lims:id="873752" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The strips, shown on Department of Transport Fort St. John Airport Zoning Plan No. (Z) B.C. 1427 dated January 20, 1981, are described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873753" lims:id="873753" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 02-20 is 300 m in width, 150 m being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and 2 161.53 m in length; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873754" lims:id="873754" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 11-29 is 300 m in width, 150 m being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and 2 622.08 m in length.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873755" lims:id="873755" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Transitional Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="873756" lims:id="873756" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Each transitional surface, shown on Department of Transport Fort St. John Airport Zoning Plan No. (Z) B.C. 1427 dated January 20, 1981, is a surface consisting of an inclined plane rising at a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 7 m measured horizontally at right angles to the centre line and centre line produced of each strip extending upward and outward from the lateral limits of each strip and its approach surfaces to an intersection with the outer surface or another transitional surface of an adjoining strip.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>