<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980966" lims:id="980966" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980967" lims:id="980967"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/96-249</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1996</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980969" lims:id="980969"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-7.8">CANADA-NOVA SCOTIA OFFSHORE PETROLEUM RESOURCES ACCORD IMPLEMENTATION ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980970" lims:id="980970">Nova Scotia Offshore Revenue Fiscal Equalization Offset Payments Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980971" lims:id="980971">Regulations Prescribing the Time and Manner of Making Fiscal Equalization Offset Payments in Respect of Offshore Revenue to Her Majesty in Right of Nova Scotia</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1996-631</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY> 1996</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980972" lims:id="980972"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980973" lims:id="980973" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Finance, pursuant to section 232 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-7.8">Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnotea_e">a</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-96-249">Regulations prescribing the time and manner of making fiscal equalization offset payments in respect of offshore revenue to Her Majesty in right of Nova Scotia</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="footnotea_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1988, c. 28</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980974" lims:id="980974"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980975" lims:id="980975" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980976" lims:id="980976"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-96-249">Nova Scotia Offshore Revenue Fiscal Equalization Offset Payments Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980977" lims:id="980977" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980978" lims:id="980978"><Label>2</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980979" lims:id="980979" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means  the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-7.8">Canada-Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980980" lims:id="980980" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>working day</DefinedTermEn> means a day that is not a Saturday or a holiday. (<DefinedTermFr>jour ouvrable</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980981" lims:id="980981" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980982" lims:id="980982"><Label>3</Label><Text>These Regulations apply in respect of payments or contributions that may be made under Part V of the Act in respect of a fiscal year referred to in sections 223 and 224 of the Act.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980983" lims:id="980983" level="1"><TitleText>Interim Estimates</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980984" lims:id="980984"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980985" lims:id="980985"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In respect of each fiscal year, the Minister of Finance shall make an estimate of the amount, if any, of the fiscal equalization offset payment that is payable to the Province under sections 224 and 225 of the Act for the fiscal year, not later than thirty days after the interim estimate of the amount, if any, of the fiscal equalization payment that is payable to the Province for the fiscal year under Parts I and VIII of the Fiscal Arrangements Act and the regulations made under that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980986" lims:id="980986"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an estimate made under subsection (1)</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980987" lims:id="980987"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>shows that a fiscal equalization offset payment is payable to the Province for a fiscal year, the Federal Minister shall pay to the Province on account of the amount that is finally payable in respect of that fiscal year an amount equal to one third of the amount so estimated, on the first working day following the fifteenth day of the months of May, November and March of that fiscal year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980988" lims:id="980988"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shows that the amount of the fiscal equalization offset payment payable to the Province in respect of a fiscal year should be adjusted, the Federal Minister shall make the payments referred to in paragraph (a) in accordance with the new estimate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980989" lims:id="980989"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the course of a fiscal year establishes that the payments to the Province made pursuant to the immediately preceding estimate in respect of that fiscal year should be adjusted, the Federal Minister shall</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980990" lims:id="980990"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>if any amount remains payable to the Province, pay that amount or adjust the remaining payments, if any, in respect of that fiscal year referred to in paragraph (a) in accordance with the new estimate, beginning with the first payment following the date of that estimate, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980991" lims:id="980991"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if an overpayment has been made to the Province, recover the amount of that overpayment before the end of the fiscal year</Text><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980992" lims:id="980992"><Label>(A)</Label><Text>from any amount payable to the Province under the Act, or</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980993" lims:id="980993"><Label>(B)</Label><Text>from the Province as a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada; and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980994" lims:id="980994"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>during the period following the end of that fiscal year and before the final determination for that fiscal year establishes that the payments to the Province made pursuant to the immediately preceding estimate in respect of that fiscal year should be adjusted, the Federal Minister shall</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980995" lims:id="980995"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>if any amount remains payable to the Province, pay that amount to the Province, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980996" lims:id="980996"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if an overpayment has been made to the Province, recover the amount of that overpayment in the month during which the estimate was made or in the following month,</Text><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980997" lims:id="980997"><Label>(A)</Label><Text>from any amount payable to the Province under the Act, or</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980998" lims:id="980998"><Label>(B)</Label><Text>from the Province as a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="980999" lims:id="980999" level="1"><TitleText>Final Computation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981000" lims:id="981000"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981001" lims:id="981001"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the time of the final computation by the Minister of Finance of the amount, if any, of the fiscal equalization payment that is payable to the Province for a fiscal year under Parts I and VIII of the Fiscal Arrangements Act and the regulations made under that Act, the Minister of Finance shall make the final computation of the fiscal equalization offset payment that is payable under the Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981002" lims:id="981002"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance shall make the final computation of the fiscal equalization offset payment under subsection (1) in respect of a fiscal year on the basis of the relevant information contained in the final computation of the fiscal equalization payment referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981003" lims:id="981003"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where, as a result of a final computation of the fiscal equalization offset payment made under subsection (1), there remains an outstanding amount payable to the Province in respect of a fiscal year, the Federal Minister shall pay to the Province the outstanding amount in the month during which the computation is made or within 45 days after the last day of that month.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981004" lims:id="981004"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where a final computation of the fiscal equalization offset payment made under subsection (1) discloses an overpayment to the Province in respect of a fiscal year, the Federal Minister shall recover the amount of that overpayment</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981005" lims:id="981005"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>from any amount payable to the Province under the Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981006" lims:id="981006"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>from the Province as a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981007" lims:id="981007"><Label>6</Label><Text>For greater certainty, notwithstanding anything in these Regulations, every fiscal equalization offset payment made under the Act is subject to such subsequent adjustments as, in the opinion of the Minister of Finance, are necessary because of any other changes made to equalization payments in respect of the fiscal year under Parts I and VIII of the Fiscal Arrangements Act and the regulations under that Act.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981008" lims:id="981008" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="981009" lims:id="981009"><Label>7</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on April 30, 1996.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>