<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019577" lims:id="1019577" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019578" lims:id="1019578"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/98-205</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1998</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019580" lims:id="1019580"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">FIREARMS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019581" lims:id="1019581">Aboriginal Peoples of Canada Adaptations Regulations (Firearms)</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1998-480</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1998</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>24</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019582" lims:id="1019582"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019583" lims:id="1019583" language-align="yes" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas, pursuant to section 118 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnotea_e">a</FootnoteRef>, the Minister of Justice had a copy of the proposed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-205">Aboriginal Peoples of Canada Adaptations Regulations (Firearms)</XRefExternal>, substantially in the annexed form, laid before each House of Parliament on November 27, 1996, which date is at least 30 sitting days before the date of this Order;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019584" lims:id="1019584" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Justice, pursuant to paragraph 117(u) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnotea_e">a</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-205">Aboriginal Peoples of Canada Adaptations Regulations (Firearms)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Footnote id="footnotea_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 1995, c. 39</Text></Footnote></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019585" lims:id="1019585"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019586" lims:id="1019586" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019587" lims:id="1019587"><Label>1</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019588" lims:id="1019588" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Aboriginal</DefinedTermEn> includes Indian, Inuit, Métis and beneficiaries under a land claims agreement referred to in section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="const">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019589" lims:id="1019589" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Aboriginal community</DefinedTermEn> means a traditional collectivity of Aboriginal people that has a distinctive culture that includes engaging in traditional hunting practices. (<DefinedTermFr>collectivité autochtone</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019590" lims:id="1019590" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>elder</DefinedTermEn> means an Aboriginal person who</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019591" lims:id="1019591"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is a member of an Aboriginal community; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019592" lims:id="1019592"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is recognized by the members of the Aboriginal community as having extensive knowledge of the culture and traditional practices of that community. (<DefinedTermFr>aîné</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019593" lims:id="1019593" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>leader</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is recognized by the members of an Aboriginal community as their representative. (<DefinedTermFr>dirigeant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019594" lims:id="1019594" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019595" lims:id="1019595"><Label>2</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, an Aboriginal individual is an individual who</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019596" lims:id="1019596"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is a member of one of the Aboriginal peoples of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019597" lims:id="1019597"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is a member of an Aboriginal community;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019598" lims:id="1019598"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>engages in the traditional hunting practices of the individual’s Aboriginal community; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019599" lims:id="1019599"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>for the purposes of applying these Regulations, other than section 20 of these Regulations, has made an application in accordance with section 3, 8 or 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal>, as adapted by section 6 of these Regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019600" lims:id="1019600"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to sections 4 to 20 of these Regulations, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> and any regulations made under that Act apply to Aboriginal individuals.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019601" lims:id="1019601" level="1"><TitleText>Adapted Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019602" lims:id="1019602"><Label>4</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 117(u) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>, sections 5 to 20 of these Regulations concern the manner in which certain provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> and the regulations made under that Act apply to the Aboriginal peoples of Canada, and adapt those provisions for the purpose of that application.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019603" lims:id="1019603" level="1"><TitleText>Application for a Licence</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019604" lims:id="1019604"><Label>5</Label><Text>Sections 3, 8 and 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal> are adapted such that a statement made by an Aboriginal applicant or by another Aboriginal person in accordance with any of those sections may be made</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019605" lims:id="1019605"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>orally, if the applicant or person is unable to make a written statement, in which case the oral statement shall be transcribed by a person acting on behalf of the applicant or person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019606" lims:id="1019606"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>by means of an interpreter, if the applicant or person is unable to communicate in English or French.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019607" lims:id="1019607"><Label>6</Label><Text>Sections 3, 8 and 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal> are adapted such that an application made by an individual who wishes to be subject to these Regulations must be accompanied by the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019608" lims:id="1019608"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a declaration that the individual</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019609" lims:id="1019609"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is a member of one of the Aboriginal peoples of Canada,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019610" lims:id="1019610"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is a member of an Aboriginal community, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019611" lims:id="1019611"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>engages in the traditional hunting practices of the individual’s Aboriginal community; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019612" lims:id="1019612"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>confirmation from an elder or a leader of the individual’s Aboriginal community that the individual is a member of that community and engages in the traditional hunting practices of that community.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019613" lims:id="1019613" level="1"><TitleText>Recommendations</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019614" lims:id="1019614"><Label>7</Label><Text>Sections 3, 8 and 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal> are adapted by adding the requirement that, if a chief firearms officer considers refusing to issue a licence to an Aboriginal applicant, the applicant shall be given an opportunity to submit to the chief firearms officer for consideration recommendations from an elder or leader of the applicant’s Aboriginal community regarding the importance to the applicant of engaging in traditional hunting practices.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019615" lims:id="1019615"><Label>8</Label><Text>Section 55 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is adapted by adding the requirement that, in determining whether an Aboriginal applicant is eligible to hold a licence under section 5 of that Act, a chief firearms officer shall consider any recommendations submitted by the applicant from an elder or leader of the applicant’s Aboriginal community regarding the importance to the applicant of engaging in traditional hunting practices.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019616" lims:id="1019616"><Label>9</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019617" lims:id="1019617"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 58(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is adapted by adding the requirement that, if a chief firearms officer considers attaching a condition to a licence for an Aboriginal applicant, the applicant shall be given an opportunity to submit to the chief firearms officer for consideration recommendations from an elder or leader of the applicant’s Aboriginal community regarding the importance to the applicant of engaging in traditional hunting practices.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019618" lims:id="1019618"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply with respect to the condition referred to in section 15 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Firearms Licences Regulations.</XRefExternal></Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019619" lims:id="1019619" level="1"><TitleText>Issuance of a Licence to Aboriginal Individuals Less than 18 Years Old</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019620" lims:id="1019620"><Label>10</Label><Text>Subsection 64(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is adapted as follows:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019621" lims:id="1019621"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a licence that is issued to an Aboriginal individual who is less than 18 years old expires on the earlier of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019622" lims:id="1019622"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the day on which the holder attains the age of 18 years, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019623" lims:id="1019623"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subject to paragraph (b), three years after the day on which it is issued; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019624" lims:id="1019624"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if a chief firearms officer determines that it is desirable to do so, taking into account the applicant’s circumstances, character and age, the chief firearms officer may issue a licence for a term that is less than three years.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019625" lims:id="1019625"><Label>11</Label><Text>Subsection 8(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is adapted such that an Aboriginal individual who is less than 12 years old is eligible to hold a licence authorizing the individual to possess, in accordance with the conditions attached to the licence, a firearm for the purpose of engaging in the traditional hunting practices of the individual’s Aboriginal community.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019626" lims:id="1019626" level="1"><TitleText>Alternative Certification</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019627" lims:id="1019627"><Label>12</Label><Text>With respect to an Aboriginal individual who is at least 18 years old, paragraph 7(4)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is adapted such that a chief firearms officer shall certify, in the prescribed circumstances, such an individual who meets the prescribed criteria relating to the safe handling and use of firearms and the laws relating to firearms.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019628" lims:id="1019628"><Label>13</Label><Text>With respect to an Aboriginal individual who is at least 18 years old, section 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal> is adapted such that, for the purposes of paragraph 7(4)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>, as adapted by section 12 of these Regulations, the circumstances are that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019629" lims:id="1019629"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the individual is an elder; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019630" lims:id="1019630"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the chief firearms officer has received a recommendation from an elder or leader of the individual’s Aboriginal community indicating that, in their opinion, the individual has the requisite knowledge to be certified under paragraph 7(4)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>, as adapted by section 12 of these Regulations, and the Canadian Firearms Safety Course or the tests that form part of that Course are not available</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019631" lims:id="1019631"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to the individual within a time, after the individual has made the application for a licence, that is reasonable in the circumstances,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019632" lims:id="1019632"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the individual’s community or at a location that can be reached from that community without undue cost or hardship to the individual, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019633" lims:id="1019633"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>at a cost that is reasonable in the circumstances.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019634" lims:id="1019634"><Label>14</Label><Text>With respect to an Aboriginal individual who is at least 18 years old, section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal> is adapted such that, for the purposes of paragraph 7(4)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>, as adapted by section 12 of these Regulations, the criteria are</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019635" lims:id="1019635"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>basic knowledge of the safe storage, display, handling, transportation and use of firearms by individuals, including the operation of common hunting firearms; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019636" lims:id="1019636"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>basic knowledge of the laws that relate to the use of firearms and to the storage, display, handling and transportation of firearms by individuals.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019637" lims:id="1019637"><Label>15</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019638" lims:id="1019638"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>With respect to an Aboriginal individual who is less than 18 years old, the portion of subsection 7(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (b) is adapted such that subsection 7(1) of that Act does not apply to such an individual who, in the prescribed circumstances, has been certified by a chief firearms officer as meeting the prescribed criteria relating to the safe handling and use of firearms and the laws relating to firearms.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019639" lims:id="1019639"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, if an Aboriginal individual has been certified in accordance with subsection (1), subsection 7(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> applies to that individual when the individual reaches 18 years of age.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019640" lims:id="1019640"><Label>16</Label><Text>With respect to an Aboriginal individual who is less than 18 years old, section 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal> is adapted such that, for the purposes of paragraph 7(4)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>, as adapted by section 15 of these Regulations, the circumstances are that the chief firearms officer has received a recommendation from any of the following persons indicating that, in that person’s opinion, the individual has the requisite knowledge to be certified under paragraph 7(4)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> as adapted by section 15 of these Regulations, namely,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019641" lims:id="1019641"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an elder of the individual’s Aboriginal community;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019642" lims:id="1019642"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a leader of the individual’s Aboriginal community; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019643" lims:id="1019643"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person who is at least 18 years of age, who has personal knowledge of the individual within the six-month period preceding the application for a licence, and who</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019644" lims:id="1019644"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>has been certified by a chief firearms officer, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019645" lims:id="1019645"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>has complied with paragraph 7(1)(a) or (b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019646" lims:id="1019646"><Label>17</Label><Text>With respect to an Aboriginal individual who is less than 18 years old, section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal> is adapted such that, for the purposes of paragraph 7(4)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>, as adapted by section 15 of these Regulations, the criteria are</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019647" lims:id="1019647"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>basic knowledge of the safe storage, handling, transportation and use of firearms by individuals, including the operation of common hunting firearms; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019648" lims:id="1019648"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>basic knowledge of the laws that relate to the use of firearms and to the storage, handling and transportation of firearms by individuals.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019649" lims:id="1019649" level="1"><TitleText>Possession of Firearms</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019650" lims:id="1019650"><Label>18</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(4)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is adapted such that, if an Aboriginal individual had, on the commencement day, in order to engage in traditional hunting practices, the use of a firearm that is neither a prohibited firearm nor a restricted firearm, the individual is deemed to possess a firearm for the purposes of that paragraph.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019651" lims:id="1019651"><Label>19</Label><Text>Subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-199">Firearms Licences Regulations</XRefExternal> is adapted such that, if an Aboriginal individual has had, in order to engage in traditional hunting practices, the continuous use of a firearm that is neither a prohibited firearm nor a restricted firearm from the day on which paragraph 7(4)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> came into force, that individual is deemed to possess a firearm for the purposes of that subsection.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019652" lims:id="1019652" level="1"><TitleText>Transfer of Treaty Ammunition</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019653" lims:id="1019653"><Label>20</Label><Text>Section 21 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is adapted such that “transfer” does not include the provision of ammunition by Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province in fulfilment of a treaty obligation.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019654" lims:id="1019654" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019655" lims:id="1019655" type="transitional"><Label>21</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on December 1, 1998.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="1019657" lims:id="1019657"><Emphasis style="regular">SOR/98-471, s. 15.</Emphasis></HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>