<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874753" lims:id="874753" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874754" lims:id="874754"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/82-712</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1982</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>16</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874756" lims:id="874756"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874757" lims:id="874757">Fort Nelson Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874758" lims:id="874758">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Fort Nelson Airport</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1982-2149</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1982</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874759" lims:id="874759"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874760" lims:id="874760" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, pursuant to section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to approve the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-82-712">Regulations respecting Zoning at Fort Nelson Airport</XRefExternal> made by the Minister of Transport.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874761" lims:id="874761"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874762" lims:id="874762" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874763" lims:id="874763"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-82-712">Fort Nelson Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874764" lims:id="874764" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874765" lims:id="874765"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874766" lims:id="874766"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874767" lims:id="874767" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means the Fort Nelson Airport, near the Village of Fort Nelson, Peace River District, in the Province of British Columbia; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874768" lims:id="874768" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874769" lims:id="874769" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from each end of a strip, which approach surface is more particularly described in Part III of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874770" lims:id="874770" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874771" lims:id="874771" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>outer surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary surface located above and in the immediate vicinity of the airport, which outer surface is more particularly described in Part IV of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface extérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874772" lims:id="874772" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means the rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport, including the runway prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction, which strip is more particularly described in Part V of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874773" lims:id="874773" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from the lateral limits of a strip and its approach surfaces, which transitional surface is more particularly described in Part VI of the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874774" lims:id="874774"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the assigned elevation of the airport reference point is deemed to be 373.68 m above sea level.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874775" lims:id="874775" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874776" lims:id="874776"><Label>3</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all the lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, that consist of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874777" lims:id="874777"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the lands within, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874778" lims:id="874778"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the lands directly under that portion of an approach surface that extends beyond</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874779" lims:id="874779"><Text>the outer limits described in Part II of the schedule.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874780" lims:id="874780" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874781" lims:id="874781"><Label>4</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct, on any land to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of that point</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874782" lims:id="874782"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the approach surface;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874783" lims:id="874783"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the outer surface; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874784" lims:id="874784"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the transitional surface.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874785" lims:id="874785" level="1"><TitleText>Natural Growth</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874786" lims:id="874786"><Label>5</Label><Text>Where an object of natural growth on any land to which these Regulations apply exceeds in elevation any of the surfaces referred to in paragraphs 4(a) to (c), the Minister may make a direction that the owner or occupier of the land on which that object is growing remove the excessive growth.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874787" lims:id="874787" level="1"><TitleText>Disposal of Waste</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874788" lims:id="874788"><Label>6</Label><Text>No owner or occupier of any land to which these Regulations apply shall permit such land or any part of it to be used for the disposal of any waste edible by or attractive to birds.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874789" lims:id="874789" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874790" lims:id="874790"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(ss. 2 and 3)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874791" lims:id="874791" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Description of the Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874792" lims:id="874792" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The airport reference point is the point of intersection of a line lying southeasterly from, parallel to and perpendicular distant 91.44 m from the centre line of strip 03-21 and a line lying south-westerly from, parallel to and perpendicular distant 91.44 m from the centre line of strip 07-25 and has U.T.M. Coordinates of 6521809.94N and 523363.24E and is identified by Department of Transport Monument No. 802303.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874793" lims:id="874793" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Limits of Lands</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874794" lims:id="874794" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The following described boundaries are the outer limits of lands:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874795" lims:id="874795" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the most northerly corner of Block “G”, of District Lot 1535, of the Peace River District; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 0°00′00″, to a point of intersection with the southerly boundary of Lot 2810, Peace River District; THENCE, north- easterly to a point of intersection with the northerly boundary of Lot 2811, Peace River District, said point of intersection being 4 000 m distant from the airport reference point; THENCE, northeasterly and along the arc of a circular curve to the right having a radius of 4 000 m and centered on the airport reference point to a point of intersection with the northerly limit of the approach surface associated with Runway 21; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 47°58′11″ and along the said approach surface to a point, said point being perpendicular to a point that is 4 000 m distant from the airport reference point and on the centre line of the said approach surface; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 146°30′02″ and perpendicular to the said centre line of the said approach surface to a point of intersection with the southerly limit of the said approach surface; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 245°01′53″ and along the said southerly limit of the approach surface to a point that is 4 000 m distant from the airport reference point; THENCE, southeasterly and along the arc of a circular curve to the right having a radius of 4 000 m and centred on the airport reference point to a point of intersection with the northerly limit of the approach surface associated with Runway 25; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 95°58′37″ and along the said northerly limit of the said approach surface to a point, said point being perpendicular to a point that is 4 000 m distant from the airport reference point and on the centre line of the said approach surface; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 191°41′15″ and perpendicular to the said centre line of the said approach surface to a point of intersection with the southerly limit of the said approach surface; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 287°23′53″ and along the said southerly limit of the said approach surface to a point that is 4 000 m distant from the airport reference point; THENCE, southwesterly and along the arc of a circular curve to the right having a radius of 4 000 m to a point of intersection with the southerly high water mark of the Muskwa River; THENCE, northwesterly and along the southerly high water mark of the Muskwa River to a point of intersection with the southerly production of the westerly boundary of Block “H”, of Disctict Lot 1535, Peace River District; THENCE, northwesterly and along the said southerly production and the said westerly boundary of Block “H” to a point 4 000 m distant from the airport reference point; THENCE, northwesterly and along the arc of a circular curve to the right having a radius of 4 000 m and centered on the airport reference point to the point of intersection with the southerly limit of the approach surface associated with Runway 03; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 227°58′11″ and along the said southerly limit of the said approach surface to a point, said point being perpendicular to a point that is 4 000 m distant from the airport reference point and on the centre line of the said approach surface; THENCE, on a grid azimuth of 326°30′02″ and perpendicular to the centre line of the said approach surface to a point of intersection with the northerly boundary of Airport Road; THENCE, easterly and along the said northerly boundary of Airport Road to the most easterly corner of Block “G”, District Lot 1535, Peace River District; THENCE, northwesterly and along the easterly boundary of the said Block “G” to the point of commencement.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874796" lims:id="874796" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Description of the Approach Surfaces</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874797" lims:id="874797" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The approach surfaces, shown on Department of Transport Fort Nelson Airport Zoning Plan No. B.C. 1421 dated December 31, 1980, are surfaces abutting each end of the strips associated with runways designated 03-21 and 07-25 and are described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874798" lims:id="874798" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 03 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; THENCE, such approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface until it reaches the south-westerly boundary thereof; THENCE, said approach surface shall slope upward at the above-specified slope of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and distant 15 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 2 400 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 283.89 m, measured vertically, above the elevation at the end of the strip;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874799" lims:id="874799" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 21 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; THENCE, such approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface until it reaches the north-easterly boundary thereof; THENCE, said approach surface shall slope upward at the above-specified slope of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and distant 15 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 2 400 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 272.92 m, measured vertically, above the elevation at the end of the strip;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874800" lims:id="874800" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 07 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1.25 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; THENCE, such approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface until it reaches an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and distant 3 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 375 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 37.68 m, measured vertically, above the elevation at the end of the strip; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874801" lims:id="874801" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 25 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1.25 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; THENCE, such approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface until it reaches the south-easterly boundary thereof; THENCE, said approach surface shall slope upward at the above-specified slope of 1.25 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line and distant 3 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 375 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 49.42 m, measured vertically, above the elevation at the end of the strip.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874802" lims:id="874802" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874803" lims:id="874803" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The outer surface, shown on Department of Transport Fort Nelson Airport Zoning Plan B.C. 1421 dated December 31, 1980, is an imaginary surface located at a common plane established at a constant elevation of 45 m above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point, except where that common plane is less than 9 m above the surface of the ground, an imaginary surface is located at 9 m above the surface of the ground.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874804" lims:id="874804" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Description of the Strips</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874805" lims:id="874805" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The strips, shown on Department of Transport Fort Nelson Airport Zoning Plan No. B.C. 1421, dated December 31, 1980, are described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874806" lims:id="874806" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 03-21, being 300 m in width, 150 m being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and 2 071.41 m in length; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874807" lims:id="874807" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 07-25, being 150 m in width, 75 m being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and 1 537.55 m in length.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874808" lims:id="874808" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Transitional Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="874809" lims:id="874809" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Each transitional surface, shown on Department of Transport Fort Nelson Airport Zoning Plan No. B.C. 1421 dated December 31, 1980, is a surface consisting of an inclined plane rising at a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 7 m measured horizontally at right angles to the centre line and centre line produced of each strip extending upward and outward from the lateral limits of each strip and its approach surfaces to an intersection with the outer surface or another transitional surface of an adjoining strip.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>