<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2010-03-26" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767591" lims:id="767591" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767592" lims:id="767592"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2010-67</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2010</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767594" lims:id="767594"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="N-14.01">CANADA NATIONAL PARKS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767595" lims:id="767595">Wapusk National Park of Canada Park Use Regulations</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>2010-386</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>2010</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767596" lims:id="767596"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767597" lims:id="767597" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of the Environment, pursuant of sections 16 and 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="N-14.01">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="fn_607693-E_hq_4896">a</FootnoteRef>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-2010-67">Wapusk National Park of Canada Park Use Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text><Footnote id="fn_607693-E_hq_4896" placement="page" status="official"><Label>a</Label><Text>S.C. 2000, c. 32</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767598" lims:id="767598"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767599" lims:id="767599" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767600" lims:id="767600"><Label>1</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in these Regulations.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767601" lims:id="767601" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act.</XRefExternal> (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767602" lims:id="767602" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>all-terrain vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means a tracked, wheeled or air-cushioned motorized vehicle designed for travel over trails, marshlands, muskeg, sand, snow or trackless terrain, but does not include a tundra vehicle. (<DefinedTermFr>véhicule tout-terrain</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767603" lims:id="767603" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>caribou</DefinedTermEn> means a member of the genus <Emphasis style="italic">Rangifer</Emphasis> and includes any part or any derivative of such animal. (<DefinedTermFr>caribou</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767604" lims:id="767604" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Chief Executive Officer</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-0.4">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal>. (<Emphasis style="italic"><DefinedTermFr>directeur général</DefinedTermFr></Emphasis>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767605" lims:id="767605" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>fur-bearing animal</DefinedTermEn> means an animal of the following species or type or any part or any derivative of such animal: beaver, short-tailed weasel, long-tailed weasel, coyote, fisher, arctic fox, red fox, river otter, badger, bobcat, marten, mink, muskrat, red squirrel, wolverine, raccoon and lynx. (<DefinedTermFr>animal à fourrure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767606" lims:id="767606" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>local use permit</DefinedTermEn> means a permit issued under section 6. (<DefinedTermFr>permis d’utilisation locale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767607" lims:id="767607" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>local user</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767608" lims:id="767608"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any person who has resided in the Local Government District of Churchill or in any settlement along the Hudson Bay Railway from Bird northward for at least five consecutive years within the period that began on April 24, 1976 and ended on April 24, 1996, and for at least six consecutive months at the time of making an application for recognition as a local user; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767609" lims:id="767609"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any person who is a son or daughter of, or an individual adopted in fact by, a person described in paragraph (a). (<DefinedTermFr>utilisateur local</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767610" lims:id="767610" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Manitoba trapping permit</DefinedTermEn> means a permit issued by Manitoba to a resident of Manitoba that authorizes them to trap fur-bearing animals on a registered trapline in the park. (<DefinedTermFr>permis de piégeage du Manitoba</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767611" lims:id="767611" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>park</DefinedTermEn> means Wapusk National Park of Canada. (<DefinedTermFr>parc</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767612" lims:id="767612" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>resource harvest cabin</DefinedTermEn> means a rudimentary building in the park that is used primarily for the carrying out of traditional activities and for the exercise of the rights referred to in subsection 2(2) of the Act. (<DefinedTermFr>cabane de récolte des ressources</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767613" lims:id="767613" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>species</DefinedTermEn> includes a subspecies, variety or geographically or genetically distinct population of an animal or plant. (<DefinedTermFr>espèce</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767614" lims:id="767614" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>traditional activity</DefinedTermEn> means any of the activities described in paragraphs 3(a) to (c). (<DefinedTermFr>activité traditionnelle</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767615" lims:id="767615" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>tundra vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means any tracked or wheeled motorized vehicle designed to provide enclosed seating or accommodation for at least 10 passengers and designed or adapted for cross-country travel on land, wetlands, snow or ice. (<DefinedTermFr>véhicule de toundra</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767616" lims:id="767616" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767617" lims:id="767617"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency between these Regulations and any other regulations made under the Act, these Regulations prevail to the extent of the inconsistency.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767618" lims:id="767618" level="1"><TitleText>Traditional Activities</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767619" lims:id="767619"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 17 of the Act, the following activities that are carried out in the park are traditional renewable resource harvesting activities:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767620" lims:id="767620"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the gathering of berries, deadwood, flowers and other natural products of the land for domestic use;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767621" lims:id="767621"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the trapping of fur-bearing animals; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767622" lims:id="767622"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the hunting of caribou for domestic consumption.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767623" lims:id="767623"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767624" lims:id="767624"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A local user may carry out a traditional activity in the park if they are the holder of a local use permit that authorizes them to do so.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767625" lims:id="767625"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A local user may hunt or possess caribou, or trap or possess fur-bearing animals, in the park if, in addition to being the holder of a local use permit, they are the holder of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767626" lims:id="767626"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in respect of the hunting or possession of caribou, a permit issued by Manitoba that authorizes them to hunt caribou in Manitoba; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767627" lims:id="767627"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in respect of the trapping or possession of fur-bearing animals, a Manitoba trapping permit.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767628" lims:id="767628"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A local user may operate an all-terrain vehicle in the park while they are carrying out a traditional activity in accordance with their local use permit.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767629" lims:id="767629"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767630" lims:id="767630"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The superintendent shall, each year, for the purpose of the protection of caribou, fur-bearing animals and other fauna and flora in the park and for the maintenance or restoration of the ecological integrity of the park, determine</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767631" lims:id="767631"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>those areas in the park in which traditional activities will be permitted or restricted, taking into account all-terrain vehicle access and the proximity of resource harvest cabins;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767632" lims:id="767632"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>those areas in the park in which all-terrain vehicle use will be permitted, restricted or prohibited, taking into account the preservation, control and management of the park and the safety of the persons who will be carrying out activities in the park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767633" lims:id="767633"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the beginning and length of the season during which each traditional activity may be carried out;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767634" lims:id="767634"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>any limit that needs to be placed on the number of local use permits to be issued in respect of a traditional activity, including by reason of the availability of resource harvest cabins; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767635" lims:id="767635"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any limit that needs to be placed on</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767636" lims:id="767636"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the species or quantity of berries or flowers, or the quantity of deadwood or other natural products, that may be gathered,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767637" lims:id="767637"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the species or number of any species of fur-bearing animals that may be trapped, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767638" lims:id="767638"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the species or number of any species of caribou that may be hunted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767639" lims:id="767639"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The superintendent may, at any time, for the purposes of management of the park, public safety or the conservation of natural resources, close areas of the park to a traditional activity for any period that the superintendent determines necessary.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767640" lims:id="767640"><Label>6</Label><Text>Subject to the other provisions of these Regulations, the superintendent may, on application in accordance with section 7, issue a local use permit to a local user authorizing them to carry out one or more traditional activities in the park.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767641" lims:id="767641"><Label>7</Label><Text>An application for a local use permit shall be submitted to the superintendent on the form provided by the superintendent and shall include the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767642" lims:id="767642"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name and date of birth of the applicant and the address of their permanent residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767643" lims:id="767643"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>written evidence that the applicant is a local user;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767644" lims:id="767644"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the case of a local use permit to hunt caribou, a copy of the permit issued by Manitoba that authorizes them to hunt caribou in that province; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767645" lims:id="767645"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case of a local use permit to trap fur-bearing animals, a copy of their Manitoba trapping permit.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767646" lims:id="767646"><Label>8</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767647" lims:id="767647"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every local use permit shall contain</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767648" lims:id="767648"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name and date of birth of the permit holder;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767649" lims:id="767649"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the address of the permanent residence of the permit holder;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767650" lims:id="767650"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the period of validity of the permit, which shall be one year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767651" lims:id="767651"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a statement that the transfer or assignment of the permit is prohibited;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767652" lims:id="767652"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a description of the traditional activity that the permit holder is authorized to carry out;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767653" lims:id="767653"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>in the case of a permit to trap fur-bearing animals, a description of the method to be used by the permit holder to indicate their traps and trails;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767654" lims:id="767654"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a statement that contravention of a condition of the permit constitutes an offence under section 24 of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767655" lims:id="767655"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>having regard to the determinations made under subsection 5(1), any conditions that are specified by the superintendent to be included in all local use permits that are issued for a given season for a particular traditional activity in respect of the matters set out in paragraphs (a) to (e) of that subsection.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767656" lims:id="767656"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (1)(c), local use permits shall not authorize the hunting of caribou or the trapping of fur-bearing animals after April 24, 2031.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767657" lims:id="767657"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The superintendent may specify that all local use permits that are issued for a given season for a particular traditional activity — and any incidental all-terrain vehicle use — include any supplementary conditions required to ensure the protection of caribou, fur-bearing animals and other fauna and flora and natural resources in the park and for the preservation, control and management of the park, including the maintenance or restoration of its ecological integrity.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767658" lims:id="767658"><Label>9</Label><Text>The holder of a local use permit shall sign their permit on receipt.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767659" lims:id="767659"><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767660" lims:id="767660"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every holder of a local use permit shall carry it with them whenever they are in the park, and, on request by a park warden or an enforcement officer, shall produce it for examination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767661" lims:id="767661"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every holder of a local use permit to hunt caribou or trap fur-bearing animals shall carry with them — whenever they are in the park — the permit that was issued to them by Manitoba in respect of the traditional activity to which the local use permit applies, and shall, on request by a park warden or an enforcement officer, produce that permit for examination.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767662" lims:id="767662"><Label>11</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767663" lims:id="767663"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The superintendent may suspend a local use permit if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767664" lims:id="767664"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the permit holder fails to comply with these Regulations or the terms and conditions of the permit; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767665" lims:id="767665"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the permit issued by Manitoba to the permit holder in respect of the traditional activity to which the local use permit applies is suspended.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767666" lims:id="767666"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The superintendent may reinstate a suspended local use permit if the failure that gave rise to the suspension has been remedied by the permit holder.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767667" lims:id="767667"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The superintendent may revoke a local use permit if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767668" lims:id="767668"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the permit holder is convicted of an offence in respect of a contravention of these Regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767669" lims:id="767669"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the permit issued by Manitoba to the permit holder in respect of the traditional activity to which the local use permit applies is revoked; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767670" lims:id="767670"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the local use permit has been suspended twice during its period of validity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767671" lims:id="767671"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person whose local use permit has been revoked under subsection (3) is not eligible to apply for another within the 12-month period following the revocation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767672" lims:id="767672" level="1"><TitleText>Tundra Vehicle Operation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767673" lims:id="767673"><Label>12</Label><Text>No person shall operate a tundra vehicle in the park unless they are</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767674" lims:id="767674"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the holder of a permit issued under section 13; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767675" lims:id="767675"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an employee of a permit holder referred to in paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767676" lims:id="767676"><Label>13</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767677" lims:id="767677"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The superintendent may, on application, issue a permit to operate a tundra vehicle in the park to any commercial operator who is licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-98-455">National Parks of Canada Businesses Regulations</XRefExternal> to provide commercial tourism services in the park.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767678" lims:id="767678"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every permit issued under this section shall contain</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767679" lims:id="767679"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the name of the permit holder and the address of their permanent residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767680" lims:id="767680"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the names of all employees of the permit holder whom the permit holder authorizes to operate a tundra vehicle and the addresses of their permanent residences;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767681" lims:id="767681"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the date of issuance of the permit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767682" lims:id="767682"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a statement that the transfer or assignment of the permit is prohibited;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767683" lims:id="767683"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a description of the duties of the permit holder and the tundra vehicle operator;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767684" lims:id="767684"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a statement that contravention of a condition of the permit constitutes an offence under section 24 of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767685" lims:id="767685"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any conditions that are specified by the superintendent in respect of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767686" lims:id="767686"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the period of validity of the permit,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767687" lims:id="767687"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the areas in the park in which a tundra vehicle may be operated, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767688" lims:id="767688"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any measures to be taken by the permit holder and the tundra vehicle operator that are necessary to protect the ecological integrity of those areas.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767689" lims:id="767689"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The permit holder shall sign their permit on receipt.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767690" lims:id="767690"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who is operating a tundra vehicle in the park shall carry the permit that authorizes their operation of the vehicle with them, and, on request by a park warden or an enforcement officer, shall produce the permit for examination.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767691" lims:id="767691"><Label>14</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767692" lims:id="767692"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The superintendent may suspend a permit issued under section 13 if the permit holder or the tundra vehicle operator fails to comply with these Regulations or the terms and conditions of the permit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767693" lims:id="767693"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The superintendent may reinstate a suspended permit if the failure that gave rise to the suspension has been remedied.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767694" lims:id="767694"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The superintendent may revoke the permit if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767695" lims:id="767695"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the permit holder or the tundra vehicle operator is convicted of an offence in respect of a contravention of these Regulations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767696" lims:id="767696"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the permit has been suspended twice during its period of validity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767697" lims:id="767697"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person whose permit has been revoked under subsection (3) is not eligible to apply for another within the 12-month period following the revocation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767698" lims:id="767698" level="1"><TitleText>Resource Harvest Cabin Use</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767699" lims:id="767699"><Label>15</Label><Text>Resource harvest cabins may be used only for the following purposes:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767700" lims:id="767700"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the carrying out of traditional activities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767701" lims:id="767701"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>trapping by aboriginal persons on a registered trapline in the park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767702" lims:id="767702"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the exercise in the park, by aboriginal persons, of the rights referred to in subsection 2(2) of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767703" lims:id="767703"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the carrying out by employees of the Parks Canada Agency of functions related to management of the park.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767704" lims:id="767704"><Label>16</Label><Text>No person shall construct, alter, re-build or occupy a resource harvest cabin unless they are the holder of a permit issued under section 17.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767705" lims:id="767705"><Label>17</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767706" lims:id="767706"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The superintendent may issue a permit authorizing the construction, alteration, re-building or occupation of a resource harvest cabin to</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767707" lims:id="767707"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a holder of a local use permit, or an aboriginal person who is the holder of a Manitoba trapping permit that authorizes them to trap fur-bearing animals in the park; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767708" lims:id="767708"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an aboriginal person who is exercising, in the park, the rights referred to in subsection 2(2) of the Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767709" lims:id="767709"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The superintendent may issue only one permit for the construction of a resource harvest cabin on a registered trapline.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767710" lims:id="767710"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every permit shall specify</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767711" lims:id="767711"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the location of the resource harvest cabin;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767712" lims:id="767712"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the name of the owner of the resource harvest cabin;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767713" lims:id="767713"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the activity or activities for which the resource harvest cabin may be used; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767714" lims:id="767714"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the period of validity of the permit, which shall be one year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767715" lims:id="767715"><Label>18</Label><Text>Every person who constructs, alters or rebuilds a resource harvest cabin shall ensure that it meets the following criteria:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767716" lims:id="767716"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the floor area of the cabin shall not exceed 29.73 m<Sup>2</Sup>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767717" lims:id="767717"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the height of the cabin shall not exceed 5 m;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767718" lims:id="767718"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the cabin shall not have indoor plumbing or sewer service;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767719" lims:id="767719"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the cabin shall not have a basement or a permanent foundation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767720" lims:id="767720"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the cabin shall be equipped with a fire extinguisher.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767721" lims:id="767721"><Label>19</Label><Text>Every person who constructs, alters, re-builds or occupies a resource harvest cabin shall keep the cabin in good repair and shall ensure that the construction site, if applicable, is kept in a neat and safe condition.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767722" lims:id="767722"><Label>20</Label><Text>Every person who constructs, alters, re-builds or occupies a resource harvest cabin shall remove all garbage, including animal remains, from the cabin and the cabin site and shall dispose of the garbage at a disposal site that is approved by Manitoba and situated outside the park.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767723" lims:id="767723" level="1"><TitleText>Firearms</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767724" lims:id="767724"><Label>21</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767725" lims:id="767725"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall be in possession of, carry, transport or discharge a firearm in the park unless they are the holder of a permit issued by the superintendent under section 22.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767726" lims:id="767726"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767727" lims:id="767727"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the superintendent, a park warden, an enforcement officer or any other employee of the Parks Canada Agency who is carrying out functions related to the management of the park; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767728" lims:id="767728"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an aboriginal person who is exercising, in the park, the rights referred to in subsection 2(2) of the Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767729" lims:id="767729"><Label>22</Label><Text>The superintendent may, on application, issue a permit to the holder of a local use permit to hunt caribou authorizing them to be in possession of, carry, transport and discharge a firearm in the park for the purpose of carrying out that traditional activity, in the following circumstances:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767730" lims:id="767730"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person possesses a registration certificate issued under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> for the firearm to be identified in their permit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767731" lims:id="767731"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the person is authorized under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11.6">Firearms Act</XRefExternal></Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767732" lims:id="767732"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to be in possession of that type of firearm, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767733" lims:id="767733"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to carry and transport the firearm;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767734" lims:id="767734"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the person has submitted with their application a detailed summary of their experience of, and skill at, travelling in the park and the adjacent region; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767735" lims:id="767735"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the person has submitted with their application a detailed summary of their skills and experience that demonstrates that they are qualified to safely possess, carry, transport and discharge the firearm in the park.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767736" lims:id="767736" level="1"><TitleText>Notice and Review of Decisions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767737" lims:id="767737"><Label>23</Label><Text>If the superintendent refuses to issue a permit or suspends or revokes a permit, the superintendent shall, as soon as possible after making their decision, provide written notice of it, including reasons, to the applicant or permit holder, as applicable.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767738" lims:id="767738"><Label>24</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767739" lims:id="767739"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any person to whom the superintendent has refused to issue a permit or whose permit has been suspended or revoked by the superintendent may request a review of the superintendent’s decision by submitting a request in writing to the Chief Executive Officer within 30 days after receipt by that person of the notice described in section 23.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767740" lims:id="767740"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of the written request for review, the Chief Executive Officer shall require that the superintendent issue or reinstate the permit if the Chief Executive Officer reaches a decision that differs from the superintendent’s decision with respect</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767741" lims:id="767741"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of a refusal, to the requirements and matters to be considered as set out in these Regulations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767742" lims:id="767742"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a suspension or revocation, to the reasons set out in section 11 or 14, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767743" lims:id="767743"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Chief Executive Officer shall provide written notice of his or her decision, including reasons, to the person who requested the review.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767744" lims:id="767744" level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767745" lims:id="767745" level="2"><TitleText>National Parks of Canada Aircraft Access Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767746" lims:id="767746"><Label>25</Label><Text>[Amendment]</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767747" lims:id="767747" level="2"><TitleText>National Parks of Canada Domestic Animals Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767748" lims:id="767748"><Label>26</Label><Text>[Amendment]</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767749" lims:id="767749"><Label>27</Label><Text>[Amendment]</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767750" lims:id="767750"><Label>28</Label><Text>[Amendment]</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-26" lims:fid="767751" lims:id="767751" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2010-03-25" lims:lastAmendedDate="2010-03-25" lims:fid="767752" lims:id="767752" type="transitional"><Label>29</Label><Text>These Regulations come into force on March 26, 2010.</Text></Section></Body></Regulation>