<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977106" lims:id="977106" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977107" lims:id="977107"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/95-76</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1995</YYYY><MM>1</MM><DD>31</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977109" lims:id="977109"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-8.3">SEIZED PROPERTY MANAGEMENT ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977110" lims:id="977110">Forfeited Property Sharing Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977111" lims:id="977111">Regulations Respecting the Sharing of the Proceeds of the Disposition of Forfeited Property, the Sharing of the Amounts Paid or Recovered on Account of Certain Fines and the Sharing of Certain Moneys Transferred to Canada by the Governments of Foreign States</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1995-125</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1995</YYYY><MM>1</MM><DD>31</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977112" lims:id="977112"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977113" lims:id="977113" language-align="yes" format-ref="indent-0-0" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Supply and Services, the Minister of Justice and the Solicitor General of Canada, pursuant to paragraph 9(f), section 11, paragraphs 13(2)(a) and (c) and sections 18 and 19 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-8.3">Seized Property Management Act</XRefExternal><FootnoteRef idref="footnote1star_e">*</FootnoteRef>, is pleased hereby to make the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Regulations respecting the sharing of the proceeds of the disposition of forfeited property, the sharing of the amounts paid or recovered on account of certain fines and the sharing of certain moneys transferred to Canada by the governments of foreign states.</XRefExternal></Text><Footnote id="footnote1star_e" placement="page" status="official"><Label>*</Label><Text>S.C. 1993, c. 37</Text></Footnote></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977114" lims:id="977114"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977115" lims:id="977115" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977116" lims:id="977116"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-95-76">Forfeited Property Sharing Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977117" lims:id="977117" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977118" lims:id="977118"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977119" lims:id="977119" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-8.3">Seized Property Management Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977120" lims:id="977120" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>agency</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977121" lims:id="977121"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case of the Government of Canada, a law enforcement agency under the authority of the Government of Canada, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977122" lims:id="977122"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a jurisdiction that is</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977123" lims:id="977123"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the government of a province, a law enforcement agency operating under provincial legislation or the Royal Canadian Mounted Police acting under contract in that province, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977124" lims:id="977124"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the government of a foreign state, a law enforcement agency within that state; (<DefinedTermFr>organisme</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977125" lims:id="977125" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>contribution</DefinedTermEn> means the contribution of the Government of Canada or a jurisdiction, as determined in accordance with section 7; (<DefinedTermFr>apport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977126" lims:id="977126" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>fine</DefinedTermEn> means the amount paid or recovered on account of a fine imposed under subsection 462.37(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in relation to proceedings commenced at the instance of the Government of Canada; (<DefinedTermFr>amende</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977127" lims:id="977127" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>jurisdiction</DefinedTermEn> means the government of a province or the government of a foreign state; (<DefinedTermFr>autorité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977128" lims:id="977128" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>net proceeds</DefinedTermEn> means the net proceeds from the disposition of property, calculated in accordance with section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-94-303">Seized Property Disposition Regulations</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>produit net</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977129" lims:id="977129" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>property</DefinedTermEn> means any property forfeited to Her Majesty pursuant to  a provision rerred to in section 10 of the Act. (<DefinedTermFr>bien</DefinedTermFr>) </Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977131" lims:id="977131">SOR/2000-115, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977132" lims:id="977132" level="1"><TitleText>Agreements with the Governments of Foreign States Respecting Sharing</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977133" lims:id="977133"><Label>3</Label><Text>No sharing under the Act and these Regulations shall take place with the government of a foreign state unless the government of that foreign state has entered into an agreement pursuant to section 11 of the Act.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977134" lims:id="977134"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977135" lims:id="977135"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An agreement with the government of a foreign state, entered into pursuant to section 11 of the Act, shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977136" lims:id="977136"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide that sharing will be between the Government of Canada and the government of that foreign state;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977137" lims:id="977137"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide that the sharing of the proceeds of disposition of property in Canada and the sharing of fines in Canada will be in accordance with Part I of these Regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977138" lims:id="977138"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>provide that there will be no conditions in respect of the use of any moneys received under the agreement; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977139" lims:id="977139"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>state the title of the official to whom the amount of any share is to be paid and sent or provide that a central authority will designate to whom the amount of any share is to be paid and sent.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977140" lims:id="977140"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An agreement referred to in subsection (1) shall not be inconsistent with the Act or these Regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977141" lims:id="977141" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Forfeited Property and Fines in Canada</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977142" lims:id="977142" level="2"><TitleText>Determination of the Amount Available for Sharing</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977143" lims:id="977143"><Label>5</Label><Text>The amount that is available for sharing shall be determined by subtracting, from the sum of, first, the amount of the net proceeds of all of a person’s property that has been forfeited in connection with one or more offenses by the person and, second, the amount of any fine ordered to be paid by the person in connection with the offence or offenses, the following amounts:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977144" lims:id="977144"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a prorated portion of the amount of the operating expenses referred to in paragraph 13(3)(a) of the Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977145" lims:id="977145"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a prorated portion of the amount reserved for</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977146" lims:id="977146"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>future losses,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977147" lims:id="977147"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the payment of claims arising from undertakings given by the Attorney General pursuant to subsection 462.32(6) or 462.33(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977148" lims:id="977148"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>payments arising from indemnifications granted pursuant to section 18 of the Act.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977149" lims:id="977149" level="2"><TitleText>Time of Sharing</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977150" lims:id="977150"><Label>6</Label><Text>The sharing of an amount determined pursuant to section 5, shall take place no later than 90 days after the end of the fiscal year in which the following amounts are paid into the Consolidated Revenue Fund and credited to the Proceeds Account:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977151" lims:id="977151"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in the case where only one property referred to in section 5 has been forfeited, the amount of the net proceeds of the property;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977152" lims:id="977152"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case where more than one property referred to in section 5 has been forfeited, the amount of the net proceeds of the property that was disposed of last;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977153" lims:id="977153"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in the case where a fine referred to in section 5 has been ordered, the amount paid or recovered on account of the fine; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977154" lims:id="977154"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case where property referred to in section 5 has been forfeited and a fine, referred to in section 5 has been ordered, the amount of the net proceeds of the property and the amount paid or recovered on account of the fine.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977155" lims:id="977155" level="2"><TitleText>Contribution of the Government of Canada and Jurisdictions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977156" lims:id="977156"><Label>7</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977157" lims:id="977157"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the sharing of an amount determined pursuant to section 5, the Attorney General shall assess the contribution of the Government of Canada and of each of the relevant jurisdictions on the basis of the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977158" lims:id="977158"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the nature of information provided by the agencies of the Government of Canada and each jurisdiction, and the importance of that information; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977159" lims:id="977159"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the participation by the agencies of the Government of Canada and each jurisdiction in the investigation and prosecution that lead to forfeiture or the imposition of a fine.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977160" lims:id="977160"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Attorney General may, for the purposes of an assessment referred to in subsection (1), consult with the relevant agencies and jurisdictions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977161" lims:id="977161"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Attorney General shall assign a percentage representing the contribution of the Government of Canada and of each relevant jurisdiction, as compared with the contribution of another jurisdiction or group of jurisdictions, as the case may be, determined as follows:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977162" lims:id="977162"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>where the contribution of the Government of Canada or a jurisdiction constitutes the predominant portion of the total contribution, it shall be considered to be 90 per cent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977163" lims:id="977163"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>where the contribution of the Government of Canada or a jurisdiction constitutes a significant portion of the total contribution, it shall be considered to be 50 per cent; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977164" lims:id="977164"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>where the contribution of the Government of Canada or a jurisdiction constitutes a minimal portion of the total contribution, it shall be considered to be 10 per cent.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977165" lims:id="977165"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Attorney General shall determine the contribution, expressed as a percentage in accordance with subsection (3), of the Government of Canada and of each of the following jurisdictions and groups of jurisdictions, in the following order:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977166" lims:id="977166"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>determine the contribution of the Government of Canada and the contribution of the group of all relevant jurisdictions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977167" lims:id="977167"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>determine the contribution of the jurisdiction that has the highest level of contribution from among the group of other jurisdictions referred to in paragraph (a), and the contribution of the group of remaining jurisdictions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977168" lims:id="977168"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>repeat the method set out in paragraph (b), for the group of remaining jurisdictions, until only two jurisdictions remain; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977169" lims:id="977169"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>where only two jurisdictions remain, determine the contribution of each of those jurisdictions.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977170" lims:id="977170"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The percentage that represents the contribution of the Government of Canada shall in no case be less than 10 per cent.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977171" lims:id="977171"><Label>8</Label><Text>The Attorney General shall provide to the Minister the percentages that represent the respective contributions, assigned pursuant to section 7, of the Government of Canada and the relevant jurisdictions and groups of jurisdictions.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977172" lims:id="977172" level="2"><TitleText>Calculation and Payment of Shares</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977173" lims:id="977173"><Label>9</Label><Text>The Minister shall, in accordance with the percentages referred to in section 8, calculate the Government of Canada’s share and each relevant jurisdiction’s share of an amount determined in accordance with section 5, as follows:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977174" lims:id="977174"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>calculate the share of the Government of Canada by multiplying the amount available for sharing by the percentage that represents the contribution of the Government of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977175" lims:id="977175"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subtract the product obtained in the preceding paragraph from the amount available for sharing, the remainder being the first residual amount available for sharing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977176" lims:id="977176"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if there is only one remaining jurisdiction, the share of that jurisdiction is the residual amount referred to in paragraph (b), otherwise calculate the share of the jurisdiction that has the highest level of contribution as determined under paragraph 7(4)(b) by multiplying the first residual amount available for sharing obtained in accordance with the preceding paragraph by the percentage that represents the contribution of that jurisdiction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977177" lims:id="977177"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>subtract the product obtained in the preceding paragraph from the first residual amount available for sharing in the preceding paragraph, the remainder being the new residual amount available for sharing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977178" lims:id="977178"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>repeat the method set out in paragraphs (c) and (d), with such modifications as the circumstances require, until such time as the shares of only two jurisdictions remain to be calculated; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977179" lims:id="977179"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>where the shares of only two jurisdictions remain to be calculated, calculate the shares of those jurisdictions by multiplying the new residual amount available for sharing obtained in accordance with the preceding step by the percentages that represent the respective contributions of those jurisdictions.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977180" lims:id="977180"><Label>10</Label><Text>The Minister shall pay to each relevant jurisdiction the amount of the share, calculated in accordance with section 9, for that jurisdiction by sending that amount to the government of a relevant province or to the appropriate official as specified in an agreement referred to in section 3.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977181" lims:id="977181"><Label>11</Label><Text>Where a government of a province signs a memorandum of understanding with the Government of Canada respecting the allocation by the province of a portion of a share received under section 10, the allocation of that portion shall be consistent with the memorandum of understanding.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977182" lims:id="977182" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Sharing of Moneys Transferred to Canada</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977183" lims:id="977183" level="2"><TitleText>Determination of the Amount Available for Sharing</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977184" lims:id="977184"><Label>12</Label><Text>The amount of the moneys transferred to Canada by the government of a foreign state under an agreement entered into pursuant to section 11 of the Act that is available for sharing between the Government of Canada and the government of the relevant provinces shall be determined by subtracting, from the moneys transferred, the amount referred to in paragraph 5(a).</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977185" lims:id="977185" level="2"><TitleText>Manner of Sharing</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977186" lims:id="977186"><Label>13</Label><Text>Sections 7 to 11 apply to the sharing of the amount determined in accordance with section 12, except that any contribution of the government of a foreign state shall not be taken into account.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977187" lims:id="977187" level="2"><TitleText>Time of Sharing</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977188" lims:id="977188"><Label>14</Label><Text>Sharing shall take place no later than 90 days after the end of the fiscal year in which the amounts received from the government of a foreign state are paid into the Consolidated Revenue Fund and credited to the Proceeds Account.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977189" lims:id="977189"><Label>15</Label><Text>Within 120 days after the end of each fiscal year, all amounts credited to the Proceeds Account that are not shared pursuant to sections 10 and 11 of the Act less such amounts reserved in accordance with section 16 of the Act shall be calculated for that fiscal year and paid into the Seized Property Non-Tax Revenue Account.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977191" lims:id="977191">SOR/98-191, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977192" lims:id="977192"><Label>16</Label><Text>On or before March 31, 2000, all amounts credited to the Proceeds Account during any of fiscal years 1993-94 to 1996-97 that have not been shared pursuant to sections 10 and 11 of the Act, less any amounts reserved in accordance with section 16 of the Act, shall be calculated and paid into the Seized Property Non-Tax Revenue Account.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="977194" lims:id="977194">SOR/98-191, s. 1; SOR/2000-115, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body></Regulation>