<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724898" lims:id="724898" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724899" lims:id="724899"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/2006-236</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>2006</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724901" lims:id="724901"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-3">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724902" lims:id="724902">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Application for Deposit Insurance By-law</LongTitle></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724903" lims:id="724903"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724904" lims:id="724904" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Board of Directors of the Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation, pursuant to paragraphs 11(2)(g)<FootnoteRef idref="footnote1_e">a</FootnoteRef> and (i) and subsection 18(1)<FootnoteRef idref="footnote2_e">b</FootnoteRef> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-3">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal>, hereby makes the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-93-515">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Application for Deposit Insurance By-law</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724905" lims:id="724905" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Ottawa, September 27, 2006</Text></Provision><Footnote id="footnote1_e" placement="page"><Label>a</Label><Text>R.S., c. 18 (3rd Supp.), s. 51</Text></Footnote><Footnote id="footnote2_e" placement="page"><Label>b</Label><Text>S.C. 1999, c. 28, s. 100</Text></Footnote></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724906" lims:id="724906"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724907" lims:id="724907" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724908" lims:id="724908"><Label>1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724909" lims:id="724909"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this By-law.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724910" lims:id="724910" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-3">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724911" lims:id="724911" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>applicant</DefinedTermEn> means a provincial institution that makes an application to the Corporation for deposit insurance. (<DefinedTermFr>demandeur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724912" lims:id="724912" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>associate</DefinedTermEn>, when used to indicate a relationship with a person, means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724913" lims:id="724913"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a corporation of which that person beneficially owns, directly or indirectly, voting securities that carry more than 10 per cent of the voting rights attached to all of the outstanding voting securities of the corporation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724914" lims:id="724914"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a partner of that person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724915" lims:id="724915"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a trust or an estate or succession in which that person has a substantial beneficial interest or in respect of which that person serves as a trustee or in a similar capacity. (<DefinedTermFr>associé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724916" lims:id="724916" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>beneficial ownership</DefinedTermEn> includes ownership through one or more trustees, legal representatives, agents or mandataries or other intermediaries. (<DefinedTermFr>véritable propriétaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724917" lims:id="724917" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>common-law partnership</DefinedTermEn> means the relationship between two individuals who are cohabiting in a conjugal relationship, having so cohabited for a period of at least one year. (<DefinedTermFr>union de fait</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724918" lims:id="724918" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>corporation</DefinedTermEn> means an incorporated body wherever or however incorporated. (<DefinedTermFr>personne morale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724919" lims:id="724919" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>direction</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of the voting securities of an entity, means the power, alone or in combination with one or more persons, directly or indirectly, to exercise or direct the exercise of the voting rights attached to those securities. (<DefinedTermFr>haute main</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724920" lims:id="724920" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>entity</DefinedTermEn> means a corporation, a trust, a partnership, a fund, an unincorporated association or organization, Her Majesty in right of Canada or of a province, an agency of Her Majesty in either of those rights, the government of a foreign country or any political subdivision of that government or any agency of that government or of that political subdivision. (<DefinedTermFr>entité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724921" lims:id="724921" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>financial statements</DefinedTermEn> includes a balance sheet, a statement of retained earnings, an income statement and a statement of changes in financial position. (<DefinedTermFr>états financiers</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724922" lims:id="724922" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>forecast</DefinedTermEn> means information in respect of prospective results of the operations and financial position or changes in the financial position of an entity, based on assumptions made in respect of future economic conditions and planned courses of action for a specified period, given management’s judgment as to the most probable set of economic conditions. (<DefinedTermFr>prévisions</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724923" lims:id="724923" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>influence</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of an entity, means the power to exercise an influence, directly or indirectly and alone or in combination with one or more persons, over the management and policies of the entity, whether through the beneficial ownership of voting securities or otherwise. (<DefinedTermFr>influence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724924" lims:id="724924" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>material</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of any matter, means a matter that has or may reasonably be expected to have a bearing on the decision of the Corporation as to whether to approve an applicant for deposit insurance. (<DefinedTermFr>important</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724925" lims:id="724925" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>misrepresentation</DefinedTermEn> means an untrue statement made in respect of a material fact or a statement that is misleading in the context in which it is made due to the omission of a material fact. (<DefinedTermFr>fausse déclaration</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724926" lims:id="724926" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>officer</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724927" lims:id="724927"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in respect of a corporation, a chief executive officer, president, vice-president, secretary, controller, treasurer and any other individual designated as an officer of the corporation by by-law or by a resolution of its directors; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724928" lims:id="724928"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in respect of any other entity, any individual designated as an officer of the entity. (<DefinedTermFr>dirigeant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724929" lims:id="724929" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> means an individual or an entity and includes a legal representative. (<DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724930" lims:id="724930" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>promoter</DefinedTermEn> means a person who</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724931" lims:id="724931"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>acting alone or in conjunction with one or more other persons, participates directly or indirectly in the founding, organizing or substantial reorganizing of the business of an applicant; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724932" lims:id="724932"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in connection with the founding, organizing or substantial reorganizing of the business of an applicant, directly or indirectly receives, in consideration of services or property or both services and property, five per cent or more of any class of securities of the applicant or five per cent or more of the proceeds from the sale of any class of securities of a particular issue, other than a person who receives such securities or proceeds either solely as underwriting commissions or solely in consideration of property but does not otherwise take part in the founding, organizing or substantial reorganizing of the business of the applicant. (<DefinedTermFr>promoteur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724933" lims:id="724933" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>regulatory authority</DefinedTermEn> means a supervisory or regulatory authority of financial institutions, capital markets, securities transactions or commodity futures that has jurisdiction over an applicant. (<DefinedTermFr>organisme de réglementation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724934" lims:id="724934" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>relative</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a person who is an individual, means an individual related to that person by birth, adoption, marriage or common-law partnership. (<DefinedTermFr>parent</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724935" lims:id="724935" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>subsidiary</DefinedTermEn>, when used to indicate a relationship between one corporation and another, means a corporation that is controlled by that other corporation. (<DefinedTermFr>filiale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724936" lims:id="724936"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this By-law,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724937" lims:id="724937"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person controls a corporation if securities of the corporation, to which are attached more than 50 per cent of the votes that may be cast to elect directors of the corporation, are beneficially owned by the person and the votes attached to those securities are sufficient, if exercised, to elect a majority of the directors of the corporation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724938" lims:id="724938"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person controls an unincorporated entity, other than a limited partnership, if more than 50 per cent of the ownership interest in the entity, however designated, is beneficially owned by the person and the person is able to direct the business and affairs of the entity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724939" lims:id="724939"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the general partner of a limited partnership controls the limited partnership; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724940" lims:id="724940"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a person controls an entity if the person has any direct or indirect influence that, if exercised, would result in control in fact of the entity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724941" lims:id="724941"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this By-law, a person who controls an entity is considered to control any other entity that is controlled, or is considered to be controlled, by the entity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724942" lims:id="724942"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this By-law, a person is considered to control an entity where the aggregate of any securities of the entity that are beneficially owned by the person and any securities of the entity that are beneficially owned by any entity controlled by that person is such that, if that person and all of the entities that beneficially own securities of the entity were one person, that person would control the entity.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724943" lims:id="724943" level="1"><TitleText>Application for Deposit Insurance</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724944" lims:id="724944"><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724945" lims:id="724945"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application for deposit insurance must contain</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724946" lims:id="724946"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the information and documentation referred to in sections 3 to 17, in one of Canada’s official languages; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724947" lims:id="724947"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an affidavit as set out in Form 1 of the schedule and, if applicable, an affidavit as set out in Form 2 of the schedule, duly executed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724948" lims:id="724948"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The information and documentation included in an application must be current as of not more than 12 months before the day on which the final information or documentation relating to the application is submitted to the Corporation by the applicant in order to complete the application.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724949" lims:id="724949" level="1"><TitleText>Applicant’s General Information</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724950" lims:id="724950"><Label>3</Label><Text>The application must include the following information in respect of the applicant:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724951" lims:id="724951"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>its legal name, including the form of that name in the other official language of Canada, if any;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724952" lims:id="724952"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the address, telephone number, e-mail address and facsimile number of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724953" lims:id="724953"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>its head office,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724954" lims:id="724954"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>its principal place of business, if that place of business is located somewhere other than at the head office, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724955" lims:id="724955"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>each of its current branches, if any, and each of its proposed branches, if any;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724956" lims:id="724956"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the date of its incorporation, the jurisdiction of its incorporation and the date on which it began to carry on business or proposes to do so;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724957" lims:id="724957"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the name, title or office, and address of each of its current and proposed directors and officers and a copy of their curriculum vitae or resumé;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724958" lims:id="724958"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>whether any director or officer referred to in paragraph (d) is an associate or a relative of any other director or officer referred to in that paragraph or of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724959" lims:id="724959"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a director or officer referred to in paragraph 13(e), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724960" lims:id="724960"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an individual referred to in section 14;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724961" lims:id="724961"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>detailed information, for each of the directors and officers referred to in paragraph (d), in respect of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724962" lims:id="724962"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>any conviction, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, for a material criminal offence,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724963" lims:id="724963"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any conviction, under the laws of such a jurisdiction, for a statutory or regulatory violation in relation to any of their businesses or the applicant’s business, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724964" lims:id="724964"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any proceedings that have been commenced against them in such a jurisdiction in respect of such an offence or violation;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724965" lims:id="724965"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>detailed information, for each of the directors and officers referred to in paragraph (d), in respect of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724966" lims:id="724966"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the suspension or revocation, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, of any licence held by them in relation to the business or affairs of the applicant,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724967" lims:id="724967"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the suspension or cancellation, under the laws of such a jurisdiction, of any registration in their name in relation to the business or affairs of the applicant, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724968" lims:id="724968"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any investigation that has been or is being conducted in such a jurisdiction in relation to such a licence or registration;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724969" lims:id="724969"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the legal name, address, telephone number, e-mail address and facsimile number of its current or proposed external auditor, as applicable;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724970" lims:id="724970"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the name, address, telephone number, e-mail address and facsimile number of any person who is, or who, within the 24-month period preceding the day referred to in subsection 2(2) has been, a promoter of the applicant; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724971" lims:id="724971"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the name, title or office, address, telephone number, e-mail address and facsimile number of the individual who is authorized to represent the applicant with respect to the application.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724972" lims:id="724972" level="1"><TitleText>Applicant’s Financial Information</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724973" lims:id="724973"><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724974" lims:id="724974"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The application must include the following documents in respect of the financial affairs of the applicant:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724975" lims:id="724975"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the applicant has been incorporated for less than one financial year, an audited opening balance sheet and unaudited interim financial statements, if any, for the financial period beginning on the day on which it began to carry on its business; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724976" lims:id="724976"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the applicant has been incorporated for one or more financial years</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724977" lims:id="724977"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>unaudited interim financial statements, if any, for the financial period following the period covered by the annual audited financial statements for the most recently completed financial year,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724978" lims:id="724978"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>audited financial statements for</Text><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724979" lims:id="724979"><Label>(A)</Label><Text>each completed financial year from the date of incorporation, if it has been incorporated for one or more, but less than three, financial years, or</Text></Clause><Clause lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724980" lims:id="724980"><Label>(B)</Label><Text>each of the last three financial years, if it has been incorporated for three or more financial years, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724981" lims:id="724981"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>its latest annual report, if any.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724982" lims:id="724982"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), all financial statements included in the application must be</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724983" lims:id="724983"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prepared in accordance with the accounting principles and auditing standards accepted under or required by the laws of the jurisdiction of incorporation of the applicant or prescribed by the regulatory authority primarily responsible for regulating the applicant; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724984" lims:id="724984"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prepared in accordance with the accounting standards and guidelines established by the Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants (“CICA”) — also referred to as “Canadian Generally Accepted Accounting Principles” (“Canadian GAAP”) — and audited in accordance with the auditing standards and guidelines established by the CICA.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724985" lims:id="724985"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If financial statements that are included in an application are provided by a foreign entity that controls the applicant, they must be</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724986" lims:id="724986"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prepared in accordance with the generally accepted or applicable accounting principles and auditing procedures in the jurisdiction where the foreign entity was incorporated or established and accompanied by a comparison between the accounting standards used to complete the applicant’s financial statements and Canadian GAAP; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724987" lims:id="724987"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prepared in accordance with Canadian GAAP and audited in accordance with the auditing standards and guidelines established by the CICA.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724988" lims:id="724988"><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724989" lims:id="724989"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The application must include a business plan that covers the three-year period beginning on the day on which the applicant proposes to begin carrying on its deposit-taking business and that contains the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724990" lims:id="724990"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the reasons why it wants to establish a deposit-taking business;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724991" lims:id="724991"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an analysis of target markets together with its business objectives for those markets, the short- and long-term strategy it will employ to achieve those objectives and the reasons why it believes that it will be successful in achieving those objectives;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724992" lims:id="724992"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an overview of each line of business to be conducted and a description of the products and services it will offer in each target market, together with the expected levels of business for those products and services;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724993" lims:id="724993"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an analysis of the competitive threats it will face in each target market, together with a description of how it plans to respond to those threats and the reasons why it believes that the response will be successful;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724994" lims:id="724994"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a detailed forecast that includes pro forma financial statements covering that three-year period and identifying the assumptions made in the preparation of the forecast;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724995" lims:id="724995"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a list of the assumptions that it made for the purposes of paragraphs (b) to (e) and the reasons why it considers those assumptions to be reasonable;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724996" lims:id="724996"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a description of the off-balance sheet activities that it proposes to carry on;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724997" lims:id="724997"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a description of its proposed outsourcing arrangements and its contingency plans respecting those arrangements;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724998" lims:id="724998"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a sensitivity analysis of its projected financial results under various assumptions or scenarios;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="724999" lims:id="724999"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>its projected staff complement during that three-year period; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725000" lims:id="725000"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>an explanation of the correlation between the business background and expertise of each director and officer and the applicant’s business objectives.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725001" lims:id="725001"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must also include any other business plan that was prepared by, or for, the applicant within the 24-month period preceding the date of the business plan referred to in subsection (1) and an explanation of any significant differences between those business plans.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725002" lims:id="725002"><Label>6</Label><Text>The application must include the following information in respect of the applicant’s capital:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725003" lims:id="725003"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>its authorized capital level;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725004" lims:id="725004"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the sources of its initial and future capital;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725005" lims:id="725005"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the amount of its issued and outstanding capital;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725006" lims:id="725006"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the amount of its paid-in or stated capital; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725007" lims:id="725007"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a description of any other forms of its capital that are accepted as, or considered to be, capital in the jurisdiction in which the applicant was incorporated.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725008" lims:id="725008"><Label>7</Label><Text>The application must include detailed information in respect of the following:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725009" lims:id="725009"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any material pending litigation to which the applicant is a party;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725010" lims:id="725010"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any material contingent liabilities, including guarantees, suretyships and indemnity obligations issued by the applicant to its shareholders, directors, officers, affiliates or associates; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725011" lims:id="725011"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any material transaction, in which the applicant has an interest, that is pending or is scheduled to occur within the 24-month period preceding the day referred to in subsection 2(2) and that confers or may confer a benefit on any of</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725012" lims:id="725012"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>its directors or officers,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725013" lims:id="725013"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>its affiliates, associates or promoter, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725014" lims:id="725014"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the directors or officers of an affiliate, associate or promoter referred to in subparagraph (ii).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725015" lims:id="725015"><Label>8</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725016" lims:id="725016"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The application must include evidence that the applicant has established appropriate, effective and prudent practices with respect to corporate governance, risk management and liquidity and capital management, as well as appropriate, effective and prudent controls in respect of its operations, that will enable it to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-93-516">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Deposit Insurance Policy By-law</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725017" lims:id="725017"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The evidence must provide a detailed description of those practices and controls, including</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725018" lims:id="725018"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the composition, mandate, roles and responsibilities of board committees and of the internal audit and compliance functions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725019" lims:id="725019"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the policies relating to and the procedures for monitoring risk tolerance and risk management for major risk areas such as credit, market, liquidity, operational (inclusive of business continuity planning), technology, legal, regulatory, reputational and strategic risks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725020" lims:id="725020"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any procedures that are or will be integrated with those of the entity that controls the applicant, if any, or any of the applicant’s subsidiaries, associates or affiliates, if any.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725021" lims:id="725021" level="1"><TitleText>Other Information About the Applicant</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725022" lims:id="725022"><Label>9</Label><Text>The application must include detailed information in respect of the following, if applicable:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725023" lims:id="725023"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any agreement or understanding that has or could have a significant effect on the management or control of the applicant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725024" lims:id="725024"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the refusal of an application for deposit insurance made by the applicant under the Act or under similar legislation in any other jurisdiction within or outside Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725025" lims:id="725025"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the suspension or revocation of the applicant’s policy of deposit insurance under the Act or under similar legislation in any other jurisdiction within or outside Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725026" lims:id="725026"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the refusal, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, of an application made by the applicant for licensing or registration as a financial institution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725027" lims:id="725027"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the suspension or revocation, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, of the applicant’s licence to carry on business as a financial institution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725028" lims:id="725028"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the suspension or cancellation, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, of the applicant’s registration as a financial institution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725029" lims:id="725029"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any investigation that was or is being conducted in relation to a licence referred to in paragraph (e) or a registration referred to in paragraph (f);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725030" lims:id="725030"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the refusal, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, of an application made by the applicant for any licence or registration related to the business or affairs of the applicant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725031" lims:id="725031"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the suspension or revocation, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, of any licence referred to in paragraph (h) and held by the applicant or the cancellation of any registration referred to in paragraph (h) in the applicant’s name;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725032" lims:id="725032"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>any investigation that was or is being conducted in relation to a licence or registration referred to in paragraph (h);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725033" lims:id="725033"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the refusal, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, of an application made by the applicant for membership in any self-regulatory organization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725034" lims:id="725034"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the suspension or revocation, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, of the applicant’s membership in any self-regulatory organization and any investigation that was or is being conducted in relation to that membership;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725035" lims:id="725035"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>the refusal of an application made by the applicant for bonding or suretyship or insurance coverage in relation to its business;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725036" lims:id="725036"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>the suspension or revocation of any bonding or suretyship or insurance coverage held by the applicant in relation to its business and any investigation that was or is being conducted in relation to such coverage; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725037" lims:id="725037"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>the conviction of the applicant, under the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada, for a material criminal offence or a finding, made by a court of law, tribunal or other quasi-judicial body or by a regulatory body that the applicant violated the laws of any jurisdiction within or outside Canada in respect of the carrying on of a business, and any proceedings relating to such an offence or violation that have been commenced in any jurisdiction within or outside Canada against the applicant by a competent authority.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725038" lims:id="725038"><Label>10</Label><Text>The applicant shall, at the request of the Corporation, provide any additional information or documents relating to the application that the Corporation considers necessary, having regard to its objects as set out in section 7 of the Act, in order to enable it to make a decision on the application.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725039" lims:id="725039" level="1"><TitleText>Information About Promoters, Affiliates, Associates and Controlling Entities of the Applicant</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725040" lims:id="725040"><Label>11</Label><Text>The application must include an organization chart that shows</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725041" lims:id="725041"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the entity that controls the applicant, if any, and the extent of the ownership interest in the applicant held by that entity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725042" lims:id="725042"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>all existing or proposed affiliates and associates of the applicant and the extent of the ownership interest held or proposed to be held by each of them in the applicant or in the entity that controls the applicant, as applicable, including the class of securities owned or controlled, the number and percentage of each issued and outstanding class of securities held and the nature of the ownership interest (that is, whether the interest is direct or indirect and whether it is registered, beneficial or exercised through direction).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725043" lims:id="725043"><Label>12</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725044" lims:id="725044"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the entity that controls the applicant is not a member institution, the application must include the information and documentation set out in sections 3, 4 and 9 in respect of that entity and the name, address, telephone number, e-mail address and facsimile number of each person who is the ultimate beneficial owner of, directly or indirectly, or who exercises direction over, 20 per cent or more of any class of voting securities of that entity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725045" lims:id="725045"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the entity that controls the applicant carries on business in a foreign jurisdiction, the application must also indicate whether that entity is subject to supervision or regulation in the foreign jurisdiction and, if so, the nature and extent of the supervision or regulation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725046" lims:id="725046"><Label>13</Label><Text>The application must include the following information in respect of any promoter of the applicant and each of the applicant’s existing and proposed affiliates and associates that is not an individual:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725047" lims:id="725047"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>their legal name, including the form of that name in the other official language of Canada, if any;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725048" lims:id="725048"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the address, telephone number, e-mail address and facsimile number of their head office and their principal place of business, if that place of business is located somewhere other than at the head office;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725049" lims:id="725049"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the date of their incorporation, the jurisdiction of their incorporation and the date on which they began to carry on business or propose to do so;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725050" lims:id="725050"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a summary of the business activities carried on or proposed to be carried on by them, including a list of the jurisdictions where those activities are carried on or are proposed to be carried on;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725051" lims:id="725051"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the name, title or office, and address of each of their current and proposed directors and officers and a copy of their curriculum vitae or resumé;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725052" lims:id="725052"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>whether any director or officer referred to in paragraph (e) is an associate or a relative of any other director or officer referred to in that paragraph;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725053" lims:id="725053"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the information referred to in paragraphs 3(f) and (g) in respect of each of their current and proposed directors and officers;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725054" lims:id="725054"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the information described in section 9 in respect of that promoter or those affiliates and associates; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725055" lims:id="725055"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the name, address, telephone number, e-mail address and facsimile number of each person who is the ultimate beneficial owner of, directly or indirectly, or who exercises direction over, 10 per cent or more of any class of voting securities of that promoter or those affiliates and associates.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725056" lims:id="725056"><Label>14</Label><Text>The application must include the following information in respect of any promoter or associate of the applicant that is an individual:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725057" lims:id="725057"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>their name, address, telephone number, e-mail address and occupation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725058" lims:id="725058"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a copy of their curriculum vitae or resumé;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725059" lims:id="725059"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>whether that promoter is an associate or a relative of any associate of the applicant or of any director or officer referred to in paragraph 13(e);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725060" lims:id="725060"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the information described in section 9 in respect of that promoter or associate; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725061" lims:id="725061"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a detailed summary of their assets and liabilities.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725062" lims:id="725062" level="1"><TitleText>Other Required Documentation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725063" lims:id="725063"><Label>15</Label><Text>The application must include the following documents:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725064" lims:id="725064"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a certified copy of the incorporating instrument of the applicant and any amendments made to it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725065" lims:id="725065"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a certified copy of all of the by-laws of the applicant and any amendments made to them;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725066" lims:id="725066"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a legal opinion attesting to the due incorporation, organization and capacity of the applicant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725067" lims:id="725067"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a copy of any application, made by the applicant or any promoter of the applicant during the 12-month period preceding the day referred to in subsection 2(2), for incorporation, registration or licensing under any federal or provincial legislation that regulates financial institutions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725068" lims:id="725068"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a copy of an agreement or understanding referred to in paragraph 9(a) if that agreement or understanding is in writing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725069" lims:id="725069"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a detailed organization chart that lists all of the current and proposed officers of the applicant and all of the applicant’s current and proposed employees;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725070" lims:id="725070"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a copy of the following bonds or insurance policies, if any, that relate to the business of the applicant, or of any suretyships similar to those bonds, namely,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725071" lims:id="725071"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a fidelity bond or a fidelity insurance policy,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725072" lims:id="725072"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a banker’s blanket bond or a banker’s blanket insurance policy,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725073" lims:id="725073"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>an extortion bond or an extortion insurance policy,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725074" lims:id="725074"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>a safe depository bond or a safe depository insurance policy,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725075" lims:id="725075"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>a director’s or officer’s insurance policy, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725076" lims:id="725076"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>any other bonds or insurance policies similar to those referred to in subparagraphs (i) to (v);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725077" lims:id="725077"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a certified copy of the resolution of the board of directors of the applicant consenting to the making of the application and approving its contents;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725078" lims:id="725078"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a certified copy of the resolution of the board of directors of the entity that controls the applicant, if applicable, consenting to the making of the application and approving its contents; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725079" lims:id="725079"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>a certificate or other evidence confirming that the applicant is authorized by the province of its incorporation to apply for deposit insurance.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725080" lims:id="725080" level="1"><TitleText>Consents and Undertakings</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725081" lims:id="725081"><Label>16</Label><Text>The application must include</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725082" lims:id="725082"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the applicant’s consent to the release by any regulatory authority or government department or by the Bank of Canada to the Corporation and its agents or mandataries of any information provided by the applicant to that authority, department or bank; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725083" lims:id="725083"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an undertaking to provide, or cause to be provided, any other consents, releases or waivers requested by the Corporation in connection with its review of the application.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725084" lims:id="725084"><Label>17</Label><Text>The application must include</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725085" lims:id="725085"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the applicant’s consent to the release by the Corporation to any regulatory authority or government department or to the Bank of Canada of any information provided in the application; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725086" lims:id="725086"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an undertaking by the applicant to provide, or cause to be provided, any other consents, releases or waivers requested by that authority, department or bank in connection with the Corporation’s review of the application.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725087" lims:id="725087" level="1"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725088" lims:id="725088"><Label>18</Label><Text>[Repeal]</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725089" lims:id="725089" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725090" lims:id="725090" type="transitional"><Label>19</Label><Text>This By-law comes into force on the day on which it is registered.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725091" lims:id="725091" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725092" lims:id="725092"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Paragraph 2(1)(b))</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><FormGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725093" lims:id="725093"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725094" lims:id="725094"><Label>FORM 1</Label><TitleText>Affidavit</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725095" lims:id="725095" pointsize="8" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725096" lims:id="725096" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725097" lims:id="725097" cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="33.93*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="25.43*" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725098" lims:id="725098"><row><entry morerows="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">In the matter of an application for deposit insurance made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-3">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal>,</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725099" lims:id="725099" format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>I, <Leader leader="solid" length="14pc" /> (<Emphasis style="italic">name in full</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" />,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725100" lims:id="725100" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>MAKE OATH AND SAY:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725101" lims:id="725101" format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>I am the <Leader leader="solid" length="12pc" /> (<Emphasis style="italic">title or office</Emphasis>) of <Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" />, the applicant, and, as such, I am submitting the application for deposit insurance.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725102" lims:id="725102" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The representations made in the application and in all attachments and any supplementary information or documents provided by the applicant to the Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation in connection with the application are true and correct, in all material respects, and contain no misrepresentations.</Text></Provision><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725103" lims:id="725103" pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="4" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725104" lims:id="725104" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725105" lims:id="725105" cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="2.53*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="0.12*" align="center" /><colspec colname="col4" colwidth="1.46*" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725106" lims:id="725106"><row><entry morerows="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>SWORN before me at the City of <Leader leader="solid" length="9pc" /> in the <Leader leader="solid" length="5pc" /> of <Leader leader="solid" length="3pc" /> this <Leader leader="solid" length="2pc" /> day of <Leader leader="solid" length="2pc" />, 20<Leader leader="solid" length="1.5pc" />.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><FormBlank width="10pc">Commissioner of Oaths</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry><entry morerows="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="middle"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><FormBlank width="6pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></FormGroup><PageBreak /><FormGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725107" lims:id="725107"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725108" lims:id="725108"><Label>FORM 2</Label><TitleText>Affidavit</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725109" lims:id="725109" pointsize="8" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725110" lims:id="725110" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725111" lims:id="725111" cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="33.92*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="25.44*" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725112" lims:id="725112"><row><entry morerows="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">In the matter of an application for deposit insurance made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-3">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal>,</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725113" lims:id="725113" format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>I, <Leader leader="solid" length="14pc" /> (<Emphasis style="italic">name in full</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="solid" length="10pc" />,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725114" lims:id="725114" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>MAKE OATH AND SAY:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725115" lims:id="725115" format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="left" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>I am the <Leader leader="solid" length="12pc" /> (<Emphasis style="italic">title or office</Emphasis>) of <Leader leader="solid" length="6pc" />, the entity that controls <Leader leader="solid" length="6pc" />, the applicant.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725116" lims:id="725116" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The representations made and the information and documents provided by the entity that controls the applicant in support of the application made by the applicant for deposit insurance are true and correct, in all material respects, and contain no misrepresentations.</Text></Provision><TableGroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725117" lims:id="725117" pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="4" rowbreak="no" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><table lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725118" lims:id="725118" frame="none"><tgroup lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725119" lims:id="725119" cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colwidth="2.53*" /><colspec colname="col2" colwidth="0.12*" align="center" /><colspec colname="col4" colwidth="1.46*" /><tbody lims:inforce-start-date="2006-09-28" lims:fid="725120" lims:id="725120"><row><entry morerows="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>SWORN before me at the City of <Leader leader="solid" length="9pc" /> in the <Leader leader="solid" length="5pc" /> of <Leader leader="solid" length="3pc" /> this <Leader leader="solid" length="2pc" /> day of <Leader leader="solid" length="2pc" />, 20<Leader leader="solid" length="1.5pc" />.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><FormBlank width="10pc">Commissioner of Oaths</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry><entry morerows="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="middle"><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text><FormBlank width="6pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row><row><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></FormGroup></Schedule></Regulation>