<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Regulation lims:pit-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878304" lims:id="878304" gazette-part="II" regulation-type="SOR" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878305" lims:id="878305"><InstrumentNumber>SOR/83-253</InstrumentNumber><RegistrationDate><Date><YYYY>1983</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></RegistrationDate><ConsolidationDate lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></ConsolidationDate><EnablingAuthority lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878307" lims:id="878307"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">AERONAUTICS ACT</XRefExternal></EnablingAuthority><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878308" lims:id="878308">Abbotsford Airport Zoning Regulations</ShortTitle><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878309" lims:id="878309">Regulations Respecting Zoning at Abbotsford Airport</LongTitle><RegulationMakerOrder><RegulationMaker>P.C.</RegulationMaker><OrderNumber>1983-802</OrderNumber><Date><YYYY>1983</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>17</DD></Date></RegulationMakerOrder></Identification><Order lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878310" lims:id="878310"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878311" lims:id="878311" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, pursuant to section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-2">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, is pleased hereby to approve the revocation made by the Minister of Transport of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-83-253">Abbotsford Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>, C.R.C., c. 74, and to approve the annexed <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-83-253">Regulations Respecting zoning at Abbotsford Airport</XRefExternal>, made by the Minister of Transport, in accordance with the schedule hereto.</Text></Provision></Order><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878312" lims:id="878312"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878313" lims:id="878313" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878314" lims:id="878314"><Label>1</Label><Text>These Regulations may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation" link="SOR-83-253">Abbotsford Airport Zoning Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878315" lims:id="878315" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878316" lims:id="878316"><Label>2</Label><Text>In these Regulations,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878317" lims:id="878317" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means Abbotsford Airport, in the District of Matsqui, in the Province of British Columbia; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878318" lims:id="878318" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport reference point</DefinedTermEn> means the point described in Part I of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>point de repère de l’aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878319" lims:id="878319" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>approach surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from each end of a strip, which approach surface is more particularly described in Part III of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface d’approche</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878320" lims:id="878320" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878321" lims:id="878321" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>outer surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary surface located above and in the immediate vicinity of the airport, which outer surface is more particularly described in Part IV of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>surface extérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878322" lims:id="878322" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>strip</DefinedTermEn> means the rectangular portion of the landing area of the airport, including the runway, prepared for the take-off and landing of aircraft in a particular direction, which strip is more particularly described in Part V of the schedule; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878323" lims:id="878323" generate-in-text="no"><Text><DefinedTermEn>transitional surface</DefinedTermEn> means an imaginary inclined plane that extends upward and outward from the lateral limits of a strip and its approach surfaces, which transitional surface is more particularly described in Part VI of the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>surface de transition</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878324" lims:id="878324"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of these Regulations, the assigned elevation of the airport reference point is 50.6 m above sea level.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878325" lims:id="878325" level="1"><TitleText>Application</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878326" lims:id="878326"><Label>4</Label><Text>These Regulations apply to all the lands, including public road allowances, adjacent to or in the vicinity of the airport, that consist of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878327" lims:id="878327"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the lands within, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878328" lims:id="878328"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the lands directly under that portion of an approach surface that extends beyond</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878329" lims:id="878329"><Text>the outer limits described in Part II of the schedule.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878330" lims:id="878330" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878331" lims:id="878331"><Label>5</Label><Text>No person shall erect or construct on any land to which these Regulations apply, any building, structure or object or any addition to any existing building, structure or object, the highest point of which will exceed in elevation at the location of that point, any</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878332" lims:id="878332"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>approach surface;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878333" lims:id="878333"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>outer surface; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878334" lims:id="878334"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>transitional surface.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878335" lims:id="878335" level="1"><TitleText>Natural Growth</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878336" lims:id="878336"><Label>6</Label><Text>Where an object of natural growth on any land to which these Regulations apply exceeds in elevation any of the surfaces referred to in paragraphs 5(a), (b) and (c), the Minister may make a direction that the owner or occupier of the land on which that object is growing remove the excessive growth.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878337" lims:id="878337" level="1"><TitleText>Disposal of Waste</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878338" lims:id="878338"><Label>7</Label><Text>No owner or occupier of any land to which these Regulations apply shall permit that land or any part of it to be used for the disposal of any waste that is edible by or attractive to birds.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878339" lims:id="878339" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878340" lims:id="878340"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(ss. 2 and 4)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878341" lims:id="878341" level="1"><Label>PART I</Label><TitleText>Description of the Airport Reference Point</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878342" lims:id="878342" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Being a point distant 448.621 m measured northerly at right angle to the centre line of runway 06-24 from a point thereon distant 951.465 m measured easterly along the centre line from the end of the strip associated with runway approach 06, which distances are ground level distances.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878343" lims:id="878343" level="1"><Label>PART II</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Limits of Lands</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878344" lims:id="878344" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The following described boundaries are the outer limits of lands:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878345" lims:id="878345" format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>COMMENCING at the intersection of the southerly production of the west boundary of Lot 1, Plan 22917 of Section 3, Township 13, N.W.D. with the International Boundary; thence, northerly along the said southerly production and the said west boundary of the said Plan 22917 and Plan 5981 to the northwest corner of Lot 1 of the said Plan 5981; thence, westerly along the north boundary of Plan 9379 and Plan 28496 to the northwest corner of Lot 31 of the said Plan 28496; thence, northerly along the east limit of Aberdeen Road to an intersection with the southerly limit of the approach surface associated with Runway Approach 06; thence, on a bearing of 355°17′10″ to an intersection with the northerly limit of the said approach surface; thence, easterly on a bearing of 93°49′01″ along the said northerly limit to the westerly boundary of Parcel A, R.P. 11534 of the West 1/2 of the Southwest 1/4, Section 10, Township 13, N.W.D.; thence, northerly along the said westerly boundary to the south boundary of the South 1/2 of the Northwest 1/4 of the said Section 10; thence, easterly along the said south boundary to the southeast corner of the said South 1/2; thence, northerly along the east boundary of the said South 1/2 and Lot 2, Plan 51482 to the northeast corner of the said Lot 2; thence, northerly across King Road to the southwest corner of the remainder of the Southeast 1/4 of Section 15, Township 13, N.W.D.; thence, northerly along the west boundary of the said Southeast 1/4 and Lot 6, Plan 48743 to the most westerly northwest corner of the said Lot 6; thence, northeasterly along the northwesterly boundary of the said Lot 6 to the south limit of Simpson Road; thence, easterly along Simpson Road to the northeast corner of Lot 5 of the said Plan 48743; thence, easterly across Ross Road to the northwest corner of Parcel C, R.P. 15575 of Section 14, Township 13, N.W.D.; thence, northerly across Simpson Road to the southwest corner of Lot 9, Plan 6497 of Section 23, Township 13, N.W.D.; thence, northerly along the east limit of Ross Road to the northwest corner of Lot 12, Plan 24818; thence, easterly along the north boundary of the said Lot 12, and the remainder of Lot 2, Plan 6497 to the northeast corner of the said Lot 2; thence, easterly across Lot 12, Plan 44019 to the northwest corner of Lot 3 of the aforementioned Plan 6497; thence, easterly along the north boundary of the said Lot 3 to an intersection with the end of the approach surface associated with Runway Approach 12; thence, on a bearing of 55°16′21″ along the end of the said approach surface to the northeast corner of the said approach surface; thence, on a bearing of 150°58′59″ along the northeasterly limit of the said approach surface to an intersection with the northerly limit of Old Yale Road; thence, easterly along the northerly limit of Old Yale Road to the most easterly corner of that part of Lot 3, Plan 4301 South of Highway; thence, easterly across the TransCanada Highway and Blue Jay Road to the southwest corner of Lot 9, Plan 34472 of Section 24, Township 13, N.W.D.; thence, easterly along the northerly limit of Old Yale Road to the southwest corner of the remainder of Lot 1, Plan 9648 of Section 19, Township 16, N.W.D.; thence, northerly along the east limit of Townline Road to the northwest corner of the said remainder of Lot 1; thence, easterly along the north boundary of the said remainder of Lot 1 to an intersection with the northwesterly limit of the approach surface associated with Runway Approach 18; thence, on a bearing of 19°34′38″ to the northwest corner of the said approach surface; thence, on a bearing of 115°17′16″ along the northerly limit of the said approach surface to an intersection with the north boundary of the said remainder of Lot 1; thence, easterly along the north boundary of the said Lot 1 and the easterly production thereof to the east boundary of the remainder of Lot 177, Plan 47795; thence, southerly along the east boundary of the said Plan 47795 to an intersection with the said northerly limit of the said approach surface; thence, on a bearing of 115°17′16″ to the northeast corner of the said approach surface; thence, on a bearing of 210°59′54″ along the southeasterly limit of the said approach surface to the northerly limit of Old Yale Road; thence, easterly along the northerly  limit of Old Yale Road to an intersection of the northerly production of the west limit of Parkview Street with the south boundary of Lot 223, Plan 43696 of Section 20, Township 16, N.W.D.; thence, southerly along the said northerly production and the west limit of Parkview Street and the southerly production thereof to the south limit of Peardonville Road; thence, easterly along the south limit of Peardonville Road to the Northeast corner of Lot 213, Plan 39101 of Section 17, Township 16, N.W.D.; thence, southerly along the east boundary of the said Plan 39101, Plan 29707, Plan 31677, and Plan 36628 to the southeast corner of Lot 190 of the said Plan 36628; thence, southerly across Bevan Crescent to the northeast corner of Lot 257, Plan 40431; thence, southerly along the east boundary of the said Plan 40431, Plan 44592, the said Plan 40431, and Plan 60062 and the southerly production thereof to the south limit of Marshall Road; thence, easterly along the south limit of Marshall Road to the northeast corner of Lot 1, Plan 18650; thence, southerly along the west limit of Gladwin Road to the southeast corner of the remainder of Lot A, Plan 8573; thence, southerly across the TransCanada Highway to the northeast corner of the remainder of Lot 4, Plan 6847; thence, southerly along the west limit of Gladwin Road to the southeast corner of Lot C, Plan 8959; thence, southerly across King Road to the northeast corner of the remainder of Lot C, R.P. 6741; thence, easterly across the aforementioned Gladwin Road to the northwest corner of Lot 4, Plan 33301 of Section 9, Township 16, N.W.D.; thence, easterly along the south limit of the aforementioned King Road to the northwest corner of Lot 10, Plan 21131; thence, southerly along the west limit of McCallum Road to an intersection with the northerly limit of the approach surface associated with Runway Approach 24; thence, on a bearing of 256°45′19″ to an intersection with a line bearing 355°17′10″, which line commences at the intersection of the northerly production of the east boundary of the North 1/2 of Lot 19, Plan 5211 of Section 4, Township 16, N.W.D. with the southerly limit of the said approach surface; thence on a bearing of 175°17′10″ along the said line to the said point of intersection; thence, southerly along the said northerly production to the northeast corner of the said North 1/2 of Lot 19, Plan 5211; thence, westerly along the south limit of Huntingdon Road to the northwest corner of Lot 34, Plan 26793; thence, westerly across Gladwin Road to the Northeast corner of District Lot 641, Group 2, N.W.D.; thence, southerly along the west limit of Gladwin Road and the southerly production thereof to an intersection with the International Boundary; thence, westerly along the International Boundary to the point of commencement;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878346" lims:id="878346" format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>which outer limits of land are shown outlined yellow on Department of Transport Plan No. (Z) B.C. 1414 dated the 7th day of November, 1980.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878347" lims:id="878347" level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Description of the Approach Surfaces</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878348" lims:id="878348" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The approach surfaces, shown on Department of Transport Abbotsford Airport Zoning Plan No. (Z) B.C. 1414 dated November 7, 1980 are surfaces abutting each end of the strips associated with runways designated 06-24, 12-30 and 18-36 and are described as follows:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878349" lims:id="878349" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 06 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; thence, the approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, which horizontal line commences at the intersection of the southerly limit of the approach surface associated with runway approach 06 with the west boundary of Lot 3 of Section 3, Township 13, Plan 11852; thence, the approach surface shall slope upward at a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip and distant 15 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 2 400 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 277.3 m above the end of the strip;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878350" lims:id="878350" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 24 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; thence, the approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip, which horizontal line commences at the intersection of the northerly production of the east boundary of the North 1/2 of Lot 19, Plan 5211 of Section 4, Township 16, N.W.D., with the southerly limit of the approach surface associated with runway approach 24; thence, the approach surface shall slope upward at a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 50 m measured horizontally to an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip and distant 15 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 2 400 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 262.38 m above the end of the strip;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878351" lims:id="878351" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 12 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 20 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; thence, the approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip and distant 3 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 345 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 41 m above the end of the strip;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878352" lims:id="878352" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 30 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 20 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; thence, the approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with the imaginary horizontal line drawn contiguous to the International border; said imaginary horizontal line being 41 m above the end of the strip;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878353" lims:id="878353" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 18 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 40 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; thence, the approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn at right angles to the projected centre line of the strip and distant 3 000 m measured horizontally from the end of the strip, the outer ends of the imaginary horizontal line being 450 m from the projected centre line; said imaginary horizontal line being 41 m above the end of the strip; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878354" lims:id="878354" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a surface abutting the end of the strip associated with runway approach 36 consisting of an inclined plane having a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 40 m measured horizontally rising to an intersection with the outer surface; thence, the approach surface shall be horizontal and contiguous to the outer surface to an intersection with an imaginary horizontal line drawn contiguous to the International border; said imaginary horizontal line being 41 m above the end of the strip.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878355" lims:id="878355" level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Description of the Outer Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878356" lims:id="878356" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The outer surface, shown on Department of Transport Abbotsford Airport Zoning Plan No. (Z) B.C. 1414 dated November 7, 1980 is an imaginary surface located at a common plane established at a constant elevation of 45 m above the assigned elevation of the airport reference point except where that common plane is less than 9 m above the surface of the ground, the imaginary surface is located at 9 m above the surface of the ground.</Text></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878357" lims:id="878357" level="1"><Label>PART V</Label><TitleText>Description of the Strips</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878358" lims:id="878358" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The strips, shown on Department of Transport Abbotsford Airport Zoning Plan No. (Z) B.C. 1414 dated November 7, 1980 are described as:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878359" lims:id="878359" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 06-24 is 300 m in width, 150 m being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and 2 558.37 m in length;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878360" lims:id="878360" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 12-30 is 90 m in width, 45 m being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and 1 726.974 m in length; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878361" lims:id="878361" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the strip associated with runway 18-36 is 300 m in width, 150 m being on each side of the centre line of the runway, and 1 726.769 m in length.</Text></Provision></Provision><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878362" lims:id="878362" level="1"><Label>PART VI</Label><TitleText>Description of Each Transitional Surface</TitleText></Heading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2006-03-22" lims:fid="878363" lims:id="878363" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Each transitional surface, shown on Department of Transport Abbotsford Airport Zoning Plan No. (Z) B.C. 1414 dated November 7, 1980 is a surface consisting of an inclined plane rising at a ratio of 1 m measured vertically to 7 m measured horizontally at right angles to the centre line and centre line produced of each strip and extending upward and outward from the lateral limits of each strip and its approach surfaces to an intersection with the outer surface or another transitional surface of an adjoining strip.</Text></Provision></Schedule></Regulation>