<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-37</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to change the names of certain electoral districts and to amend the Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Riding Name Change Act, 2014</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Riding Name Change, 2014</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>19</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2014</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-5-30">90740</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment changes the names of 30 electoral districts (in Quebec, Ontario, Saskatchewan, Alberta and British Columbia) and amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal> to change the name of the electoral district of the Northwest Territories.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Riding Name Change Act, 2014</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ELECTORAL DISTRICTS IN QUEBEC, ONTARIO, SASKATCHEWAN, ALBERTA AND BRITISH COLUMBIA</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Quebec</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Thérèse-De Blainville”</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 13 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Thérèse-De Blainville” for the name “Blainville”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Pierre-Boucher — ​​Les Patriotes — ​​Verchères”</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 14 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Pierre-Boucher — Les Patriotes — Verchères” for the name “Boucher — Les Patriotes — Verchères”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Rimouski-Neigette — ​​Témiscouata — ​​Les Basques”</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 18 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Rimouski-Neigette — Témiscouata — Les Basques” for the name “Centre-du-Bas-Saint-Laurent”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Beauport — ​​Côte-de-Beaupré — ​​Île d’Orléans — ​​Charlevoix”</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 20 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Beauport — Côte-de-Beaupré — Île d’Orléans — ​Charlevoix” for the name “Charlevoix — Montmorency”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Chicoutimi — ​​Le Fjord”</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 22 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Chicoutimi — Le Fjord” for the name “Chicoutimi”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Dorval — ​​Lachine — ​​LaSalle”</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 24 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Dorval — Lachine — LaSalle” for the name “Dorval — Lachine”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “LaSalle — ​​Émard — ​​Verdun”</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 37 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “LaSalle — Émard — Verdun” for the name “LaSalle — Verdun”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Longueuil — ​​Charles-LeMoyne”</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 41 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Longueuil — Charles-LeMoyne” for the name “LeMoyne”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Longueuil — ​​Saint-Hubert”</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 43 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Longueuil — Saint-Hubert” for the name “Longueuil”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Mount Royal”</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>In the English version of the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 52 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Mount Royal” for the name “Mont-Royal”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Marc-Aurèle-Fortin”</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 65 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Marc-Aurèle-Fortin” for the name “Sainte-Rose”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Vaudreuil — ​​Soulanges”</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 74 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Vaudreuil — Soulanges” for the name “Soulanges — Vaudreuil”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Ville-Marie — ​​Le Sud-Ouest — ​​Île-des-Soeurs”</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 77 of the part relating to Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Ville-Marie — Le Sud-Ouest — Île-des-Soeurs” for the name “Ville-Marie”.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Ontario</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Brantford — ​​Brant”</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 13 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Brantford — Brant” for the name “Brant”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Lanark — ​​Frontenac — ​​Kingston”</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 49 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Lanark — Frontenac — Kingston” for the name “Lanark — Frontenac”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Leeds — ​​Grenville — ​​Thousand Islands and Rideau Lakes”</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 50 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Leeds — Grenville — Thousand Islands and Rideau Lakes” for the name “Leeds — Grenville”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Mississauga East — ​​Cooksville”</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 59 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Mississauga East — Cooksville” for the name “Mississauga — Cooksville”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Northumberland — ​​Peterborough South”</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 71 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Northumberland — Peterborough South” for the name “Northumberland — Pine Ridge”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Orléans”</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 76 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Orléans” for the name “Ottawa — Orléans”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Peterborough — ​​Kawartha”</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 84 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Peterborough — Kawartha” for the name “Peterborough”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Carleton”</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 88 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Carleton” for the name “Rideau — Carleton”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Toronto — ​​St. Paul’s”</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 90 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Toronto — St. Paul’s” for the name “St. Paul’s”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Humber River — ​​Black Creek”</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 121 of the part relating to Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Humber River — Black Creek” for the name “York West”.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Saskatchewan</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Carlton Trail — ​​Eagle Creek”</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 4 of the part relating to Saskatchewan is amended by substituting the name “Carlton Trail — Eagle Creek” for the name “Humboldt — Warman — Martensville — ​Rosetown”.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Alberta</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Grande Prairie — ​​Mackenzie”</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 24 of the part relating to Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Grande Prairie — Mackenzie” for the name “Grande Prairie”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Medicine Hat — ​​Cardston — ​​Warner”</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 27 of the part relating to Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Medicine Hat — Cardston — Warner” for the name “Medicine Hat”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Red Deer — ​​Lacombe”</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 30 of the part relating to Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Red Deer — Lacombe” for the name “Red Deer — Wolf Creek”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Sturgeon River — ​​Parkland”</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 33 of the part relating to Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Sturgeon River — Parkland” for the name “Sturgeon River”.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>British Columbia</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Esquimalt — ​​Saanich — ​​Sooke”</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 26 of the part relating to British Columbia is amended by substituting the name “Esquimalt — Saanich — Sooke” for the name “Saanich — Esquimalt — Juan de Fuca”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “North Island — ​​Powell River”</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of October 1, 2013 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 37 of the part relating to British Columbia is amended by substituting the name “North Island — Powell River” for the name “Vancouver Island North — Comox — Powell River”.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-3</MarginalNote><TitleText>AMENDMENT TO THE <XRefExternal reference-type="act">ELECTORAL BOUNDARIES READJUSTMENT ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2014, c. 2, s. 8</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>Section 30 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Territorial electoral districts</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Text>In each of Yukon, the Northwest Territories and Nunavut, there shall be one electoral district respectively named and described as follows, each of which shall return one member:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>Yukon: consisting of Yukon as bounded and described in Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>Northwest Territories: consisting of the Northwest Territories as bounded and described in the definition <DefinedTermEn>Northwest Territories</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2"><Text>Nunavut: consisting of Nunavut as bounded and described in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nunavut Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>