<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-34</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to give effect to the Tla’amin Final Agreement and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Tla’amin Final Agreement Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Tla’amin Final Agreement</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2014</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-4-2">90728</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment gives effect to the Tla’amin Final Agreement. It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> recognizes and affirms the existing Aboriginal and treaty rights of the Aboriginal peoples of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the reconciliation between the prior presence of Aboriginal peoples and the assertion of sovereignty by the Crown is of significant social and economic importance to Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Canadian courts have stated that this reconciliation is best achieved through negotiation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Tla’amin Nation is an Aboriginal people of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Tla’amin Nation, the Government of Canada and the Government of British Columbia have negotiated the Agreement to achieve this reconciliation and to establish a new relationship among them;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas the Agreement requires that legislation be enacted by the Parliament of Canada in order for the Agreement to be ratified;</Text></Provision><?Pub Caret?></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tla’amin Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Tla’amin Final Agreement, between the Tla’amin Nation, Her Majesty in right of Canada and Her Majesty in right of British Columbia, including any amendments made to it.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tax Treatment Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord sur le traitement fiscal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tax Treatment Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the tax treatment agreement referred to in paragraph 22 of Chapter 21 of the Agreement, including any amendments made to it.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions in Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Former Sliammon Indian Reserves</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Other Tla’amin Lands</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Sliammon Indian Band</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tla’amin Citizen</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tla’amin Corporation</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tla’amin Government</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tla’amin Lands</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tla’amin Law</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tla’amin Nation</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Tla’amin Public Institution</DefinedTermEn> have the same meanings as in Chapter 1 of the Agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Status of Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Agreement is a treaty and a land claims agreement within the meaning of sections 25 and 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>AGREEMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement given effect</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, any person or body referred to in the Agreement has the powers, rights, privileges and benefits conferred on the person or body by the Agreement and must perform the duties, and is subject to the liabilities, imposed on the person or body by the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Third parties</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Agreement is binding on, and may be relied on by, all persons and bodies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement prevails</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agreement prevails over this Act and any other federal law to the extent of any inconsistency between them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Act prevails</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This Act prevails over any other federal law to the extent of any conflict between them.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>APPROPRIATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>There must be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund any sums that are required to meet the monetary obligations of Her Majesty in right of Canada under Chapters 18 and 19 of the Agreement.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>LANDS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Fee simple estate</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>On the effective date of the Agreement, the Tla’amin Nation owns the estate in fee simple, as set out in Chapter 3 of the Agreement, in the Tla’amin Lands, except for the lands described in Part 1 of Appendix C-3 of the Agreement, and in the Other Tla’amin Lands.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TAXATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tax Treatment Agreement given effect</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>The Tax Treatment Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law during the period that it is in effect.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>The Tax Treatment Agreement does not form part of the Agreement and is not a treaty or a land claims agreement within the meaning of sections 25 and 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>APPLICATION OF OTHER ACTS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>Subject to section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal>, to the provisions of Chapter 17 of the Agreement that deal with the continuing application of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> and to paragraphs 16 to 21 of Chapter 21 of the Agreement, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the Tla’amin Nation, Tla’amin Citizens, the Tla’amin Government, Tla’amin Public Institutions, Tla’amin Lands or Other Tla’amin Lands as of the effective date of the Agreement, except for the purpose of determining whether an individual is an Indian.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Subject to section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal>, the Framework Agreement as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act and the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Sliammon First Nation Land Code</XRefExternal> adopted under subsection 6(1) of that Act do not apply to the Tla’amin Nation, Tla’amin Citizens, the Tla’amin Government, Tla’amin Public Institutions or Tla’amin Lands as of the effective date of the Agreement.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>By-laws, land code and laws</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a by-law made by the Sliammon Indian Band under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Sliammon First Nation Land Code</XRefExternal> or a law made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal> and made in accordance with that land code is in effect immediately before the effective date of the Agreement, it continues to be in effect on the Former Sliammon Indian Reserves for a period of 90 days beginning on that date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>However, during that period, the Tla’amin Nation may repeal a by-law or law or the land code. Once repealed, the by-law, law or land code ceases to have effect.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Indemnification</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>For as long as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal> is in force, Her Majesty in right of Canada or the Tla’amin Nation, as the case may be, must, as of the effective date of the Agreement, indemnify the other in respect of anything done or omitted to be done in relation to the Former Sliammon Indian Reserves, in the same manner and under the same conditions as would be applicable if that Act continued to apply to the Former Sliammon Indian Reserves.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>Tla’amin Laws and other instruments made under the Agreement are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>APPLICATION OF LAWS OF BRITISH COLUMBIA</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>To the extent that a law of British Columbia does not apply of its own force to the Tla’amin Nation, Tla’amin Citizens, the Tla’amin Government, Tla’amin Public Institutions, Tla’amin Corporations, Tla’amin Lands or Other Tla’amin Lands, because of the exclusive legislative authority of Parliament set out in Class 24 of section 91 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>, that law of British Columbia applies to it or to them by virtue of this section, in accordance with the Agreement and subject to this Act and any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>GENERAL</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice of Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice must be taken of the Agreement and the Tax Treatment Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agreement and the Tax Treatment Agreement must be published by the Queen’s Printer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A copy of the Agreement or the Tax Treatment Agreement published by the Queen’s Printer is evidence of that agreement and of its contents, and a copy purporting to be published by the Queen’s Printer is presumed to be so published unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice of Tla’amin Laws</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice must be taken of Tla’amin Laws.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence of Tla’amin Laws</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A copy of a Tla’amin Law purporting to be deposited in the public registry referred to in subparagraph 19.a of Chapter 15 of the Agreement is evidence of that law and of its contents, unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of issues arising</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an issue arises in any judicial or administrative proceeding in respect of the interpretation or validity of the Agreement, or the validity or applicability of this Act, the British Columbia <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tla’amin Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal> or any Tla’amin Law, then the issue must not be decided until the party raising the issue has served notice on the Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of British Columbia and the Tla’amin Nation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content and timing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The notice must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>describe the proceeding;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify the subject matter of the issue;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>state the day on which the issue is to be argued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>give the particulars that are necessary to show the point to be argued; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>be served at least 14 days before the day of argument, unless the court or tribunal authorizes a shorter period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Participation in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of British Columbia and the Tla’amin Nation may appear and participate in any proceeding in respect of which subsection (1) applies as parties with the same rights as any other party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Saving</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsections (2) and (3) do not require that an oral hearing be held if one is not otherwise required.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Chapters 22 and 23 of Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>Despite subsection <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(1), Chapters 22 and 23 of the Agreement are deemed to have effect as of April 1, 2009.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make any orders and regulations that are necessary for the purpose of carrying out any of the provisions of the Agreement or of the Tax Treatment Agreement.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tla’amin Government, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tla’amin Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-14</MarginalNote><TitleText>Fisheries Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Subsection 5(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Tla’amin Laws, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tla’amin Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, made under Chapter 9 of the Agreement, as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act, given effect by that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. M-13; 2000, c. 8, s. 2</MarginalNote><TitleText>Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>The definition “taxing authority” in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tla’amin Government, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tla’amin Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, if it levies and collects a real property tax or a frontage or area tax in respect of Tla’amin Lands, as defined in that subsection;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Subsection 8(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tla’amin Government, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tla’amin Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 24</MarginalNote><TitleText>First Nations Land Management Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>SOR/2003-178, s. 1; 2012, c. 19, ss. 638 and 645</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Item 30 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 22</MarginalNote><TitleText>Specific Claims Tribunal Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>Part 1 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Tla’amin Final Agreement Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’accord définitif concernant les Tlaamins</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, other than section <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal>, come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>