<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-501</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting a National Hunting, Trapping and Fishing Heritage Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">National Hunting, Trapping and Fishing Heritage Day Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Hunting, Trapping and Fishing Heritage Day</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>26</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2014</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2006-12-07">411745</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment designates the third Saturday in September in each and every year as <DefinedTermEn>National Hunting, Trapping and Fishing Heritage Day</DefinedTermEn>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas hunting, trapping and fishing are part of Canada’s national heritage;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas the Aboriginal peoples of Canada have traditionally participated in hunting, trapping and fishing;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas Canada’s hunters, trappers and fishers have made a significant contribution to the development of our nation by traversing and mapping the prairies, forests, streams and rivers from coast to coast to coast;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas millions of Canadians participate in and enjoy hunting, trapping and fishing;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>And whereas hunting, trapping and fishing contribute significantly to the national economy;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Hunting, Trapping and Fishing Heritage Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>NATIONAL HUNTING, TRAPPING AND FISHING HERITAGE DAY</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National Hunting, Trapping and Fishing Heritage Day</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the third Saturday in September is to be known as “National Hunting, Trapping and Fishing Heritage Day”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, National Hunting, Trapping and Fishing Heritage Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>