<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-13</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code, the Canada Evidence Act, the Competition Act and the Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Protecting Canadians from Online Crime Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code, Canada Evidence, Competition and Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>31</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2014</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2013-11-14">90708</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to provide, most notably, for</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a new offence of non-consensual distribution of intimate images as well as complementary amendments to authorize the removal of such images from the Internet and the recovery of expenses incurred to obtain the removal of such images, the forfeiture of property used in the commission of the offence, a recognizance order to be issued to prevent the distribution of such images and the restriction of the use of a computer or the Internet by a convicted offender;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the power to make preservation demands and orders to compel the preservation of electronic evidence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>new production orders to compel the production of data relating to the transmission of communications and the location of transactions, individuals or things;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a warrant that will extend the current investigative power for data associated with telephones to transmission data relating to all means of telecommunications;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>warrants that will enable the tracking of transactions, individuals and things and that are subject to legal thresholds appropriate to the interests at stake; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a streamlined process of obtaining warrants and orders related to an authorization to intercept private communications by ensuring that those warrants and orders can be issued by a judge who issues the authorization and by specifying that all documents relating to a request for a related warrant or order are automatically subject to the same rules respecting confidentiality as the request for authorization.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> to ensure that the spouse is a competent and compellable witness for the prosecution with respect to the new offence of non-consensual distribution of intimate images.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Competition Act</XRefExternal> to make applicable, for the purpose of enforcing certain provisions of that Act, the new provisions being added to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> respecting demands and orders for the preservation of computer data and orders for the production of documents relating to the transmission of communications or financial data. It also modernizes the provisions of the Act relating to electronic evidence and provides for more effective enforcement in a technologically advanced environment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Lastly, it amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Act</XRefExternal> to make some of the new investigative powers being added to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> available to Canadian authorities executing incoming requests for assistance and to allow the Commissioner of Competition to execute search warrants under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Protecting Canadians from Online Crime Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">CRIMINAL CODE</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (7):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Means of telecommunication</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, for the purposes of this Act, if the elements of an offence contain an explicit or implicit element of communication without specifying the means of communication, the communication may also be made by a means of telecommunication.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 162:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Publication, etc., of an intimate image without consent</MarginalNote><Label>162.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone who knowingly publishes, distributes, transmits, sells, makes available or advertises an intimate image of a person knowing that the person depicted in the image did not give their consent to that conduct, or being reckless as to whether or not that person gave their consent to that conduct, is guilty</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>intimate image</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermFr>intimate image</DefinedTermFr> means a visual recording of a person made by any means including a photographic, film or video recording,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in which the person is nude, is exposing his or her genital organs or anal region or her breasts or is engaged in explicit sexual activity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of which, at the time of the recording, there were circumstances that gave rise to a reasonable expectation of privacy; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of which the person depicted retains a reasonable expectation of privacy at the time the offence is committed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall be convicted of an offence under this section if the conduct that forms the subject-matter of the charge serves the public good and does not extend beyond what serves the public good.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Question of fact and law, motives</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (3),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is a question of law whether the conduct serves the public good and whether there is evidence that the conduct alleged goes beyond what serves the public good, but it is a question of fact whether the conduct does or does not extend beyond what serves the public good; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the motives of an accused are irrelevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition order</MarginalNote><Label>162.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When an offender is convicted, or is discharged on the conditions prescribed in a probation order under section 730, of an offence referred to in subsection 162.1(1), the court that sentences or discharges the offender, in addition to any other punishment that may be imposed for that offence or any other condition prescribed in the order of discharge, may make, subject to the conditions or exemptions that the court directs, an order prohibiting the offender from using the Internet or other digital network, unless the offender does so in accordance with conditions set by the court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The prohibition may be for any period that the court considers appropriate, including any period to which the offender is sentenced to imprisonment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court may vary order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A court that makes an order of prohibition or, if the court is for any reason unable to act, another court of equivalent jurisdiction in the same province may, on application of the offender or the prosecutor, require the offender to appear before it at any time and, after hearing the parties, that court may vary the conditions prescribed in the order if, in the opinion of the court, the variation is desirable because of changed circumstances after the conditions were prescribed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who is bound by an order of prohibition and who does not comply with the order is guilty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 3(1); 1997, c. 18, s. 5; 2005, c. 32, ss. 8(1)(F) and 8(2)</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant of seizure</MarginalNote><Label>164.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A judge may issue a warrant authorizing seizure of copies of a recording, a publication, a representation or of written materials if the judge is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds for believing that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the recording, copies of which are kept for sale or distribution in premises within the jurisdiction of the court, is a voyeuristic recording;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the recording, copies of which are kept for sale or distribution in premises within the jurisdiction of the court, is an intimate image;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the publication, copies of which are kept for sale or distribution in premises within the jurisdiction of the court, is obscene or a crime comic, within the meaning of section 163; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the representation, written material or recording, copies of which are kept in premises within the jurisdiction of the court, is child pornography within the meaning of section 163.1.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 32, s. 8(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 164(3) to (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Owner and maker may appear</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The owner and the maker of the matter seized under subsection (1), and alleged to be obscene, a crime comic, child pornography, a voyeuristic recording or an intimate image, may appear and be represented in the proceedings in order to oppose the making of an order for the forfeiture of the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order of forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the publication, representation, written material or recording referred to in subsection (1) is obscene, a crime comic, child pornography, a voyeuristic recording or an intimate image, it may make an order declaring the matter forfeited to Her Majesty in right of the province in which the proceedings take place, for disposal as the Attorney General may direct.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposal of matter</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is not satisfied that the publication, representation, written material or recording referred to in subsection (1) is obscene, a crime comic, child pornography, a voyeuristic recording or an intimate image, it shall order that the matter be restored to the person from whom it was seized without delay after the time for final appeal has expired.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 32, s. 8(4)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consent</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If an order is made under this section by a judge in a province with respect to one or more copies of a publication, a representation, written material or a recording, no proceedings shall be instituted or continued in that province under section 162, 162.1, 163 or 163.1 with respect to those or other copies of the same publication, representation, written material or recording without the consent of the Attorney General.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(8) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>intimate image</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>image intime</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>intimate image</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 162.1(2).</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 32, s. 9(1)</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 164.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant of seizure</MarginalNote><Label>164.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a judge is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is material  —  namely child pornography within the meaning of section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording or an intimate image within the meaning of subsection 164(8) or computer data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography, a voyeuristic recording or an intimate image available  —  that is stored on and made available through a computer system within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that is within the jurisdiction of the court, the judge may order the custodian of the computer system to</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 32, s. 9(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 164.1(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the material is child pornography within the meaning of section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording or an intimate image within the meaning of subsection 164(8) or computer data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography, the voyeuristic recording or the intimate image available, it may order the custodian of the computer system to delete the material.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 32, s. 9(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 164.1(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of material</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the court is not satisfied that the material is child pornography within the meaning of section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording or intimate image within the meaning of subsection 164(8) or computer data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography, the voyeuristic recording or the intimate image available, the court shall order that the electronic copy be returned to the custodian and terminate the order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 1, s. 18</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 164.2(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture after conviction</MarginalNote><Label>164.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On application of the Attorney General, a court that convicts a person of an offence under section 162.1, 163.1, 172.1 or 172.2, in addition to any other punishment that it may impose, may order that anything — other than real property — be forfeited to Her Majesty and disposed of as the Attorney General directs if it is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the thing</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xxvii.1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xxvii.2)</Label><Text>section 162.1 (intimate image),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 108</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(lviii) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(lviii)</Label><Text>section 342.2 (possession of device to obtain unauthorized use of computer system or to commit mischief),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 108</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(lxvii) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(lxvii)</Label><Text>section 372 (false information),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Section 184.2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Related warrant or order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A judge who gives an authorization under this section may, at the same time, issue a warrant or make an order under any of sections 487, 487.01, 487.014 to 487.018, 487.02, 492.1 and 492.2 if the judge is of the opinion that the requested warrant or order is related to the execution of the authorization.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Section 186 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (7):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Related warrant or order</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>A judge who gives an authorization under this section may, at the same time, issue a warrant or make an order under any of sections 487, 487.01, 487.014 to 487.018, 487.02, 492.1 and 492.2 if the judge is of the opinion that the requested warrant or order is related to the execution of the authorization.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>Section 187 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (7):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Documents to be kept secret — related warrant or order</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The rules provided for in this section apply to all documents relating to a request for a related warrant or order referred to in subsection 184.2(5), 186(8) or 188(6) with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>Section 188 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Related warrant or order</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A judge who gives an authorization under this section may, at the same time, issue a warrant or make an order under any of sections 487, 487.01, 487.014 to 487.018, 487.02, 492.1 and 492.2 if the judge is of the opinion that the requested warrant or order is related to the execution of the authorization, that the urgency of the situation requires the warrant or the order and that it can be reasonably executed or complied with within 36 hours.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 14, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>Subsection 318(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>identifiable group</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>identifiable group</DefinedTermEn> means any section of the public distinguished by colour, race, religion, national or ethnic origin, age, sex, sexual orientation, or mental or physical disability.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 10</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 320.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant of seizure</MarginalNote><Label>320.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a judge is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is material that is hate propaganda within the meaning of subsection 320(8) or computer data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes hate propaganda available, that is stored on and made available to the public through a computer system within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that is within the jurisdiction of the court, the judge may order the custodian of the computer system to</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 10</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 320.1(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the material is available to the public and is hate propaganda within the meaning of subsection 320(8) or computer data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes hate propaganda available, it may order the custodian of the computer system to delete the material.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 10</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 320.1(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of material</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the court is not satisfied that the material is available to the public and is hate propaganda within the meaning of subsection 320(8) or computer data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes hate propaganda available, the court shall order that the electronic copy be returned to the custodian and terminate the order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 326(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>soit utilise une installation de télécommunication ou obtient un service de télécommunication.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 326(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>Section 327 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Possession, etc., of device to obtain use of telecommunication facility or telecommunication service</MarginalNote><Label>327.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone who, without lawful excuse, makes, possesses, sells, offers for sale, imports, obtains for use, distributes or makes available a device that is designed or adapted primarily to use a telecommunication facility or obtain a telecommunication service without payment of a lawful charge, under circumstances that give rise to a reasonable inference that the device has been used or is or was intended to be used for that purpose, is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under subsection (1) or paragraph 326(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), in addition to any punishment that is imposed, any device in relation to which the offence was committed or the possession of which constituted the offence may be ordered forfeited to Her Majesty and may be disposed of as the Attorney General directs.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No order for forfeiture is to be made in respect of telecommunication facilities or equipment by means of which an offence under subsection (1) is committed if they are owned by a person engaged in providing a telecommunication service to the public or form part of such a person’s telecommunication service or system and that person is not a party to the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>device</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>device</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a component of a device; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a computer program within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 45; 1997, c. 18, s. 18(1)</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 342.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized use of computer</MarginalNote><Label>342.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years, or is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction who, fraudulently and without colour of right,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>obtains, directly or indirectly, any computer service;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>by means of an electro-magnetic, acoustic, mechanical or other device, intercepts or causes to be intercepted, directly or indirectly, any function of a computer system;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>uses or causes to be used, directly or indirectly, a computer system with intent to commit an offence under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or under section 430 in relation to computer data or a computer system; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>uses, possesses, traffics in or permits another person to have access to a computer password that would enable a person to commit an offence under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 45</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 342.1(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 45; 1997, c. 18, s. 18(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>computer password</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>computer program</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>computer service</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>computer system</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 342.1(2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>computer password</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>mot de passe</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>computer password</DefinedTermEn> means any computer data by which a computer service or computer system is capable of being obtained or used;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>computer program</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>programme d’ordinateur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>computer program</DefinedTermEn> means computer data representing instructions or statements that, when executed in a computer system, causes the computer system to perform a function;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>computer service</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>service d’ordinateur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>computer service</DefinedTermEn> includes data processing and the storage or retrieval of computer data;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>computer system</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ordinateur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>computer system</DefinedTermEn> means a device that, or a group of interconnected or related devices one or more of which,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>contains computer programs or other computer data, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>by means of computer programs,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>performs logic and control, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>may perform any other function;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 342.1(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>computer data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données informatiques</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>computer data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, including signs, signals or symbols, that are in a form suitable for processing in a computer system; </Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 18, s. 19</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 342.2(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Possession of device to obtain unauthorized use of computer system or to commit mischief</MarginalNote><Label>342.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone who, without lawful excuse, makes, possesses, sells, offers for sale, imports, obtains for use, distributes or makes available a device that is designed or adapted primarily to commit an offence under section 342.1 or 430, under circumstances that give rise to a reasonable inference that the device has been used or is or was intended to be used to commit such an offence, is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under subsection (1), in addition to any punishment that is imposed, any device in relation to which the offence was committed or the possession of which constituted the offence may be ordered forfeited to Her Majesty and may be disposed of as the Attorney General directs.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 342.2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>device</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>device</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a component of a device; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a computer program within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>Sections 371 and 372 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Message in false name</MarginalNote><Label>371.</Label><Text>Everyone who, with intent to defraud, causes a message to be sent as if it were sent under the authority of another person, knowing that it is not sent under that authority and with intent that it should be acted on as if it were, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>False information</MarginalNote><Label>372.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone commits an offence who, with intent to injure or alarm a person, conveys information that they know is false, or causes such information to be conveyed by letter or any means of telecommunication.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indecent communications</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone commits an offence who, with intent to alarm or annoy a person, makes an indecent communication to that person or to any other person by a means of telecommunication.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Harassing communications</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Everyone commits an offence who, without lawful excuse and with intent to harass a person, repeatedly communicates, or causes repeated communications to be made, with them by a means of telecommunication.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits an offence under this section is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 57(1)</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 430(1.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mischief in relation to computer data</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Everyone commits mischief who wilfully</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>destroys or alters computer data;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>renders computer data meaningless, useless or ineffective;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>obstructs, interrupts or interferes with the lawful use of computer data; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>obstructs, interrupts or interferes with a person in the lawful use of computer data or denies access to computer data to a person who is entitled to access to it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 57(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 430(5) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mischief in relation to computer data</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Everyone who commits mischief in relation to computer data</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 57(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 430(5.1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>Everyone who wilfully does an act or wilfully omits to do an act that it is their duty to do, if that act or omission is likely to constitute mischief causing actual danger to life, or to constitute mischief in relation to property or computer data,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 57(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 430(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>computer data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>computer data</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 342.1(2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 18, s. 43; 2004, c. 3, s. 7</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>Sections 487.011 to 487.02 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>487.011</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and in sections <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.0199</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>computer data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données informatiques</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>computer data</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection <XRefInternal>342.1</XRefInternal>(2).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, including signs, signals or symbols, that are capable of being understood by an individual or processed by a computer system or other device.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>document</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>document</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>document</DefinedTermEn> means a medium on which data is registered or marked.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>juge</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn> means a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction or a judge of the Court of Quebec.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>public officer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fonctionnaire public</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>public officer</DefinedTermEn> means a public officer who is appointed or designated to administer or enforce a federal or provincial law and whose duties include the enforcement of this Act or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>tracking data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données de localisation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>tracking data</DefinedTermEn> means data that relates to the location of a transaction, individual or thing.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>transmission data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données de transmission</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>transmission data</DefinedTermEn> means data that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>relates to the telecommunication functions of dialling, routing, addressing or signalling;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is transmitted to identify, activate or configure a device, including a computer program as defined in subsection 342.1(2), in order to establish or maintain access to a telecommunication service for the purpose of enabling a communication, or is generated during the creation, transmission or reception of a communication and identifies or purports to identify the type, direction, date, time, duration, size, origin, destination or termination of the communication; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>does not reveal the substance, meaning or purpose of the communication.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Preservation demand</MarginalNote><Label>487.012</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A peace officer or public officer may make a demand to a person in Form 5.001 requiring them to preserve computer data that is in their possession or control when the demand is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for making demand</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The peace officer or public officer may make the demand only if they have reasonable grounds to suspect that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament or has been committed under a law of a foreign state;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an offence committed under a law of a foreign state, an investigation is being conducted by a person or authority with responsibility in that state for the investigation of such offences; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the computer data is in the person’s possession or control and will assist in the investigation of the offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A demand may not be made to a person who is under investigation for the offence referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expiry and revocation of demand</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A peace officer or public officer may revoke the demand by notice given to the person at any time. Unless the demand is revoked earlier, the demand expires</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an offence that has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament, 21 days after the day on which it is made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an offence committed under a law of a foreign state, 90 days after the day on which it is made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions in demand</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The peace officer or public officer who makes the demand may impose any conditions in the demand that they consider appropriate  — including conditions prohibiting the disclosure of its existence or some or all of its contents  — and may revoke a condition at any time by notice given to the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No further demand</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A peace officer or public officer may not make another demand requiring the person to preserve the same computer data in connection with the investigation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Preservation order — computer data</MarginalNote><Label>487.013</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application made by a peace officer or public officer, a justice or judge may order a person to preserve computer data that is in their possession or control when they receive the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for making order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before making the order, the justice or judge must be satisfied by information on oath in Form 5.002</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament or has been committed under a law of a foreign state, that the computer data is in the person’s possession or control and that it will assist in the investigation of the offence; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that a peace officer or public officer intends to apply or has applied for a warrant or an order in connection with the investigation to obtain a document that contains the computer data.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence against law of foreign state</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an offence has been committed under a law of a foreign state, the justice or judge must also be satisfied that a person or authority with responsibility in that state for the investigation of such offences is conducting the investigation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The order is to be in Form 5.003.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who is under investigation for an offence referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) may not be made subject to an order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expiry of order</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Unless the order is revoked earlier, it expires 90 days after the day on which it is made.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>General production order</MarginalNote><Label>487.014</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to sections <XRefInternal>487.015</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal>, on <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application made by a peace officer or public officer, a justice or judge may order a person to produce a document that is a copy of a document that is in their possession or control when they receive the order, or to prepare and produce a document containing data that is in their possession or control at that time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for making order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before making the order, the justice or judge must be satisfied by information on oath in Form 5.004 that there are reasonable grounds to believe that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the document or data is in the person’s possession or control and will afford evidence respecting the commission of the offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The order is to be in Form 5.005.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person who is under investigation for the offence referred to in subsection (2) may not be made subject to an order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Production order to trace specified communication</MarginalNote><Label>487.015</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application made by a peace officer or public officer for the purpose of identifying a device or person involved in the transmission of a communication, a justice or judge may order a person to prepare and produce a document containing transmission data that is related to that purpose and that is, when they are served with the order, in their possession or control.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for making order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before making the order, the justice or judge must be satisfied by information on oath in Form 5.004 that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the identification of a device or person involved in the transmission of a communication will assist in the investigation of the offence; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>transmission data that is in the possession or control of one or more persons whose identity is unknown when the application is made will enable that identification.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The order is to be in Form 5.006.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Service</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A peace officer or public officer may serve the order on any person who was involved in the transmission of the communication and whose identity was unknown when the application was made</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within 60 days after the day on which the order is made; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within one year after the day on which the order is made, in the case of an offence under section 467.11, 467.12 or 467.13, an offence committed for the benefit of, at the direction of or in association with a criminal organization, or a terrorism offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who is under investigation for the offence referred to in subsection (2) may not be made subject to an order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A peace officer or public officer named in the order must provide a written report to the justice or judge who made the order as soon as feasible after the person from whom the communication originated is identified or after the expiry of the period referred to in subsection (4), whichever occurs first. The report must state the name and address of each person on whom the order was served, and the date of service.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Production order — transmission data</MarginalNote><Label>487.016</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application made by a peace officer or public officer, a justice or judge may order a person to prepare and produce a document containing transmission data that is in their possession or control when they receive the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for making order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before making the order, the justice or judge must be satisfied by information on oath in Form 5.004 that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the transmission data is in the person’s possession or control and will assist in the investigation of the offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The order is to be in Form 5.007.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person who is under investigation for the offence referred to in subsection (2) may not be made subject to an order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Production order —  tracking data</MarginalNote><Label>487.017</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application made by a peace officer or public officer, a justice or judge may order a person to prepare and produce a document containing tracking data that is in their possession or control when they receive the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for making order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before making the order, the justice or judge must be satisfied by information on oath in Form 5.004 that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the tracking data is in the person’s possession or control and will assist in the investigation of the offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The order is to be in Form 5.007.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person who is under investigation for the offence referred to in subsection (2) may not be made subject to an order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Production order — financial data</MarginalNote><Label>487.018</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application made by a peace officer or public officer, a justice or judge may order a financial institution, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal>, or a person or entity referred to in section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal>, to prepare and produce a document setting out the following data that is in their possession or control when they receive the order:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>either the account number of a person named in the order or the name of a person whose account number is specified in the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the type of account;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the status of the account; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the date on which it was opened or closed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Identification of person</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of confirming the identity of a person who is named or whose account number is specified in the order, the order may also require the institution, person or entity to prepare and produce a document setting out the following data that is in their possession or control:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the date of birth of a person who is named or whose account number is specified in the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that person’s current address; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any previous addresses of that person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for making order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Before making the order, the justice or judge must be satisfied by information on oath in Form 5.004 that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the data is in the possession or control of the institution, person or entity and will assist in the investigation of the offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The order is to be in Form 5.008.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A financial institution, person or entity that is under investigation for the offence referred to in subsection (3) may not be made subject to an order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conditions in preservation and production orders</MarginalNote><Label>487.019</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> may contain any conditions that the justice or judge considers appropriate including, in the case of an order made under section <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal>, conditions to protect a privileged communication between a person who is qualified to give legal advice and their client.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The order has effect throughout Canada and, for greater certainty, no endorsement is needed for the order to be effective in a territorial division that is not the one in which the order is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power to revoke or vary order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application made by a peace officer or public officer, the justice or judge who made the order  —  or a judge in the judicial district where the order was made  —  may, on the basis of an information on oath in Form 5.0081, revoke or vary the order. The peace officer or public officer must give notice of the revocation or variation to the person who is subject to the order as soon as feasible.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Order prohibiting disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>487.0191</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application made by a peace officer or public officer, a justice or judge may make an order prohibiting a person from disclosing the existence or some or all of the contents of a preservation demand made under section <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal> or a preservation or production order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> during the period set out in the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for making order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before making the order, the justice or judge must be satisfied by information on oath in Form 5.009 that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure during that period would jeopardize the conduct of the investigation of the offence to which the preservation demand or the preservation or production order relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The order is to be in Form 5.0091.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application to revoke or vary order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A peace officer or a public officer or a person, financial institution or entity that is subject to an order made under subsection (1) may apply in writing to the justice or judge who made the order  —  or to a judge in the judicial district where the order was made  —  to revoke or vary the order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Particulars — production orders</MarginalNote><Label>487.0192</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>487.016</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> must require a person, financial institution or entity to produce the document to a peace officer or public officer named in the order within the time, at the place and in the form specified in the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Particulars — production order to trace specified communication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made under section <XRefInternal>487.015</XRefInternal> must require a person to produce the document to a peace officer or public officer named in the order as soon as feasible after they are served with the order at the place and in the form specified in the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form of production</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, an order under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> may specify that a document may be produced on or through an electro-magnetic medium.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 489.1 and 490 do not apply to a document that is produced under an order under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Probative force of copies</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every copy of a document produced under section <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> is admissible in evidence in proceedings under this or any other Act of Parliament on proof by affidavit that it is a true copy and has the same probative force as the document would have if it were proved in the ordinary way.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A document that is prepared for the purpose of production is considered to be original for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for review of production order</MarginalNote><Label>487.0193</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before they are required by an order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> to produce a document, a person, financial institution or entity may apply in writing to the justice or judge who made the order  —  or to a judge in the judicial district where the order was made  —  to revoke or vary the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice required</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The person, institution or entity may make the application only if they give notice of their intention to do so to a peace officer or public officer named in the order within 30 days after the day on which the order is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No obligation to produce</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The person, institution or entity is not required to prepare or produce the document until a final decision is made with respect to the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Revocation or variation of order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The justice or judge may revoke or vary the order if satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is unreasonable in the circumstances to require the applicant to prepare or produce the document; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>production of the document would disclose information that is privileged or otherwise protected from disclosure by law.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Destruction of preserved computer data and documents — preservation demand</MarginalNote><Label>487.0194</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person to whom a preservation demand is made under section <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal> shall destroy the computer data that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving computer data under that section as soon as feasible after the demand expires or is revoked, unless they are subject to an order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.017</XRefInternal> with respect to the computer data.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of preserved computer data and documents — preservation order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to a preservation order made under section <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> shall destroy the computer data that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving computer data under that section as soon as feasible after the order expires or is revoked, unless they are subject to a new preservation order or to a production order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.017</XRefInternal> with respect to the computer data.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of preserved computer data and documents — production order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to a production order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.017</XRefInternal> with respect to computer data that they preserved under a preservation demand or order made under section <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> shall destroy the computer data that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving computer data under that section as soon as feasible after the earlier of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which the production order is revoked, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which a document that contains the computer data is produced under the production order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of preserved computer data and documents — warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (1) to (3), a person who preserved computer data under a preservation demand or order made under section <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> shall destroy the computer data that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving computer data under that section when a document that contains the computer data is obtained under a warrant.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>487.0195</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, no preservation demand, preservation order or production order is necessary for a peace officer or public officer to ask a person to voluntarily preserve data that the person is not prohibited by law from preserving or to voluntarily provide a document to the officer that the person is not prohibited by law from disclosing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No civil or criminal liability</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who preserves data or provides a document in those circumstances does not incur any criminal or civil liability for doing so.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Self-incrimination</MarginalNote><Label>487.0196</Label><Text>No one is excused from complying with an order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> on the ground that the document that they are required to produce may tend to incriminate them or subject them to a proceeding or penalty. However, no document that an individual is required to prepare may be used or received in evidence against them in a criminal proceeding that is subsequently instituted against them, other than a prosecution for an offence under section 132, 136 or 137.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offence — preservation demand</MarginalNote><Label>487.0197</Label><Text>A person who contravenes a preservation demand made under section <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal> without lawful excuse is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable to a fine of not more than $5,000.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offence — preservation or production order</MarginalNote><Label>487.0198</Label><Text>A person, financial institution or entity that contravenes an order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> without lawful excuse is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable to a fine of not more than $250,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offence — destruction of preserved data</MarginalNote><Label>487.0199</Label><Text>A person who contravenes section <XRefInternal>487.0194</XRefInternal> without lawful excuse is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Assistance order</MarginalNote><Label>487.02</Label><Text>If an authorization is given under section 184.2, 184.3, 186 or 188 or a warrant is issued under this Act, the judge or justice who gives the authorization or issues the warrant may order a person to provide assistance, if the person’s assistance may reasonably be considered to be required to give effect to the authorization or warrant.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>487.021</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within seven years after the coming into force of this section, a comprehensive review of the provisions and operation of sections 487.011 to 487.02 shall be undertaken by such committee of the House of Commons as may be designated or established by the House for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee referred to in subsection (1) shall, within a year after a review is undertaken pursuant to that subsection or within such further time as the House may authorize, submit a report on the review to the Speaker of the House, including a statement of any changes the committee recommends.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 27, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>The heading before section 487.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Other Provisions Respecting Search Warrants, Preservation Orders and Production Orders</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 3, s. 8(1)</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 487.3(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Order denying access to information</MarginalNote><Label>487.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On application made at the time an application is made for a warrant under this or any other Act of Parliament, an order under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> or an authorization under section 529 or 529.4, or at a later time, a justice, a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction or a judge of the Court of Quebec may make an order prohibiting access to, and the disclosure of, any information relating to the warrant, order or authorization on the ground that</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 23, s. 14</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 487.3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the reason referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) outweighs in importance the access to the information.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 40, s. 18; 1999, c. 5, ss. 18 and 19</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>Sections 492.1 and 492.2 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant for tracking device — transactions and things</MarginalNote><Label>492.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A justice or judge who is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament and that tracking the location of one or more transactions or the location or movement of a thing, including a vehicle, will assist in the investigation of the offence may issue a warrant authorizing a peace officer or a public officer to obtain that tracking data by means of a tracking device.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Warrant for tracking device — individuals</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A justice or judge who is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to believe that an offence has been or will be committed under this or any other Act of Parliament and that tracking an individual’s movement by identifying the location of a thing that is usually carried or worn by the individual will assist in the investigation of the offence may issue a warrant authorizing a peace officer or a public officer to obtain that tracking data by means of a tracking device.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Scope of warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The warrant authorizes the peace officer or public officer, or a person acting under their direction, to install, activate, use, maintain, monitor and remove the tracking device, including covertly.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A warrant may contain any conditions that the justice or judge considers appropriate, including conditions to protect a person’s interests.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period of validity</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (6), a warrant is valid for the period specified in it as long as that period ends no more than 60 days after the day on which the warrant is issued.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period of validity — organized crime and terrorism offence</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A warrant is valid for the period specified in it as long as that period ends no more than one year after the day on which the warrant is issued, if the warrant relates to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under any of sections 467.11 to 467.13;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence committed for the benefit of, at the direction of, or in association with a criminal organization; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a terrorism offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal after expiry of warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application supported by an affidavit, the justice or judge who issued a warrant or another justice or judge who has jurisdiction to issue such warrants may authorize the covert removal of the tracking device after the expiry of the warrant under any conditions that the justice or judge considers advisable in the public interest. The authorization is valid for the period specified in it as long as that period is not more than 90 days.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, including signs, signals or symbols, that are capable of being understood by an individual or processed by a computer system or other device.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>juge</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn> means a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction or a judge of the Court of Quebec.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>public officer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fonctionnaire public</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>public officer</DefinedTermEn> means a public officer who is appointed or designated to administer or enforce a federal or provincial law and whose duties include the enforcement of this or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>tracking data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données de localisation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>tracking data</DefinedTermEn> means data that relates to the location of a transaction, individual or thing.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>tracking device</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>dispositif de localisation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>tracking device</DefinedTermEn> means a device, including a computer program within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2), that may be used to obtain or record tracking data or to transmit it by a means of telecommunication.</Text></Definition></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant for transmission data recorder</MarginalNote><Label>492.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A justice or judge who is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that an offence has been or will be committed against this or any other Act of Parliament and that transmission data will assist in the investigation of the offence may issue a warrant authorizing a peace officer or a public officer to obtain the transmission data by means of a transmission data recorder.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Scope of warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The warrant authorizes the peace officer or public officer, or a person acting under their direction, to install, activate, use, maintain, monitor and remove the transmission data recorder, including covertly.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No warrant shall be issued under this section for the purpose of obtaining tracking data.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period of validity</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (5), a warrant is valid for the period specified in it as long as that period ends no more than 60 days after the day on which the warrant is issued.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period of validity — organized crime or terrorism offence</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The warrant is valid for the period specified in it as long as that period ends no more than one year after the day on which the warrant is issued, if the warrant relates to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under any of sections 467.11 to 467.13;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence committed for the benefit of, at the direction of, or in association with a criminal organization; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a terrorism offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, including signs, signals or symbols, that are capable of being understood by an individual or processed by a computer system or other device.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>juge</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn> means a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction or a judge of the Court of Quebec.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>public officer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fonctionnaire public</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>public officer</DefinedTermEn> means a public officer who is appointed or designated to administer or enforce a federal or provincial law and whose duties include the enforcement of this or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>transmission data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données de transmission</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>transmission data</DefinedTermEn> means data that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>relates to the telecommunication functions of dialling, routing, addressing or signalling;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is transmitted to identify, activate or configure a device, including a computer program as defined in subsection 342.1(2), in order to establish or maintain access to a telecommunication service for the purpose of enabling a communication, or is generated during the creation, transmission or reception of a communication and identifies or purports to identify the type, direction, date, time, duration, size, origin, destination or termination of the communication; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>does not reveal the substance, meaning or purpose of the communication.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>transmission data recorder</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>enregistreur de données de transmission</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>transmission data recorder</DefinedTermEn> means a device, including a computer program within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2), that may be used to obtain or record transmission data or to transmit it by a means of telecommunication.</Text></Definition></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Subsection 738(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an offence under subsection 162.1(1), by paying to a person who, as a result of the offence, incurs expenses to remove the intimate image from the Internet or other digital network, an amount that is not more than the amount of those expenses, to the extent that they are reasonable, if the amount is readily ascertainable.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Text>Subsection 810(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>If injury or damage feared</MarginalNote><Label>810.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An information may be laid before a justice by or on behalf of any person who fears on reasonable grounds that another person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>will cause personal injury to him or her or to his or her spouse or common-law partner or child or will damage his or her property; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>will commit an offence under section 162.1.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by adding the following after Form 5:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.001</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.012(1))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>PRESERVATION DEMAND</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Because I have reasonable grounds to suspect that the computer data specified below is in your possession or control and that that computer data</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>will assist in the investigation of an offence that has been or will be committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Act of Parliament</Emphasis>),</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>will assist in the investigation of an offence that has been committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the law of the foreign state</Emphasis>) that is being conducted by a person or authority, (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person or authority</Emphasis>), with responsibility in (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the name of the foreign state</Emphasis>) for the investigation of such offences,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>you are required to preserve (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the computer data</Emphasis>) that is in your possession or control when you receive this demand until (<Emphasis style="italic">insert date</Emphasis>) unless, before that date, this demand is revoked or a document that contains that data is obtained under a warrant or an order.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This demand is subject to the following conditions:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you contravene this demand without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You are required to destroy the computer data that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business, and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving the computer data, in accordance with section <XRefInternal>487.0194</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>. If you contravene that provision without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="15pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.002</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.013(2))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>INFORMATION TO OBTAIN A PRESERVATION ORDER</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" hyphenation="no" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This is the information of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /> (“the informant”).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant says that they have reasonable grounds to suspect that an offence has been or will be committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Act of Parliament</Emphasis>) (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> has been committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the law of the foreign state</Emphasis>)) and that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the computer data</Emphasis>) is in the possession or control of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>) and will assist in the investigation of the offence.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant also says that a peace officer or public officer intends to apply or has applied for a warrant or order in connection with the investigation to obtain a document that contains the computer data (<Emphasis style="italic">and, if applicable,</Emphasis> and that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person or authority</Emphasis>) is conducting the investigation and has responsibility for the investigation of such offences in (<Emphasis style="italic">insert the name of the foreign state</Emphasis>)).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The reasonable grounds are: (<Emphasis style="italic">including, if applicable, whether a preservation demand was made under section 487.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant therefore requests that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>) be ordered to preserve (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the computer data</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they receive the order for 90 days after the day on which the order is made.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sworn before me on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of informant</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.003</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.013(4))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>PRESERVATION ORDER</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas I am satisfied by information on oath of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that an offence has been or will be committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Act of Parliament</Emphasis>) (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> has been committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the law of the foreign state</Emphasis>)) and that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the computer data</Emphasis>) is in your possession or control and will assist in the investigation of the offence; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that a peace officer or public officer intends to apply or has applied for a warrant or order to obtain a document that contains the computer data (<Emphasis style="italic">and, if applicable,</Emphasis> and that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person or authority</Emphasis>) is conducting the investigation and has responsibility for the investigation of such offences in (<Emphasis style="italic">insert the name of the foreign state</Emphasis>));</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, you are required to preserve the specified computer data that is in your possession or control when you receive this order until (<Emphasis style="italic">insert date</Emphasis>) unless, before that date, this order is revoked or a document that contains that data is obtained under a warrant or an order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This order is subject to the following conditions:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you contravene this order without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You are required to destroy the computer data that would not be retained in the ordinary course of business, and any document that is prepared for the purpose of preserving the computer data, in accordance with section <XRefInternal>487.0194</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>. If you contravene that provision without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.004</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsections 487.014(2), 487.015(2), 487.016(2), 487.017(2) and 487.018(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>INFORMATION TO OBTAIN A PRODUCTION ORDER</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" hyphenation="no" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This is the information of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /> (“the informant”).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant says that they have reasonable grounds to suspect (<Emphasis style="italic">or, if the application is for an order under section 487.014 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Emphasis> reasonable grounds to believe)</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that an offence has been or will be committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Act of Parliament</Emphasis>); and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.014 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the document or data</Emphasis>) is in the possession or control of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>) and will afford evidence respecting the commission of the offence.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.015 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that the identification of a device or person involved in the transmission of (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the communication</Emphasis>) will assist in the investigation of the offence and that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the transmission data</Emphasis>) that is in the possession or control of one or more persons whose identity is unknown will enable that identification.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.016 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the transmission data</Emphasis>) is in the possession or control of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>) and will assist in the investigation of the offence.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.017 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the tracking data</Emphasis>) is in the possession or control of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>) and will assist in the investigation of the offence.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.018 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the data</Emphasis>) is in the possession or control of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the financial institution, person or entity</Emphasis>) and will assist in the investigation of the offence.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The reasonable grounds are:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant therefore requests</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.014 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>) be ordered to produce a document that is a copy of (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the document</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they receive the order (<Emphasis style="italic">and/or</Emphasis> to prepare and produce a document containing (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the data</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they receive the order).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.015 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that a person who is served with the order in accordance with subsection 487.015(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> be ordered to prepare and produce a document containing (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the transmission data</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they are served with the order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.016 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>) be ordered to prepare and produce a document containing (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the transmission data</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they receive the order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.017 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>) be ordered to prepare and produce a document containing (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the tracking data</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they receive the order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">if the application is for an order under section 487.018 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>) that (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the financial institution, person or entity</Emphasis>) be ordered to prepare and produce a document setting out (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the data</Emphasis>) that is in their possession or control when they receive the order.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sworn before me on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of informant</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.005</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.014(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>PRODUCTION ORDER FOR DOCUMENTS</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas I am satisfied by information on oath of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />, that there are reasonable grounds to believe that an offence has been or will be committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Act of Parliament</Emphasis>) and that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the document or data</Emphasis>) is in your possession or control and will afford evidence respecting the commission of the offence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, you are ordered to</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>produce a document that is a copy of (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the document</Emphasis>) that is in your possession or control when you receive this order</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">and/or</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>prepare and produce a document containing (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the data</Emphasis>) that is in your possession or control when you receive this order.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The document must be produced to (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>) within (<Emphasis style="italic">time</Emphasis>) at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>) in (<Emphasis style="italic">form</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This order is subject to the following conditions:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You have the right to apply to revoke or vary this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you contravene this order without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.006</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.015(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>PRODUCTION ORDER TO TRACE A COMMUNICATION</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas I am satisfied by information on oath of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />, that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that an offence has been or will be committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Act of Parliament</Emphasis>), that the identification of a device or person involved in the transmission of (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the communication</Emphasis>) will assist in the investigation of the offence and that one or more persons whose identity was unknown when the application was made have possession or control of (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the transmission data</Emphasis>) that will enable that identification;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, on being served with this order in accordance with subsection <XRefInternal>487.015</XRefInternal>(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, you are ordered to prepare and produce a document containing (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the transmission data</Emphasis>) that is in your possession or control when you are served with this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The document must be produced to (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>) as soon as feasible at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>) in (<Emphasis style="italic">form</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This order is subject to the following conditions:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You have the right to apply to revoke or vary this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you contravene this order without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Served on (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person</Emphasis>) on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="15pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of person served</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.007</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsections 487.016(3) and 487.017(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>PRODUCTION ORDER FOR TRANSMISSION DATA OR TRACKING DATA</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas I am satisfied by information on oath of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />, that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that an offence has been or will be committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Act of Parliament</Emphasis>) and that (<Emphasis style="italic">if the order is made under section <XRefInternal>487.016</XRefInternal> of the</Emphasis> <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, <Emphasis style="italic">specify the transmission data</Emphasis>) (<Emphasis style="italic">or, if the order is made under section <XRefInternal>487.017</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, specify the tracking data</Emphasis>) is in your possession or control and will assist in the investigation of the offence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, you are ordered to prepare and produce a document containing the data specified that is in your possession or control when you receive this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The document must be produced to (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>) within (<Emphasis style="italic">time</Emphasis>) at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>) in (<Emphasis style="italic">form</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This order is subject to the following conditions:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You have the right to apply to revoke or vary this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you contravene this order without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.008</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.018(4))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>PRODUCTION ORDER FOR FINANCIAL DATA</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To (<Emphasis style="italic">name of financial institution, person or entity</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas I am satisfied by information on oath of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />, that there are reasonable grounds to suspect that an offence has been or will be committed under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or other Act of Parliament</Emphasis>) and that (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the data</Emphasis>) is in your possession or control and will assist in the investigation of the offence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, you are ordered to prepare and produce a document setting out (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the data</Emphasis>) that is in your possession or control when you receive this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The document must be produced to (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>) within (<Emphasis style="italic">time</Emphasis>) at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>) in (<Emphasis style="italic">form</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This order is subject to the following conditions:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You have the right to apply to revoke or vary this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you contravene this order without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.0081</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.019(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>INFORMATION TO REVOKE OR VARY AN ORDER MADE UNDER ANY OF SECTIONS 487.013 TO 487.018 OF THE <XRefExternal reference-type="act">CRIMINAL CODE</XRefExternal></TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" hyphenation="no" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This is the information of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /> (“the informant”).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant says that on or after (<Emphasis style="italic">insert date</Emphasis>) the informant became aware of the following facts that justify the revocation (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> variation) of an order made on (<Emphasis style="italic">insert date</Emphasis>) under (<Emphasis style="italic">specify the provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Emphasis>):</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant therefore requests that the order be revoked (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> be varied as follows: <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sworn before me on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of informant</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.009</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.0191(2))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>INFORMATION TO OBTAIN A NON-DISCLOSURE ORDER</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" hyphenation="no" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This is the information of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /> (“the informant”).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant says that they have reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure of the existence (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> any of the contents <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> any of the following portion or portions) of (<Emphasis style="italic">identify the preservation demand made under section <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the preservation order made under section <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> of that Act or the production order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> of that Act, as the case may be</Emphasis>) during (<Emphasis style="italic">identify the period</Emphasis>) would jeopardize the conduct of the investigation of the offence to which it relates:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">specify portion or portions</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The reasonable grounds are:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The informant therefore requests an order prohibiting (<Emphasis style="italic">name of the person</Emphasis>, financial institution or entity) from disclosing the existence (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> any of the contents <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> any of the specified portion or portions) of the demand (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> the order) during a period of (<Emphasis style="italic">identify the period</Emphasis>) after the day on which the order is made.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Sworn before me on (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of informant</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 5.0091</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 487.0191(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>NON-DISCLOSURE ORDER</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Province of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" /></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>To (<Emphasis style="italic">name of person, financial institution or entity</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas I am satisfied by information on oath of (<Emphasis style="italic">name of peace officer or public officer</Emphasis>), of <Leader leader="dot" length="4pc" />, that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the disclosure of the existence (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> any of the contents <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> any of the portion or portions, specified in the information,) of (<Emphasis style="italic">identify the preservation demand made under section <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the preservation order made under section <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal> of that Act or the production order made under any of sections <XRefInternal>487.014</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> of that Act, as the case may be</Emphasis>) during (<Emphasis style="italic">identify the period</Emphasis>) would jeopardize the conduct of the investigation of the offence to which it relates;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Therefore, you are prohibited from disclosing the existence (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> any of the contents <Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> any of the following portion or portions) of the demand (<Emphasis style="italic">or</Emphasis> the order) during a period of (<Emphasis style="italic">identify the period</Emphasis>) after the day on which this order is made.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">specify portion or portions</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>You have the right to apply to revoke or vary this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>If you contravene this order without lawful excuse, you may be subject to a fine, to imprisonment or to both.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Dated (<Emphasis style="italic">date</Emphasis>), at (<Emphasis style="italic">place</Emphasis>).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text><FormBlank width="12pc">(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of justice or judge</Emphasis>)</FormBlank></Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S. c. C-5</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">CANADA EVIDENCE ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>Subsection 4(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> is amended by replacing “160(2) or (3)” with “160(2) or (3) or 162.1(1)”.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-34; R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 19</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">COMPETITION ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 20(3)</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Competition Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>document</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn> means a medium on which information is registered or marked;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>computer system</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ordinateur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>computer system</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 342.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, including signs, signals or symbols, that are capable of being understood by an individual or processed by a computer system or other device;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>renseignement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>information</DefinedTermEn> includes data;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 14:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> — preservation demand and orders for preservation or production of data</MarginalNote><Label>14.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>487.012</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>487.013</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>487.015</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>487.016</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>487.018</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, which apply to the investigation of offences under any Act of Parliament, also apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to an investigation in relation to a contravention of an order made under section 32, 33 or 34 or Part VII.1 or VIII; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to an investigation in relation to whether grounds exist for the making of an order under Part VII.1 or VIII.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> referred to in subsection (1) apply whether or not an inquiry has been commenced under section 10.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 24</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Text>Subsection 16(6) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (2nd Supp.), s. 24</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>Subsection 20(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copies</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Copies of any records referred to in subsection (1), made by any process of reproduction, on proof orally or by affidavit that they are true copies, are admissible in evidence in any proceedings under this Act and have the same probative force as the original.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 16, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> in section 30 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 12(1)</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>Paragraph 52(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>made in the course of in-store or door-to-door selling to a person as ultimate user, or by communicating orally by any means of telecommunication to a person as ultimate user, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 13</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 52.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>telemarketing</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>52.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>telemarketing</DefinedTermEn> means the practice of communicating orally by any means of telecommunication for the purpose of promoting, directly or indirectly, any business interest or the supply or use of a product.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 13</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 52.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>disclosure is made, in a fair and reasonable manner at the beginning of each communication, of the identity of the person on behalf of whom the communication is made, the nature of the business interest or product being promoted and the purposes of the communication;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 13</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 52.1(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time of disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The disclosure of information referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) must be made during the course of a communication unless it is established by the accused that the information was disclosed within a reasonable time before the communication, by any means, and the information was not requested during the communication.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 2, s. 22</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>Paragraph 74.03(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>made in the course of in-store or door-to-door selling to a person as ultimate user, or by communicating orally by any means of telecommunication to a person as ultimate user, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 30 (4th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">MUTUAL LEGAL ASSISTANCE IN CRIMINAL MATTERS ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>36.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mutual Legal Assistance in Criminal Matters Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, including signs, signals or symbols, that are capable of being understood by an individual or processed by a computer system or other device;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>document</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn> means a medium on which data is registered or marked;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37.</Label><Text>Section 12 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commissioner of Competition</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The judge may, in addition to or instead of a peace officer, authorize the Commissioner of Competition appointed under subsection 7(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Competition Act</XRefExternal> or his or her authorized representative named in the warrant to execute the search warrant, in which case the Commissioner or his or her representative, as the case may be, has, in relation to the warrant, all of the powers and duties that are set out for a peace officer in this section and sections 13 and 14.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 24, s. 61</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>Section 13.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 16:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Other warrants</MarginalNote><Label>16.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A judge of the province to whom an application is made under subsection 11(2) may, in the manner provided for by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, issue a warrant, other than a warrant referred to in section 12, to use any device or investigative technique or do anything described in the warrant that would, if not authorized, constitute an unreasonable search or seizure in respect of a person or a person’s property.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), a warrant issued under subsection (1) may be obtained, issued and executed in the manner provided for by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — certain warrants</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 12(3) and (4) and sections 14 to 16 apply in respect of a warrant issued under subsection (1)  —  other than a warrant issued in the manner provided for by section 492.1 or 492.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>  —  and prevail over any provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that are inconsistent with them.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Sending abroad —  certain warrants</MarginalNote><Label>16.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a judge referred to in subsection 16.1(1) issues a warrant in the manner provided for under section 492.1 or 492.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the judge must also order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the peace officer who executes the warrant send a record containing the data obtained under the warrant directly to the state or entity that made the request under subsection 11(1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that sections 20 and 21 apply to the warrant with any necessary modifications.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The peace officer who executes the warrant must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make a report concerning the execution of the warrant to the judge who issued the warrant or to another judge of the same court, accompanied by a general description of the data obtained under the warrant and, if the judge requires it, a record containing the data; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>send a copy of the report to the Minister without delay.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Timing of report and sending abroad</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the judge makes an order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the peace officer must make the report to the judge and send a record containing the data to the state or entity that made the request no later than five days after the day on which all of the data is obtained under the warrant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40.</Label><Text>The heading before section 17 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Production Orders</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 22:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>22.01</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies, with any necessary modifications, in respect of an order made under subsection 22.03(1) in the manner provided for under any of sections 487.015 to 487.018 and 487.0191 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, except to the extent that that Act is inconsistent with this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Approval of request to obtain production</MarginalNote><Label>22.02</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister approves a request of a state or entity to obtain an order under this Act made in the manner provided for under any of sections 487.015 to 487.018 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to require the production of a record containing data, the Minister must provide a competent authority with any documents or information necessary to apply for the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application for orders</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The competent authority must apply <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> for an order made in the manner provided for under any of sections 487.015 to 487.018 and 487.0191 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to a justice as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction as defined in that section or a judge of the Court of Quebec.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Production and non-disclosure orders</MarginalNote><Label>22.03</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The justice or judge to whom the application is made may make an order in the manner provided for under any of sections 487.015 to 487.018 and 487.0191 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> if the conditions set out in that section have been met.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Condition in order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made in the manner provided for under any of sections 487.015 to 487.018 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> must require that a record containing the data be given to a designated person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Sending abroad</MarginalNote><Label>22.04</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the justice or judge makes an order in the manner provided for under any of sections 487.015 to 487.018 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the justice or judge must also order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the person designated in the order send a record containing the data directly to the state or entity that made the request under subsection 22.02(1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that sections 20 and 21 apply to the order with any necessary modifications.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The person designated in the order must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make a report concerning the execution of the order to the justice or judge who made it  —  or to another justice for the same territorial division or another judge in the judicial district where the order was made  —  accompanied by a general description of the data contained in the record obtained under the order and, if the justice or judge requires it, a record containing the data; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>send a copy of the report to the Minister without delay.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Timing of report and sending abroad</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the justice or judge makes an order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the person designated in the order must make the report to the justice or judge and send a record containing the data to the state or entity that made the request no later than five days after the day on which such a record is obtained under the order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>22.05</Label><Text>Section 487.0198 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies to everyone who is subject to an order made under subsection 22.03(1) in the manner provided for under any of sections 487.015 to 487.018 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Video Link</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 22.4:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Arrest Warrant</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 23:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Examination of Place or Site</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 18, s. 120</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Text>Subsection 36(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Probative value</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of determining the probative value of a record or a copy of a record admitted in evidence under this Act, the trier of fact may examine the record or copy, receive evidence orally or by affidavit, or by a certificate or other statement pertaining to the record in which a person attests that the certificate or statement is made in conformity with the laws that apply to a state or entity, whether or not the certificate or statement is in the form of an affidavit attested to before an official of the state or entity, including evidence as to the circumstances in which the data contained in the record or copy was written, stored or reproduced, and draw any reasonable inference from the form or content of the record or copy.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 18, s. 127</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 44(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Documents protégés</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sous réserve du paragraphe 38(2), les documents transmis au ministre par un État ou entité en conformité avec une demande canadienne sont protégés. Jusqu’à ce qu’ils aient été, en conformité avec les conditions attachées à leur transmission au ministre, rendus publics ou révélés au cours ou aux fins d’une déposition devant un tribunal, il est interdit de communiquer à quiconque ces documents, leur teneur ou des données qu’ils contiennent.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 44(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Privilege</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person in possession of a record mentioned in subsection (1) or of a copy of such a record, or who has knowledge of any data contained in the record, shall be required, in connection with any legal proceedings, to produce the record or copy or to give evidence relating to any data that is contained in it.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2010, c. 23</MarginalNote><Label>46.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>other Act</DefinedTermEn> means <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to promote the efficiency and adaptability of the Canadian economy by regulating certain activities that discourage reliance on electronic means of carrying out commercial activities, and to amend the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission Act, the Competition Act, the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act and the Telecommunications Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act comes into force before subsection 70(1) of the other Act, then that subsection 70(1) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If subsection 70(1) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subsection <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act, then that subsection 70(1) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If subsection 70(2) of the other Act comes into force before subsection <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then that subsection <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>(2) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, including signs, signals or symbols, that are capable of being understood by an individual or processed by a computer system or other device;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act comes into force before subsection 70(2) of the other Act, then that subsection 70(2) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>electronic message</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>message électronique</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>electronic message</DefinedTermEn> means a message sent by any means of telecommunication, including a text, sound, voice or image message;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>locator</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>localisateur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>locator</DefinedTermEn> means a name or information used to identify a source of data on a computer system, and includes a URL;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>sender information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>renseignements sur l’expéditeur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>sender information</DefinedTermEn> means the part of an electronic message  —  including the data relating to source, routing, addressing or signalling  —  that identifies or purports to identify the sender or the origin of the message;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>subject matter information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>objet</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>subject matter information</DefinedTermEn> means the part of an electronic message that purports to summarize the contents of the message or to give an indication of them;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If subsection 70(2) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subsection <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then that subsection 70(2) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>(2) and subsection (4) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If section 71 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>30</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>30</XRefInternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>30</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 71 of the other Act, then that section 71 is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If section 71 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>30</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section 71 is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>30</XRefInternal> and subsection (7) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>If section 72 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 72 of the other Act, then that section 72 is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(12)</Label><Text>If section 72 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section 72 is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> and subsection (10) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(13)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before subsection 74(2) of the other Act, then that subsection 74(2) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(14)</Label><Text>If subsection 74(2) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that subsection 74(2) is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(15)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act comes into force before subsection 76(1) of the other Act, then that subsection 76(1) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(16)</Label><Text>If subsection 76(1) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act, then that subsection 76(1) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(17)</Label><Text>If subsection 76(2) of the other Act comes into force before subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then that subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(2) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(18)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act comes into force before subsection 76(2) of the other Act, then that subsection 76(2) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(19)</Label><Text>If subsection 76(2) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then that subsection 76(2) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(2) and subsection (17) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(20)</Label><Text>If subsection 76(3) of the other Act comes into force before subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(3) of this Act, then that subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(3) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(21)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(3) of this Act comes into force before subsection 76(3) of the other Act, then that subsection 76(3) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(22)</Label><Text>If subsection 76(3) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(3) of this Act, then that subsection 76(3) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(3) and subsection (20) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(23)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 78 of the other Act, then that section 78 is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(24)</Label><Text>If section 78 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section 78 is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Three months after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Text>This Act, other than section 46, comes into force three months after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>