<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-213</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting Lincoln Alexander Day</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Lincoln Alexander Day Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Lincoln Alexander Day</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>9</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><?Pub Caret1?><AnnualStatuteNumber>30</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2014</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2013-12-03">1324</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment designates the twenty-first day of January in each and every year as “Lincoln Alexander Day”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Colonel The Honourable Lincoln MacCauley Alexander demonstrated, through his life’s pursuits, a longstanding interest in and commitment to serving his country and his community;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas Colonel The Honourable Lincoln MacCauley Alexander had a long and distinguished record of public service, including as an airman in the Royal Canadian Air Force, as a Member of Parliament in the House of Commons and a Minister of the Crown, and later as the twenty-fourth Lieutenant Governor of the Province of Ontario;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas Colonel The Honourable Lincoln MacCauley Alexander was the first Black Canadian to be elected as Member of Parliament in the House of Commons, to be appointed as Cabinet minister and to be appointed as Lieutenant Governor;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas Colonel The Honourable Lincoln MacCauley Alexander was a passionate advocate for the advancement of education, race relations and youth issues, including by serving as Chancellor of the University of Guelph and Chair of the Canadian Race Relations Foundation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>And whereas the Parliament of Canada wishes to honour and recognize the significant contributions of Colonel The Honourable Lincoln MacCauley Alexander to Canada by designating January 21 — the day of his birth in 1922 — as “Lincoln Alexander Day”;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lincoln Alexander Day Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>LINCOLN ALEXANDER DAY</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Lincoln Alexander Day</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the twenty-first day of January shall be known as “Lincoln Alexander Day”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a legal holiday</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, Lincoln Alexander Day is not a legal holiday or a non-juridical day.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>