<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-24</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Citizenship Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Strengthening Canadian Citizenship Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Citizenship</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2014</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>22</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2014</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-2-5">90658</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, update eligibility requirements for Canadian citizenship, strengthen security and fraud provisions and amend provisions governing the processing of applications and the review of decisions.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Amendments to the eligibility requirements include</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>clarifying the meaning of being resident in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>modifying the period during which a permanent resident must reside in Canada before they may apply for citizenship;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>expediting access to citizenship for persons who are serving in, or have served in, the Canadian Armed Forces;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring that an applicant for citizenship demonstrate, in one of Canada’s official languages, knowledge of Canada and of the responsibilities and privileges of citizenship;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specifying the age as of which an applicant for citizenship must demonstrate the knowledge referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and must demonstrate an adequate knowledge of one of Canada’s official languages;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring that an applicant meet any applicable requirement under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to file a return of income;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>conferring citizenship on certain individuals and their descendants who may not have acquired citizenship under prior legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>extending an exception to the first-generation limit to citizenship by descent to children born to or adopted abroad by parents who were themselves born to or adopted abroad by Crown servants; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring, for a grant of citizenship for an adopted person, that the adoption not have circumvented international adoption law.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Amendments to the security and fraud provisions include</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>expanding the prohibition against granting citizenship to include persons who are charged outside Canada for an offence that, if committed in Canada, would constitute an indictable offence under an Act of Parliament or who are serving a sentence outside Canada for such an offence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>expanding the prohibition against granting citizenship to include persons who, while they were permanent residents, engaged in certain actions contrary to the national interest of Canada, and permanently barring those persons from acquiring citizenship;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>aligning the grounds related to security and organized criminality on which a person may be denied citizenship with those grounds in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and extending the period during which a person is barred from acquiring citizenship on that basis;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>expanding the prohibition against granting citizenship to include persons who, in the course of their application, misrepresent material facts and prohibiting new applications by those persons for a specified period;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>increasing the period during which a person is barred from applying for citizenship after having been convicted of certain offences;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>increasing the maximum penalties for offences related to citizenship, including fraud and trafficking in documents of citizenship;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the regulation of citizenship consultants;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing a hybrid model for revoking a person’s citizenship in which the Minister will decide the majority of cases and the Federal Court will decide the cases related to inadmissibility based on security grounds, on grounds of violating human or international rights or on grounds of organized criminality;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>increasing the period during which a person is barred from applying for citizenship after their citizenship has been revoked;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the revocation of citizenship of dual citizens who, while they were Canadian citizens, engaged in certain actions contrary to the national interest of Canada, and permanently barring these individuals from reacquiring citizenship; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorizing regulations to be made respecting the disclosure of information.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Amendments to the provisions governing the processing of applications and the review of decisions include</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring that an application must be complete to be accepted for processing;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>expanding the grounds and period for the suspension of applications and providing for the circumstances in which applications may be treated as abandoned;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>limiting the role of citizenship judges in the decision-making process, subject to the Minister periodically exercising his or her power to continue the period of application of that limitation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>giving the Minister the power to make regulations concerning the making and processing of applications;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the judicial review of any matter under the Act and permitting, in certain circumstances, further appeals to the Federal Court of Appeal; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>transferring to the Minister the discretionary power to grant citizenship in special cases.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Finally, the enactment makes consequential amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-29</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">CITIZENSHIP ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 2(1)</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subparagraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(ii) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> before clause (A) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>sa citoyenneté a été révoquée pour cause de fausse déclaration, fraude ou dissimulation de faits essentiels au titre de l’une des dispositions suivantes :</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)(iii) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person, before January 1, 1947, was born or naturalized in Canada but ceased to be a British subject, and did not become a citizen on that day;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person, before April 1, 1949, was born or naturalized in Newfoundland and Labrador but ceased to be a British subject, and did not become a citizen on or before that day;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person, on January 1, 1947, was a British subject neither born nor naturalized in Canada and was ordinarily resident in Canada, and did not become a citizen on that day;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person, on April 1, 1949, was a British subject neither born nor naturalized in Newfoundland and Labrador and was ordinarily resident there, and did not become a citizen on or before that day;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person was born outside Canada and Newfoundland and Labrador before January 1, 1947 to a parent who is a citizen under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>), and the person did not become a citizen on that day;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person was born outside Canada and Newfoundland and Labrador before April 1, 1949 to a parent who is a citizen under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>), and the person did not become a citizen on or before that day;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person was born outside Canada and Newfoundland and Labrador before January 1, 1947 to a parent who became a citizen on that day under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, S.C. 1946, c. 15, and the person did not become a citizen on that day; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person was born outside Canada and Newfoundland and Labrador before April 1, 1949 to a parent who became a citizen on that day under section 44A of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, S.C. 1946, c. 15, as enacted by S.C. 1949, c. 6, and the person did not become a citizen on or before that day.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(1.01)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the reference to “Canada” <?Pub Caret?>in paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>) is a reference to Canada as it existed immediately before the union of Newfoundland and Labrador with Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Citizen despite death of parent</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A person who would not become a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) for the sole reason that, on the coming into force of this subsection, his or her parent  —  referred to in one of those paragraphs  —  is deceased, is a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) if that parent, but for his or her death, would have been a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Citizen despite death of parent</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>A person who would not become a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) for the sole reason that, on the coming into force of this subsection, his or her parent  —  referred to in one of those paragraphs  —  is deceased, is a citizen under that paragraph if that parent, but for his or her death, would have been a citizen under any of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Citizen despite death of parent</MarginalNote><Label>(1.3)</Label><Text>A person who would not become a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) for the sole reason that his or her parent died before January 1, 1947 and did not become a citizen on that day under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, S.C. 1946, c. 15, is, nonetheless, a citizen under that paragraph if his or her parent would have been a citizen if that Act had come into force immediately before their death and the date referred to in the provisions of that Act that set out the requirements to be met to become a citizen had been the day of that coming into force rather than January 1, 1947.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Citizen despite death of parent</MarginalNote><Label>(1.4)</Label><Text>A person who would not become a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>) for the sole reason that his or her parent died before April 1, 1949 and did not become a citizen on that day under section 44A of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, S.C. 1946, c. 15, as enacted by S.C. 1949, c. 6, is, nonetheless, a citizen under that paragraph if his or her parent would have been a citizen if that Act had come into force immediately before their death and the date referred to in the provisions of that Act that set out the requirements to be met to become a citizen had been the day of that coming into force rather than April 1, 1949.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not applicable  — paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) do not apply to a person if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>before January 1, 1947, the person made a declaration of alienage, had his or her status as a British subject revoked or ceased to be a British subject as a consequence of the revocation of another person’s status as a British subject; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person became a citizen by way of grant on or after January 1, 1947 and subsequently</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>renounced his or her citizenship under any of the provisions set out in clauses (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(i)(A) to (F), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>had his or her citizenship revoked for false representation, fraud or concealment of material circumstances under any of the provisions set out in clauses (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(ii)(A) to (G).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not applicable  — paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) do not apply to a person  —  who, but for this subsection, would be a citizen under one of those paragraphs for the sole reason that one or both of his or her parents are persons referred to in any of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)  —  if the person became a citizen by way of grant on or after January 1, 1947 and subsequently</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>renounced his or her citizenship under any of the provisions set out in clauses (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(i)(A) to (F); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>had his or her citizenship revoked for false representation, fraud or concealment of material circumstances under any of the provisions set out in clauses (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(ii)(A) to (G).<?xm-replace_text PageBreak?></Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not applicable  — paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>) do not apply to a person if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>before April 1, 1949, the person made a declaration of alienage, had his or her status as a British subject revoked or ceased to be a British subject as a consequence of the revocation of another person’s status as a British subject; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person became a citizen by way of grant on or after April 1, 1949 and subsequently</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>renounced his or her citizenship under any of the provisions set out in clauses (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(i)(A) to (F), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>had his or her citizenship revoked for false representation, fraud or concealment of material circumstances under any of the provisions set out in clauses (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(ii)(A) to (G).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not applicable  — paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(2.4)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) do not apply to a person  —  who, but for this subsection, would be a citizen under one of those paragraphs for the sole reason that one or both of his or her parents are persons referred to in any of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)  —  if the person became a citizen by way of grant on or after April 1, 1949 and subsequently</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>renounced his or her citizenship under any of the provisions set out in clauses (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(i)(A) to (F); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>had his or her citizenship revoked for false representation, fraud or concealment of material circumstances under any of the provisions set out in clauses (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(ii)(A) to (G).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, ss. 2(2) and 13(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 3(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not applicable  — after first generation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>) do not apply to a person born outside Canada</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if, at the time of his or her birth, only one of the person’s parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), or both of the person’s parents were citizens under any of those paragraphs; or</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 3(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not applicable  — after first generation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>) do not apply to a person born outside Canada</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if, at the time of his or her birth, only one of the person’s parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>) or both of the person’s parents were citizens under any of those paragraphs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person was born before January 1, 1947 and, on that day, only one of the person’s parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>), or both of the person’s parents were citizens under either of those paragraphs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person was born before April 1, 1949 and, on that day, only one of the person’s parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>), or both of the person’s parents were citizens under either of those paragraphs; or</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 3(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>à un moment donné, seul le père ou la mère avait qualité de citoyen, et ce, au titre de l’une des dispositions ci-après, ou les deux parents avaient cette qualité au titre de l’une de celles-ci :</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception  — transitional provision</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (3) does not apply to a person who, on the coming into force of that subsection, was a citizen. However, that subsection applies to a person who, on that coming into force, would have been a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) only by operation of any of paragraphs (7)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) in respect of one of his or her parents.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception  — transitional provision</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Subsection (3) does not apply to a person who, on the coming into force of this subsection, was a citizen. However, that subsection applies to a person who, on that coming into force, would have been a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) only by operation of paragraph (7)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>) in respect of one of his or her parents.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception  — child or grandchild of person in service abroad</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection (3) does not apply to a person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>born to a parent who, at the time of the person’s birth, was employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>born to a parent one or both of whose parents, at the time of that parent’s birth, were employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>born to a parent one or both of whose adoptive parents, at the time of that parent’s adoption, were employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(13)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Citizenship other than by way of grant  — grandchild of person in service abroad</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>A person who is born outside Canada to a parent referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and who is either a citizen under prior legislation or the former Act  —  other than under any provision referred to in subparagraphs (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) to (viii)  —  or was granted citizenship under paragraph 5(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of this Act, as it read before April 17, 2009, or under subsection 5(1), (2) or (4) or 11(1) of this Act is deemed, as of the coming into force of this subsection, never to have been a citizen by way of grant:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a parent one or both of whose parents, at the time of that parent’s birth, were employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a parent one or both of whose adoptive parents, at the time of that parent’s adoption, were employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application of subsection (5.1)</MarginalNote><Label>(5.2)</Label><Text>Subsection (5.1) does not apply to a person born outside Canada after February 14, 1977 who, before April 17, 2009, ceased to be a citizen because he or she failed to make an application to retain his or her citizenship under section 8, as it read before April 17, 2009, or made an application but the application was not approved.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(14)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Citizenship other than by way of grant  —  certain children born after February 14, 1977</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>A person who was born outside Canada after February 14, 1977 and who, before the coming into force of this subsection, was granted citizenship under section 5 is deemed never to have been a citizen by way of grant if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>he or she was born to a parent who was born in Canada and who is a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>he or she was born to a parent who was born outside Canada to parents neither of whom was a citizen at the time of that parent’s birth, and who is a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(15)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6.1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Citizenship other than by way of grant</MarginalNote><Label>(6.2)</Label><Text>A person referred to in any of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)  —  or a person referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) who is a citizen under that paragraph for the sole reason that one or both of his or her parents are persons referred to in any of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)  —  who became a citizen by way of grant before the coming into force of this subsection is deemed, except for the purposes of paragraph (2.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), subsection (2.2), paragraph (2.3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), subsection (2.4) and subparagraphs 27(<Emphasis style="italic">j.1</Emphasis>)(ii) and (iii), never to have been a citizen by way of grant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed application</MarginalNote><Label>(6.3)</Label><Text>A person who is referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>) and also in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>) is deemed to be a citizen only under that paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(16)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(7) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) who is a citizen under that paragraph for the sole reason that one or both of his or her parents are referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) is deemed to be a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) from the time that he or she was born.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(17)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(7) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) who is a citizen under that paragraph for the sole reason that one or both of his or her parents are referred to in any of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>) is deemed to be a citizen under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) from the time that he or she was born;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>) is deemed to be a citizen under that paragraph as of January 1, 1947;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) is deemed to be a citizen under that paragraph as of January 1, 1947;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>) is deemed to be a citizen under that paragraph as of April 1, 1949; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>) is deemed to be a citizen under that paragraph as of April 1, 1949.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(18)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 3(8) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>For any period before the day on which subsection (7) first takes effect with respect to a person,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection (7) does not have the effect of conferring any rights, powers or privileges  —  or imposing any obligations, duties or liabilities  —  under any Act of Parliament other than this Act or any other law on the person or on any other person who may have any of those rights, powers, privileges, obligations, duties and liabilities as a result of the first person becoming a citizen; and</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(19)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (8):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>by way of grant</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>In subsections (2.1) to (2.4) and (6.2), <DefinedTermEn>by way of grant</DefinedTermEn> means by way of grant under this Act or under prior legislation, by way of acquisition under this Act or by way of resumption under prior legislation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27, s. 228(1)</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, has, subject to the regulations, no unfulfilled conditions under that Act relating to his or her status as a permanent resident and has, since becoming a permanent resident,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>been physically present in Canada for at least 1,460 days during the six years immediately before the date of his or her application,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>been physically present in Canada for at least 183 days during each of four calendar years that are fully or partially within the six years immediately before the date of his or her application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>met any applicable requirement under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to file a return of income in respect of four taxation years that are fully or partially within the six years immediately before the date of his or her application;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>intends, if granted citizenship,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to continue to reside in Canada,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to enter into, or continue in, employment outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to reside with his or her spouse or common-law partner or parent, who is a Canadian citizen or permanent resident and is employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if under 65 years of age at the date of his or her application, has an adequate knowledge of one of the official languages of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if under 65 years of age at the date of his or her application, demonstrates in one of the official languages of Canada that he or she has an adequate knowledge of Canada and of the responsibilities and privileges of citizenship; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 44 (3rd Supp.), s. 1; 2000, c. 12, s. 75; 2003, c. 22, s. 149(E)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(1.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period of physical presence  — spouse or common-law partner of citizen</MarginalNote><Label>(1.01)</Label><Text>Any day during which an applicant for citizenship resided with the applicant’s spouse or common-law partner who at the time was a Canadian citizen and was employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person, shall be treated as equivalent to one day of physical presence in Canada for the purposes of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period of physical presence  — permanent residents</MarginalNote><Label>(1.02)</Label><Text>Any day during which an applicant for citizenship was a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and was employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person, shall be treated as equivalent to one day of physical presence in Canada for the purposes of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period of physical presence  — residing with permanent residents</MarginalNote><Label>(1.03)</Label><Text>Any day during which an applicant for citizenship was the spouse or common-law partner, or child, of a permanent resident referred to in subsection (1.02) and resided with that permanent resident shall be treated as equivalent to one day of physical presence in Canada for the purposes of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Intention</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) and 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>), the person’s intention must be continuous from the date of his or her application until they have taken the oath of citizenship.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is amended by adding the following before subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Armed Forces  — permanent resident</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) does not apply to a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> who, within the period referred to in that paragraph, completed a number of years of service in the Canadian Armed Forces that is equal to the length of residence required under that paragraph less one year. However, that paragraph does apply to the permanent resident if he or she was released other than honourably from the Canadian Armed Forces.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Armed Forces  —  person attached or seconded</MarginalNote><Label>(1.3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) does not apply to a person who is or was attached or seconded to the Canadian Armed Forces and who, within the period referred to in that paragraph, completed a number of years of service with the Canadian Armed Forces that is equal to the length of residence required under that paragraph less one year.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections 5(1.2) and (1.3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Armed Forces  — permanent resident</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) does not apply to a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> who has, subject to the regulations, no unfulfilled conditions under that Act relating to his or her status as a permanent resident and who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>during the six years immediately before the date of his or her application, completed three years of service in the Canadian Armed Forces; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has met any applicable requirement under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to file a return of income in respect of three taxation years that are fully or partially within the six years immediately before the date of his or her application.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>However, paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) does apply to the permanent resident if he or she was released other than honourably from the Canadian Armed Forces.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Armed Forces  —  person attached or seconded</MarginalNote><Label>(1.3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) does not apply to a person who is or was attached or seconded to the Canadian Armed Forces and who, within the six years immediately before the date of his or her application, completed three years of service with the Canadian Armed Forces.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 4(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Grant of citizenship</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall grant citizenship to any person who is a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and is the minor child of a citizen, if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an application for citizenship is made to the Minister by a person authorized by regulation to make the application on behalf of the minor child;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person has, subject to the regulations, no unfulfilled conditions under that Act relating to his or her status as a permanent resident;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a person who is 14 years of age or over at the date of the application, he or she has an adequate knowledge of one of the official languages of Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a person who is 14 years of age or over at the date of the application, he or she demonstrates in one of the official languages of Canada that he or she has an adequate knowledge of Canada and of the responsibilities and privileges of citizenship.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 21, s. 7</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver by Minister on compassionate grounds</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in his or her discretion, after having reviewed a person’s particular circumstances, waive on compassionate grounds,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of any person, the requirements of paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a minor,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the requirement respecting age set out in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the requirement respecting length of physical presence in Canada set out in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the requirement respecting intent set out in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the requirement respecting the taking of the oath of citizenship;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of any person who is incapable of forming the intent referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) or 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) because of a mental disability, the requirement respecting that intent; and</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special cases</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, the Minister may, in his or her discretion, grant citizenship to any person to alleviate cases of special and unusual hardship or to reward services of an exceptional value to Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 4(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has been physically present in Canada for at least 1,095 days during the four years immediately before the date of his or her application;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, par. 13(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Adoptees  — minors</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (4), the Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person who was adopted by a citizen on or after January 1, 1947 while the person was a minor child if the adoption</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Adoptees  — minors</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (4), the Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person who, while a minor child, was adopted by a citizen on or after January 1, 1947, was adopted before that day by a person who became a citizen on that day, or was adopted before April 1, 1949 by a person who became a citizen on that later day further to the union of Newfoundland and Labrador with Canada, if the adoption</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 5.1(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>did not occur in a manner that circumvented the legal requirements for international adoptions; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, par. 13(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5.1(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Adoptees  — adults</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (4), the Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person who was adopted by a citizen on or after January 1, 1947 while the person was at least 18 years of age if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5.1(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Adoptees  — adults</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (4), the Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person who, while at least 18 years of age, was adopted by a citizen on or after January 1, 1947, was adopted before that day by a person who became a citizen on that day, or was adopted before April 1, 1949 by a person who became a citizen on that later day further to the union of Newfoundland and Labrador with Canada, if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2007, c. 24, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Paragraph 5.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the adoption meets the requirements set out in paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, par. 13(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5.1(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Quebec adoptions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), the Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person in respect of whose adoption  —  by a citizen who is subject to Quebec law governing adoptions  —  a decision was made abroad on or after January 1, 1947 if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5.1(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Quebec adoptions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), the Minister shall, on application, grant citizenship to a person in respect of whose adoption, by a citizen who is subject to Quebec law governing adoptions, a decision was made abroad on or after January 1, 1947  —  or to a person in respect of whose adoption, by a person who became a citizen on that day and who is subject to Quebec law governing adoptions, a decision was made abroad before that day  —  if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Section 5.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not applicable  — after first generation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No person who is adopted may be granted citizenship under any of subsections (1) to (3)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if, at the time of his or her adoption, only one of the adoptive parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under paragraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), or both of the adoptive parents were citizens under any of those paragraphs; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if, at any time, only one of the adoptive parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under any of the provisions referred to in subparagraphs 3(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) to (viii), or both of the adoptive parents were citizens under any of those provisions.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception  — child or grandchild of person in service abroad</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection (4) does not apply to a person who was</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>adopted by a parent who, at the time of the person’s adoption, was employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>adopted by a parent one or both of whose parents, at the time of that parent’s birth, were employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>adopted by a parent one or both of whose adoptive parents, at the time of that parent’s adoption, were employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Paragraph 5.1(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if, at the time of his or her adoption, only one of the adoptive parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under paragraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>), or both of the adoptive parents were citizens under any of those paragraphs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person was adopted before January 1, 1947 and, on that day, only one of the adoptive parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under paragraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>), or both of the adoptive parents were citizens under either of those paragraphs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person was adopted before April 1, 1949 and, on that day, only one of the adoptive parents was a citizen and that parent was a citizen under paragraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>), or both of the adoptive parents were citizens under either of those paragraphs; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Section 5.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception  — Canada and Newfoundland and Labrador</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 5.1(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) do not apply to a person who is adopted before April 1, 1949 if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>only one adoptive parent was a citizen at the time of the adoption, in the case of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), or was a citizen on January 1, 1947, in the case of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the other adoptive parent became a citizen on April 1, 1949 further to the union of Newfoundland and Labrador with Canada, other than under paragraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 5.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Citizenship by way of grant under section 5.1  — grandchild of person in service abroad</MarginalNote><Label>5.2</Label><Text>A person born outside Canada who was adopted by a parent referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and who is either a citizen under prior legislation or the former Act  —  other than under any provision referred to in any of subparagraphs 3(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) to (viii)  —  or was granted citizenship under paragraph 5(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of this Act, as it read before April 17, 2009, or under subsection 5(1), (2), or (4) or 11(1) of this Act is deemed, as of the coming into force of this section, to have been granted citizenship under section 5.1:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a parent one or both of whose parents, at the time of that parent’s birth, were employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a parent one or both of whose adoptive parents, at the time of that parent’s adoption, were employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 5</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>No loss except as provided</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>A person who is a citizen shall not cease to be a citizen except in accordance with this Part or regulations made under paragraph 27(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">j.1</Emphasis>).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 9(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Renunciation of citizenship</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2.1), a citizen may, on application, renounce his citizenship if he</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 9 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>No application for renunciation may be made if the Minister has provided the applicant with a notice referred to in subsection 10(3) or has commenced an action under subsection 10.1(1) or (2) for a declaration in respect of the applicant until the Minister provides the applicant with his or her decision under subsection 10(5) or a final judgment has been rendered in that action, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Processing of application suspended</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>If an application for renunciation is made and the Minister subsequently provides the applicant with a notice referred to in subsection 10(3) or commences an action under subsection 10.1(1) or (2) for a declaration in respect of the applicant, the processing of that application is suspended until the Minister provides the applicant with his or her decision under subsection 10(5) or a final judgment has been rendered in that action, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 9(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate of renunciation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an application under subsection (1) is approved by the Minister, the Minister shall issue a certificate of renunciation to the applicant and the applicant ceases to be a citizen after the expiration of the day on which the certificate is issued or any later day that the certificate may specify.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Section 10 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Revocation by Minister  — fraud, false representation, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection 10.1(1), the Minister may revoke a person’s citizenship or renunciation of citizenship if the Minister is satisfied on a balance of probabilities that the person has obtained, retained, renounced or resumed his or her citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Revocation by Minister  — convictions relating to national security</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may revoke a person’s citizenship if the person, before or after the coming into force of this subsection and while the person was a citizen,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted under section 47 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> of treason and sentenced to imprisonment for life or was convicted of high treason under that section;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of a terrorism offence as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>  —  or an offence outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would constitute a terrorism offence as defined in that section  —  and sentenced to at least five years of imprisonment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under any of sections 73 to 76 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life because the person acted traitorously;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under section 78 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under section 130 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> in respect of an act or omission that is punishable under section 47 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> of a terrorism offence as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act and sentenced to at least five years of imprisonment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence described in section 16 or 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under section 130 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> in respect of an act or omission that is punishable under section 16 or 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Before revoking a person’s citizenship or renunciation of citizenship, the Minister shall provide the person with a written notice that specifies</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person’s right to make written representations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the period within which the person may make his or her representations and the form and manner in which they must be made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the grounds on which the Minister is relying to make his or her decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A hearing may be held if the Minister, on the basis of prescribed factors, is of the opinion that a hearing is required.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister shall provide his or her decision to the person in writing.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Revocation for fraud  — declaration of Court</MarginalNote><Label>10.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that a person obtained, retained, renounced or resumed his or her citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances, with respect to a fact described in section 34, 35 or 37 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> other than a fact that is also described in paragraph 36(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of that Act, the person’s citizenship or renunciation of citizenship may be revoked only if the Minister seeks a declaration, in an action that the Minister commences, that the person has obtained, retained, renounced or resumed his or her citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances and the Court makes such a declaration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Revocation for engaging in armed conflict with Canada  — declaration of Court</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that a person, before or after the coming into force of this subsection and while the person was a citizen, served as a member of an armed force of a country or as a member of an organized armed group and that country or group was engaged in an armed conflict with Canada, the person’s citizenship may be revoked only if the Minister  —  after giving notice to the person  —  seeks a declaration, in an action that the Minister commences, that the person so served, before or after the coming into force of this subsection and while they were a citizen, and the Court makes such a declaration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of declaration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Each of the following has the effect of revoking a person’s citizenship or renunciation of citizenship:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a declaration made under subsection (1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a declaration made under subsection (2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), the Minister need prove only that the person has obtained, retained, renounced or resumed his or her citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Presumption</MarginalNote><Label>10.2</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsections 10(1) and 10.1(1), a person has obtained or resumed his or her citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances if the person became a permanent resident, within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances and, because of having acquired that status, the person subsequently obtained or resumed citizenship.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Effect of revocation</MarginalNote><Label>10.3</Label><Text>A person whose citizenship is revoked under subsection 10(2) or paragraph 10.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) becomes a foreign national within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>10.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 10(2) and 10.1(2) do not operate so as to authorize any decision, action or declaration that conflicts with any international human rights instrument regarding statelessness to which Canada is signatory.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an instrument referred to in subsection (1) prohibits the deprivation of citizenship that would render a person stateless, a person who claims that subsection 10(2) or 10.1(2) would operate in the manner described in subsection (1) must prove, on a balance of probabilities, that the person is not a citizen of any country of which the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe the person is a citizen.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Inadmissibility</MarginalNote><Label>10.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the request of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, the Minister shall, in the originating document that commences an action under subsection 10.1(1), seek a declaration that the person who is the subject of the action is inadmissible on security grounds, on grounds of violating human or international rights or on grounds of organized criminality under, respectively, subsection 34(1), paragraph 35(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or subsection 37(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Party</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When a declaration is sought under subsection (1), the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness becomes a party to the action commenced under subsection 10.1(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A declaration that the person is inadmissible on one of the grounds referred to in subsection (1) is a removal order against the person under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> that comes into force when it is made, without the necessity of holding or continuing an examination or an admissibility hearing under that Act. The removal order is a deportation order as provided for in regulations made under that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a declaration is sought under subsection (1), the Court shall first hear and decide all matters related to the declaration sought under subsection 10.1(1). If the Court denies the declaration sought under subsection 10.1(1), it shall also deny the declaration sought under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If a declaration sought under subsection (1) is not denied under subsection (4), the Court</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall assess the facts  —  whether acts or omissions  —  alleged in support of the declaration on the basis of reasonable grounds to believe that they have occurred, are occurring or may occur;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall take into account the evidence already admitted by it and consider as conclusive any finding of fact already made by it in support of the declaration sought under subsection 10.1(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with respect to any additional evidence, is not bound by any legal or technical rules of evidence and may receive and base its decision on any evidence adduced in the proceedings that it considers credible or trustworthy in the circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Single judgment</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Court shall issue a single judgment in respect of the declarations sought under subsections (1) and 10.1(1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No appeal from interlocutory judgment</MarginalNote><Label>10.6</Label><Text>Despite paragraph 27(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>, no appeal may be made from an interlocutory judgment made with respect to a declaration referred to in subsection 10.1(1) or (2) or 10.5(1).</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No appeal unless question stated</MarginalNote><Label>10.7</Label><Text>An appeal to the Federal Court of Appeal may be made from a judgment under section 10.1 or 10.5 only if, in rendering judgment, the judge certifies that a serious question of general importance is involved and states the question.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is not the subject of an order made under section 10, as it read immediately before the coming into force of section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, a decision made under section 10, a declaration made under section 10.1 or an order made under section 18 of the former Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is not the subject of a declaration made under section 20;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27, s. 229</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and by replacing paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has become a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, has, subject to the regulations, no unfulfilled conditions under that Act relating to his or her status as a permanent resident and has, since having ceased to be a citizen and become a permanent resident,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>been physically present in Canada for at least 365 days during the two years immediately before the date of the application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>met any applicable requirement under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to file a return of income in respect of the taxation year immediately before the year in which the application is made; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>intends, if granted citizenship,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to continue to reside in Canada,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to enter into, or continue in, employment outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to reside with his or her spouse or common-law partner or parent, who is a Canadian citizen or permanent resident and is employed outside Canada in or with the Canadian Armed Forces, the federal public administration or the public service of a province, otherwise than as a locally engaged person.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 11 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Armed Forces  — permanent resident</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) does not apply to a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> who, within the year immediately preceding the date of the application, completed six months of service in the Canadian Armed Forces. However, that paragraph does apply to the permanent resident if he or she was released other than honourably from the Canadian Armed Forces.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Armed Forces  — person attached or seconded</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) does not apply to a person who is or was attached or seconded to the Canadian Armed Forces and who, within the year immediately preceding the date of the application, completed six months of service with the Canadian Armed Forces.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections 11(1.1) and (1.2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Armed Forces  — permanent resident</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) does not apply to a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> who has, subject to the regulations, no unfulfilled conditions under that Act relating to his or her status as a permanent resident and who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>during the two years immediately before the date of the application, completed six months of service in the Canadian Armed Forces; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has met any applicable requirement under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> to file a return of income in respect of the taxation year immediately before the year in which the application is made.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>However, paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) does apply to the permanent resident if he or she was released other than honourably from the Canadian Armed Forces.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Armed Forces  —  person attached or seconded</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) does not apply to a person who is or was attached or seconded to the Canadian Armed Forces and who, during the two years immediately before the date of the application, completed six months of service with the Canadian Armed Forces.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 13(4)</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>Part IV of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>EVIDENCE OF CITIZENSHIP</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application for evidence of citizenship</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall  —  on application by a person  —  determine, including by way of an electronic system, whether they are a citizen and, if they are,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to any regulations made under paragraph 27(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>), issue a certificate of citizenship to them; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to any regulations made under paragraph 27(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">i.1</Emphasis>), provide them with some other means to establish their citizenship.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Providing evidence of citizenship on acquisition</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After a person acquires citizenship as a result of an application under section 5 or 5.1 or subsection 11(1), the Minister shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>issue a certificate of citizenship to the person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide the person with some other means to establish their citizenship.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 9</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Applications</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>An application is to be accepted for processing under this Act only if all of the following conditions are satisfied:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application is made in the form and manner and at the place required under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it includes the information required under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is accompanied by any supporting evidence and fees required under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Suspension of processing</MarginalNote><Label>13.1</Label><Text>The Minister may suspend the processing of an application for as long as is necessary to receive</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any information or evidence or the results of any investigation or inquiry for the purpose of ascertaining whether the applicant meets the requirements under this Act relating to the application, whether the applicant should be the subject of an admissibility hearing or a removal order under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> or whether section 20 or 22 applies with respect to the applicant; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an applicant who is a permanent resident and who is the subject of an admissibility hearing under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, the determination as to whether a removal order is to be made against the applicant.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Abandonment of application</MarginalNote><Label>13.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may treat an application as abandoned</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the applicant fails, without reasonable excuse, when required by the Minister under section 23.1,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case where the Minister requires additional information or evidence without requiring an appearance, to provide the additional information or evidence by the date specified, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case where the Minister requires an appearance for the purpose of providing additional information or evidence, to appear at the time and at the place  —  or at the time and by the means  —  specified or to provide the additional information or evidence at his or her appearance; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an applicant who must take the oath of citizenship to become a citizen, if the applicant fails, without reasonable excuse, to appear and take the oath at the time and at the place  —  or at the time and by the means  —  specified in an invitation from the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of abandonment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Minister treats an application as abandoned, no further action is to be taken with respect to it.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 10</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 14(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Consideration by citizenship judge</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an application is accepted for processing and later referred to a citizenship judge because the Minister is not satisfied that the applicant meets the requirements of the following provisions, the citizenship judge shall determine whether the applicant meets those requirements within 60 days after the day on which the application is referred:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), in the case of an application for citizenship under subsection 5(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 5(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), in the case of an application for citizenship under subsection 5(5); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), in the case of an application for resumption of citizenship under subsection 11(1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 14(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subparagraphs 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)(i) and (ii), in the case of an application for citizenship under subsection 5(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 5(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), in the case of an application for citizenship under subsection 5(5); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subparagraph 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)(i), in the case of an application for resumption of citizenship under subsection 11(1).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27, s. 230</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 14(1.1) to (6) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interruption of proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), the citizenship judge is not authorized to make a determination until</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the completion of any investigation or inquiry for the purpose of ascertaining whether the applicant should be the subject of an admissibility hearing or a removal order under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> or whether section 20 or 22 applies to the applicant; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the applicant is the subject of an admissibility hearing under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, a determination as to whether a removal order is to be made against that applicant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application returned to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), the citizenship judge is not authorized to make a determination if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>after the completion of an investigation or inquiry referred to in paragraph (1.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), it is determined that section 20 or 22 applies to the applicant; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>after an admissibility hearing referred to in paragraph (1.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), there has been a determination to make a removal order against the applicant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Without delay after making a determination under subsection (1) in respect of an application, the citizenship judge shall approve or not approve the application in accordance with his or her determination, notify the Minister accordingly and provide the Minister with the reasons for his or her decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to applicant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a citizenship judge does not approve an application under subsection (2), the citizenship judge shall without delay notify the applicant of his or her decision, of the reasons for it and of the right to apply for judicial review.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 8, par. 182(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Sections 15 to 17 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation  — answer truthfully</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>A person who makes an application under this Act must answer truthfully all questions put to him or her that are related to the application.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Text>Section 18 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 19(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Review Committee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may make a report to the Review Committee if the Minister is of the opinion that a person should not be granted citizenship under section 5 or subsection 11(1) or administered the oath of citizenship or be issued a certificate of renunciation under section 9 because there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person has engaged, is engaging or may engage in activity</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 19(2) of the English version of the Act after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 22, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 20(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Declaration by Governor in Council  — security</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, a person shall not be granted citizenship under section 5 or subsection 11(1) or administered the oath of citizenship or be issued a certificate of renunciation under section 9 if, after considering the report made under subsection 19(6) by the Review Committee or the person appointed under subsection 19.1(1), the Governor in Council declares that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person with respect to whom the report was made has engaged, is engaging or may engage in an activity described in paragraph 19(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 20(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect on applications and appeals</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person is the subject of a declaration made under subsection (1), any application that has been made by that person under section 5 or 9 or subsection 11(1) is deemed to be refused and any related application for judicial review or appeal is deemed to be dismissed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 20(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expiration of declaration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A declaration made under subsection (1) ceases to have effect 10 years after the day on which it is made.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>The portion of section 21 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Periods not counted as physical presence</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, no period may be counted as a period of physical presence for the purpose of this Act during which a person has been, under any enactment in force in Canada,</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 21:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Representation or advice for consideration</MarginalNote><Label>21.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who knowingly, directly or indirectly, represents or advises a person for consideration  —  or offers to do so  —  in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Persons who may represent or advise</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a lawyer who is a member in good standing of a law society of a province or a notary who is a member in good standing of the Chambre des notaires du Québec;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other member in good standing of a law society of a province; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a member in good standing of a body designated under subsection (5).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Students-at-law</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to a student-at-law who offers or provides representation or advice to a person if the student-at-law is acting under the supervision of a person described in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) who is representing or advising the person  —  or offering to do so  —  in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement or arrangement with Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to an entity, including a person acting on its behalf, that offers or provides services to assist persons in connection with an application under this Act if it is acting in accordance with an agreement or arrangement between that entity and Her Majesty in right of Canada that authorizes it to provide those services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by regulation, designate a body whose members in good standing may represent or advise a person for consideration  —  or offer to do so  —  in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations  — required information</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations requiring the designated body to provide the Minister with any information set out in the regulations, including information relating to its governance and information to assist the Minister to evaluate whether the designated body governs its members in a manner that is in the public interest so that they provide professional and ethical representation and advice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations  — transitional measures</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by regulation, provide for measures respecting any transitional issues raised by the exercise of his or her power under subsection (5), including measures</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>making any person or member of a class of persons a member for a specified period of a body that is designated under that subsection; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing that members or classes of members of a body that has ceased to be a designated body under that subsection continue for a specified period to be authorized to represent or advise a person for consideration  —  or offer to do so  —  in connection with a proceeding or application under this Act without contravening subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Persons made members of body</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in the measures described in paragraph (7)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) exempts a person made a member of a body under the measures from the body’s disciplinary rules concerning suspension or revocation of membership for providing  —  or offering to provide  —  representation or advice that is not professional or is not ethical.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of <DefinedTermEn>proceeding</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, in this section <DefinedTermEn>proceeding</DefinedTermEn> does not include a proceeding before a superior court.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 47, s. 67(1)</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 22(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>while the person is serving a sentence outside Canada for an offence committed outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would constitute an offence under an enactment in force in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>while the person is serving a sentence outside Canada for an offence under any Act of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>while the person is charged with, on trial for, subject to or a party to an appeal relating to an offence under subsection 21.1(1) or 29.2(1) or (2), or an indictable offence under subsection 29(2) or (3) or any other Act of Parliament, other than an offence that is designated as a contravention under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (1.1), while the person is charged with, on trial for, subject to or a party to an appeal relating to an offence committed outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would constitute an indictable offence under any Act of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 49, s. 124</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 22(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and by replacing paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person directly or indirectly misrepresents or withholds material circumstances relating to a relevant matter, which induces or could induce an error in the administration of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if, during the five years immediately before the person’s application, the person was prohibited from being granted citizenship or taking the oath of citizenship under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e.1</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if, during the 10 years immediately before the person’s application, the person ceased to be a citizen under paragraph 10(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), as it read immediately before the coming into force of section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, or under subsection 10(1) or paragraph 10.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person’s citizenship has been revoked under subsection 10(2) or paragraph 10.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 30 (3rd Supp.), s. 11(2)(E); 1992, c. 47, s. 67(2); 2008, c. 14, s. 11(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 22(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in his or her discretion in the case of any person, waive the application of paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) on compassionate grounds.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, but subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal>, a person shall not be granted citizenship under subsection 5(1), (2) or (4) or 11(1) or take the oath of citizenship if the person has been convicted of an offence under subsection 21.1(1) or 29.2(1) or (2), or an indictable offence under subsection 29(2) or (3) or any other Act of Parliament, other than an offence that is designated as a contravention under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>during the four-year period immediately before the date of the person’s application; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>during the period beginning on the date of the person’s application and ending on the date on which the person would otherwise be granted citizenship or take the oath of citizenship.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition  — conviction of offence outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, a person shall not be granted citizenship under subsection 5(1), (2) or (4) or 11(1) or take the oath of citizenship if the person has been convicted of an offence outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would constitute an indictable offence under any Act of Parliament, regardless of whether the person was pardoned or otherwise granted amnesty for the offence, and the conviction occurred during</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the four-year period immediately before the date of the person’s application; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the period beginning on the date of the person’s application and ending on the date that he or she would otherwise be granted citizenship or take the oath of citizenship.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition  — specific cases</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, a person shall not be granted citizenship under subsection 5(1), (2) or (4) or 11(1) or take the oath of citizenship if the person, before or after the coming into force of this subsection and while the person was a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted under section 47 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> of treason and sentenced to imprisonment for life or was convicted of high treason under that section;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of a terrorism offence as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>  —  or an offence outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would constitute a terrorism offence as defined in that section  —  and sentenced to at least five years of imprisonment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under any of sections 73 to 76 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life because the person acted traitorously;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under section 78 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under section 130 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> in respect of an act or omission that is punishable under section 47 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> of a terrorism offence as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act and sentenced to at least five years of imprisonment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence described in section 16 or 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was convicted of an offence under section 130 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> in respect of an act or omission that is punishable under section 16 or 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> and sentenced to imprisonment for life; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>served as a member of an armed force of a country or as a member of an organized armed group and that country or group was engaged in an armed conflict with Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptional circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the Minister considers that exceptional circumstances warrant it, he or she may decide that subsection (4) does not apply in respect of a person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition  — taking oath</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act, a person shall not take the oath of citizenship if they never met or they no longer meet the requirements of this Act for the grant of citizenship.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 22:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART V.1</Label><TitleText>JUDICIAL REVIEW</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application for judicial review only with leave</MarginalNote><Label>22.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application for judicial review with respect to any matter under this Act may be made only with leave of the Court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application for leave</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The following provisions govern an application for leave:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application must be filed in the Registry of the Court and served on the other party within 30 days after the day on which the applicant is notified of or otherwise becomes aware of the matter;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a judge of the Court may, for special reasons, allow an extended time for filing and serving the application;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a judge of the Court shall dispose of the application without delay and in a summary way and, unless a judge of the Court directs otherwise, without personal appearance; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no appeal lies from the decision of the Court with respect to the application or with respect to an interlocutory decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may make an application in respect of a decision of a citizenship judge.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial review</MarginalNote><Label>22.2</Label><Text>The following provisions govern the judicial review:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the judge who grants leave shall fix the day and place for a hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the hearing shall be held no later than 90 days after the day on which leave is granted and, unless the parties agree otherwise, no earlier than 30 days after that day;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the judge shall dispose of the application without delay and in a summary way; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an appeal to the Federal Court of Appeal may be made only if, in rendering judgment, the judge certifies that a serious question of general importance is involved and states the question.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rules</MarginalNote><Label>22.3</Label><Text>With the approval of the Governor in Council, the rules committee established under section 45.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal> may make rules governing the practice and procedure in relation to applications for leave to commence an application for judicial review, applications for judicial review and appeals. The rules are binding despite any rule or practice that would otherwise apply.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Inconsistency with <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>22.4</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency between the provisions of this Part and any provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>, this Part prevails to the extent of the inconsistency.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Section 23 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Delegation of authority</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>Anything that is required to be done or that may be done by the Minister or the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness under this Act or the regulations may be done on that Minister’s behalf by any person authorized by that Minister in writing to act on that Minister’s behalf without proof of the authenticity of the authorization.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 23:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Additional information, evidence or appearance</MarginalNote><Label>23.1</Label><Text>The Minister may require an applicant to provide any additional information or evidence relevant to his or her application, specifying the date by which it is required. For that purpose, the Minister may require the applicant to appear in person or by any means of telecommunication to be examined before the Minister or before a citizenship judge, specifying the time and the place  —  or the time and the means  —  for the appearance.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>Subsection 25(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of certificates or other documents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A certificate of citizenship, a document provided under paragraph 12(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), a certificate of naturalization or a certificate of renunciation may be proved in any legal proceeding by the production of the original certificate or document or of a document that is certified by the Minister as bearing the same information.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 12(1)</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 27(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 27(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (ii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the provision under paragraph 12(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of any means of establishing citizenship other than a certificate of citizenship,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 27 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the circumstances in which an unfulfilled condition referred to in paragraph 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) need not be fulfilled;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 27(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>has an adequate knowledge of Canada and of the responsibilities and privileges of citizenship, as demonstrated in one of the official languages of Canada;</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 14, s. 12(5)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 27(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the number of copies of any declaration, certificate, or other document made, issued or provided under this Act or prior legislation that any person is entitled to have;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the provision under paragraph 12(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of a means of establishing citizenship other than a certificate of citizenship;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the surrender and retention of certificates of citizenship, certificates of naturalization and certificates of renunciation issued or granted under this Act or prior legislation and of documents provided under paragraph 12(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) if there is reason to believe that their holder may not be entitled to them or has contravened any of the provisions of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the renunciation of citizenship by persons</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>who are citizens under paragraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>who are citizens under any of paragraphs 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>) and who did not, before the coming into force of this subparagraph, become citizens by way of grant as defined in subsection 3(9), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>who are citizens under paragraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) for the sole reason that one or both parents are persons referred to in any of paragraphs 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>) and who did not, before the coming into force of this subparagraph, become citizens by way of grant as defined in subsection 3(9);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the factors that the Minister shall consider in forming an opinion as to whether a hearing is required under subsection 10(4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the surrender and cancellation of certificates and documents referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>) if their holder is not entitled to them;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the collection, retention, use, disclosure and disposal of information for the purposes of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the disclosure of information for the purposes of national security, the defence of Canada or the conduct of international affairs, including the implementation of an agreement or arrangement entered into under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Citizenship and Immigration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k.3</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the disclosure of information to verify the citizenship status or identity of any person for the purposes of administering any federal or provincial law or law of another country;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k.4</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the disclosure of information for the purposes of cooperation within the Government of Canada and between the Government of Canada and the government of a province;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k.5</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the disclosure of information relating to the professional or ethical conduct of a person referred to in any of paragraphs 21.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) in connection with a proceeding  —  other than a proceeding before a superior court  —  or application under this Act to a body that is responsible for governing or investigating that conduct or to a person who is responsible for investigating that conduct, for the purposes of ensuring that persons referred to in those paragraphs offer and provide professional and ethical representation and advice to persons in connection with such proceedings and applications; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Section 27 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 27(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k.1</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">k.5</Emphasis>) may include conditions under which the collection, retention, use, disposal and disclosure may be made.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2007, c. 24, s. 3.1</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Subsection 27.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Laying of proposed regulations</MarginalNote><Label>27.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause a copy of each regulation proposed to be made under paragraph 27(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>) to be laid before each House of Parliament, and each House shall refer the proposed regulation to the appropriate Committee of that House.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 27.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations  — Minister</MarginalNote><Label>27.2</Label><Text>The Minister may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the manner in which and the place at which applications are to be made and notices are to be given under this Act and specifying the information and evidence that is to be provided in support of them;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the acceptance for processing of applications made under this Act by a person who has been represented or advised by a third party for consideration;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with regard to the requirements of paragraphs 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and 5(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>),</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>respecting the procedures to be followed or evaluation methods or tools to be used in determining whether an applicant meets those requirements or any of the criteria provided for under paragraph 27(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>respecting the organizations or institutions that may conduct assessments related to those requirements or criteria, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>respecting what constitutes evidence that an applicant meets those requirements or criteria; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring an applicant who seeks a waiver by the Minister under subsection 5(3) or 9(2) to request the waiver, specifying the time and manner for making the request and respecting the justification or evidence to be provided in support.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 28:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Sunset  —  after five years</MarginalNote><Label>28.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 14 expires five years after the day on which subsection 22.1(3) comes into force unless, before then, the Minister extends its application for up to five years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sunset  —  further periods of up to five years</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, before the expiry of each extended period, extend the application of that section for up to five years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sunset  — subsection 22.1(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 22.1(3) expires 30 days after the day on which section 14 expires.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28.</Label><Text>Subsections 29(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>document of citizenship</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, <DefinedTermEn>document of citizenship</DefinedTermEn> means a certificate of citizenship, a document provided under paragraph 12(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), a certificate of naturalization or a certificate of renunciation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indictable offences and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years if that person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>obtains or uses a document of citizenship of another person to personate that other person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>knowingly permits a document of citizenship relating to him or her to be used by another person to personate him or her; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is in possession of a document of citizenship that he or she knows has been unlawfully issued or altered, or counterfeited.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 14 years if that person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>without lawful authority issues, provides or alters a document of citizenship;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>counterfeits a document of citizenship;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>uses, acts on or causes or attempts to cause any person to use or act on a document of citizenship, knowing it to have been unlawfully issued, provided or altered or to have been counterfeited; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>traffics in documents of citizenship or has such documents in his or her possession for the purpose of trafficking.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 29:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Contravention of subsection 21.1(1)</MarginalNote><Label>29.1</Label><Text>A person who commits an offence under subsection 21.1(1) is liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $100,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $20,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Counselling misrepresentation</MarginalNote><Label>29.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who knowingly counsels, induces, aids or abets or attempts to counsel, induce, aid or abet any person to directly or indirectly misrepresent or withhold material circumstances relating to a relevant matter, which induces or could induce an error in the administration of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Misrepresentation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who knowingly</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for any of the purposes of this Act, directly or indirectly, makes any false representation, commits fraud or conceals any material circumstances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>communicates directly or indirectly, by any means, false or misleading information or representations with the intent to induce a person to make, or deter a person from making, an application to become a citizen, to obtain a certificate of citizenship or another document establishing citizenship or to renounce citizenship; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>refuses to answer a question put to him or her at an interview or a proceeding held under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Penalties</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) or (2)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to a fine of not more than $100,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable to a fine of not more than $50,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Text>Section 31 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>Any proceedings in respect of an offence under this Act or the regulations that is punishable on summary conviction may be instituted at any time within but not later than 10 years after the time when the offence was committed.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing applications  — sections 5, 5.1, 9 and 11</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3), an application that was made under subsection 5(1), (2), or (5), 5.1(1), (2) or (3), 9(1) or 11(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> before the day on which subsection <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(7) comes into force and was not finally disposed of before that day is to be dealt with and disposed of in accord­ance with</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the provisions of that Act  —  except section 3, subsection 5(4), sections 5.1 and 14 and paragraph 22(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)  —  as they read immediately before that day; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the following provisions of that Act as they read on that day:</Text><Subparagraph type="transitional"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 3,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="transitional"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 5(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and subsection 5(4),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="transitional"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 5.1 other than paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="transitional"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>sections 13.1 to 14, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="transitional"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>paragraphs 22(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e.2</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) and subsections 22(1.1), (3) and (4).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the day on which section <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal> comes into force, the reference to subsection <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(7) in subsection (1) is replaced by a reference to that section <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Paragraphs 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the day on which subsection <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>(2) comes into force</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the reference to section <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal> in subsection (1) is replaced by a reference to that subsection <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>(2); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the requirement described in paragraph 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of that Act, as enacted by subsections <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(1) and <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>(2), respectively, that a person have no unfulfilled conditions relating to their status as a permanent resident, applies to an application referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Reports under former section 10</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>If, immediately before the day on which section 8 comes into force, the Minister, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, was entitled to make or had made a report referred to in section 10 of that Act, as that section 10 read immediately before that day, the matter is to be dealt with and disposed of in accordance with that Act, as it read immediately before that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Judicial review  — subsection 10(1)</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>If a matter is the subject of an order that is made under subsection 10(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> before the day on which section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> comes into force or as a result of the application of section <XRefInternal>32</XRefInternal> or subsection <XRefInternal>40</XRefInternal>(1) and that is set aside by the Federal Court and referred back for determination, the matter is to be determined by the Governor in Council in accordance with that subsection 10(1) as it read immediately before that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing applications  — subsections 5(1.2) and (1.3) and 11(1.1) and (1.2)</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), subsections 5(1.2) and (1.3) and 11(1.1) and (1.2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsections <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(3) and <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>(3), respectively, continue to apply in respect of applications that were made before the day on which subsections <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(4) and <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>(4) come into force and were not finally disposed of before that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The requirement described in subsections 5(1.2) and 11(1.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsections <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(4) and <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>(4), respectively, that a person have no unfulfilled conditions relating to his or her status as a permanent resident applies in respect of applications referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Redetermination of decisions  — sections 5, 9 and 11</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>Any decision that is made under section 5, 9 or 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> before the day on which subsection 12(1) comes into force and that is set aside by the Federal Court and sent back for a redetermination on or after the day on which that subsection comes into force is to be determined in accordance with that Act as it reads on that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Expiry of section 14  — decisions under section 5 or 11</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>In the event that section 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> expires in accordance with section 28.1 of that Act, any decision that is made under section 5 or 11 of that Act before the day on which that section 14 expires and that is set aside by the Federal Court and sent back for a redetermination on or after that day is to be determined in accordance with that Act as it reads on that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing applications  — subsection 12(1)</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application that was made under subsection 12(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> before the day on which subsection 3(7) comes into force and was not finally disposed of before that day is to be dealt with and disposed of in accordance with</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the provisions of that Act  —  except section 3  —  as they read immediately before that day; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 3 of that Act as it reads on that day.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the day on which subsection <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>(2) comes into force, the reference to subsection 3(7) in subsection (1) is replaced by a reference to that subsection <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>(2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing applications  — expiry of section 14</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>In the event that section 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> expires in accordance with section 28.1 of that Act, every application that is referred to a citizenship judge for determination under that section 14 and in respect of which a decision to approve or not to approve is not made before the expiry of that section 14 is to be dealt with and disposed of in accordance with the provisions of that Act, as if that section 14 had been repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing appeals and judicial review applications</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>An appeal under subsection 14(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>  —  or an application for judicial review with respect to any matter under that Act  —  that was commenced before the day on which section <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal> comes into force and was not finally disposed of before that day is to be dealt with and disposed of in accordance with that Act and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal> as they read immediately before that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Proceeding pending</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A proceeding that is pending before the Federal Court immediately before the day on which section 8 comes into force, as a result of a referral under section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> as that section 18 read immediately before that day, is to be dealt with and disposed of in accordance with that Act, as it read immediately before that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Revocation cases  —  sections 34, 35 and 37 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any proceeding with respect to allegations that a person obtained, retained, renounced or resumed his or her citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances, with respect to a fact described in section 34, 35 or 37 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> other than a fact that is also described in paragraph 36(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of that Act, that is pending before the Federal Court immediately before the day on which section 8 comes into force, as a result of a referral under section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> as that section 18 read immediately before that day, is to be continued as a proceeding under subsection 10.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In a proceeding that is continued as set out in subsection (2), the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration, on the request of the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, may seek a declaration that the person is inadmissible on security grounds, on grounds of violating human or international rights or on grounds of organ­ized criminality under, respectively, subsection 34(1), paragraph 35(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or subsection 37(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Other cases</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If, immediately before the coming into force of section 8, a notice has been given under subsection 18(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as that subsection read immediately before that coming into force, and the case is not provided for under section <XRefInternal>32</XRefInternal> or any of subsections (1) to (3), the notice is cancelled and any proceeding arising from it is terminated on that coming into force, in which case the Minister, within the meaning of that Act, may provide the person to whom that notice was given a notice under subsection 10(3) of that Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>, or may commence an action for a declaration in respect of that person under subsection 10.1(1) of that Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-7; 2002, c. 8, s. 14</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 8, s. 30</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Text>Section 21 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>42.</Label><Text>Paragraph 40(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on ceasing to be a citizen under</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 10(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the coming into force of section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, in the circumstances set out in subsection 10(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before that coming into force,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 10(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, in the circumstances set out in section 10.2 of that Act, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>Paragraph 10.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, in the circumstances set out in section 10.2 of that Act.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43.</Label><Text>Subsection 46(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of ceasing to be citizen</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person becomes a permanent resident if he or she ceases to be a citizen under</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 10(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the coming into force of section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Strengthening Canadian Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, other than in the circumstances set out in subsection 10(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before that coming into force;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 10(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, other than in the circumstances set out in section 10.2 of that Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 10.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, other than in the circumstances set out in section 10.2 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2013, c. 33</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, “other Act” means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Economic Action Plan 2013 Act, No. 1</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 170 of the other Act comes into force before subsection <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then that subsection <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal>(2) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 170 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subsection <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then that subsection <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal>(2) is deemed to have come into force before that section 170.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 27.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 171 of the other Act, and section 27.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal> of this Act, are in force, section 27.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 171 of the other Act, is renumbered as section 27.3 and is repositioned accordingly if required.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-425</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill C-425, introduced in the 1st session of the 41st Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Citizenship Act (honouring the Canadian Armed Forces)</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the other Act comes into force before subsection 3(3) of this Act, then, on the day on which that subsection 3(3) comes into force, paragraph 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e.1</Emphasis>), subsections 9(1.1) and (1.2) and paragraph 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> are repealed and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding “and” at the end of paragraphs 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and 11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If subsection 3(3) of this Act comes into force before the other Act, then, on the day on which the other Act comes into force, the other Act is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If subsection 3(3) of this Act comes into force on the same day as the other Act, then that subsection 3(3) is deemed to have come into force before the other Act and subsection (3) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>46.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(3), section <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal>(1) and (3), section <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal>, subsection <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>(2) and sections <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>22</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>27</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>41</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>(2), (3), (5), (6), (8), (11), (15) and (17) to (19), <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(1), (2), (4) to (6) and (8) and <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(2), (3), (5), (6), (8), (10) and (11), section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) and (2), section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>(1), (2) and (4), section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal>, subsection <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal>(2), sections <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>(1) and (3), sections <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal>(2) to (6) and sections <XRefInternal>25</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>30</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>42</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council that is made not earlier than one day after the day on which an order is made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal>(1) and section <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>April 17, 2009</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>(4), (7), (9), (10), (12), (14) and (16) and <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(1), (4), (7) and (9) are deemed to have come into force on April 17, 2009.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>