<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-12</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>55-56</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2006-2007</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to provide for emergency management and to amend and repeal certain Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Emergency Management Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Emergency Management</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2007</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>15</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2007</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2006-4-27">90357</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment provides for a national emergency management system that strengthens Canada’s capacity to protect Canadians.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergency Management Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>emergency management</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>gestion</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>emergency management</DefinedTermEn> means the prevention and mitigation of, preparedness for, response to and recovery from emergencies.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>emergency management plan</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>plan de gestion des urgences</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>emergency management plan</DefinedTermEn> means a program, arrangement or other measure</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for dealing with an emergency by the civil population; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for dealing with a civil emergency by the Canadian Forces in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>government institution</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>institution fédérale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>government institution</DefinedTermEn> means any department, branch, office, board, agency, commission, corporation or other body for the administration or affairs of which a minister of the Crown is accountable to Parliament.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>provincial emergency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>urgence provinciale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial emergency</DefinedTermEn> means an emergency occurring in a province if the province or a local authority in the province has the primary responsibility for dealing with the emergency.</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>MINISTER’S RESPONSIBILITIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Ministerial responsibilities — general</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Minister is responsible for exercising leadership relating to emergency management in Canada by coordinating, among government institutions and in cooperation with the prov-inces and other entities, emergency management activities.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Responsibilities — Canada</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister’s responsibilities under section 3 include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing policies, programs and other measures respecting the preparation, maintenance, testing and implementation by a government institution of emergency management plans;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing advice to government institutions respecting the preparation, maintenance, testing and implementation of emergency management plans;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>analysing and evaluating emergency management plans prepared by government institutions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>monitoring potential, imminent and actual emergencies and advising other ministers accordingly;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>coordinating the Government of Canada’s response to an emergency;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>coordinating the activities of government institutions relating to emergency management with those of the provinces — and supporting the emergency management activities of the provinces — and through the provinces, those of local authorities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing arrangements with each prov­ince whereby any consultation with its lieutenant governor in council with respect to a declaration of an emergency under an Act of Parliament may be carried out effectively;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>coordinating the provision of assistance to a province in respect of a provincial emergency, other than the provision of financial assistance and the calling out of the Canadian Forces for service in aid of the civil power under Part VI of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing assistance other than financial assistance to a province if the province requests it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing financial assistance to a prov-ince if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a provincial emergency in the province has been declared to be of concern to the federal government under section 7,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Minister is authorized under that section to provide the assistance, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the province has requested the assistance;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>participating, in accordance with Canada’s foreign relations policies, in international emergency management activities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing the necessary arrangements for the continuity of constitutional government in the event of an emergency;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing policies and programs respecting emergency management;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>conducting exercises and providing education and training related to emergency management;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>promoting a common approach to emergency management, including the adoption of standards and best practices;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>conducting research related to emergency management;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>promoting public awareness of matters related to emergency management; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>facilitating the authorized sharing of information in order to enhance emergency management.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other responsibilities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister has any other responsibilities in relation to emergency management that the Governor in Council may specify.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Responsibilities — United States</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>In consultation with the Minister of Foreign Affairs, the Minister may develop joint emergency management plans with the relevant United States’ authorities and, in accordance with those plans, coordinate Canada’s response to emergencies in the United States and provide assistance in response to those emergencies.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>MINISTERS’ RESPONSIBILITIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Ministers’ responsibilities</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The emergency management responsibilities of each minister accountable to Parliament for a government institution are to identify the risks that are within or related to his or her area of responsibility — including those related to critical infrastructure — and to do the following in accordance with the policies, programs and other measures established by the Minister:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prepare emergency management plans in respect of those risks;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>maintain, test and implement those plans; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>conduct exercises and training in relation to those plans.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of emergency management plans</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each minister shall include in an emergency management plan</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any programs, arrangements or other measures to assist provincial governments and, through the provincial governments, local authorities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any federal-provincial regional plans;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any programs, arrangements or other measures to provide for the continuity of the operations of the government institution in the event of an emergency; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of war or other armed conflict, the programs, arrangements or other measures that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>support the overall defence effort,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>support the Canadian Forces and the armed forces of Canada’s allies in the conduct of military operations,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>contribute to meeting Canada’s military and civil wartime obligations to its allies, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>mitigate the effects of foreign armed conflict on Canada.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provincial emergencies</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A government institution may not respond to a provincial emergency unless the government of the province requests assistance or there is an agreement with the province that requires or permits the assistance.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ORDERS OR REGULATIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Orders or regulations</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may on the recommendation of the Minister make orders or regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the preparation, maintenance, testing and implementation of emergency management plans;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the use of federal civil resources in response to civil emergencies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>declaring a provincial emergency to be of concern to the federal government; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorizing the Minister to provide financial assistance to a province under paragraph 4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>RELATED AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 20(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>information that is supplied in confidence to a government institution by a third party for the preparation, maintenance, testing or implementation by the government institution of emergency management plans within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergency Management Act</XRefExternal> and that concerns the vulnerability of the third party’s buildings or other structures, its networks or systems, including its computer or communications networks or systems, or the methods used to protect any of those buildings, structures, networks or systems;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 20(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure authorized if in public interest</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The head of a government institution may disclose all or part of a record requested under this Act that contains information described in any of paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the disclosure would be in the public interest as it relates to public health, public safety or protection of the environment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the public interest in disclosure clearly outweighs in importance any financial loss or gain to a third party, any prejudice to the security of its structures, networks or systems, any prejudice to its competitive position or any interference with its contractual or other negotiations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Subsection 27(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to third parties</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the head of a government institution intends to disclose a record requested under this Act that contains or that the head has reason to believe might contain trade secrets of a third party, information described in paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) that was supplied by a third party, or information the disclosure of which the head can reasonably foresee might effect a result described in paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) in respect of a third party, the head shall make every reasonable effort to give the third party written notice of the request and of the head’s intention to disclose within 30 days after the request is received.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 35(2) of the Act after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a third party if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Information Commissioner intends to recommend the disclosure under subsection 37(1) of all or part of a record that contains — or that the Information Commissioner has reason to believe might contain — trade secrets of the third party, information described in paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) that was supplied by the third party or information the disclosure of which the Information Commissioner can reasonably foresee might effect a result described in paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) in respect of the third party, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the third party can reasonably be located.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>However no one is entitled as of right to be present during, to have access to or to comment on representations made to the Information Commissioner by any other person.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 10</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>Subsection 4(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>National leadership</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister is responsible for exercising leadership at the national level relating to public safety and emergency preparedness.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-2</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>If Bill C-2, introduced in the 1st session of the 39th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Accountability Act</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the later of the day on which section 154 of that Act comes into force and the day on which section 1 of this Act comes into force — or, if those days are the same day, then on that day — paragraph 35(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>un tiers, s’il est possible de le joindre sans difficultés, dans le cas où le Commissaire à l’information a l’intention de recommander, aux termes du paragraphe 37(1), la communication de tout ou partie d’un document qui contient ou est, selon lui, susceptible de contenir des secrets industriels du tiers, des renseignements visés aux alinéas 20(1)<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) ou <Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) qui ont été fournis par le tiers ou des renseignements dont la communication risquerait, selon lui, d’entraîner pour le tiers les conséquences visées aux alinéas 29(1)<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) ou <Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>REPEAL</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergency Preparedness Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 6 of the 4th Supplement to the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>This Act other than section 12 comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>