<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>C-61</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>55-56</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2006-2007</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Geneva Conventions Act, An Act to incorporate the Canadian Red Cross Society and the Trade-marks Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Geneva Conventions Act, an Act to incorporate The Canadian Red Cross Society and the Trade-marks Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Geneva Conventions, Canadian Red Cross Society and Trade-marks</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2007</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>26</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2007</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2007-5-31">90411</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Geneva Conventions Act</XRefExternal>, <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to incorporate the Canadian Red Cross Society</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trade-marks Act</XRefExternal> to implement the Protocol set out in the schedule.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to incorporate the Canadian Red Cross Society</XRefExternal> to provide the same protection for the Red Crescent emblem as that Act provides for the Red Cross emblem, and to add a short title to that Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. G-3</MarginalNote><TitleText>GENEVA CONVENTIONS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Geneva Conventions Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protocol approved</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Protocol additional to the Geneva Conventions of 12 August 1949, and relating to the adoption of an additional distinctive emblem, which Protocol is set out in Schedule VII, is approved.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Third Protocol emblem</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), the distinctive emblems mentioned in Article 85, paragraph 3(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of Schedule V are deemed to include the third Protocol emblem, referred to in Article 2, paragraph 2 of Schedule VII.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding, after Schedule VI, the Schedule VII set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1909, c. 68</MarginalNote><TitleText>AN ACT TO INCORPORATE THE CANADIAN RED CROSS SOCIETY</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1922, c. 13, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Section 4 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to incorporate the Canadian Red Cross Society</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Fraudulent representation</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall fraudulently represent himself or herself to be a member or representative of, or agent for, the Society for the purposes of soliciting, collecting or receiving money or material.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unlawful use of name, emblem, badge, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person shall wear, use or display for the purposes of his or her trade or business, for the purpose of inducing the belief that he or she is a member or representative of, or agent for, the Society or for any other purposes whatsoever, without the Society’s written authorization, any of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the heraldic emblem of the Red Cross on a white ground, or the words “Red Cross” or “Geneva Cross”;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the emblem of the Red Crescent on a white ground, referred to in Article 38 of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Geneva Conventions Act</XRefExternal>, or the words “Red Crescent”;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the third Protocol emblem — commonly known as the “Red Crystal” — referred to in Article 2, paragraph 2 of Schedule VII to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Geneva Conventions Act</XRefExternal> and composed of a red frame in the shape of a square on edge on a white ground, or the words “Red Crystal”; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other word, mark, device or thing likely to be mistaken for anything mentioned in paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Penalty</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (1) or (2) is guilty of an offence, and is liable on summary conviction to a fine of not less than $100 but not more than $500, or imprisonment for a term not exceeding one year, or both, for each offence, and any goods, wares or merchandise on which, or in connection with which, any of the emblems or words mentioned in paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or any coloured imitation of them were used are liable to forfeiture to Her Majesty in right of Canada. The proceeds of the fine so collected shall be paid to the Society.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No person contravenes subsection (2) by wearing, using or displaying the emblem or words referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), or any other word, mark, device or thing likely to be mistaken for them, if the person has done so lawfully since before the coming into force of this subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 9:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Red Cross Society Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. T-13</MarginalNote><TitleText>TRADE-MARKS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Subsection 9(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trade-marks Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the third Protocol emblem — commonly known as the “Red Crystal” — referred to in Article 2, paragraph 2 of Schedule VII to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Geneva Conventions Act</XRefExternal> and composed of a red frame in the shape of a square on edge on a white ground, adopted for the same purpose as specified in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 3)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE VII</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsection 2(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>PROTOCOL III</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>PROTOCOL ADDITIONAL TO THE GENEVA CONVENTIONS OF 12 AUGUST 1949, AND RELATING TO THE ADOPTION OF AN ADDITIONAL DISTINCTIVE EMBLEM (PROTOCOL III)</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>PREAMBLE</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The High Contracting Parties</Emphasis>,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Reaffirming</Emphasis> the provisions of the Geneva Conventions of 12 August 1949 (in particular Articles 26, 38, 42 and 44 of the First Geneva Convention) and, where applicable, their Additional Protocols of 8 June 1977 (in particular Articles 18 and 38 of Additional Protocol I and Article 12 of Additional Protocol II), concerning the use of distinctive emblems,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Desiring</Emphasis> to supplement the aforementioned provisions so as to enhance their protective value and universal character,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Noting</Emphasis> that this Protocol is without prejudice to the recognized right of High Contracting Parties to continue to use the emblems they are using in conformity with their obligations under the Geneva Conventions and, where applicable, the Protocols additional thereto,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Recalling</Emphasis> that the obligation to respect persons and objects protected by the Geneva Conventions and the Protocols additional thereto derives from their protected status under international law and is not dependent on use of the distinctive emblems, signs or signals,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Stressing</Emphasis> that the distinctive emblems are not intended to have any religious, ethnic, racial, regional or political significance,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Emphasizing</Emphasis> the importance of ensuring full respect for the obligations relating to the distinctive emblems recognized in the Geneva Conventions, and, where applicable, the Protocols additional thereto,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Recalling</Emphasis> that Article 44 of the First Geneva Convention makes the distinction between the protective use and the indicative use of the distinctive emblems,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Recalling further</Emphasis> that National Societies undertaking activities on the territory of another State must ensure that the emblems they intend to use within the framework of such activities may be used in the country where the activity takes place and in the country or countries of transit,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Recognizing</Emphasis> the difficulties that certain States and National Societies may have with the use of the existing distinctive emblems,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Noting</Emphasis> the determination of the International Committee of the Red Cross, the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies and the International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement to retain their current names and emblems,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Have agreed</Emphasis> on the following:</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4.5" topmarginspacing="8pt"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 1 —</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Respect for and scope of application of this Protocol</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The High Contracting Parties undertake to respect and to ensure respect for this Protocol in all circumstances.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>This Protocol reaffirms and supplements the provisions of the four Geneva Conventions of 12 August 1949 (“the Geneva Conventions”) and, where applicable, of their two Additional Protocols of 8 June 1977 (“the 1977 Additional Protocols”) relating to the distinctive emblems, namely the red cross, the red crescent and the red lion and sun, and shall apply in the same situations as those referred to in these provisions.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 2 — Distinctive emblems</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Protocol recognizes an additional distinctive emblem in addition to, and for the same purposes as, the distinctive emblems of the Geneva Conventions. The distinctive emblems shall enjoy equal status.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>This additional distinctive emblem, composed of a red frame in the shape of a square on edge on a white ground, shall conform to the illustration in the Annex to this Protocol. This distinctive emblem is referred to in this Protocol as the “third Protocol emblem”.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The conditions for use of and respect for the third Protocol emblem are identical to those for the distinctive emblems established by the Geneva Conventions and, where applicable, the 1977 Additional Protocols.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The medical services and religious personnel of armed forces of High Contracting Parties may, without prejudice to their current emblems, make temporary use of any distinctive emblem referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article where this may enhance protection.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 3 — Indicative use of the third Protocol emblem</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>National Societies of those High Contracting Parties which decide to use the third Protocol emblem may, in using the emblem in conformity with relevant national legislation, choose to incorporate within it, for indicative purposes:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a distinctive emblem recognized by the Geneva Conventions or a combination of these emblems; or</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>another emblem which has been in effective use by a High Contracting Party and was the subject of a communication to the other High Contracting Parties and the International Committee of the Red Cross through the depositary prior to the adoption of this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="no" list-item="no" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>Incorporation shall conform to the illustration in the Annex to this Protocol.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>A National Society which chooses to incorporate within the third Protocol emblem another emblem in accordance with paragraph 1 above, may, in conformity with national legislation, use the designation of that emblem and display it within its national territory.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3.</Label><Text>National Societies may, in accordance with national legislation and in exceptional circumstances and to facilitate their work, make temporary use of the distinctive emblem referred to in Article 2 of this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4.</Label><Text>This Article does not affect the legal status of the distinctive emblems recognized in the Geneva Conventions and in this Protocol, nor does it affect the legal status of any particular emblem when incorporated for indicative purposes in accordance with paragraph 1 of this Article.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="4.5" topmarginspacing="8pt"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 4 —</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">International Committee of the Red Cross and International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The International Committee of the Red Cross and the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies, and their duly authorized personnel, may use, in exceptional circumstances and to facilitate their work, the distinctive emblem referred to in Article 2 of this Protocol.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 5 — Missions under United Nations auspices</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The medical services and religious personnel participating in operations under the auspices of the United Nations may, with the agreement of participating States, use one of the distinctive emblems mentioned in Articles 1 and 2.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 6 — Prevention and repression of misuse</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The provisions of the Geneva Conventions and, where applicable, the 1977 Additional Protocols, governing prevention and repression of misuse of the distinctive emblems shall apply equally to the third Protocol emblem. In particular, the High Contracting Parties shall take measures necessary for the prevention and repression, at all times, of any misuse of the distinctive emblems mentioned in Articles 1 and 2 and their designations, including the perfidious use and the use of any sign or designation constituting an imitation thereof.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Notwithstanding paragraph 1 above, High Contracting Parties may permit prior users of the third Protocol emblem, or of any sign constituting an imitation thereof, to continue such use, provided that the said use shall not be such as would appear, in time of armed conflict, to confer the protection of the Geneva Conventions and, where applicable, the 1977 Additional Protocols, and provided that the rights to such use were acquired before the adoption of this Protocol.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 7 — Dissemination</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The High Contracting Parties undertake, in time of peace as in time of armed conflict, to disseminate this Protocol as widely as possible in their respective countries and, in particular, to include the study thereof in their programmes of military instruction and to encourage the study thereof by the civilian population, so that this instrument may become known to the armed forces and to the civilian population.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 8 — Signature</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Protocol shall be open for signature by the Parties to the Geneva Conventions on the day of its adoption and will remain open for a period of twelve months.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 9 — Ratification</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Protocol shall be ratified as soon as possible. The instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Swiss Federal Council, depositary of the Geneva Conventions and the 1977 Additional Protocols.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 10 — Accession</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Protocol shall be open for accession by any Party to the Geneva Conventions which has not signed it. The instruments of accession shall be deposited with the depositary.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 11 — Entry into force</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Protocol shall enter into force six months after two instruments of ratification or accession have been deposited.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>For each Party to the Geneva Conventions thereafter ratifying or acceding to this Protocol, it shall enter into force six months after the deposit by such Party of its instrument of ratification or accession.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="5" topmarginspacing="8pt"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 12 —</Emphasis></Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Treaty relations upon entry into force of this Protocol</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>When the Parties to the Geneva Conventions are also Parties to this Protocol, the Conventions shall apply as supplemented by this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>When one of the Parties to the conflict is not bound by this Protocol, the Parties to the Protocol shall remain bound by it in their mutual relations. They shall furthermore be bound by this Protocol in relation to each of the Parties which are not bound by it, if the latter accepts and applies the provisions thereof.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 13 — Amendment</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Any High Contracting Party may propose amendments to this Protocol. The text of any proposed amendment shall be communicated to the depositary, which shall decide, after consultation with all the High Contracting Parties, the International Committee of the Red Cross and the International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies, whether a conference should be convened to consider the proposed amendment.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The depositary shall invite to that conference all the High Contracting Parties as well as the Parties to the Geneva Conventions, whether or not they are signatories of this Protocol.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 14 — Denunciation</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>In case a High Contracting Party should denounce this Protocol, the denunciation shall only take effect one year after receipt of the instrument of denunciation. If, however, on the expiry of that year the denouncing Party is engaged in a situation of armed conflict or occupation, the denunciation shall not take effect before the end of the armed conflict or occupation.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The denunciation shall be notified in writing to the depositary, which shall transmit it to all the High Contracting Parties.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The denunciation shall have effect only in respect of the denouncing Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Any denunciation under paragraph 1 shall not affect the obligations already incurred, by reason of the armed conflict or occupation, under this Protocol by such denouncing Party in respect of any act committed before this denunciation becomes effective.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 15 — Notifications</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The depositary shall inform the High Contracting Parties as well as the Parties to the Geneva Conventions, whether or not they are signatories of this Protocol, of:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>signatures affixed to this Protocol and the deposit of instruments of ratification and accession under Articles 8, 9 and 10;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the date of entry into force of this Protocol under Article 11 within ten days of said entry into force;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>communications received under Article 13;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>denunciations under Article 14.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 16 — Registration</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>After its entry into force, this Protocol shall be transmitted by the depositary to the Secretariat of the United Nations for registration and publication, in accordance with Article 102 of the Charter of the United Nations.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The depositary shall also inform the Secretariat of the United Nations of all ratifications, accessions and denunciations received by it with respect to this Protocol.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 17 — Authentic texts</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The original of this Protocol, of which the Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian and Spanish texts are equally authentic, shall be deposited with the depositary, which shall transmit certified true copies thereof to all the Parties to the Geneva Conventions.</Text></Provision></Provision><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><Label>ANNEX</Label><TitleText>THIRD PROTOCOL EMBLEM</TitleText><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">(Article 2, paragraph 2, and Article 3, paragraph 1 of the Protocol)</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 1 — Distinctive emblem</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><ImageGroup><Image source="G-3_ef001.jpg" /></ImageGroup></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Article 2 — Indicative use of the third Protocol emblem</Emphasis></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><ImageGroup><Image source="G-3_e002.jpg" /></ImageGroup></Provision></Provision></Group></DocumentInternal></Schedule></Schedule></Bill>