<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-2</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>55-56</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2006-2007</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Hazardous Materials Information Review</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2007</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><?Pub Caret?><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>7</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2007</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2006-4-4">90331</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal> to</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>allow a claimant to make a declaration that information in respect of which an exemption is claimed is confidential business information and that information substantiating the claim is available and will be provided on request;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>allow a claimant to give an undertaking to the Hazardous Materials Information Review Commission to bring a material safety data sheet or a label into compliance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> or of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>allow the limited participation of the Commission before an appeal board.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 24 (3rd Supp.), Part III</MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Subsection 11(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Materials Information Review Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of claim</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A claim for exemption shall be accompanied by the material safety data sheet or label to which the claim relates and shall contain</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the information in respect of which the exemption is claimed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a declaration stating that the claimant believes that the information in respect of which the exemption is claimed is confidential business information that meets the criteria prescribed under paragraph 48(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and that information substantiating the claim — as specified in the regulations — is in the possession of, or is available to, the claimant and will be provided on request;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a summary of the information substantiating the claim; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other prescribed information.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Substantiating information</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The screening officer may, for the purpose of determining the matter referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), ask the claimant to provide the information substantiating the claim for exemption in the following circumstances:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an affected party has made written representations with respect to the claim;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the information contained in the summary referred to in paragraph 11(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) is to be verified; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other prescribed circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 16:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Undertaking</MarginalNote><Label>16.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a screening officer determines under paragraph 13(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) that a material safety data sheet or label to which a claim for exemption relates does not comply with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> or the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, as the case may be, the screening officer may send an undertaking to the claimant setting out the measures that are required to be taken for the purpose of ensuring compliance with those provisions, except to the extent that they would require the claimant to disclose the information in respect of which the claim is made, in the manner and within the period specified in the undertaking.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement by claimant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the claimant agrees with the measures set out in the undertaking, the claimant shall sign the undertaking and return it to the screening officer together with the amended material safety data sheet or label.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On receipt of the signed undertaking, if the screening officer is satisfied, after reviewing the material safety data sheet or label, that the claimant has taken the measures set out in the undertaking in the manner and within the period specified in it, the screening officer shall send a notice to the claimant confirming their compliance with the undertaking.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed compliance</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A claimant to whom the notice is sent is, for the purposes of the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> or the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, as the case may be, deemed to have complied with those provisions.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 17(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Order re material safety data sheet</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the screening officer does not receive the signed undertaking, or is not satisfied that the claimant has taken the measures set out in the undertaking in the manner and within the period specified in it, the screening officer shall order the claimant to comply with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal> or the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, as the case may be, except to the extent that they would require the claimant to disclose the information in respect of which the claim is made, in the manner and within the period specified in the order.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Subsections 18(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chief Screening Officer shall cause to be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of each decision made under section 15 and each order made under section 16 or 17</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a notice containing prescribed information, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a notice containing any information that, in the opinion of a screening officer, should have been disclosed on any material safety data sheet or label reviewed by the screening officer; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of each undertaking for which a notice has been sent under subsection 16.1(3)</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a notice containing prescribed information, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a notice containing any information that has been disclosed on any material safety data sheet or label in compliance with the undertaking.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copies</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Chief Screening Officer shall make copies of any notice published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> under subsection (1) available to any person on request in writing.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Subsection 20(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A claimant or an affected party may appeal any decision or order made under section 15, 16 or 17, and an affected party may also appeal any undertaking in respect of which a notice has been published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure on appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>An appeal shall be brought by filing with the Chief Appeals Officer, within the prescribed period, a statement of appeal setting out the grounds on which the appeal is made and any submissions in support of the appeal.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 34, s. 51(F)</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 23(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the record of the screening officer in respect of the decision, order or undertaking being appealed,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 23(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of subparagraph (ii) and by adding the following after subparagraph (iii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>any clarifications made by the Commission, in accordance with the regulations, in respect of the record referred to in subparagraph (i); and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 23(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of an appeal of a decision or order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An appeal board may dispose of an appeal of a decision or an order by</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 23 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal of an undertaking</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An appeal board may dispose of an appeal of an undertaking by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>dismissing the appeal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>allowing the appeal and making any order that the appeal board considers appropriate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No retrospective effect</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No order made under paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) shall have retrospective effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compliance with order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A claimant to whom an order under paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is directed shall comply with the order in the manner and within the period specified in the order.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Subsection 48(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specifying the information that is required for the purpose of substantiating a claim for an exemption;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the participation of the Commission in an appeal heard before an appeal board;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>