<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-59</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>55-56</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2006-2007</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (unauthorized recording of a movie)</LongTitle><?Pub Caret?><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (unauthorized recording of a movie)</ShortTitle><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2007</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>28</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2007</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2007-5-30">90420</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to prohibit the unauthorized recording of a movie in a movie theatre (camcording).</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 431.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized recording of a movie</MarginalNote><Label>432.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who, without the consent of the theatre manager, records in a movie theatre a performance of a cinematographic work within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Copyright Act</XRefExternal> or its soundtrack</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unauthorized recording for purpose of sale, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who, without the consent of the theatre manager, records in a movie theatre a performance of a cinematographic work within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Copyright Act</XRefExternal> or its soundtrack for the purpose of the sale, rental or other commercial distribution of a copy of the cinematographic work</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In addition to any punishment that is imposed on a person who is convicted of an offence under this section, the court may order that anything that is used in the commission of the offence be forfeited to Her Majesty in right of the province in which the proceedings are taken. Anything that is forfeited may be disposed of as the Attorney General directs.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forfeiture — limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No order may be made under subsection (3) in respect of anything that is the property of a person who is not a party to the offence.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>