<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-31</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>55-56</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2006-2007</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act and the Public Service Employment Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Canada Elections Act and the Public Service Employment Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2007</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>21</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2007</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2006-10-17">90387</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> to improve the integrity of the electoral process by reducing the opportunity for electoral fraud or error. It requires that electors, before voting, provide one piece of government-issued photo identification showing their name and address or two pieces of identification authorized by the Chief Electoral Officer showing their name and address, or take an oath and be vouched for by another elector.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, make operational changes to improve the accuracy of the National Register of Electors, facilitate voting and enhance communications with the electorate.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>It amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal> to permit the Public Service Commission to make regulations to extend the maximum term of employment of casual workers.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 9</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA ELECTIONS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>list of electors</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>polling day</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>list of electors</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>liste électorale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>list of electors</DefinedTermEn> means the list showing the surname, given names, civic address and mailing address of every elector in a polling division and the identifier that is assigned to the elector by the Chief Electoral Officer. </Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>polling day</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>jour du scrutin</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>polling day</DefinedTermEn>, in relation to an election, means the date fixed under paragraph 57(1.2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) for voting at the election.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Subsection 17(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Power to adapt Act</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>During an election period or within 30 days after it, if an emergency, an unusual or unforeseen circumstance or an error makes it necessary, the Chief Electoral Officer may adapt any provision of this Act and, in particular, may extend the time for doing any act, subject to subsection (2), or may increase the number of election officers or polling stations.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 43:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Right of access</MarginalNote><Label>43.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person who is in control of an apartment building, condominium building or other multiple-residence building or a gated community may prevent an election officer or a member of the staff of a returning officer from obtaining access to the building or gated community, as the case may be, between 9:00 a.m. and 9:00 p.m., to perform his or her duties under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply in respect of a person who is in control of a multiple-residence building whose residents’ physical or emotional well-being may be harmed as a result of permitting the activities referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Section 44 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Identifier</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Register of Electors must also contain, for each elector, a unique, randomly generated identifier that is assigned by the Chief Electoral Officer.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Subsections 45(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Members and registered parties</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>By November 15 in each year, the Chief Electoral Officer shall send to the member for each electoral district and, on request, to each registered party that endorsed a candidate in the electoral district in the last election, a copy in electronic form — taken from the Register of Electors — of the lists of electors for the electoral district.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of lists of electors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The lists of electors shall set out each elector’s surname, given names, civic address and mailing address, and the identifier that is assigned to the elector by the Chief Electoral Officer and shall be arranged in the form established by the Chief Electoral Officer according to the civic addresses of the electors or, if that is not appropriate, in alphabetical order by their surnames.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>This section does not apply if November 15 falls during an election period or if the vote at a general election was held during the six months before that date.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Section 46 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retention of certain information</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer may retain information collected under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), but not included in the Register of Electors, for the purpose of correlating information subsequently collected with information already contained in the Register of Electors.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 46:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Citizenship information</MarginalNote><Label>46.1</Label><Text>For the purpose of assisting the Chief Electoral Officer in updating the Register of Electors, the Minister of National Revenue may, on a return of income referred to in subsection 150(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, request that an individual who is filing a return of income under paragraph 150(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of that Act indicate in the return whether he or she is a Canadian citizen.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Information in respect of deceased individuals</MarginalNote><Label>46.2</Label><Text>For the purpose of updating the Register of Electors, the Minister of National Revenue shall, at the request of the Chief Electoral Officer, provide the name, date of birth and address of any individual to whom paragraph 150(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> applies if that individual has, in his or her last return of income filed under paragraph 150(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of that Act, authorized that Minister to provide his or her name, date of birth and address to the Chief Electoral Officer for the Register of Electors.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 47:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Other duties</MarginalNote><Label>47.1</Label><Text>Between election periods, a returning officer shall perform any duties related to the updating of the Register of Electors that are requested by the Chief Electoral Officer.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Subsections 55(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Provincial bodies</MarginalNote><Label>55.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer may enter into an agreement with any body responsible under provincial law for establishing a list of electors, governing the giving of information contained in the Register of Electors, or the giving of information referred to in subsection 44(2) or (2.1) that the Chief Electoral Officer intends to include in the Register of Electors, if that information is needed for establishing such a list.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer shall include in the agreement conditions regarding the use and protection of personal information given under the agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 56(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>knowingly make a false or misleading statement, orally or in writing, relating to another person’s qualification as an elector, to the surname, given names, sex, civic address or mailing address of that person, or to the identifier assigned to that person by the Chief Electoral Officer, for the purpose of having that person’s name deleted from the Register of Electors;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 56 of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and by replacing paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>knowingly use personal information that is obtained from the Register of Electors except as follows:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to enable registered parties, members or candidates to communicate with electors in accordance with section 110,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for the purpose of a federal election or referendum, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in accordance with the conditions included in an agreement made under section 55, in the case of information that is transmitted in accordance with the agreement; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>knowingly use other personal information that is transmitted in accordance with an agreement made under section 55 except in accordance with the conditions included in the agreement.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 81(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Canvassing, etc., in residential areas</MarginalNote><Label>81.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person who is in control of an apartment building, condominium building or other multiple-residence building or a gated community may prevent a candidate or his or her representative from</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an apartment building, condominium building or gated community, canvassing, between 9:00 a.m. and 9:00 p.m., at the doors to the apartments, units or houses, as the case may be; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a multiple-residence building, campaigning, between 9:00 a.m. and 9:00 p.m., in a common area in the multiple residence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 81(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le paragraphe (1) ne s’applique pas au responsable d’un immeuble à logements multiples si le fait de permettre les activités de campagne visées à ce paragraphe peut mettre en danger la santé physique ou affective des résidants de l’immeuble.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 81:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Campaigning in public places</MarginalNote><Label>81.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person who is in control of a building, land, street or any other place, any part of which is open without charge to members of the public, whether on a continuous, periodic or occasional basis — including any commercial, business, cultural, historical, educational, religious, governmental, entertainment or recreational place — may prevent a candidate or his or her representative from campaigning in or on that part when it is open without charge to members of the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply in respect of a place if campaigning in or on it would be incompatible with the function and purpose of the place or inconsistent with public safety.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>Subsection 93(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distribution of preliminary lists</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer shall distribute, to each registered party or eligible party that requests it, one copy in electronic form of the preliminary lists of electors for an electoral district in respect of which a writ has been issued.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form of preliminary list of electors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A preliminary list of electors shall contain only the name and address of each elector in the electoral district and the identifier that is assigned to the elector by the Chief Electoral Officer and shall be arranged according to the civic addresses of the electors or, if that is not appropriate, in alphabetical order by their names.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 95(2) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Teneur de l’avis</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>L’avis de confirmation d’inscription, en la forme établie par le directeur général des élections, indique :</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 95(2) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), by adding the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the fact that proof of an elector’s identity and residence will be required before the elector is allowed to vote.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 99:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Information in Register of Electors</MarginalNote><Label>99.1</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer may, for the purpose of section 99, provide to the returning officer and assistant returning officer information contained in the Register of Electors.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 101(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), by adding the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the elector, or another elector who lives at the same residence as the elector, at their residence and in the presence of the revising agents completes the prescribed registration form and takes the prescribed oath.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 101 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Addition of elector’s name</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The returning officer or assistant returning officer may also add to the preliminary list of electors the name of any elector whose name is added to the Register of Electors after that list has been prepared.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 104:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Updated Preliminary Lists of Electors</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Distribution of lists</MarginalNote><Label>104.1</Label><Text>Each returning officer shall, on the 19th day before polling day, distribute to each candidate in the electoral district who requests it, one copy in electronic form of the most current preliminary lists of electors for that electoral district.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>Subsections 107(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transmittal of list</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each returning officer shall deliver to each deputy returning officer the revised list of electors or official list of electors, as the case may be, that the deputy returning officer needs to conduct the vote in his or her respective advance polling station or polling station. The list shall indicate each elector’s sex and date of birth.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transmittal to candidates</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Each returning officer shall deliver to each candidate a printed copy and a copy in electronic form of a version of the revised lists of electors and the official lists of electors that does not indicate an elector's sex or date of birth.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Text>Subsection 110(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Candidates</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A candidate who receives a copy of the preliminary lists of electors under section 94 or 104.1, or a copy of the revised lists of electors or the official lists of electors under subsection 107(3), may use the lists for communicating with his or her electors during an election period, including using them for soliciting contributions and campaigning.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 24, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>Paragraph 117(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no later than 48 hours after the close of nominations, the party is a registered party.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Sections 143 to 145 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Elector to declare name, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>143.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Each elector, on arriving at the polling station, shall give his or her name and address to the deputy returning officer and the poll clerk, and, on request, to a candidate or his or her representative.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of identity and residence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the poll clerk determines that the elector’s name and address appear on the list of electors or that the elector is allowed to vote under section 146, 147, 148 or 149, then, subject to subsection (3), the elector shall provide to the deputy returning officer and the poll clerk the following proof of his or her identity and residence:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>one piece of identification issued by a Canadian government, whether federal, provincial or local, or an agency of that government, that contains a photograph of the elector and his or her name and address; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>two pieces of identification authorized by the Chief Electoral Officer each of which establish the elector’s name and at least one of which establishes the elector’s address.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Chief Electoral Officer may authorize as a piece of identification for the purposes of paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) any document, regardless of who issued it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person registered as an Indian</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), a document issued by the Government of Canada that certifies that a person is registered as an Indian under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> constitutes an authorized piece of identification.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Oath</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An elector may instead prove his or her identity and residence by taking the prescribed oath if he or she is accompanied by an elector whose name appears on the list of electors for the same polling division and who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provides to the deputy returning officer and the poll clerk the piece or pieces of identification referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), respectively; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>vouches for him or her on oath in the prescribed form.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Voting</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the deputy returning officer is satisfied that an elector’s identity and residence have been proven in accordance with subsection (2) or (3), the elector’s name shall be crossed off the list and, subject to section 144, the elector shall be immediately allowed to vote.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — vouching for more than one elector</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No elector shall vouch for more than one elector at an election.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — vouchee acting as voucher</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An elector who has been vouched for at an election may not vouch for another elector at that election.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer shall publish each year, and within three days after the issue of a writ, in a manner that he or she considers appropriate, a notice setting out the types of identification that are authorized for the purpose of paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>). The first annual notice shall be published no later than six months after the coming into force of this subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Requirement before administering oath</MarginalNote><Label>143.1</Label><Text>If a person decides to prove his or her identity and residence by taking the prescribed oath, the person who administers the oath shall, before doing so, orally advise the oath taker of the qualifications for electors and the penalty that may be imposed under this Act on a person who is convicted of voting or attempting to vote at an election knowing that he or she is not qualified as an elector.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Proof of qualification as elector</MarginalNote><Label>144.</Label><Text>A deputy returning officer, poll clerk, candidate or candidate’s representative who has reasonable doubts concerning whether a person intending to vote is qualified as an elector may request that the person take the prescribed oath, and the person shall not be allowed to vote unless he or she takes that oath.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Proof of identity, etc., or oath not required</MarginalNote><Label>144.1</Label><Text>Once an elector has been given a ballot, no person shall require the elector to prove his or her identity and residence in accordance with subsection 143(2) or (3).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Sections 146 to 148 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Name and address corresponding closely to another</MarginalNote><Label>146.</Label><Text>If a name and address in the list of electors correspond so closely with the name and address of a person who demands a ballot as to suggest that it is intended to refer to that person, the person shall not be allowed to vote unless he or she takes the prescribed oath.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Person in whose name another has voted</MarginalNote><Label>147.</Label><Text>If a person asks for a ballot at a polling station after someone else has voted under that person’s name, the person shall not be allowed to vote unless he or she takes the prescribed oath.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name inadvertently crossed off list</MarginalNote><Label>148.</Label><Text>If an elector claims that his or her name has been crossed off in error from an official list of electors under subsection 176(2) or (3), the elector shall not be allowed to vote unless the returning officer verifies that the elector’s name was crossed off in error or the elector takes the oath referred to in section 147.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Failure to prove identity or residence</MarginalNote><Label>148.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An elector who fails to prove his or her identity and residence in accordance with subsection 143(2) or (3) or to take an oath otherwise required by this Act shall not receive a ballot or be allowed to vote.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When elector refuses to take improper oath</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an elector refuses to take an oath because he or she is not required to do so under this Act, the elector may appeal to the returning officer. If, after consultation with the deputy returning officer or the poll clerk of the polling station, the returning officer decides that the elector is not required to take the oath, and if the elector is entitled to vote in the polling division, the returning officer shall direct that he or she be allowed to do so.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 149 of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Elector not allowed to vote</MarginalNote><Label>149.</Label><Text>An elector whose name does not appear on the official list of electors in his or her polling station shall not be allowed to vote unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the elector gives the deputy returning officer a transfer certificate described in section 158 or 159 and, for a certificate described in subsection 158(2), fulfils the conditions described in subsection 158(3);</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 149(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the deputy returning officer ascertains with the returning officer that the elector is listed on the preliminary list of electors or was registered during the revision period; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 149(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the elector gives the deputy returning officer a registration certificate described in subsection 161(4).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Section 158 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfer certificate for elector whose polling station has moved</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If an elector’s polling station moves to another location after the notice of confirmation of registration has been sent, an elector who attends at the polling station set out in the notice is entitled on request to receive a transfer certificate to vote at that polling station.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 12, par. 40(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Subsection 159(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application shall be in the prescribed form and shall be personally delivered to the returning officer or assistant returning officer for the elector’s electoral district by the elector, his or her friend, spouse, common-law partner or relative, or a relative of his or her spouse or common-law partner.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 161(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Registration in person</MarginalNote><Label>161.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An elector whose name is not on the list of electors may register in person on polling day if the elector</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provides as proof of his or her identity and residence the piece or pieces of identification referred to in paragraph 143(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), respectively; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>proves his or her identity and residence by taking the prescribed oath, and is accompanied by an elector whose name appears on the list of electors for the same polling division and who</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>provides the piece or pieces of identification referred to in paragraph 143(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), respectively, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>vouches for him or her on oath in the prescribed form.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 161(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — vouching for more than one elector</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>No elector shall vouch for more than one elector at an election.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — vouchee acting as voucher</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>An elector who has been vouched for at an election may not vouch for another elector at that election.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 161:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Requirement before administering oath</MarginalNote><Label>161.1</Label><Text>If a person decides to prove his or her identity and residence by taking the prescribed oath, the person who administers the oath shall, before doing so, orally advise the oath taker of the qualifications for electors.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 162(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>indicate, if applicable, on the prescribed form that the elector has taken an oath and the type of oath;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>indicate, if applicable, on the prescribed form that the elector refused to comply with a legal requirement to provide the piece or pieces of identification referred to in paragraph 143(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), respectively, or to take an oath;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>indicate, if applicable, on the prescribed form that the elector has been allowed to vote under subsection 148.1(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>indicate, if applicable, on the prescribed form that an elector has voted in the circumstances described in section 147, that the prescribed oath has been taken or that any other oath that was required to be taken was taken, note any objection that was made on behalf of any of the candidates and indicate the candidate’s name;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on request, and at intervals of no less than 30 minutes, provide to a candidate's representative, on the prescribed form and as directed by the Chief Electoral Officer, the identity of every elector who has exercised his or her right to vote on polling day, excluding that of electors who registered on that day; </Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on request, after the close of the advance polling station, provide to a candidate's representative, on the prescribed form and as directed by the Chief Electoral Officer, the identity of every elector who has exercised his or her right to vote on that day excluding that of electors who registered on that day; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Text>Subsection 168(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of advance polling districts</MarginalNote><Label>168.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Each returning officer shall, as directed by the Chief Electoral Officer, establish in his or her electoral district advance polling districts that consist of one or more polling divisions.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 169(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An elector shall not be registered unless he or she</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provides as proof of his or her identity and residence the piece or pieces of identification referred to in paragraph 143(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), respectively; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>proves his or her identity and residence by taking the prescribed oath, and is accompanied by an elector whose name appears on the list of electors for the same polling division and who</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>provides the piece or pieces of identification referred to in paragraph 143(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), respectively, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>vouches for him or her on oath in the prescribed form.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 169 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — vouching for more than one elector</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No elector shall vouch for more than one elector at an election.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — vouchee acting as voucher</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An elector who has been vouched for at an election may not vouch for another elector at that election.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 169:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Requirement before administering oath</MarginalNote><Label>169.1</Label><Text>If a person chooses to prove his or her identity and residence by taking the prescribed oath, the person who administers the oath shall, before doing so, orally advise the oath taker of the qualifications for electors.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Text>Paragraph 173(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the deputy returning officer has ascertained with the returning officer that the elector is listed on the preliminary list of electors or was registered during the revision period; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33.</Label><Text>Paragraph 174(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the elector fails to prove his or her identity and residence in accordance with subsection 143(2) or (3) or to take an oath otherwise required by this Act; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 442(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Estimated expenses</MarginalNote><Label>442.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On November 15 in each year, the Chief Electoral Officer shall calculate the maximum amount referred to in section 440 for each electoral district, based on the lists of electors in the Register of Electors, as if an election were then to be held.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 442 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>This section does not apply if November 15 falls during an election period or if the vote at a general election was held during the six months before that date.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 50</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>Section 466 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Audit fee</MarginalNote><Label>466.</Label><Text>On receipt of the documents referred to in subsection 451(1) and, if applicable, those referred to in subsection 455(1), including the auditor’s report, and a copy of the auditor’s invoice for that report, the Chief Electoral Officer shall provide the Receiver General with a certificate that sets out the greater of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of the expenses incurred for the audit, up to a maximum of the lesser of 3% of the candidate’s election expenses and $1,500, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$250.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36.</Label><Text>Subsection 484(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences requiring intent — summary conviction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>being a returning officer, wilfully contravenes subsection 24(3) (failure to take promptly any necessary election proceedings); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 43.1(1) (refusal to give access to building or gated community).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37.</Label><Text>Subsection 486(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences requiring intent — summary conviction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection 81(1) (refusal to give access to building or gated community) or subsection 81.1(1) (refusal to give access to place open to the public) is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37.1</Label><Text>Subsection 487(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><Label>487.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence who contravenes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 111(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) (applying improperly to be included on list of electors); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 111(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) (unauthorized use of personal information contained in list of electors).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 489(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) of the Act are renumbered as 489(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">a.3</Emphasis>), respectively.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 489(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 143(5) (vouching for more than one elector);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 143(6) (vouch-ee acting as voucher);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 489(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a.3</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.4</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 161(7) (vouch-ee acting as voucher);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 489(2) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 169(5) (vouching for more than one elector); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>contravenes subsection 169(6) (vouchee acting as voucher).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 58(7)</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 497(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">z.1</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>being a registered agent or financial agent, contravenes section 476 (improper or unauthorized transfer of funds);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 497(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">s</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">s</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>being a candidate, wilfully contravenes subsection 451(5) (failure to send electoral campaign return declaration);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 19, s. 58(16)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 497(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">x</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">x</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>being a registered agent or financial agent, knowingly contravenes section 476 (unauthorized or improper transfer of funds);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39.1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 500(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who is guilty of an offence under any of subsection 485(1), paragraph 487(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), subsections 488(1), 489(2) and 491(2), section 493 and subsection 495(2) is liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $1,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three months, or to both.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 500 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>Every person who is guilty of an offence under paragraph 487(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $5,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than one year, or to both.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22, ss. 12 and 13</MarginalNote><TitleText>PUBLIC SERVICE EMPLOYMENT ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>40.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 50:</Text><AmendedText><Section><Label>50.1</Label><Text>Despite subsection 50(2), the maximum period of employment of casual workers appointed in the Office of the Chief Electoral Officer for the purposes of an election under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> or a referendum held under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Referendum Act</XRefExternal> is 165 working days in one calendar year.</Text></Section></AmendedText><?Pub Caret?></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 554(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal>, sections 3, 6, 8 and 9, subsection 10(2), sections 11, 12, 14 to 16, 20 to 27, 28(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>), 29 to 33 and 35 to 39 come into force two months after the day on which this Act receives royal assent unless, before that day, the Chief Electoral Officer publishes a notice in the <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> that the necessary preparations have been made for the bringing into operation of the provisions set out in the notice and that they may come into force on the day set out in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The amendment to the definition “list of electors” in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 1, sections 4, 5 and 7, subsection 10(1) and sections 13, 17 to 19 and 34 come into force 10 months after the day on which this Act receives royal assent unless, before that day, the Chief Electoral Officer publishes a notice in the <Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis> that the necessary preparations have been made for the bringing into operation of the provisions set out in the notice and that they may come into force on the day set out in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 162(<Emphasis style="italic">i.1</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">i.2</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 28, come into force six months after the day on which this Act receives royal assent unless, before that day, the Chief Electoral Officer publishes a notice in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> that the necessary preparations have been made for the bringing into operation of the provisions set out in the notice and that they may come into force on the day set out in the notice.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>