<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-3</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>55-56</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2006-2007</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the National Defence Act, the Criminal Code, the Sex Offender Information Registration Act and the Criminal Records Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Defence Act, Criminal Code, Sex Offender Information Registration Act and Criminal Records Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Defence, Criminal Code, Sex Offender Information Registration and Criminal Records</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2007</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>5</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2007</YYYY><?Pub Caret?></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2006-4-19">90315</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> to create a scheme that requires offenders who have committed service offences of a sexual nature to provide information for registration in a national database under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>. The new scheme parallels the one in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, and that Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal> are amended accordingly. The amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> also establish mechanisms to accommodate military operational requirements when necessary.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment creates a new offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> for failure to comply with an order or obligation to provide information to a designated registration centre.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>It also makes certain amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> to enhance the administration and enforcement of the current registration scheme for sex offender information.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. N-5</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">NATIONAL DEFENCE ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>verdict de non-responsabilité pour cause de troubles mentaux</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn> means a finding made under subsection 202.14(1);</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Provost Marshal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>prévôt</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Provost Marshal</DefinedTermEn> means the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 119:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Offence in Relation to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Failure to comply with order or obligation</MarginalNote><Label>119.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who, without reasonable excuse, fails to comply with an order made under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, or with an obligation under section 227.06 of this Act or section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, is guilty of an offence and on conviction is liable to imprisonment for less than two years or to less punishment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasonable excuse</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a lawful command that prevents a person from complying with an order or obligation is a reasonable excuse.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 18</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>Subsection 202.14(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder</MarginalNote><Label>202.14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a court martial finds that an accused person committed the act or made the omission that forms the basis of the offence charged but was suffering at the time from a mental disorder so as to be exempt from responsibility, the court martial shall make a finding that the accused person committed the act or made the omission but is not responsible on account of mental disorder.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 226:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><Label>Division 8.1</Label><TitleText>Sex Offender Information</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>227.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Division.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>crime of a sexual nature</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>crime de nature sexuelle</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>crime of a sexual nature</DefinedTermEn> means a crime referred to in subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>database</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>banque de données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>database</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>infraction désignée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence within the meaning of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that is punishable under section 130 of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence within the meaning of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> that is punishable under section 130 of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>verdict de non-responsabilité pour cause de troubles mentaux</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn> includes a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder within the meaning of subsection 672.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>officer, or non-commis­sioned member, of the primary reserve</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>officier ou militaire du rang de la première réserve</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>officer, or non-commis­sioned member, of the primary reserve</DefinedTermEn> means an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the reserve force</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>who is required, whether on active service or not, to perform military or any other form of duty or training;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whose primary duty is not the supervision, administration and training of cadet organizations referred to in section 46; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>who is required to undergo annual training.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>pardon</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>réhabilitation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>pardon</DefinedTermEn> means a pardon granted by any authority under law, other than a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or under section 748 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, that has not ceased to have effect or been revoked.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>prescribed form</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>formulaire réglementaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>prescribed form</DefinedTermEn> means a form prescribed in the regulations made by the Governor in Council.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>bureau d’inscription</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Review Board</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commission d’examen</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Review Board</DefinedTermEn> means the Review Board established or designated for a province under subsection 672.38(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Order to Comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>227.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after a court martial imposes a sentence on a person for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 or finds the person not responsible on account of mental disorder for such an offence, it shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in the prescribed form requiring the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in section 227.02.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after a court martial imposes a sentence on a person for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227, it shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in the prescribed form requiring the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in section 227.02, if the prosecutor establishes beyond a reasonable doubt that the person committed the offence with the intent to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of that definition.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after a court martial imposes a sentence on a person for a designated offence in connection with which an order may be made under subsection (1) or (2) or finds the person not responsible on account of mental disorder for such an offence, it shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in the prescribed form requiring the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in section 227.02, if the prosecutor establishes that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person was, before or after the coming into force of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, previously convicted of, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder for, an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of this Act or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person has not been served with a notice under section 227.08 of this Act or section 490.021 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in connection with the previous offence; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no order was made under subsection (1) or under subsection 490.012(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in connection with the previous offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purpose of paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), a previous conviction includes a conviction for an offence</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for which a person is given an adult sentence within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that is made in ordinary court within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Young Offenders Act</XRefExternal>, chapter Y-1 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The court martial is not required to make an order under this section if it is satisfied that the person has established that, if the order were made, the impact on them, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The court martial shall give reasons for its decision.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Date order begins</MarginalNote><Label>227.02</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An order made under section 227.01 begins on the day on which it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 227.01(1) or (2)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 10 years after it was made if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence in connection with which it was made is five years or less;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 20 years after it was made if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is 10 or 14 years; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies for life if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is life.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 227.01(1) or (2) applies for life if the person is, or was at any time, subject to an obligation under section 227.06 of this Act or section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 227.01(1) or (2) applies for life if the person is, or was at any time, subject to an order made previously under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 227.01(3) applies for life.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for termination order</MarginalNote><Label>227.03</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an order may apply for a termination order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if five years have elapsed since the order was made, in the case of an order referred to in paragraph 227.02(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if 10 years have elapsed since the order was made, in the case of an order referred to in paragraph 227.02(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if 20 years have elapsed since the order was made, in the case of an order referred to in paragraph 227.02(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or subsection 227.02(3) or (5).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Multiple orders</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to more than one order made under section 227.01 may apply for a termination order if 20 years have elapsed since the most recent order was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pardon</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (1) and (2), a person may apply for a termination order once they receive a pardon.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Scope of application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The application shall be in relation to every order that is in effect. If a person is subject to an obligation under section 227.06 of this Act or section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the application shall also be in relation to that obligation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Re-application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person whose application is refused may re-apply if five years have elapsed since they made the previous application. They may also re-apply once they receive a pardon. However, they may not re-apply under this subsection if an order is made with respect to them under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> after the previous application was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The application shall be made to the Chief Military Judge if the applicant is subject to the Code of Service Discipline or is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve at the time. In any other case, the application shall be made to a court under section 490.015 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court martial</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>On receipt of the application, the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a court martial to try the issue.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Termination order</MarginalNote><Label>227.04</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court martial shall make a termination order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact on them of continuing the order or orders and any obligation, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court martial shall give reasons for the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Provost Marshal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the court martial makes a termination order, it shall cause the Provost Marshal to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>227.05</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a court martial makes an order under section 227.01, it shall cause</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the order to be read by or to the person who is subject to it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a copy of the order to be given to that person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that person to be informed of sections 4 to 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, section 119.1 of this Act and sections 490.031 and 490.0311 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a copy of the order to be sent to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Review Board that is responsible for making a disposition with respect to that person, if applicable,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the person in charge of the place in which the person who is subject to the order is to serve the custodial portion of a sentence or is to be detained in custody as part of a disposition under Division 7 of this Part, if applicable, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the Provost Marshal.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice on disposition by Review Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A Review Board shall cause a copy of the order to be given to the person who is subject to the order when it directs,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the exercise of the powers and performance of the duties assigned to it under paragraph 672.54(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, that the person be discharged absolutely; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the exercise of the powers and performance of the duties assigned to it under paragraph 672.54(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, that the person be discharged subject to conditions, unless the conditions restrict the person’s liberty in a manner and to an extent that prevent them from complying with sections 4, 4.1, 4.3 and 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice before release</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The person in charge of the place in which the person who is subject to the order is serving the custodial portion of a sentence, or is detained in custody, before their release or discharge shall give them a copy of the order not earlier than 10 days before their release or discharge.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Notice and Obligation to Comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to comply</MarginalNote><Label>227.06</Label><Text>A person who is served with a notice in the prescribed form shall comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in section 227.09 of this Act unless an exemption order is made under subsection 227.1(4) of this Act or subsection 490.023(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Persons who may be served</MarginalNote><Label>227.07</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Provost Marshal may serve a person with a notice if, on the day on which this section comes into force, they are subject to a sentence for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 or have not been discharged absolutely or unconditionally released from custody under Division 7 of this Part in connection with such an offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice shall not be served on a person if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they may be served with a notice under section 490.021 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they have been finally acquitted of, or have received a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or under section 748 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> for, every offence in connection with which the notice may be served on them; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an application has been made for an order under subsection 227.01(3) of this Act or subsection 490.012(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in relation to any offence in connection with which the notice may be served on them.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Period for and method of service</MarginalNote><Label>227.08</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The notice shall be personally served within one year after the day on which section 227.07 comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person is unlawfully at large or is in breach of any terms of their sentence or their discharge or release under Division 7 of this Part, or of any conditions set under this Part, that relate to residence, the notice may be served by registered mail at their last known address.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of service</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An affidavit of the person who served the notice, sworn before a commissioner or other person authorized to take affidavits, is evidence of the service and the notice if it sets out that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who served the notice has charge of the appropriate records and has knowledge of the facts in the particular case;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the notice was personally served on, or mailed to, the person to whom it was directed on a named day; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who served the notice identifies a true copy of the notice as an exhibit attached to the affidavit.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The person who served the notice shall send a copy of the affidavit and the notice to the Provost Marshal without delay.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Date obligation begins</MarginalNote><Label>227.09</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The obligation under section 227.06 begins</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>either one year after the day on which the person is served with the notice, or when an exemption order is refused under subsection 227.1(4) of this Act or subsection 490.023(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, whichever is later; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when an exemption order is quashed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Date obligation ends</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The obligation ends when an exemption order is made on an appeal from a decision made under subsection 227.1(4) of this Act or subsection 490.023(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of obligation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If subsection (2) does not apply earlier, the obligation</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 10 years after the person was sentenced, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder, for the offence listed in the notice if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is five years or less;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 20 years after the person was sentenced, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder, for the offence listed in the notice if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is 10 or 14 years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies for life if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence listed in the notice is life; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies for life if, at any time, the person was convicted of, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder for, more than one offence that is referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of this Act or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> and if more than one of those offences is listed in the notice.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>227.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is not subject to an order under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> may apply for an order exempting them from the obligation within one year after they are served with a notice under section 227.08.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application shall be made to the Chief Military Judge if the applicant is subject to the Code of Service Discipline or is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve at the time. In any other case, the application shall be made to a court under section 490.023 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court martial</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On receipt of the application, the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a court martial to try the issue.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The court martial shall make an exemption order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact of the obligation on them, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act.</XRefExternal></Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The court martial shall give reasons for the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of information from database</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the court martial makes an exemption order, it shall also make an order requiring the permanent removal from the database of all information that relates to the person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>227.11</Label><Text>If the court martial refuses to make an exemption order or if the Court Martial Appeal Court dismisses an appeal from such a decision or quashes an exemption order, it shall cause the Provost Marshal to be notified of the decision and shall cause the person who applied for the order to be informed of sections 4 to 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, section 119.1 of this Act and sections 490.031 and 490.0311 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for termination order</MarginalNote><Label>227.12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an obligation under section 227.06 and is not subject to an order under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> may apply for a termination order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time for application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person may apply for a termination order if the following period has elapsed since they were sentenced, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder, for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>five years if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is five years or less;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>10 years if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is 10 or 14 years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>20 years if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is life.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>More than one offence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If more than one offence is listed in the notice served under section 227.08, the person may apply for a termination order if 20 years have elapsed since they were sentenced, or found not responsible on account of mental disorder, for the most recent offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of this Act or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pardon</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (2) and (3), a person may apply for a termination order once they receive a pardon.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Re-application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person whose application is refused may re-apply if five years have elapsed since they made the previous application. They may also re-apply once they receive a pardon. However, they may not re-apply under this subsection if an order is made with respect to them under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> after the previous application was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The application shall be made to the Chief Military Judge if the applicant is subject to the Code of Service Discipline or is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve at the time. In any other case, the application shall be made to a court under section 490.026 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court martial</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>On receipt of the application, the Chief Military Judge shall cause the Court Martial Administrator to convene a court martial to try the issue.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Termination order</MarginalNote><Label>227.13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court martial shall make an order terminating the obligation if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact on them of continuing the obligation, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court martial shall give reasons for the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the court martial makes a termination order, it shall cause the Provost Marshal to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deemed application</MarginalNote><Label>227.14</Label><Text>If a person is eligible to apply for both an exemption order under section 227.1 and a termination order under section 227.12 within one year after they are served with a notice under section 227.08, an application within that period for one order is deemed to be an application for both.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Suspension of Time Limits, Proceedings and Obligations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Determination — inability to act for operational reasons</MarginalNote><Label>227.15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff may determine that a person who is subject to the Code of Service Discipline, or who is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve, is, for operational reasons, unable to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>apply for an exemption order under section 227.1 of this Act or section 490.023 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> within the required period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>appeal the legality of a decision made under section 227.01 or subsection 227.04(1), 227.1(4) or 227.13(1) of this Act, or appeal a decision made under section 490.012 or subsection 490.016(1), 490.023(2) or 490.027(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, within the required period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>participate in a proceeding relating to an exemption order referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or in an appeal proceeding referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>comply with section 4, 4.1, 4.3 or 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> within the required period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effects of determination</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Chief of the Defence Staff makes a determination, the following rules apply:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the running of the period during which the person may apply for an exemption order is suspended from the day on which the operational reasons first apply until 45 days after the day on which they cease to apply;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the running of the period during which the person may appeal the legality of a decision, or a decision, is suspended from the day on which the operational reasons first apply until 45 days after the day on which they cease to apply;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>),</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>any proceeding relating to an exemption order is suspended from the day on which the operational reasons first apply until 45 days after the day on which they cease to apply, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an application may be made to appeal the legality of a decision, or a decision, after the day on which the operational reasons first apply, but any appeal proceeding is suspended from the day on which the operational reasons first apply until 45 days after the day on which they cease to apply; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), the person’s obligation to comply with the relevant section of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> is suspended from the day on which the operational reasons first apply until 15 days after the day on which they cease to apply.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors for consideration</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff may make a determination only if he or she is of the opinion that the operational reasons clearly outweigh in importance the public interest in applying the provisions of the Act that, but for the determination, would apply in the circumstances.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff shall notify the Minister before making a determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review of operational reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Every 15 days after a determination is made, the Chief of the Defence Staff shall consider whether the operational reasons cease to apply.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff shall notify the Minister without delay that a determination has been made under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff shall notify the Provost Marshal without delay of the determination, the date on which the operational reasons first apply and the date on which they cease to apply, and the Provost Marshal shall notify the person without delay.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Provost Marshal shall notify the following persons without delay of a determination made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), the effect of the determination, the date on which the suspension of the time limit or proceeding first applies and the date on which it ceases to apply:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister or counsel instructed by the Minister if the decision in relation to which an appeal may be brought was made under this Act, or the Minister or counsel instructed by the Minister and the Court Martial Administrator if the proceeding was commenced under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the attorney general of a province or the minister of justice of a territory if the decision in relation to which an appeal may be brought was made, or the proceeding was commenced, in that jurisdiction under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Determination — information relating to an operation</MarginalNote><Label>227.16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff may determine that the communication, under section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, of information that relates to an operation could jeopardize national security, international relations or the security of an operation that is within a class of operations designated by a regulation made under paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff shall notify the Minister without delay that a determination has been made under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff shall notify the Provost Marshal without delay of the determination, and the Provost Marshal shall notify without delay any participant in the operation who is required to comply with section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of determination</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A participant in the operation is exempted from the requirement under section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> to provide the information relating to the operation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>227.17</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a determination made by the Chief of the Defence Staff under subsection 227.15(1) or 227.16(1).</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual Report</MarginalNote><Label>227.171</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff shall, within 30 days after the end of each year, submit a report to the Minister on the operation of sections 227.15 and 227.16 for that year that includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the number of determinations made under each of paragraphs 227.15(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and the duration of the suspension resulting from each determination; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the number of determinations made under subsection 227.16(1) and the number of persons exempted under subsection 227.16(4) as a result of each determination.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the report.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Disclosure of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure by Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>227.18</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the request of the Provost Marshal, the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police shall disclose information that is registered in the database, or the fact that information is registered in the database, to the Provost Marshal if the disclosure is necessary to enable the Provost Marshal to determine</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether a person may be served with a notice under section 227.08;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the purpose of a proceeding for an order under section 227.01, a termination order under subsection 227.04(1) or 227.13(1) or an exemption order under subsection 227.1(4), or for the purpose of an appeal respecting the legality of a decision made under any of those provisions, whether a person who is subject to the Code of Service Discipline, or who is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve, is, or was at any time, required to comply with an order made under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or with an obligation under section 227.06 of this Act or section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the purpose of enabling compliance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, whether a person who is subject to the Code of Service Discipline, or who is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve, is required to comply with an order made under section 227.01 of this Act or section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or with an obligation under section 227.06 of this Act or section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether a person who is subject to the Code of Service Discipline, or who is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve, may be the subject of a determination under subsection 227.15(1) or 227.16(1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure by Provost Marshal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Provost Marshal shall disclose the information</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to a prosecutor if the disclosure is necessary for the purpose of a proceeding for an order under section 227.01, a termination order under subsection 227.04(1) or 227.13(1) or an exemption order under subsection 227.1(4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the Minister or counsel instructed by the Minister if the disclosure is necessary for the purpose of an appeal respecting the legality of a decision made in a proceeding referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to a person’s commanding officer if the disclosure is necessary to enable the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the Chief of the Defence Staff if the disclosure is necessary for the purpose of a determination under subsection 227.15(1) or 227.16(1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The prosecutor or the Minister or counsel instructed by the Minister may, if the information is relevant to the proceeding or appeal referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), disclose it to the presiding judge, court or court martial.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure by Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>227.19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person, in connection with a proceeding or an appeal other than one referred to in paragraph 227.18(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), discloses the fact that information relating to them is registered in the database, the Provost Marshal shall request that the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police disclose all of the information relating to the person that is registered in the database. The Commissioner shall disclose the information to the Provost Marshal without delay.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure by Provost Marshal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Provost Marshal shall disclose the information</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the officer who has jurisdiction to try the person and to a person who provides legal advice to the officer with respect to the proceeding, in the case of a summary trial; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the prosecutor or to the Minister or counsel instructed by the Minister in any other case.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The officer who has jurisdiction to try the person may, if the officer is unable to preside over the summary trial, disclose the information to another officer who has jurisdiction to try the person and to a person who provides legal advice to that officer with respect to the summary trial.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The officer who presides over the summary trial may disclose the information to a review authority and to a person who provides legal advice to the review authority with respect to a review of a finding of guilty made or a punishment imposed in the summary trial, if the information is relevant to the review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The prosecutor or the Minister or counsel instructed by the Minister may disclose the information to the presiding judge, court or court martial in the proceeding or appeal or in any subsequent appeal, or to a review authority and to a person who provides legal advice to the review authority with respect to a review of a finding of guilty made or a punishment imposed in the proceeding or appeal, if the information is relevant to the proceeding, appeal or review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A review authority may disclose the information to another review authority and to a person who provides legal advice to the other review authority with respect to a review by that review authority of a finding of guilty made or punishment imposed in a proceeding or appeal referred to in subsection (1) or in any subsequent appeal, if the information is relevant to the review.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Authorizations, Designations and Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations by Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>227.2</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the means by which designated classes of persons who are subject to the Code of Service Discipline and officers, or non-commissioned members, of the primary reserve are required to report under section 4, 4.1 or 4.3, or to provide notification under section 6, of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> to registration centres designated under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating classes of operations in respect of which a determination may be made under subsection 227.16(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorizing persons or classes of persons in or outside Canada to collect information under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> that relates to persons who are subject to the Code of Service Discipline and to officers, or non-commissioned members, of the primary reserve;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorizing persons or classes of persons in or outside Canada to register information under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> that relates to persons who are subject to the Code of Service Discipline and to officers, or non-commissioned members, of the primary reserve; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating places or classes of places in or outside Canada as registration centres for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> and the area, or classes of persons who are subject to the Code of Service Discipline and officers, or non-commissioned members, of the primary reserve, served by each registration centre.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization</MarginalNote><Label>227.21</Label><Text>The Chief of the Defence Staff, the Provost Marshal, the Chief Military Judge or a commanding officer may authorize a person to communicate or disclose information, or give notice, under this Division on their behalf.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Section 230 of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), by adding the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the legality of a decision made under section 227.01.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Section 230.1 of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f.1</Emphasis>), by adding the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the legality of a decision made under section 227.01.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 230.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal from order</MarginalNote><Label>230.2</Label><Text>Subject to subsection 232(3), a person who applied for an exemption order under section 227.1 or a termination order under section 227.03 or 227.12 and the Minister or counsel instructed by the Minister have the right to appeal to the Court Martial Appeal Court in respect of the legality of the decision made by the court martial.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 22; 1998, c. 35, par. 92(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>Subsection 232(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Délai d’appel</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>L’appel interjeté ou la demande d’autorisation d’appel présentée aux termes de la présente section ne sont recevables que si, dans les trente jours suivant la date à laquelle la cour martiale met fin à ses délibérations, l’avis d’appel est transmis au greffe de la Cour d’appel de la cour martiale ou, dans les circonstances prévues par un règlement du gouverneur en conseil, à toute personne désignée par ce règlement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 240.4:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal against order or decision</MarginalNote><Label>240.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the hearing of an appeal respecting the legality of a decision made under section 227.01 or subsection 227.04(1), 227.1(4) or 227.13(1), the Court Martial Appeal Court, or another court hearing the appeal, may dismiss the appeal, allow it and order a new hearing, quash the order or make an order that may be made under that provision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court makes an order that may be made under section 227.01, it shall cause the requirements set out in section 227.05 to be fulfilled.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court makes an order that may be made under subsection 227.04(1) or 227.13(1), it shall cause the Provost Marshal to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of information from database</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Court Martial Appeal Court or other court makes an exemption order that may be made under subsection 227.1(4), it shall also make the order referred to in subsection 227.1(6).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 35, s. 82</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Provost Marshal</DefinedTermEn> in section 250 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">CRIMINAL CODE</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>verdict de non-responsabilité</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn> means a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder within the meaning of subsection 672.1(1) or a finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as the case may be.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)(v) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsection 246(1) (assault with intent) if the intent is to commit an offence referred to in any of subparagraphs (i) to (iv);</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under any of the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as enacted by section 19 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Criminal Code in relation to sexual offences and other offences against the person and to amend certain other Acts in relation thereto or in consequence thereof</XRefExternal>, chapter 125 of the Statutes of Canada, 1980-81-82-83:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 246.1 (sexual assault),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 246.2 (sexual assault with a weapon, threats to a third party or causing bodily harm), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 246.3 (aggravated sexual assault);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>The heading before section 490.012 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading><TitleText>Order to Comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Subsections 490.012(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>490.012</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after a court imposes a sentence on a person for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) or renders a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for such an offence, it shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in Form 52 requiring the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in section 490.013.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after a court imposes a sentence on a person for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1), it shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in Form 52 requiring the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in section 490.013, if the prosecutor establishes beyond a reasonable doubt that the person committed the offence with the intent to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of that definition.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after a court imposes a sentence on a person for a designated offence in connection with which an order may be made under subsection (1) or (2) or renders a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for such an offence, it shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in Form 52 requiring the person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in section 490.013, if the prosecutor establishes that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person was, before or after the coming into force of that Act, previously convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of this Act or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person has not been served with a notice under section 490.021 of this Act or section 227.08 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> in connection with the previous offence; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no order was made under subsection (1) or under subsection 227.01(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> in connection with the previous offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 490.013(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 10 years after it was made if the offence in connection with which it was made was prosecuted summarily or if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is two or five years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 20 years after it was made if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is 10 or 14 years; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies for life if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is life.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 490.013(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 490.012(1) or (2) applies for life if the person is, or was at any time, subject to an obligation under section 490.019 of this Act or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 490.012(1) or (2) applies for life if the person is, or was at any time, subject to an order made previously under section 490.012 of this Act or section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.013(5) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 490.012(3) applies for life.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>Section 490.015 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application for termination order</MarginalNote><Label>490.015</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an order may apply for a termination order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if five years have elapsed since the order was made, in the case of an order referred to in paragraph 490.013(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if 10 years have elapsed since the order was made, in the case of an order referred to in paragraph 490.013(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if 20 years have elapsed since the order was made, in the case of an order referred to in paragraph 490.013(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or subsection 490.013(3) or (5).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Multiple orders</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to more than one order made under section 490.012 of this Act, or under that section and section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, may apply for a termination order if 20 years have elapsed since the most recent order was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pardon</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (1) and (2), a person may apply for a termination order once they receive a pardon.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Scope of application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The application shall be in relation to every order that is in effect. If a person is subject to an obligation under section 490.019 of this Act or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, the application shall also be in relation to that obligation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Re-application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person whose application is refused may re-apply if five years have elapsed since they made the previous application. They may also re-apply once they receive a pardon. However, they may not re-apply under this subsection if an order is made with respect to them under section 490.012 of this Act or section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> after the previous application was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The application shall be made to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a superior court of criminal jurisdiction if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>one or more of the orders to which it relates were made by such a court under section 490.012, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>one or more of the orders to which it relates were made under section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and the Chief Military Judge does not have jurisdiction to receive the application under subsection 227.03(6) of that Act; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a court of criminal jurisdiction, in any other case in which the application relates to one or more orders made under section 490.012.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.016(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Termination order</MarginalNote><Label>490.016</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court shall make a termination order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact on them of continuing the order or orders and any obligation, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 490.016 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the court makes a termination order, it shall cause the Attorney General of the province or the minister of justice of the territory to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>Section 490.017 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 490.017(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the appeal court makes an order that may be made under subsection 490.016(1), it shall cause the Attorney General of the province or the minister of justice of the territory in which the application for the order was made to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 490.018(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that person to be informed of sections 4 to 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, sections 490.031 and 490.0311 of this Act and section 119.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 490.018(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under paragraph 672.54(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), that the person be discharged subject to conditions, unless the conditions restrict the person’s liberty in a manner and to an extent that prevent them from complying with sections 4, 4.1, 4.3 and 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>The heading before section 490.019 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading><TitleText>Notice and Obligation to Comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 490.02(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Persons who may be served</MarginalNote><Label>490.02</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of a province or minister of justice of a territory may serve a person with a notice only if the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) and</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 490.02(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if they have been finally acquitted of, or have received a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or under section 748 for, every offence in connection with which a notice may be served on them under section 490.021 of this Act or section 227.08 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if an application has been made for an order under subsection 490.012(3) of this Act or subsection 227.01(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> in relation to any offence in connection with which a notice may be served on them under section 490.021 of this Act or section 227.08 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 490.02(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>who is referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) if they have provided proof of a pardon in accordance with subsection 9(1) of the Ontario Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.021(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Signification</MarginalNote><Label>490.021</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>L’avis est signifié à personne dans l’année qui suit la date d’entrée en vigueur de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur l’enregistrement de renseignements sur les délinquants sexuels</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.021(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person referred to in paragraph 490.02(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is unlawfully at large or is in breach of any terms of their sentence or discharge, or of any conditions set under this Act or under Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, that relate to residence, the notice may be served by registered mail at their last known address.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 490.022(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>either one year after the day on which the person is served with the notice or when an exemption order is refused under subsection 490.023(2), whichever is later; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when an exemption order is quashed.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 490.022(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 10 years after the person was sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for the offence listed in the notice if the offence was prosecuted summarily or if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is two or five years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 20 years after the person was sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for the offence listed in the notice if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is 10 or 14 years;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 490.022(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies for life if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence listed in the notice is life; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 490.022(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies for life if, at any time, the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, more than one offence that is referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of this Act or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and if more than one of those offences is listed in the notice.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>Subsection 490.023(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application for exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>490.023</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is not subject to an order under section 490.012 of this Act or section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> may apply for an order exempting them from the obligation within one year after they are served with a notice under section 490.021 of this Act or section 227.08 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The application shall be made to a court of criminal jurisdiction if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it relates to an obligation under section 490.019 of this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it relates to an obligation under section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and the Chief Military Judge does not have jurisdiction to receive the application under subsection 227.1(2) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>Sections 490.025 and 490.026 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>490.025</Label><Text>If a court refuses to make an exemption order or an appeal court dismisses an appeal from such a decision or quashes an exemption order, it shall cause the Attorney General of the province or the minister of justice of the territory in which the application for the order was made to be notified of the decision, and shall cause the person who applied for the order to be informed of sections 4 to 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, sections 490.031 and 490.0311 of this Act and section 119.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for termination order</MarginalNote><Label>490.026</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an obligation under section 490.019 and is not subject to an order under section 490.012 of this Act or section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> may apply for a termination order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time for application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person may apply for a termination order if the following period has elapsed since they were sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of this Act or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>five years if the offence was prosecuted summarily or if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is two or five years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>10 years if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is 10 or 14 years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>20 years if the maximum term of imprisonment for the offence is life.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>More than one offence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If more than one offence is listed in the notice served under section 490.021, the person may apply for a termination order if 20 years have elapsed since they were sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for the most recent offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of this Act or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pardon</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (2) and (3), a person may apply for a termination order once they receive a pardon.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Re-application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person whose application is refused may re-apply if five years have elapsed since they made the previous application. They may also re-apply once they receive a pardon. However, they may not re-apply under this subsection if an order is made with respect to them under section 490.012 of this Act or section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> after the previous application was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The application shall be made to a court of criminal jurisdiction if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it relates to an obligation under section 490.019 of this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it relates to an obligation under section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and the Chief Military Judge does not have jurisdiction to receive the application under subsection 227.12(6) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 490.027(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Termination order</MarginalNote><Label>490.027</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court shall make an order terminating the obligation if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact on them of continuing the obligation, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 490.027 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the court makes a termination order, it shall cause the Attorney General of the province or the minister of justice of the territory to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Text>Sections 490.028 and 490.029 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Deemed application</MarginalNote><Label>490.028</Label><Text>If a person is eligible to apply for both an exemption order under section 490.023 and a termination order under section 490.026 within one year after they are served with a notice under section 490.021 of this Act or section 227.08 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, an application within that period for one order is deemed to be an application for both.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>490.029</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General or the person who applied for a termination order may appeal from a decision of the court made under subsection 490.027(1) on any ground of appeal that raises a question of law or of mixed law and fact. The appeal court may dismiss the appeal, or allow it and order a new hearing, quash the termination order or make an order that may be made under that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the appeal court makes an order that may be made under subsection 490.027(1), it shall cause the Attorney General of the province or the minister of justice of the territory in which the application for the order was made to be notified of the decision.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 490.03(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the prosecutor if the disclosure is necessary for the purpose of a proceeding for an order under section 490.012; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the Attorney General if the disclosure is necessary for the purpose of a proceeding for a termination order under subsection 490.016(1) or 490.027(1) or an exemption order under subsection 490.023(2), or for the purpose of an appeal from a decision made in a proceeding under any of those subsections or in a proceeding for an order under section 490.012.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 490.03(2) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in connection with proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person, in connection with a proceeding or an appeal other than one referred to in subsection (1), discloses the fact that information relating to them is registered in the database, the Commissioner shall, on request, disclose to the prosecutor or the Attorney General all of the information relating to the person that is registered in the database.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The prosecutor or the Attorney General may, if the information is relevant to the proceeding, appeal or any subsequent appeal, disclose it to the presiding court.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 490.031 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>490.031</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who, without reasonable excuse, fails to comply with an order made under section 490.012 of this Act or section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, or with an obligation under section 490.019 of this Act or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, is guilty of an offence and liable</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 490.031 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasonable excuse</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a lawful command that prevents a person from complying with an order or obligation is a reasonable excuse if, at the time, the person is subject to the Code of Service Discipline within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 490.031:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>490.0311</Label><Text>Every person who knowingly provides false or misleading information under subsection 5(1) or 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a first offence, on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a second or subsequent offence,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years, or to both, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 21</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The paragraph before section 1 of Form 52 in Part XXVIII of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Vous avez été déclaré coupable d’avoir ............... (<Emphasis style="italic">décrire chaque infraction</Emphasis>), infraction(s) désignée(s) au sens du paragraphe 490.011(1) du <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Code criminel</XRefExternal>, en violation de ............. (<Emphasis style="italic">citer la disposition du <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Code criminel</XRefExternal> relative à chaque infraction désignée</Emphasis>) ou un verdict de non-responsabilité a été rendu à votre égard.</Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 21</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 1 and 2 of Form 52 in Part XXVIII of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>You must report for the first time to the registration centre referred to in section 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, whenever required under subsection 4(1) of that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>You must subsequently report to the registration centre referred to in section 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, whenever required under section 4.1 or 4.3 of that Act, for a period of ...... years after this order is made (<Emphasis style="italic">or if paragraph 490.013(2)(c) or any of subsections 490.013(3) to (5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies,</Emphasis> for life).</Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 21</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 5 of Form 52 in Part XXVIII of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5.</Label><Text>If you believe that the information registered in the database contains an error or omission, you may ask a person who collects information at the registration centre referred to in section 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> or, if applicable, the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal, to correct the information.</Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 21</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The paragraph before section 1 of Form 53 in Part XXVIII of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Because, on ....... (<Emphasis style="italic">insert date(s)</Emphasis>), you were convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, ......... (<Emphasis style="italic">insert description of offence(s)</Emphasis>), one or more offences referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, under ....... (<Emphasis style="italic">insert the applicable offence provision(s)</Emphasis>), this is provided to give you notice that you are required to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 21</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 1 and 2 of Form 53 in Part XXVIII of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1.</Label><Text>You must report for the first time to the registration centre referred to in section 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, whenever required under subsection 4(2) of that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2.</Label><Text>You must subsequently report to the registration centre referred to in section 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, whenever required under section 4.1 or 4.3 of that Act, for a period of ....... years after you were sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for the offence (<Emphasis style="italic">or if paragraph 490.022(3)(c) or (d) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies</Emphasis>, for life) or for any shorter period set out in subsection 490.022(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 21</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 5 of Form 53 in Part XXVIII of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5.</Label><Text>If you believe that the information registered in the database contains an error or omission, you may ask a person who collects information at the registration centre referred to in section 7.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> or, if applicable, the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal, to correct the information.</Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">SEX OFFENDER INFORMATION REGISTRATION ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>order</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>person who collects information</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>person who registers information</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>sex offender</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>order</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ordonnance</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>order</DefinedTermEn> means an order under section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>person who collects information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>préposé à la collecte</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>person who collects information</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is authorized to collect information under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1) of this Act or paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>person who registers information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>préposé à l’enregistrement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>person who registers information</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is authorized to register information under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1) of this Act or paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>bureau d’inscription</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn> means a place that is designated as a registration centre under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1) of this Act or paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>sex offender</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>délinquant sexuel</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>sex offender</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is subject to one or more orders or to an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>finding of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>verdict de non-responsabilité</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>finding of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn> means a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder within the meaning of subsection 672.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or a finding of not responsible on account of mental disorder within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as the case may be.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 4(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>First obligation to report</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an order shall report to a registration centre referred to in section 7.1 within 15 days after</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sa libération inconditionnelle ou sous conditions au titre de la partie XX.1 du <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Code criminel</XRefExternal> en cas de verdict de non-responsabilité à l’égard de l’infraction en cause;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they receive an absolute or conditional discharge or are released from custody under Division 7 of Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, if they are found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for the offence in connection with which the order is made;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the imprisonment or detention to which they are sentenced for the offence in connection with which the order is made is suspended under section 215 or 216 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 4(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>First obligation to report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> shall report to a registration centre referred to in section 7.1 of this Act</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>they receive an absolute or conditional discharge or are released from custody under Division 7 of Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.2)</Label><Text>an imprisonment or a detention to which they are sentenced is suspended under section 215 or 216 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Means of reporting</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a sex offender is required to report to a registration centre designated under this Act, they shall report in person. If they are required to report to a registration centre designated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, they shall report in person unless regulations are made under paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of that Act, in which case they shall report in accordance with those regulations.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 4.1 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 4.1(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 4.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Subsequent obligation to report</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A sex offender shall subsequently report to the registration centre referred to in section 7.1,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 4.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Means of reporting</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a sex offender is required to report to a registration centre designated under this Act, they shall report in person or in accordance with regulations made under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1). If they are required to report to a registration centre designated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, they shall report in person unless regulations are made under paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of that Act, in which case they shall report in accordance with those regulations.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35.</Label><Text>Subsection 4.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation and order</MarginalNote><Label>4.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person who is subject to an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> becomes subject to an order, they shall report on the reporting dates established under the order only.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 4.3 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 4.3(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 4.3(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Séjour hors du Canada</MarginalNote><Label>4.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le délinquant sexuel qui est à l’étranger au moment où il est tenu de comparaître en application de l’article 4.1 comparaît au bureau d’inscription au plus tard quinze jours après son retour.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 4.3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian Forces</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to a sex offender who is required to report to a registration centre designated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> while they are outside Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation de fournir des renseignements</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Lorsqu’il comparaît au bureau d’inscription, le délinquant sexuel fournit les renseignements suivants au préposé à la collecte :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if applicable, their status as an officer or a non-commissioned member of the Canadian Forces within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and the address and telephone number of their unit within the meaning of that subsection;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When a sex offender reports to a registration centre, the person who collects the information from them may ask them when and where they were convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, an offence in connection with which an order was made or, if they are subject to an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 6(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Notification of absence</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A sex offender shall notify a person who collects information at the registration centre referred to in section 7.1</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 6(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Means of notification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a sex offender is required to provide notification to a registration centre designated under this Act, they shall provide the notification by registered mail or in accordance with regulations made under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1). If they are required to provide notification to a registration centre designated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, they shall provide the notification by registered mail unless regulations are made under paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of that Act, in which case they shall provide the notification in accordance with those regulations.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 7:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Registration centre</MarginalNote><Label>7.1</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 4, 4.1, 4.3 and 6, the registration centre is one that is designated under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1) that serves the area of the province in which the sex offender’s main residence is located, unless a registration centre designated under paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> serves a class of persons of which the sex offender is a member or the area in which the unit of the Canadian Forces in which the sex offender is serving is located.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(2) of the Act is repealed and subsection 8(1) is renumbered as section 8.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 8(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(v) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>les lieu et date de la déclaration de culpabilité ou du verdict de non-responsabilité pour chacune des infractions,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 8:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Registration of information</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory receives a copy of an affidavit of service and a notice sent in accordance with subsection 490.021(6) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a person who registers information for the Attorney General or the minister of justice shall register without delay in the database only the following information relating to the person who was served with the notice:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>their given name and surname;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the number that identifies a record of fingerprints collected from them under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>, if such a record exists;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the date on which the notice was served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>every offence listed in the notice;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when and where the offence or offences were committed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when and where the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, the offence or offences;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the age and gender of every victim of the offence or offences, and the victim’s relationship to the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the expected duration of the person’s obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a person referred to in paragraph 490.02(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the date, if any, on which the person last reported under the Ontario Act and the duration of their obligation to comply with section 3 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory receives a notice referred to in subsection 490.016(3), 490.017(2), 490.027(3) or 490.029(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a person who registers information for the Attorney General or the minister of justice shall register without delay in the database the fact that a termination order was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who registers information for the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory may register in the database the fact that a person has applied in that jurisdiction for an exemption order under section 490.023 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>When the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory receives a notice referred to in section 490.025 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a person who registers information for the Attorney General or the minister of justice shall register without delay in the database the fact that the court refused to make an exemption order under subsection 490.023(2) of that Act or that the appeal court dismissed an appeal from such a decision or quashed an exemption order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who registers information for the Attorney General of a province or the minister of justice of a territory may register in the database the date on which the custodial portion of a sex offender’s sentence or detention in custody begins and the date of their release or discharge if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the sex offender was prosecuted in that jurisdiction for the offence to which the sentence or detention relates; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offence was not prosecuted under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidentiality and copy of information</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A person who registers information under this section shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ensure that the registration of the information is done in a manner and in circumstances that ensure its confidentiality; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>once the information is registered, on request, send the sex offender or the person served with a notice under section 490.021 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> a copy of all of the information relating to them that is registered in the database, by registered mail, free of charge and without delay.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Registration of information — Canadian Forces</MarginalNote><Label>8.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal receives a copy of an order sent in accordance with subparagraph 227.05(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)(iii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, a person who registers information for the Provost Marshal shall register without delay in the database only the following information relating to the person who is subject to the order:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>their given name and surname;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the number that identifies a record of fingerprints collected from them under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>, if such a record exists;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>every offence to which the order relates;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when and where the offence or offences were committed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when and where the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, the offence or offences;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the age and gender of every victim of the offence or offences, and the victim’s relationship to the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the date and duration of the order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information — Canadian Forces</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal receives a copy of an affidavit of service and a notice sent in accordance with subsection 227.08(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, a person who registers information for the Provost Marshal shall register without delay in the database only the following information relating to the person who was served with the notice:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>their given name and surname;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the number that identifies a record of fingerprints collected from them under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>, if such a record exists;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the date on which the notice was served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>every offence listed in the notice;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when and where the offence or offences were committed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when and where the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, the offence or offences;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the age and gender of every victim of the offence or offences, and the victim’s relationship to the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the expected duration of the person’s obligation under section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information — Canadian Forces</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>When the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal receives a notice referred to in subsection 227.04(3), 227.13(3) or 240.5(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, a person who registers information for the Provost Marshal shall register without delay in the database the fact that a termination order was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information — Canadian Forces</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person who registers information for the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal may register in the database the fact that a person has applied for an exemption order under section 227.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information — Canadian Forces</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>When the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal receives a notice referred to in section 227.11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, a person who registers information for the Provost Marshal shall register without delay in the database the fact that a court martial refused to make an exemption order under subsection 227.1(4) of that Act or that the Court Martial Appeal Court dismissed an appeal from such a decision or quashed an exemption order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information — Canadian Forces</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A person who registers information for the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal may register in the database the date on which the custodial portion of a sex offender’s sentence or detention in custody begins and the date of their release or discharge, if the sex offender was prosecuted under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> for the offence to which the sentence or detention relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information — Canadian Forces</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>A person who registers information for the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal shall register without delay in the database</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the fact that a person is the subject of a determination under subsection 227.15(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, the effect of the determination on the person, the date on which the suspension of the time limit, proceeding or obligation first applies and the date on which it ceases to apply;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the fact that a person is the subject of a determination under subsection 227.16(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and the date on which the determination was made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the fact that a person has become, or has ceased to be, subject to a regulation made under paragraph 227.2(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidentiality and copy of information</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>A person who registers information under this section shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ensure that the registration of the information is done in a manner and in circumstances that ensure its confidentiality; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>once the information is registered under any of subsections (2) to (7), on request, send the sex offender or the person served with a notice under section 227.08 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> a copy of all of the information relating to them that is registered in the database, by registered mail, free of charge and without delay.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 10(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall, subject to paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and any regulations made under paragraph 19(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), register without delay in the database only the information collected under sections 5 and 6, the date on which the sex offender reported or provided notification to the registration centre and the province of registration;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may register at any time in the database the number that identifies a record of fingerprints collected from a sex offender under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>, if such a record exists; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 11 of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Copie des renseignements</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Il incombe au préposé à la collecte au bureau d’inscription, sans frais pour le délinquant sexuel :</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>either give a copy of the information collected under section 5, dated and signed by the person who collected it, to the sex offender when they report to the registration centre in person and provide information under this Act, or send it to the sex offender by mail or another means agreed to by the sex offender, without delay after it is collected, if they report other than in person;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 12(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Request for correction of information</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), a sex offender or a person served with a notice under section 490.021 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.08 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> may, at any time, ask a person who collects information at the registration centre referred to in section 7.1 to correct any information relating to them that is registered in the database and that they believe contains an error or omission.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Request for correction of information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The request shall be made to the Canadian Forces Provost Marshal if the information is registered in the database under section 8.2.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 12(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Correction or notation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The person to whom the request is made shall, without delay, ensure that</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45.</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization for research</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police may authorize a person to consult information that is registered in the database, compare the information with other information or, by electronic means, combine the information with, or link it to, any other information contained in a computer system within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, for research or statistical purposes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall not provide the authorization unless the Commissioner</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is satisfied that those purposes cannot reasonably be accomplished without consulting the information or without comparing or combining the information with, or linking it to, the other information, as the case may be; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>obtains from the person a written undertaking that no subsequent disclosure of the information or of any information resulting from the comparison or combination of the information with, or the linking of the information to, other information will be made, or be allowed to be made, in a form that could reasonably be expected to identify any individual to whom it relates.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46.</Label><Text>Subsections 15(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permanent removal and destruction of information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, all information that is collected under this Act, or registered in the database, in connection with an order shall be destroyed and permanently removed from the database if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who is subject to the order is finally acquitted of every offence in connection with which the order was made or receives a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or under section 748 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> for every such offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the sentence for every offence in connection with which the order was made ceases to have force and effect under subsection 249.11(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permanent removal and destruction of information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, all information that is collected under this Act, or registered in the database, in connection with an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> shall be destroyed and permanently removed from the database if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who is subject to the obligation is finally acquitted of every offence to which it relates or receives a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or under section 748 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> for every such offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the sentence for every offence to which the obligation relates ceases to have force and effect under subsection 249.11(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who is subject to the obligation is granted an exemption order under subsection 490.023(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or subsection 227.1(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> or on an appeal from a decision made under that subsection.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who collects information at a registration centre designated under this Act in the province in which a sex offender’s main residence is located who consults the information to verify compliance by the sex offender with an order or orders or with an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic"><Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis></Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who collects information at a registration centre designated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> who consults the information to verify compliance by a sex offender who is subject to the Code of Service Discipline, or who is an officer, or non-commissioned member, of the primary reserve as defined in section 227 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, with an order or orders or with an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who collects or registers information who consults the information in order to exercise the functions or perform the duties assigned to them under this Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or a person authorized by the Commissioner who consults information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database in order to perform the duties of the Commissioner under this Act, under subsection 490.03(1) or (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or under subsection 227.18(1) or 227.19(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 16(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unauthorized comparison of information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall compare any information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database with any other information unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they compare information that was consulted in accordance with paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) with other information for the purpose of investigating a specific crime that there are reasonable grounds to suspect is of a sexual nature;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they compare information that was consulted in accordance with paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) with other information to verify compliance by the sex offender with one or more orders or with an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, or to investigate an offence under section 490.031 or 490.0311 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, an offence under either of those provisions that is punishable under section 130 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, or an offence under section 119.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they compare the information in accordance with an authorization under section 13.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unauthorized combination or linking of information</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>No person shall, by electronic means, combine any information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database with, or link it to, any other information contained in a computer system within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they combine the information that is registered in the database with, or link it to, information contained in the sex offender registry established under the Ontario Act, for the purpose of registering information under section 8, 8.1 or 10; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they combine or link information in accordance with an authorization under section 13.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 16(4) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Communication interdite</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Il est interdit à quiconque de communiquer ou laisser communiquer les renseignements recueillis au titre de la présente loi ou enregistrés dans la banque de données, ou le fait que des renseignements ont été recueillis ou enregistrés à l’égard d’une personne, à moins que la communication :</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 16(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is to the sex offender, or the person served with a notice under section 490.021 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or section 227.08 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, to whom the information relates;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is expressly authorized under this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is to a member or an employee of, or a person retained by, a police service and is necessary</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to enable them to investigate an offence under section 17 or to lay a charge for such an offence,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to enable them to investigate a specific crime that there are reasonable grounds to suspect is of a sexual nature, an offence under section 119.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, an offence under section 490.031 or 490.0311 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or an offence under either of those provisions that is punishable under section 130 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, or to lay a charge for such an offence, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to enable them to investigate a criminal offence or a service offence within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> or to lay a charge for such an offence, as long as the investigation or charge results from an investigation referred to in subparagraph (ii);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is to a prosecutor and is necessary to enable the prosecutor to determine whether a charge for an offence resulting from an investigation referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) should be laid;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is to a person who is responsible under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> for laying, referring or preferring a charge for a service offence and to a person who provides legal advice with respect to the charge, and the disclosure is necessary to enable them to determine whether a charge for a service offence resulting from an investigation referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) should be laid, referred or preferred;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is to a prosecutor, judge or justice in a proceeding relating to an application for a search warrant in connection with an investigation referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), and the information is relevant to the application;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is to a person who is authorized under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> to issue a search warrant in connection with the investigation of a service offence and to a person who provides legal advice with respect to the issuance of the search warrant, and the information is relevant to an application for a search warrant in connection with an investigation referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the information disclosed is relevant to the proceeding, appeal or review and the disclosure is</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to a prosecutor in connection with a proceeding that results from an investigation referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and that is before a court of criminal jurisdiction or superior court of criminal jurisdiction within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or a service tribunal within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to the Attorney General within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, or the Minister of National Defence or counsel instructed by the Minister, in connection with an appeal of a decision made in such a proceeding,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>to the court or service tribunal presiding over the proceeding or appeal and, in the case of a summary trial under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, to a person who provides legal advice to the presiding officer, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>to a review authority under section 249 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal> and to a person who provides legal advice to the review authority in connection with its review of a finding of guilty made or punishment imposed in the proceeding or appeal;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure to the person is necessary to assist an investigation of any act or omission referred to in subsection 7(4.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> by a police service in the state where the act or omission was committed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is to an employee of, or a person retained by, a person referred to in any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) who is authorized by that person to receive information disclosed under that paragraph on their behalf; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the disclosure is by a person who is authorized under section 13 to consult information that is registered in the database or to compare or combine that information with, or link it to, other information, the disclosure is for research or statistical purposes and it is not made, or allowed to be made, in a form that could reasonably be expected to identify any individual to whom it relates.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsection 16(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unauthorized use</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person shall use any information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database, or allow it to be used, for a purpose other than that for which it is consulted, compared, combined, linked or disclosed, as the case may be, under this section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48.</Label><Text>Subsection 17(1) of the Act is repealed and subsection 17(2) is renumbered as section 17.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49.</Label><Text>Paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the means by which designated classes of persons may report under section 4.1 or 4.3, or provide notification under section 6, to registration centres designated under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-47</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">CRIMINAL RECORDS ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10, s. 23</MarginalNote><Label>50.</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the pardon is subsequently revoked or ceases to have effect, requires the judicial record of the conviction to be kept separate and apart from other criminal records and removes any disqualification or obligation to which the person so convicted is, by reason of the conviction, subject by virtue of the provisions of any Act of Parliament, other than section 109, 110, 161, 259, 490.012 or 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or subsection 147.1(1) or section 227.01 or 227.06 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, or of a regulation made under an Act of Parliament.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 10</MarginalNote><Label>51.</Label><Text>If section 32 of this Act comes into force on or before December 15, 2006, then, on the day on which that section 32 comes into force</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 21.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> and the heading before it are repealed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 19:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>REVIEW AND REPORT TO PARLIAMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>19.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Two years after this Act comes into force, a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that is designated or established for the purpose shall undertake a comprehensive review of sections 1 to 19 of this Act, sections 490.011 to 490.032 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, sections 119.1 and 227 to 227.21, paragraphs 230(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and 230.1(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), section 230.2, subsection 232(3) and section 240.5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, and of the operation of those provisions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee shall submit a report on the review to Parliament, including a statement of any changes that it recommends, within six months after it undertakes the review or within any further time authorized by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 25</MarginalNote><Label>52.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If section 3 of this Act comes into force before section 30 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Criminal Code, the DNA Identification Act and the National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 25 of the Statutes of Canada, 2005 (the “other Act”), then, on the day on which that section 30 comes into force, subsection 202.14(1) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by that section 30, is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Verdict de non-responsabilité pour cause de troubles mentaux</MarginalNote><Label>202.14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>La cour martiale qui conclut que l’accusé a commis l’acte ou l’omission qui a donné lieu à l’accusation et que l’accusé était atteint, au moment de la perpétration de l’acte ou de l’omission, de troubles mentaux de nature à ne pas engager sa responsabilité doit rendre un verdict portant que l’accusé a commis l’acte ou l’omission mais n’est pas responsable pour cause de troubles mentaux.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 3 of this Act comes into force on the same day as section 30 of the other Act, then section 30 of the other Act is deemed to have come into force before section 3 of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>53.</Label><Text>This Act, other than sections 51 and 52, comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>