<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>C-31</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Export Development Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Export Development Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Export Development</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>33</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2001</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2001-12-18">90160</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal> by</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>changing the name of the Corporation to Export Development Canada and making consequential amendments to other Acts and to regulations;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enabling the Board to delegate its powers and duties to committees that it may establish, other than the executive committee;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring the Corporation, before entering into a transaction that is related to a project, to determine, in accordance with a directive established by the Board, whether the project is likely to have adverse environmental effects and, if such is the case, whether the Corporation is justified in entering into the transaction;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring the Auditor General to audit the design and implementation of the directive established by the Board, at least once every five years;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing that the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> cannot be made to apply to certain activities of the Corporation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing that an environmental assessment is not required under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> where the Minister for International Trade, the Minister of Finance or the Governor in Council exercise certain powers with respect to the Corporation; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enabling the Board to make by-laws respecting the establishment of a pension plan for the officers and employees of the Corporation and their dependants.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-20</MarginalNote><TitleText>EXPORT DEVELOPMENT ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 26, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>The long title of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><LongTitle>An Act to establish Export Development Canada and to support and develop trade between Canada and other countries and Canada’s competitiveness in the international market-place</LongTitle></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 1 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Titre abrégé</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur le développement des exportations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Chairman</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Vice-Chairman</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the English version of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Corporation</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Corporation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote> <DefinedTermFr>Société</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Corporation</DefinedTermEn> means Export Development Canada, the corporation established by section 3;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the English version of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Chairperson</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinitionEnOnly>Version anglaise seulement</DefinitionEnOnly></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Chairperson</DefinedTermEn> means the Chairperson of the Board;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Vice-chairperson</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinitionEnOnly>Version anglaise seulement</DefinitionEnOnly></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Vice-chairperson</DefinedTermEn> means the Vice-chairperson of the Board.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Corporation established</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>A corporation is hereby established, to be known as Export Development Canada, consisting of a Board of Directors composed of fifteen directors, including a Chairperson and a President.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>The heading before section 7 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading><TitleText>COMMITTEES OF THE BOARD</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 7:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Other committees</MarginalNote><Label>7.1</Label><Text>The Board may establish any other committee and that committee may exercise any powers and perform any duties of the Board delegated to it by the Board.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Subsection 8(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Management of Corporation vested in President</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President is the chief executive officer of the Corporation and has on behalf of the Board the direction and management of the business of the Corporation, with authority to act in the conduct of the business of the Corporation in all matters that are not by this Act or the by-laws of the Corporation specifically reserved to the Board or any committee of the Board.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 26, s. 4(2)</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>Subsection 10(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit of liability</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3.1) and (4), the contingent liability of the Corporation in respect of the principal amount owing under all outstanding arrangements entered into under paragraph (1.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) shall at no time exceed the greater of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an amount equal to ten times the authorized capital of the Corporation, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>seventeen billion, five hundred million dollars.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appropriation Act</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>The amount referred to in paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) may be varied in an appropriation Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 10:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ENVIRONMENTAL EFFECTS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Requirement</MarginalNote><Label>10.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before entering, in the exercise of its powers under subsection 10(1.1), into a transaction that is related to a project, the Corporation must determine, in accordance with the directive referred to in subsection (2),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether the project is likely to have adverse environmental effects despite the implementation of mitigation measures; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if such is the case, whether the Corporation is justified in entering into the transaction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directive</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Board shall issue a directive respecting the determination referred to in subsection (1), which directive may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>define the words and expressions that the Board considers necessary for the application of that subsection, including the words and expressions “transaction”, “project”, “adverse environmental effects” and “mitigation measures”;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establish the criteria that the Corporation must apply in making the determination; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establish exceptions specifically or by any class, as defined by the Board, to the Corporation’s obligation to make the determination.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The directive is not a statutory instrument for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the regulation of its proceedings, including the delegation of any of its powers and duties to any committee of the Board and the fixing of quorums for meetings of the Board and any committee of the Board;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>delegating, subject to any terms and conditions specified in the by-laws and despite any delegation of such authority to any committee of the Board, to any one or more officers of the Corporation, jointly or severally, any authority to authorize the Corporation to exercise a power under this Act that is given specifically to the Board by any provision of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the establishment, management and administration of a pension plan for the officers and employees of the Corporation and their dependants,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the contributions to be made by the Corporation to the associated pension fund,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the provision of benefits under the pension plan,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the payment of pensions, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the investment of the assets of the fund; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>Section 21 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 21(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report re directive</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As auditor of the Corporation, the Auditor General must, at least once every five years, audit the design and the implementation of the directive referred to in subsection 10.1(2) and submit a report on the audit to the Board and to the Minister. The Auditor General must submit the report to each House of Parliament on any of the first thirty days on which it is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 24:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal>: s. 5(1)</MarginalNote><Label>24.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> does not apply where the Minister or the Minister of Finance exercises a power or performs a duty or function under this Act or any regulation made under it, or exercises a power of authorization or approval with respect to the Corporation under any other Act of Parliament or any regulation made under it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsection 5(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> does not apply where the Governor in Council exercises a power of authorization or approval under regulations made under this Act, or where the Governor in Council exercises a power of authorization or approval with respect to the Corporation under any other Act of Parliament or regulations made under it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsection 8(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the Corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Use of Corporation’s name or initials</MarginalNote><Label>24.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except with the written consent of the Corporation, no person shall in any prospectus or advertisement, or for any other business purpose, use the following names and initials: “Export Development Canada”, “Exportation et développement Canada”, “Export Development Corporation”, “Société pour l’expansion des exportations”, “E.D.C.”, “EDC”, “S.E.E.” and “SEE”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who contravenes subsection (1) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or to both.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacing “Chairman” and “Vice-Chairman” with “Chairperson” and “Vice-chairperson”</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>The English version of the Act is amended by replacing the words “Chairman” and “Vice-Chairman” with the words “Chairperson” and “Vice-chairperson”, respectively, wherever they occur in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 4;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 6;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 7(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 9(2).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>Wherever, under any Act of Parliament, any instrument made under an Act of Parliament or any contract, lease, licence or other document, a power, duty or function is vested in or exercisable by the Export Development Corporation, that power, duty or function is vested in or exercisable by Export Development Canada.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>Every reference to the Export Development Corporation in any deed, contract or other document executed by the Export Development Corporation in its own name shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be read as a reference to Export Development Canada.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations transferred</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Text>All rights and property of the Export Development Corporation, rights and property held in its name or held in trust for it and all its obligations and liabilities are deemed to be rights, property, obligations and liabilities of Export Development Canada.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of legal proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Text>Any legal proceeding to which the Export Development Corporation is party pending in any court immediately before the day on which this section comes into force may be continued by or against Export Development Canada in the same manner and to the same extent as it could have been continued by or against the Export Development Corporation.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. B-7; R.S., c. 24 (1st Supp.), s. 3</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bretton Woods and Related Agreements Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 21, s. 130</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 8.3(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bretton Woods and Related Agreements Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Export Development Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Export Development Canada may, on the request of the Minister of Finance, act as agent of the Minister of Finance for the purpose of providing financial assistance to any foreign state under this section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 21, s. 130</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 8.3(8)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to compensate Export Development Canada for its services as agent of the Minister of Finance under subsection (7) in accordance with any agreement between Export Development Canada and the Minister of Finance.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-8; 1995, c. 17, s. 45(1)</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Corporation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Société pour l’expansion des exportations</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote /><Label>20.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Exportation et développement Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule III to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Corporation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Société pour l’expansion des exportations</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule III to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Exportation et développement Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. M-13; 2000, c. 8, s. 2</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>Schedule IV to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Corporation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Société pour l’expansion des exportations</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Schedule IV to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Exportation et développement Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Text>The schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Corporation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Société pour l’expansion des exportations</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Exportation et développement Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-36</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>SOR/2000-168</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>Part III of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Corporation</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Société pour l’expansion des exportations</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28.</Label><Text>Part III of Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Export Development Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Exportation et développement Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Other Federal Acts</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, every reference to “Export Development Corporation” is replaced by a reference to “Export Development Canada” in any other Act of Parliament, with any grammatical modifications that are required.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Regulations and Other Instruments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, every reference to “Export Development Corporation” is replaced by a reference to “Export Development Canada”, and every reference to “Société pour l’expansion des exportations” is replaced by a reference to “Exportation et développement Canada”, with any grammatical modifications or changes in order that are required, in regulations, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>, and in any other instrument made in execution of a power conferred by or under an Act of Parliament or by or under the authority of the Governor in Council, and more particularly in the following provisions with the changes indicated:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>clause (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)(i)(E) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>specified international finance trust</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 5000(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Income Tax Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Designation of Certain Portions of the Public Service Order</XRefExternal>, with the French version of that reference being placed in alphabetical order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Public Service Superannuation Regulations</XRefExternal>, with the French version of that reference being placed in alphabetical order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>item 41 of the schedule to the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Privacy Act Heads of Government Institutions Designation Order</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>item 108 of the schedule to the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Privacy Act Heads of Government Institutions Designation Order</XRefExternal>, with that item being renumbered and placed as item 79.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>item 42 of the schedule to the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act Deputy Heads of the Public Service of Canada Order</XRefExternal>, made by Order in Council P.C. 1993-1073 of May 25, 1993 and registered as SI/93-81;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>item 110 of the schedule to the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act Deputy Heads of the Public Service of Canada Order</XRefExternal>, made by Order in Council P.C. 1993-1073 of May 25, 1993 and registered as SI/93-81, with that item being renumbered and placed as item 75.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of Order in Council P.C. 1993-1454 made on June 25, 1993 and registered as SI/93-108;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the long title and section 1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Export Development Corporation Exercise of Certain Powers Regulations</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 13(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Crown Corporation General Regulations, 1995</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31.</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, every reference to “Loi sur l’expansion des exportations” is replaced by a reference to “Loi sur le développement des exportations” in the French version of regulations, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>, made under any Act of Parliament and more particularly in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of Order in Council P.C. 1993-1454 made on June 25, 1993 and registered as SI/93-108; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>Loi</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Export Development Canada Exercise of Certain Powers Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>