<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-9</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Elections Act and the Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Canada Elections Act and the Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canada Elections</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>21</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2001</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2001-6-14">90130</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> with respect to the information included on ballots. It also clarifies and harmonizes certain provisions of that Act and makes a related amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 9</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA ELECTIONS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>political affiliation</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>political affiliation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>appartenance politique</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>political affiliation</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a candidate, means the name of the political party that has endorsed him or her or the word “independent”, as the case may be, included in the nomination paper in accordance with subparagraph 66(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(v).</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(v) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>election documents</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>a packet containing the list of electors used at the polling station, the written authorizations of candidates’ representatives and the used transfer certificates, if any, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 18.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Electronic voting process</MarginalNote><Label>18.1</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer may carry out studies on voting, including studies respecting alternative voting means, and may devise and test an electronic voting process for future use in a general election or a by-election. Such a process may not be used for an official vote without the prior approval of the committees of the Senate and of the House of Commons that normally consider electoral matters.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Paragraph 32(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a registration officer for each registration desk.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 44(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of Register</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Register of Electors shall contain, for each elector who is included in it, his or her surname, given names, sex, date of birth, civic address, mailing address and any other information that is provided under subsections 49(2), 194(7), 195(7), 223(2), 233(2) and 251(3).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Subsection 57(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>General election — proclamation</MarginalNote><Label>57.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall issue a proclamation in order for a general election to be held.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>By-election — order</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall make an order in order for a by-election to be held.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>The proclamation or order shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct the Chief Electoral Officer to issue a writ to the returning officer for each electoral district to which the proclamation or order applies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fix the date of issue of the writ; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fix the date for voting at the election, which date must be at least 36 days after the issue of the writ.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Section 58 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Writs forwarded to returning officer</MarginalNote><Label>58.</Label><Text>The Chief Electoral Officer shall issue a writ in Form 1 of Schedule 1 to the returning officer for the electoral district in which the election is to be held without delay after the proclamation is issued or the order is made by the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 66(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(v) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the name of the political party that has endorsed the prospective candidate or, if none, the prospective candidate’s choice to either have the word “independent” or no designation of political affiliation under his or her name in election documents;</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Paragraph 67(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if applicable, an instrument in writing, signed by the leader of the political party or by a person referred to in subsection 383(2), that states that the prospective candidate is endorsed by the party in accordance with section 68.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Section 68 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Party may endorse only one candidate per district</MarginalNote><Label>68.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A political party may endorse only one prospective candidate in each electoral district for a given election.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>New endorsement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, with respect to a particular electoral district, a candidate who has been endorsed by a political party dies before 2:00 p.m. on the 5th day before the closing day for nominations or withdraws in accordance with subsection 74(1), the party may endorse another candidate in that electoral district before the close of nominations.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>Section 91 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Publishing false statements to affect election results</MarginalNote><Label>91.</Label><Text>No person shall, with the intention of affecting the results of an election, knowingly make or publish any false statement of fact in relation to the personal character or conduct of a candidate or prospective candidate.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>Subsection 109(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extra copies</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the request of a registered party or member referred to in subsection (2), the Chief Electoral Officer may provide a maximum of four additional printed copies of the final lists of electors.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>Subsections 117(2) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Name of party</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The name, in the form referred to in paragraph 366(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), of the political party that has endorsed the candidate shall be listed on the ballot under the name of the candidate if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the candidate’s nomination paper includes it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the condition described in paragraph 67(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) is met;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at the close of nominations, the party is in compliance with sections 366 and 368; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the party has candidates whose nominations have been confirmed in at least 12 electoral districts for the general election or, in the case of a by-election, in the immediately preceding general election.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation of candidate as independent</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The word “independent” shall be listed on the ballot under the name of the candidate who has requested it in accordance with subparagraph 66(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(v) and may not be so listed in any other case.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>Section 165 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — use of loudspeakers on polling day</MarginalNote><Label>165.</Label><Text>No person shall use a loudspeaking device within hearing distance of a polling station on polling day for the purpose of promoting or opposing a political party that is listed on the ballot under the name of a candidate or the election of a candidate.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 166(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>post or display in, or on the exterior surface of, a polling place any campaign literature or other material that could be taken as an indication of support for or opposition to a political party that is listed on the ballot under the name of a candidate or the election of a candidate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>while in a polling station, wear any emblem, flag, banner or other thing that indicates that the person supports or opposes any candidate or political party that is listed on the ballot under the name of a candidate, or the political or other opinions entertained, or supposed to be entertained, by the candidate or party; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 166(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), a representative of a candidate in a polling station may, in the manner authorized by the Chief Electoral Officer, wear a badge identifying his or her function and the name of the political party that is listed on the ballot under the name of the candidate.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>Subsection 279(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Political affiliation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The deputy returning officer shall not reject a special ballot for the sole reason that the elector has written, in addition to the name of a candidate, the candidate’s political affiliation, if the ballot clearly indicates the elector’s intent.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Text>Paragraph 324(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the transmission of a message that was transmitted to the public on what is commonly known as the Internet before the blackout period described in that subsection and that was not changed during that period; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>Subsection 335(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Broadcasting time to be provided to registered parties</MarginalNote><Label>335.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the period beginning on the issue of the writs for a general election and ending at midnight on the day before polling day, every broadcaster shall, subject to the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal> and the conditions of its licence, make available, for purchase by all registered parties for the transmission of political announcements and other programming produced by or on behalf of the registered parties, six and one-half hours of broadcasting time during prime time on its facilities.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 345(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Free broadcasting time</MarginalNote><Label>345.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the period beginning on the issue of the writs for a general election and ending at midnight on the day before polling day at that election, every network operator shall, subject to the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal> and to the conditions of its licence, make available, at no cost, to the registered parties and eligible parties referred to in subsection (2), for the transmission of political announcements and other programming produced by or on behalf of those parties, broadcasting time as determined under that subsection if the network formed and operated by the network operator</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Text>Paragraph 348(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a rate for broadcasting time made available to the party or candidate, in the period beginning on the issue of the writs and ending at midnight on the day before polling day, that exceeds the lowest rate charged by the person for an equal amount of equivalent time on the same facilities made available to any other person at any time within that period; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 359(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Election advertising report</MarginalNote><Label>359.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every third party that is required to be registered in accordance with subsection 353(1) shall file an election advertising report in the prescribed form with the Chief Electoral Officer within four months after polling day.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 359(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a list of all election advertising expenses other than those referred to in subparagraph (i) and the time and place of broadcast or publication of the advertisements to which the expenses relate; and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 359(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a by-election, a list of election advertising expenses referred to in subsection 350(4) and the time and place of the broadcast or publication of the advertisements to which the expenses relate.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Subparagraphs 403(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) and (ii) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a statement, prepared in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles, of its assets and liabilities, including any surplus or deficit, at the date of the merger,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an auditor’s report, submitted to the chief agent of the merged party, as to whether the statement presents fairly and in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles the information on which it was based, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Section 441 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Base amount of candidate’s election expenses</MarginalNote><Label>441.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The base amount of a candidate’s election expenses in an electoral district is the higher of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount calculated, on the basis of the preliminary lists of electors for the electoral district, in accordance with subsections (3) to (6), and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount calculated, on the basis of the revised lists of electors for the electoral district, in accordance with subsections (7) to (10).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Death of candidate of registered party</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a candidate for an electoral district whose nomination was endorsed by a registered party dies in the period beginning at 2:00 p.m. on the 5th day before the closing day for nominations and ending on polling day, the base amount for that electoral district is increased by 50 %.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Calculation using preliminary lists of electors</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The amount referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is the aggregate of the following amounts, based on the number of the electors on the preliminary lists of electors:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$2.07 for each of the first 15,000 electors;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$1.04 for each of the next 10,000 electors; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.52 for each of the remaining electors.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fewer electors than average — general election</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the number of electors on the preliminary lists of electors for the electoral district is less than the average number of electors on all preliminary lists of electors in a general election, then, in making a calculation under subsection (3), the number of electors is deemed to be half-way between the number on the preliminary lists of electors for the electoral district and that average number.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fewer electors than average — by-election</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In the case of a by-election, if the number of electors on the preliminary lists of electors for the electoral district is less than the average number of electors on all revised lists of electors in the immediately preceding general election, then, in making a calculation under subsection (3), the number of electors is deemed to be half-way between the number on the preliminary lists of electors for the electoral district and that average number.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Districts with lower population density</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the number of electors per square kilometre, calculated on the basis of the preliminary lists of electors for the electoral district, is less than 10, the amount calculated under subsection (3) is increased by the lesser of $0.31 per square kilometre and 25 % of that amount.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Calculation using revised list of electors</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The amount referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is the aggregate of the following amounts, based on the number of the electors on the revised lists of electors:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$2.07 for each of the first 15,000 electors;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$1.04 for each of the next 10,000 electors; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.52 for each of the remaining electors.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fewer electors than average — general election</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If the number of electors on the revised lists of electors for the electoral district is less than the average number of electors on all revised lists of electors in a general election, then, in making a calculation under subsection (7), the number of electors is deemed to be half-way between the number on the revised lists of electors for the electoral district and that average number.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fewer electors than average — by-election</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>In the case of a by-election, if the number of electors on the revised lists of electors for the electoral district is less than the average number of electors on all revised lists of electors in the immediately preceding general election, then, in making a calculation under subsection (7), the number of electors is deemed to be half-way between the number on the revised lists of electors for the electoral district and that average number.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Districts with lower population density</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>If the number of electors per square kilometre, calculated on the basis of the revised lists of electors for the electoral district, is less than 10, the amount calculated under subsection (7) is increased by the lesser of $0.31 per square kilometre and 25 % of that amount.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>Section 467 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Honoraires du vérificateur</MarginalNote><Label>467.</Label><Text>Sur réception du certificat visé à l’article 465 ou de l’attestation de conformité visée à l’article 466, le receveur général paie au vérificateur, sur le Trésor, une somme au titre des honoraires que celui-ci a facturés, non inférieure à 250 $, représentant 3 % des dépenses électorales du candidat, jusqu’à concurrence de 1 500 $.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Section 504 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial proceedings and compliance agreements</MarginalNote><Label>504.</Label><Text>In the case of judicial proceedings or a compliance agreement involving an eligible party, a registered party or a suspended party,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the eligible party, registered party or suspended party is deemed to be a person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any act or thing done or omitted to be done by an officer, a chief agent or other registered agent of the eligible party, registered party or suspended party, within the scope of their authority to act, is deemed to be an act or thing done or omitted to be done by the eligible party, registered party or suspended party, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Text>Subsection 517(7) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Renegotiation</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Commissioner and the contracting party may renegotiate the terms of the compliance agreement at the request of the Commissioner or contracting party at any time before it is fully executed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>Section 558 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Electoral campaign return of candidate</MarginalNote><Label>558.</Label><Text>For contributions made before September 1, 2000, the official agent shall include in the electoral campaign return in respect of a candidate the information referred to in paragraphs 451(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>), other than the addresses of the contributors.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-3</MarginalNote><TitleText>ELECTORAL BOUNDARIES READJUSTMENT ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>Subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties of the commissions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The ten commissions established pursuant to subsection (1) shall consider and report on the readjustment of the representation of the provinces in the House of Commons required to be made on the completion of each decennial census.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>