<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-26</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Customs Act, the Customs Tariff, the Excise Act, the Excise Tax Act and the Income Tax Act in respect of tobacco</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Tobacco Tax Amendments Act, 2001</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Tobacco Tax, 2001</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>16</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2001</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2001-6-14">90152</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment implements tobacco tax measures announced by the Minister of Finance on April 5, 2001 as part of the government’s initiative to reduce tobacco consumption in Canada, especially among youth. It also implements a measure proposed in Budget 2000 reducing the exemption threshold under the tax on exports of tobacco products before April 6, 2001.</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>The amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act,</XRefExternal> the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> announced on April 5, 2001 implement new tax measures with respect to domestic tobacco tax rates, exports of tobacco products, tobacco products sold in duty free shops or as ships’ stores, and tobacco products imported by resident travellers, as well as changes to the surtax on tobacco manufacturing profits.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Tobacco Excise Tax Rate Increases.</Emphasis> The amendments increase excise tax rates by $2.00 per carton on cigarettes for sale in Ontario and Quebec, $1.35 per carton in Prince Edward Island, 30 cents per carton in New Brunswick and 10 cents per carton in Nova Scotia. The amendments increase excise taxes on tobacco sticks by $1.00 per 200 sticks nation-wide, and on manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks by $2.80 per 200 grams on products for sale in Ontario and by $1.00 per 200 grams on products for sale in other provinces and the territories. These tax increases are effective April 6, 2001.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Tax on Exports of Tobacco Products.</Emphasis> This enactment implements the Budget 2000 proposal to reduce the exemption threshold under the tax on exports of tobacco products before April 6, 2001 from 2.5% to 1.5% of a manufacturer’s production of tobacco products in the previous calendar year.</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>The amendments also implement the April 5, 2001 proposal to impose a new two-tiered tax on exports of tobacco products. For exports up to 1.5% of a manufacturer’s production in the preceding calendar year, a new excise tax is imposed at a rate of $10 per carton for cigarettes, $7 per 200 sticks for tobacco sticks, and $6 per 200 grams for manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks. The amendments authorize the Minister of National Revenue to refund this tax where the importer provides evidence satisfactory to the Minister that all taxes and duties imposed at the national level under the laws of the foreign country into which the tobacco products are imported have been paid.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>For exports over 1.5% of a manufacturer’s production in the preceding calendar year, the amendments impose the current excise duty on tobacco products plus a new excise tax. The sum of the excise duty and excise tax is $22 per carton for cigarettes, $16 per 200 sticks for tobacco sticks, and $12 per 200 grams for manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>The amendments related to the new two-tiered export tax are effective April 6, 2001.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Tax on Tobacco Products for Sale in Duty Free Shops.</Emphasis> The amendments impose excise duty and a new excise tax on Canadian-manufactured tobacco products delivered to duty free shops in Canada, or exported for delivery to foreign duty free shops, payable by the domestic manufacturer. The sum of excise duty and excise tax is $10 per carton for cigarettes, $7 per 200 sticks for tobacco sticks, and $6 per 200 grams for manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks. The amendments also impose an equivalent excise tax on imported tobacco products delivered to a duty free shop in Canada, payable by the operator of the duty free shop. The tax on imported tobacco products will be refunded on the first carton or equivalent of each product category sold to an individual who is not a resident of Canada and who exports the product. These measures are effective April 6, 2001.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Tax on Tobacco Products Delivered as Ships’ Stores.</Emphasis> The amendments impose excise duty and a new excise tax on Canadian-manufactured tobacco products delivered as ships’ stores in Canada, or exported for delivery as foreign ships’ stores, payable by the domestic manufacturer. The sum of excise duty and tax is $10 per carton for cigarettes, $7 per 200 sticks for tobacco sticks, and $6 per 200 grams for manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks. These measures are effective April 6, 2001.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Duty on Traveller’s Tobacco Products.</Emphasis> The amendments impose a new duty under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> on manufactured tobacco products imported by a resident of Canada under the terms of the traveller’s allowance. The new duty is imposed at a rate of $10 per carton for cigarettes, $7 per 200 sticks for tobacco sticks, and $6 per 200 grams for manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks. This duty will not be imposed on tobacco products imported by an individual for personal use that are stamped in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> and on which excise duty has been imposed under that Act. These amendments are effective October 1, 2001.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Tobacco Manufacturers’ Surtax.</Emphasis> The amendment increases the rate of the existing surtax imposed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> on a corporation’s tax on profits from tobacco manufacturing. The rate increase is from 40% to 50% for taxation years ending after April 5, 2001, and is prorated for any taxation year straddling that date.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text><Emphasis style="bold">Miscellaneous Amendments.</Emphasis> This enactment also implements a number of related and consequential measures, including provisions related to the application of interest in respect of taxes or duties amended or implemented by this enactment, new restrictions on the entry of tobacco products into bonding warehouses, and on their subsequent removal, and new stamping requirements and new offence and penalty provisions.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tobacco Tax Amendments Act, 2001</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>CUSTOMS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 70(1)</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 24(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>as a duty free shop for the sale of goods free of certain duties or taxes levied on goods under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or any other law relating to customs, to persons who are about to leave Canada</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36</MarginalNote><TitleText>CUSTOMS TARIFF</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 21(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty on tobacco imported by traveller</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>There shall be levied on traveller’s tobacco, at the time of its importation, and paid in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, a duty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.05 per cigarette, in the case of cigarettes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.035 per stick, in the case of tobacco sticks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.03 per gram, in the case of manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — excise duty-paid manufactured tobacco</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A duty shall not be levied under this section on manufactured tobacco imported by an individual for their personal use if it is stamped in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> and duty has been imposed on it under section 200 of that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>goods subject to excise</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>marchandises assujetties à l’accise</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>goods subject to excise</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>beer or malt liquor, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, of heading No. 22.03 or of tariff item No. 2202.90.10 or 2206.00.80;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>spirits, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, of an alcoholic strength by volume exceeding 22.9% volume, of tariff item No. 2204.21.32, 2204.29.32, 2205.10.30, 2205.90.30, 2206.00.22, 2206.00.72 or 2206.00.92;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>spirits, within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, of heading No. 22.07 or 22.08, other than of tariff item No. 2207.20.11, 2207.20.90, 2208.90.30 or 2208.90.91;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>cigars or manufactured tobacco of tariff item No. 2402.10.00, 2402.20.00, 2403.10.00, 2403.91.90, 2403.99.10 or 2403.99.90; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>goods referred to in any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) that are classified with the container in which they are imported.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>traveller’s tobacco</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>tabac du voyageur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>traveller’s tobacco</DefinedTermEn> means manufactured tobacco that is imported by a person at any time and</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is classified under tariff item No. 9804.10.00, 9804.20.00, 9805.00.00 or 9807.00.00; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>would be classified under tariff item No. 9804.10.00 or 9804.20.00 but for the fact that the total value for duty as determined under section 46 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> of all goods imported by the person at that time exceeds the maximum value specified in that tariff item.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001, except that subsection 21(2) of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1), does not apply to tobacco imported before October 1, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 83(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of goods that would have been classified under tariff item No. 9804.10.00 or 9804.20.00, the value for duty of the goods shall be reduced by an amount equal to that maximum specified value and, in the case of alcoholic beverages and tobacco, the quantity of those goods shall, for the purposes of assessing duties other than a duty under subsection 21(2), be reduced by the quantity of alcoholic beverages and tobacco up to the maximum quantities specified in tariff item No. 9804.10.00 or 9804.20.00, as the case may be;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) comes into force or is deemed to have come into force on October 1, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 92 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application to Canadian manufactured tobacco</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>This section does not apply to any tax imposed under Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, or any duty imposed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, in respect of manufactured tobacco that is manufactured or produced in Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001, except that subsection 92(3) of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1), does not apply to manufactured tobacco entered into a bonding warehouse before that day.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Note 4 to Chapter 98 of the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="1.5"><Label>4.</Label><Text>For the purpose of this Chapter, <DefinedTermEn>duties</DefinedTermEn> means duties or taxes levied or imposed on imported goods under Part 2 of the Act (other than subsection 21(2)), the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or any other Act of Parliament relating to customs.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) comes into force or is deemed to have come into force on October 1, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-14</MarginalNote><TitleText>EXCISE ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 32(1); 1999, c. 17, par. 144(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>cigar stamp</DefinedTermEn> in section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>cigar stamp</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>estampille de cigares</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>cigar stamp</DefinedTermEn> means any stamp required by this Act and the ministerial regulations to be affixed to a cigar, or a package, carton, box, crate or other container containing cigars, entered for consumption or imported into Canada, to indicate</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 37, s. 2; 1999, c. 17, par. 144(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>tobacco stamp</DefinedTermEn> in section 6 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>tobacco stamp</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>estampille de tabac</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>tobacco stamp</DefinedTermEn> means any stamp required by this Act and the ministerial regulations to be impressed on, printed on, marked on, indented into or affixed to a cigarette, or a package, carton, box, crate or other container containing manufactured tobacco, entered for consumption or imported into Canada, or to be affixed to Canadian raw leaf tobacco entered for consumption, to indicate</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>foreign duty free shop</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>boutique hors taxes à l’étranger</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign duty free shop</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>foreign ships’ stores</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>provisions de bord à l’étranger </DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign ships’ stores</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (3) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 52:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation on entry of tobacco into bonding warehouse</MarginalNote><Label>52.1</Label><Text>Manufactured tobacco shall not be entered into a bonding warehouse if it is intended to be removed for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>delivery to a duty free shop licensed as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>export for delivery to a foreign duty free shop;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>export for delivery as foreign ships’ stores;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>entry into a bonded warehouse, licensed as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>delivery as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 7 (2nd Supp.), s. 63(1); 1993, c. 25, s. 37; 1995, c. 41, s. 109; 1999, c. 17, par. 144(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 58 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer of goods other than cigars and manufactured tobacco in bond</MarginalNote><Label>58.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Goods, other than cigars and manufactured tobacco, warehoused under this Act may, without payment of duty, be transferred or removed from one bonding warehouse to another in bond, exported in bond or released from bond to accredited representatives for their personal or official use, if the transfer, removal, exportation or release is in accordance with the regulations and the ministerial regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal to customs bonded warehouse or duty free shop</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Goods subject to excise, other than cigars and manufactured tobacco, may, without payment of duty, be removed from a bonding warehouse</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to a bonded warehouse, licensed as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, if the goods are</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>designated for delivery as ships’ stores,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for sale to accredited representatives for their personal or official use, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>for export; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to a duty free shop, licensed as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, if the goods are for sale to persons who are about to leave Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delivery and sale to be in accordance with regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Goods removed under subsection (2) shall be delivered and sold in accordance with any ministerial regulations that apply.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>58.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>foreign brand tobacco</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>tabac de marque étrangère</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign brand tobacco</DefinedTermEn> means tobacco in respect of which the excise tax imposed under section 23.13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> is not payable because of section 23.3 of that Act.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>manufactured tobacco</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>tabac fabriqué</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>manufactured tobacco</DefinedTermEn> does not include partially manufactured tobacco or foreign brand tobacco.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>partially manufactured tobacco</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>tabac partiellement fabriqué</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>partially manufactured tobacco</DefinedTermEn> means a tobacco product made by a tobacco manufacturer that is cut filler or cut rag or that is manufactured less fully than cut filler or cut rag.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Categories of manufactured tobacco</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (4), each of the following constitutes a category of manufactured tobacco:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>cigarettes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>tobacco sticks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of manufactured tobacco in bond</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Manufactured tobacco may, without payment of duty, be removed from a bonding warehouse only if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>removed by its manufacturer and exported in bond in accordance with subsection (4) and not for delivery to a foreign duty free shop or as foreign ships’ stores,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>removed by its manufacturer and entered into another bonding warehouse in bond, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>released to accredited representatives for their personal or official use; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the removal and exportation, entry or release, as the case may be, are in accordance with the regulations and the ministerial regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum quantity permitted to be exported in bond</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A tobacco manufacturer shall not, at a particular time in a calendar year, remove a particular quantity of a category of manufactured tobacco from the manufacturer’s bonding warehouse for export in bond if the total quantity of that category of manufactured tobacco removed in the year up to that time by the manufacturer from a bonding warehouse for export in bond, plus the particular quantity, exceeds 1.5% of the total quantity of manufactured tobacco of that category manufactured by the manufacturer in the preceding calendar year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Quantities to be excluded for the purpose of subsection (4)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The total quantities referred to in subsection (4) shall not include any quantity of manufactured tobacco that was exported by the manufacturer for delivery to a foreign duty free shop or as foreign ships’ stores.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of cigars in bond</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Cigars may, without payment of duty, be removed from a bonding warehouse only if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they are</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>removed by their manufacturer and</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>exported in bond,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>entered into another bonding warehouse in bond,</Text></Clause><?Pub _bookmark Command="[Quick Mark]"?><Clause><Label>(C)</Label><Text>entered into a bonded warehouse, licensed as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, if the person entering the cigars into the bonded warehouse certifies to the manufacturer that they are for delivery as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(D)</Label><Text>transferred to a duty free shop, licensed as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, if the operator of the duty free shop certifies to the manufacturer that the cigars are for sale to persons who are about to leave Canada, or</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(E)</Label><Text>delivered as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>released to accredited representatives for their personal or official use; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the removal and export, entry, transfer, sale, delivery or release, as the case may be, are in accordance with the regulations and the ministerial regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of partially manufactured tobacco or foreign brand tobacco in bond</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Partially manufactured tobacco or foreign brand tobacco may, without payment of duty, be removed by its manufacturer from a bonding warehouse only if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is entered into another bonding warehouse in bond or exported in bond and not for delivery to a foreign duty free shop or as foreign ships’ stores; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the removal and entry or export, as the case may be, are in accordance with the regulations and the ministerial regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Diversion</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>A person who has acquired goods that are manufactured tobacco, foreign brand tobacco or cigars is liable to pay the duty that would have been payable on the goods at the time the goods were completely manufactured, if the goods</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>have been relieved, under this Act or otherwise, from the duty because of the purpose for which the person acquired them;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>are removed from a bonded warehouse licensed as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, sold or used by the person for another purpose; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>would not have been relieved from the duty if the person had acquired them for the other purpose.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty payable at time of acquisition</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The duty a person is liable to pay under subsection (8) on goods is deemed to have become payable by the person at the time the person acquired the goods.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001, except that</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 58(1), (3) and (4) of the Act, as they read immediately before that day, apply to manufactured tobacco (as defined in section 6 of the Act) entered into a bonding warehouse before that day and are subject to subsection 58.1(4) of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 58.1(3) and (7) of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1), do not apply to tobacco entered into a bonding warehouse before that day; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 58.1(4) of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1), does not apply to tobacco exported for delivery to a foreign duty free shop or as foreign ships’ stores if it had been entered into a bonding warehouse before that day.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 102:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Penalty for removal from bonding warehouse for certain exports</MarginalNote><Label>102.1</Label><Text>Every person who removes from a bonding warehouse and exports in bond manufactured tobacco (as defined in subsection 58.1(1)) otherwise than in accordance with subparagraph 58.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) and paragraph 58.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is liable to pay, in addition to any duties or taxes that are payable under this or any other Act in respect of the tobacco, a penalty equal to the total of those duties and taxes, and that penalty becomes payable at the time the tobacco is exported.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 12 (4th Supp.), s. 61</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 110.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Penalty and interest</MarginalNote><Label>110.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), on default in payment of any duty or penalty payable under this Act within the time prescribed by this Act or the regulations, the person liable to pay that duty or penalty shall pay without delay, in addition to the amount in default,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 40; 1994, c. 37, s. 5(F); 1999, c. 17, par. 144(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">z.7</Emphasis>)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>Subsections 201(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Packaging and stamping of manufactured tobacco and cigars manufactured in Canada</MarginalNote><Label>201.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before manufactured tobacco, or cigars, that are manufactured in Canada are entered for consumption under this Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they shall be put up and prepared by their manufacturer in packages that have printed on them such information as is prescribed by the ministerial regulations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the manufactured tobacco or cigars and their packages, cartons, boxes, crates and other containers shall be stamped with tobacco stamps or cigar stamps by the manufacturer as required by the ministerial regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Packaging and stamping of imported manufactured tobacco and cigars</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), before imported manufactured tobacco or imported cigars are released under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they shall be put up and prepared by the importer in packages that have printed on them such information as is prescribed by the ministerial regulations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the manufactured tobacco or cigars and their packages, cartons, boxes, crates and other containers shall be stamped with tobacco stamps or cigar stamps by the importer as required by the ministerial regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 37, s. 6; 1999, c. 17, par. 144(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">z.11</Emphasis>)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Section 211 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Stamp regulations</MarginalNote><Label>211.</Label><Text>The Minister may make regulations prescribing the form of stamps to be impressed on, printed on, marked on, indented into or affixed to Canadian raw leaf tobacco, cigarettes, cigars and packages, cartons, boxes, crates and other containers containing manufactured tobacco or cigars, the information to be provided on the stamps and the manner in which the stamps are to be affixed.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 37, s. 8; 1999, c. 17, par. 144(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">z.19</Emphasis>)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 239.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Absence of stamps to be notice</MarginalNote><Label>239.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The absence of the proper tobacco stamp or cigar stamp required by this Act and the ministerial regulations to be impressed on, printed on, marked on, indented into or affixed to any cigarette or cigar or any package, carton, box, crate or other container of manufactured tobacco or cigars sold, offered for sale, kept for sale or found in the possession of any person is notice to all persons that</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 52; 1995, c. 41, s. 111(1); 1999, c. 17, par. 144(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">z.19</Emphasis>)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 239.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of manufactured tobacco, by a licensed tobacco manufacturer for export from Canada in accordance with this Act and the ministerial regulations,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>in the case of cigars, by a licensed cigar manufacturer</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for export from Canada in accordance with this Act and the ministerial regulations, or</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 111(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Clauses 239.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(iii)(A) and (B) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>the cigars were manufactured in Canada and are sold or offered for sale as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>the manufactured tobacco or cigars were imported and are, in accordance with this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, sold or offered for sale to an accredited representative, to a duty free shop licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, to an operator of a bonded warehouse licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> or for export, or</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 52</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 239.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(iv) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>by a person licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to operate a duty free shop, if</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>the manufactured tobacco was imported and is sold or offered for sale in accordance with that Act to a person about to leave Canada, or</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>the cigars are sold or offered for sale in accordance with that Act to a person about to leave Canada,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 111(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 239.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(iv) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>in the case of cigars or imported manufactured tobacco, in the possession of a person licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> to operate a bonded warehouse or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to operate a sufferance warehouse or duty free shop in that warehouse or duty free shop,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 111(4)</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 239.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(vi) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>in the case of cigars or imported manufactured tobacco, in the possession of a person as ships’ stores, if the acquisition and possession of the cigars or manufactured tobacco by that person are in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (6) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001, but do not apply to manufactured tobacco entered into a bonding warehouse before that day.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 112(1)</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 240(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of cigars or imported manufactured tobacco, by a person licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> to operate a bonded warehouse or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to operate a sufferance warehouse or duty free shop, in that warehouse or duty free shop;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 112(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 240(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of cigars or imported manufactured tobacco, as ships’ stores by a person if the acquisition and possession of the cigars or manufactured tobacco by that person are in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 52; 1995, c. 41, s. 112(3); 1999, c. 17, par. 144(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">z.20</Emphasis>)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 240(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of manufactured tobacco, by a licensed tobacco manufacturer for export from Canada in accordance with this Act and the ministerial regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of cigars, by a licensed cigar manufacturer</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for export from Canada in accordance with this Act and the ministerial regulations, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 112(4)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subparagraphs 240(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)(i) and (ii) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the cigars were manufactured in Canada and are sold or offered for sale as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the manufactured tobacco or cigars were imported and are, in accordance with this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, sold or offered for sale to an accredited representative, to a duty free shop licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, to an operator of a bonded warehouse licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> or for export; or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 52</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraph 240(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>by a person licensed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to operate a duty free shop, if</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the manufactured tobacco was imported and is sold or offered for sale in accordance with that Act to a person about to leave Canada, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the cigars are sold or offered for sale in accordance with that Act to a person about to leave Canada.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) to (5) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001, but do not apply to manufactured tobacco entered into a bonding warehouse before that day.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-15</MarginalNote><TitleText>EXCISE TAX ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 1(1)</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Atlantic manufactured tobacco</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>black stock manufactured tobacco</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>licensed tobacco manufacturer</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>foreign duty free shop</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>boutique hors taxes à l’étranger</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign duty free shop</DefinedTermEn> means a retail store that is located in a country other than Canada and that is authorized under the laws of that country to sell goods free of certain duties and taxes to individuals who are about to leave that country;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>foreign ships’ stores</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>provisions de bord à l’étranger</DefinedTermFr> </MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>foreign ships’ stores</DefinedTermEn> means tobacco products taken on board a vessel or aircraft while the vessel or aircraft is outside Canada and that are intended for consumption by or sale to the passengers or crew while the passengers and crew are on board the vessel or aircraft;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 1(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(7) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) to (3) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 55(1)</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 23(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Tax on various articles at schedule rates</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (6) to (8.3), whenever goods mentioned in Schedules I and II are imported into Canada or manufactured or produced in Canada and delivered to a purchaser of those goods, there shall be imposed, levied and collected, in addition to any other duty or tax that may be payable under this or any other Act or law, an excise tax in respect of the goods at the applicable rate set out in the applicable section in whichever of those Schedules is applicable, computed, if that rate is specified as a percentage, on the duty paid value or the sale price, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 55(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 23(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tax on release by duty free shop of Schedule II tobacco products</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to section 66.1, whenever tobacco products mentioned in Schedule II are sold by the operator of a duty free shop or are retained for the use of the operator, there shall be imposed, levied and collected, in addition to any other duty or tax payable under this Act or any other Act or law, an excise tax in respect of those tobacco products at the applicable rate set out in the applicable section in that Schedule, computed, if that rate is specified as a percentage, on the duty paid value or the price at which the tobacco products were purchased by the operator, as the case may be, and payable by the operator at the time the tobacco products are delivered to the purchaser or so retained for use.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 23(8) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>manufactured tobacco imported into Canada by an individual for their personal use if it is stamped in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> and duty has been imposed on it under section 200 of that Act; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 55(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 23(8.2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of cigars, products in respect of which section 23.3 applies that are not exported for delivery to a foreign duty free shop or as foreign ships’ stores, or cut filler or cut rag or products manufactured less fully than cut filler or cut rag, the products have been exported in bond by their manufacturer or producer;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of products other than those to which paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) applies, the products have been exported by their manufacturer or producer;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) to (3) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsection (4) applies to tobacco products exported after April 5, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 5(1)</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 23.1 and 23.2 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>tobacco product</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>23.1</Label><Text>In sections 23.11 to 23.3, <DefinedTermEn>tobacco product</DefinedTermEn> means manufactured tobacco other than cut filler, cut rag or products manufactured less fully than cut filler or cut rag.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tax on domestic tobacco delivered to a duty free shop or as ships’ stores</MarginalNote><Label>23.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There shall be imposed, levied and collected, in addition to any other duty or tax payable under this Act or any other Act or law, an excise tax, at the applicable rate set out in subsection (2), in respect of tobacco products that are manufactured or produced in Canada and are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>delivered to a duty free shop;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>delivered to a bonded warehouse, licensed as such under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>delivered to a person for use as ships’ stores in accordance with the regulations made under this Act and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>exported for delivery to a foreign duty free shop or as foreign ships’ stores.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rate of tax</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The rate of tax imposed under subsection (1) is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.0225 per cigarette, in the case of cigarettes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.01665 per stick, in the case of tobacco sticks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$11.65 per kilogram, in the case of manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When and by whom tax is payable</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The tax imposed under subsection (1) is payable by the manufacturer or producer of the tobacco products and is payable at the time</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) applies, they are exported; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in any other case, they are delivered.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tax on imported tobacco delivered to a duty free shop</MarginalNote><Label>23.12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If imported tobacco products are delivered to a duty free shop, there shall be imposed, levied and collected in respect of them, in addition to any other duty or tax payable under this Act or any other Act or law, an excise tax at the rate of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.05 per cigarette, in the case of cigarettes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.035 per stick, in the case of tobacco sticks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.03 per gram, in the case of manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When and by whom tax payable</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The tax imposed under this section is payable at the time of delivery and is payable by the operator of the duty free shop.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tax on exports of tobacco products not exceeding maximum quantity</MarginalNote><Label>23.13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If tobacco products manufactured or produced in Canada are exported in bond in accordance with subparagraph 58.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) and paragraph 58.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> by their manufacturer or producer, there shall be imposed, levied and collected in respect of the tobacco products, in addition to any other duty or tax payable under this Act or any other Act or law, an excise tax at the rate of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.05 per cigarette, in the case of cigarettes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.035 per stick, in the case of tobacco sticks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$30.00 per kilogram, in the case of manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tax on exports of tobacco products exceeding maximum quantity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If tobacco products manufactured or produced in Canada are exported and subsection (1) does not apply to those products, there shall be imposed, levied and collected in respect of those products, in addition to any other duty or tax payable under this Act or any other Act or law, an excise tax at the rate of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.0825 per cigarette, in the case of cigarettes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.06165 per stick, in the case of tobacco sticks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$41.65 per kilogram, in the case of manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When and by whom tax is payable</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The tax imposed under this section is payable at the time the tobacco products are exported and is payable by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if subsection (1) applies, the manufacturer or producer of the products; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if subsection (2) applies, the exporter of the products.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tax not payable on exports to foreign duty free shops or as foreign ships’ stores</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The tax imposed under this section is not payable in respect of tobacco products that are exported by their manufacturer or producer for delivery</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to a foreign duty free shop for sale in the shop; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>as foreign ships’ stores.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001, except that section 23.11 of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1), does not apply to tobacco products that had been entered into a bonding warehouse before that day.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 30, s. 3(1)</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 23.21(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption for limited exports</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The excise tax imposed under subsection 23.2(1) is not payable by a manufacturer or producer in respect of a particular quantity of a category of tobacco product exported at a time in a calendar year if the total quantity of that category of tobacco product exported by the manufacturer or producer in the calendar year up to and including that time, plus the particular quantity, does not exceed 1 1/2% of the total quantity of that category of tobacco product manufactured or produced by the manufacturer or producer in the preceding calendar year.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 23.21 of the Act, as amended by subsection (1), is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 1, 2000, except that, in applying subsection 23.21(2) of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1), before January 2001, the reference in that subsection to “1 1/2%” shall be read as a reference to “1 3/4%”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 26, s. 60(1)</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 23.22 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 56</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 23.3(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exemption for prescribed tobacco product</MarginalNote><Label>23.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The excise tax imposed under section 23.13 is not payable in the case of a tobacco product of a particular brand that is manufactured or produced in Canada and exported from Canada, if</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 56</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 23.3(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption for prescribed cigarettes</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The excise tax imposed under section 23.13 is not payable in the case of cigarettes of a particular type or formulation, manufactured or produced in Canada and exported under a brand that is also applied to cigarettes of a different type or formulation that are manufactured or produced in Canada and sold in Canada, if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 6(1); 1997, c. 26, s. 61; 2000, c. 30, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 23.31 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Tax on cigarettes sold to purchaser not authorized to resell in Ontario</MarginalNote><Label>23.31</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An excise tax shall be imposed, levied and collected on cigarettes that are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>marked or stamped in accordance with a statute of the Province of Ontario to indicate that they are intended for retail sale in the province; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sold by their manufacturer or producer, or by a person who is authorized under a statute of the province to sell cigarettes in the province, to a purchaser who is not authorized under a statute of the province to sell cigarettes in the province.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where tax not imposed</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Tax shall not be imposed under subsection (1) if the purchaser referred to in that subsection is a consumer in the Province of Ontario and the purchase is for consumption by the purchaser or by others at the expense of the purchaser.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When and by whom tax is payable</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The tax imposed under subsection (1) is payable by the person selling the cigarettes to the purchaser referred to in that subsection and is payable at the time of the sale.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amount of tax</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The tax imposed on cigarettes under subsection (1) is equal to the amount by which</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that would have been imposed under section 23 in respect of the cigarettes if the applicable rate of excise tax had been the rate set out in paragraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of Schedule II</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>exceeds</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that was imposed under section 23 in respect of the cigarettes.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 26, s. 62(2); 2000, c. 30, ss. 5(1) and (2)(F)</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 23.32(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Tax on cigarettes sold to purchaser not authorized to resell in Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>23.32</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An excise tax shall be imposed, levied and collected on cigarettes that are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>marked or stamped in accordance with a statute of the Province of Quebec to indicate that they are intended for retail sale in that province; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sold by their manufacturer or producer, or by a person who is authorized under a statute of the province to sell manufactured tobacco in the province, to a purchaser who is not authorized under a statute of the province to sell manufactured tobacco in the province.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where tax not imposed</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Tax shall not be imposed under subsection (1) if the purchaser referred to in that subsection is a consumer located in the Province of Quebec and the purchase is for consumption by the purchaser or by others at the expense of the purchaser.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 6(1); 1995, c. 36, ss. 2, 3(1) and 4; 1997, c. 26, ss. 63 and 64; 2000, c. 30, ss. 6(2) and 7(1), (2)(F) and (3) and par. 140(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 23.33 to 23.341 of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 30, s. 8(1)</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 23.35(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tax on excess sale of black stock cigarettes</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a supplier sells to an on-reserve retailer a quantity of black stock cigarettes in respect of which subparagraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of Schedule II applies that exceeds the quantity of black stock cigarettes that the on-reserve retailer is authorized under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tobacco Tax Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.O. 1990, c. T.10, to purchase, an excise tax shall be imposed, levied and collected on those excess cigarettes.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tax on illegal sale of black stock cigarettes</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a supplier sells to a person, other than an Indian consumer in Ontario or an on-reserve retailer, black stock cigarettes in respect of which subparagraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of Schedule II applies, an excise tax shall be imposed, levied and collected on those cigarettes.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 6(1); 2000, c. 30, s. 8(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 23.35(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amount of tax</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The tax imposed on black stock cigarettes under subsection (2) or (3) is equal to the amount by which</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that would have been imposed under section 23 in respect of those cigarettes if the applicable rate of excise tax had been the rate set out in paragraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of Schedule II</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>exceeds</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that was imposed under section 23 in respect of those cigarettes.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 6(1); 1997, c. 26, s. 66; 2000, c. 30, paras. 140(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 23.36 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 7(1); 1995, c. 36, s. 6; 1997, c. 26, ss. 67(1) and 68; 1998, c. 21, s. 81(1); 2000, c. 30, s. 13 and paras. 140(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 68.161 to 68.169 of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 68.17:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Rebate of tax to importer if foreign taxes paid</MarginalNote><Label>68.171</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may pay, to a person who has imported into a foreign country tobacco products (as defined in section 23.1) that were manufactured or produced in Canada and exported in bond by their manufacturer or producer to the foreign country in accordance with subparagraph 58.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) and paragraph 58.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, a rebate determined in accordance with subsection (2) in respect of the products if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person provides evidence satisfactory to the Minister that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>all taxes and duties imposed on the products under the laws of the foreign country having national application have been paid, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the products were marked in accordance with section 202 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person applies to the Minister for the rebate within two years after the products were exported to the foreign country.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of rebate</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The amount of the rebate under subsection (1) is equal to the lesser of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the total of the taxes and duties referred to in subparagraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) that are paid in respect of the tobacco products, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of the tax imposed under subsection 23.13(1) in respect of the tobacco products that is paid by their manufacturer or producer.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Overpayment of rebate or interest</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an amount has been paid to a person as a rebate under subsection (1) in respect of tobacco products exported by their manufacturer or producer or as interest in respect of such a rebate and tax under subsection 23.13(2) was imposed in respect of those products, the amount is deemed to be an amount of tax payable under Part III by the manufacturer or producer that became payable on the last day of the first month following that in which the amount was paid to the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Refund of tax to manufacturer if foreign taxes paid</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a rebate under subsection (1) has been paid in respect of exported tobacco products, the Minister may refund to the manufacturer or producer of the products the amount, if any, by which the tax imposed under subsection 23.13(1) in respect of the products and paid by the manufacturer or producer exceeds the amount of the rebate if the manufacturer or producer applies to the Minister for the refund within two years after the tobacco products were exported.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Refund of tax to operator of duty free shop</MarginalNote><Label>68.172</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), if the operator of a duty free shop provides evidence satisfactory to the Minister that the operator has sold imported tobacco products (as defined in section 23.1) in accordance with the regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to an individual who is not a resident of Canada and that the products were exported at any time, the Minister may refund to the operator the tax paid under section 23.12 in respect of that portion of the total quantity of the products sold by the operator to the individual and exported at that time that does not exceed</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of cigarettes, 200 cigarettes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of tobacco sticks, 200 sticks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks, 200 grams.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No refund shall be paid under subsection (1) to the operator of a duty free shop in respect of a sale of tobacco unless the operator applies to the Minister for the refund within two years after the sale.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 68.18 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception for tobacco products</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not apply in respect of taxes imposed under Part III on tobacco products mentioned in Schedule II.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 8(1)</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 72(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form and contents of application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application shall be made in the prescribed form and contain the prescribed information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Filing of application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An application shall be filed with the Minister in any manner that the Governor in Council may, by regulation, prescribe.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 8(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 72(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest on payment</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If an amount is paid to an applicant under subsection (6), interest at the prescribed rate shall be paid in respect of each day between the day that is sixty days after the day on which the application was received by the Minister and the day on which the payment is sent, and compounded monthly on the total amount of the payment and interest outstanding.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 26, s. 69(1)</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 74(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Deductions of tax, other than Part I tax, where application</MarginalNote><Label>74.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In lieu of making a payment, other than a payment in respect of Part I, pursuant to an application under any of sections 68 to 68.11 or 68.17 to 69, the Minister may, on request of the applicant, authorize the applicant to deduct, on such terms and conditions and in such manner as the Minister may specify, the amount that would otherwise be paid to the applicant from the amount of any payment or remittance of tax, penalty, interest or other sum that is reported in a return under section 78 by the applicant.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 15 (1st Supp.), s. 26(1), c. 7 (2nd Supp.), s. 35(1)</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 78(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Monthly returns</MarginalNote><Label>78.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who is required to pay tax under Part III or IV shall make each month a return in the prescribed form containing prescribed information of all amounts that became payable by the person on account of that tax in the preceding month.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Nil returns</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who holds a licence granted under or in respect of Part III or IV and whose tax payable under Parts III and IV in the preceding month is nil shall make a return as required by subsection (1) reporting that fact.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 12 (4th Supp.), s. 31(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 78(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorize any person whose activities that give rise to tax payable by the person under Part III or IV are predominantly limited to a seasonal period of operation to make a return in respect of any period longer than one month but not longer than six months, if the total tax payable by the person under Parts III and IV for the equivalent period in the preceding calendar year did not exceed an average of four hundred dollars per month throughout that equivalent period.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 15 (1st Supp.), s. 26(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 78(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in a case where the return is required to be made in a month in accordance with subsection (1) or (2), not later than the last day of that month;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) to (3) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 9(1)</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 81.38(8) and (8.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest on refunds</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If a payment is made under subsection (1) or (4) in respect of an application under any of sections 68 to 69, interest at the prescribed rate shall be paid, in respect of each day between the day that is sixty days after the day on which the application was received by the Minister and the day on which the payment was sent, and compounded monthly on the total amount of the payment and interest outstanding.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 10; 2000, c. 30, s. 15(1)</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 97.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Offence of selling in another province cigarettes marked for sale in Ontario</MarginalNote><Label>97.1</Label><Text>If cigarettes have been marked or stamped in accordance with a statute of the Province of Ontario to indicate that they are intended for sale in that province, every person who sells or offers for sale the cigarettes to a consumer in any other province is guilty of an offence and is liable on summary conviction to a fine of not less than $1,000 and not more than the greater of $1,000 and triple the amount by which</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that would have been imposed under section 23 in respect of the cigarettes if the applicable rate of excise tax had been the rate set out in paragraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of Schedule II</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>exceeds</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that was imposed under section 23 in respect of the cigarettes.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 30, s. 16(1)</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 97.2 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Offence of selling in another province cigarettes marked for sale in Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>97.2</Label><Text>If cigarettes have been marked or stamped in accordance with a statute of the Province of Quebec to indicate that they are intended for sale in that province, every person who sells or offers for sale the cigarettes to a consumer in any other province is guilty of an offence and is liable on summary conviction to a fine of not less than $1,000 and not more than the greater of $1,000 and triple the amount by which</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that would have been imposed under section 23 in respect of the cigarettes if the applicable rate of excise tax had been the rate set out in paragraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of Schedule II</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>exceeds</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 26, s. 72(1)</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 97.3 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 10; 1997, c. 26, s. 73(1); 2000, c. 30, s. 17(1) and par. 140(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 97.4 and 97.5 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Offence of unauthorized sale of cigarettes intended for Indian reserve</MarginalNote><Label>97.4</Label><Text>Every person who sells or offers for sale black stock cigarettes described in subparagraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of Schedule II in respect of which tax under section 23 was imposed at the rate set out in paragraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of that Schedule to a person other than a supplier, an on-reserve retailer or an Indian consumer in the Province of Ontario is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine of not less than $1,000 and not more than the greater of $1,000 and triple the amount by which</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that would have been imposed under section 23 in respect of the cigarettes if the applicable rate of excise tax had been the rate set out in paragraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of Schedule II</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>exceeds</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the excise tax that was imposed under section 23 in respect of the cigarettes.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 11(1); 1999, c. 17, s. 156(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 98.2 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 12</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 100(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Failure to make records and books available</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with section 98.1 is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine of not less than $200 and not more than $2,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than 6 months or to both the fine and imprisonment.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 30, s. 107(1)</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of Schedule II to the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.13138 for each five cigarettes or fraction of five cigarettes contained in any package, if</Text></Provision></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 30, s. 107(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 1(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of Schedule II to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>$0.12138 for each five cigarettes or fraction of five cigarettes contained in any package, if the cigarettes are marked or stamped in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tobacco Tax Act</XRefExternal>, R.S.Q. 1977, c. I-2, to indicate that the cigarettes are intended for retail sale in the Province of Quebec; and</Text></Provision></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 14(1); 1997, c. 26, ss. 74(3) and (4); 2000, c. 30, ss. 107(3) to (5) and par. 140(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 1(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of Schedule II to the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) to (3) are deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 29, s. 14(1); 1997, c. 26, s. 76(1); 2000, c. 30, s. 108(1)</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 2 and 3 of Schedule II to the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Tobacco sticks: $0.01965 per stick.</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Manufactured tobacco other than cigarettes and tobacco sticks: $15.648 per kilogram.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on April 6, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Schedule VII to the Act is amended by adding the following after section 1:</Text><AmendedText><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Label>1.1</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 1, “duty” does not include a duty levied under subsection 21(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) comes into force or is deemed to have come into force on October 1, 2001.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>INCOME TAX ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>43.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 182(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Surtax</MarginalNote><Label>182.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every corporation shall pay a tax under this Part for each taxation year equal to 50% of the corporation’s Part I tax on tobacco manufacturing profits for the year.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies to taxation years ending after April 5, 2001, except that, in its application to a corporation’s taxation year that includes that day, subsection 182(1) of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1), shall be read as follows:</Text><ReadAsText><Section><Label>182.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every corporation shall pay a tax under this Part for the corporation’s taxation year that includes April 5, 2001, equal to the total of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>40% of that proportion of the corporation’s Part I tax on tobacco manufacturing profits for the year that the number of days in the year that are before April 6, 2001, is of the total number of days in the year, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>50% of that proportion of the corporation’s Part I tax on tobacco manufacturing profits for the year that the number of days in the year that are after April 5, 2001, is of the total number of days in the year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></ReadAsText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>APPLICATION</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>44.</Label><Text>For the purposes of applying the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> that provide for the payment of, or liability to pay, interest in respect of any amount, the amount shall be determined and interest shall be computed on it as though this Act had been assented to on April 6, 2001.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>