<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-34</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>29</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2001</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2001-12-18">90162</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment establishes the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada, which replaces the Civil Aviation Tribunal established under Part IV of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, and extends the new Tribunal’s jurisdiction to the marine and railway sectors.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The enactment provides for the appointment of members to the Tribunal, and sets out the general powers and authorities of the Tribunal to conduct its affairs. It also provides for an independent process of review by the Tribunal of administrative enforcement actions — including the suspension and cancellation of licences, certificates and other documents of entitlement, and the imposition of monetary penalties — taken under various federal transportation Acts. The Tribunal will also hear appeals from determinations made on review.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Transportation Security Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Safety Act</XRefExternal> to establish the jurisdiction and decision-making authorities of the Tribunal under those Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TRANSPORTATION APPEAL TRIBUNAL OF CANADA</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is hereby established a tribunal to be known as the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada (“the Tribunal”).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction generally</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tribunal has jurisdiction in respect of reviews and appeals as expressly provided for under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Transportation Security Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Safety Act</XRefExternal> and any other federal Act regarding transportation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction in respect of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Tribunal also has jurisdiction in respect of reviews and appeals in connection with administrative monetary penalties provided for under sections 177 to 181 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Members</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall appoint as members of the Tribunal persons who, in the opinion of the Governor in Council, collectively have expertise in the transportation sectors in respect of which the federal government has jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Full- or part-time members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Members may be appointed as full-time or part-time members.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Chairperson and Vice-Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall designate one member as Chairperson of the Tribunal and one member as Vice-Chairperson. The Chairperson and Vice-Chairperson must be full-time members.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duties of Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chairperson is the chief executive officer of the Tribunal and has supervision over, and direction of, the work of the members and staff of the Tribunal, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the apportionment of work among members and the assignment of members to hear matters brought before the Tribunal and, when the Tribunal sits in panels, the assignment of members to panels and to preside over panels; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>generally, the conduct of the work of the Tribunal and the management of its internal affairs.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence of Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Chairperson or if the office of Chairperson is vacant, the Vice-Chairperson shall act as Chairperson during the continuance of that absence or incapacity or until a new Chairperson is designated.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Term of office</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A member shall be appointed to hold office during good behaviour for a term not exceeding seven years and may be removed for cause by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reappointment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A member is eligible to be reappointed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition after member ceases to hold office</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>At the request of the Chairperson, a former member, within eight weeks after ceasing to be a member, may make or take part in a determination or decision on a matter that they heard as a member. For that purpose, the former member is deemed to be a member.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Members shall receive the remuneration that is fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each member is entitled to be paid reasonable travel and living expenses incurred while absent in the course of their duties from, in the case of a full-time member, their ordinary place of work and, in the case of a part-time member, their ordinary place of residence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Status</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Members are deemed to be employed in the public service of Canada for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Inconsistent interests — full-time members</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Full-time members shall not accept or hold any office, membership, employment or interest, or engage in any business activity, that is inconsistent with the proper performance of their duties and functions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Divesting of interests</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an interest that is prohibited under subsection (1) vests, by whatever means, in a full-time member, the member shall disclose the interest to the Chairperson without delay and, within three months after the interest vests, either divest himself or herself of the interest or resign as a member.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties of full-time members</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Full-time members shall devote the whole of their time to the performance of their duties and functions under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inconsistent interests — part-time members</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a part-time member who is assigned to hear or is hearing any matter before the Tribunal, either alone or as a member of a panel, holds any pecuniary or other interest that could be inconsistent with the proper performance of their duties and functions in relation to the matter, the member shall disclose the interest to the Chairperson without delay and is ineligible to hear, or to continue to hear, the matter.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Principal office</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>The principal office of the Tribunal shall be in the National Capital Region described in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Employees</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The employees that are necessary for the proper conduct of the work of the Tribunal shall be appointed in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Status</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Employees appointed under subsection (1) are deemed to be employed in the Public Service for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Experts</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Tribunal may engage experts or persons having technical or specialized knowledge to assist the Tribunal in any matter in an advisory capacity and may, subject to the approval of the Treasury Board, fix their remuneration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Sittings</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall sit at those times and places in Canada that the Chairperson considers necessary for the proper performance of its functions.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Hearings on review</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>A review shall be heard by a member, sitting alone, who has expertise in the transportation sector to which the review relates. However, a review that concerns a matter of a medical nature shall be heard by a member with medical expertise, whether or not that member has expertise in the transportation sector to which the review relates.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Hearings on appeal</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), an appeal to the Tribunal shall be heard by an appeal panel consisting of three members.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Size of panel</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Chairperson may, if he or she considers it appropriate, direct that an appeal be heard by an appeal panel consisting of more than three members or, with the consent of the parties to the appeal, of one member.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Composition of panel</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A member who conducts a review may not sit on an appeal panel that is established to hear an appeal from his or her determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Qualifications of members</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>With the exception of the Chairperson and Vice-Chairperson, who may sit on any appeal panel, an appeal shall be heard by an appeal panel consisting of members who have expertise in the transportation sector to which the appeal relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Medical matters</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (4), in an appeal that concerns a matter of a medical nature, at least one member of the appeal panel shall have medical expertise, whether or not that member has expertise in the transportation sector to which the appeal relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision of panel</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A decision of a majority of the members of an appeal panel is a decision of the panel.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Nature of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>An appeal shall be on the merits based on the record of the proceedings before the member from whose determination the appeal is taken, but the appeal panel shall allow oral argument and, if it considers it necessary for the purposes of the appeal, shall hear evidence not previously available.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Nature of hearings</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the Tribunal is not bound by any legal or technical rules of evidence in conducting any matter that comes before it, and all such matters shall be dealt with by it as informally and expeditiously as the circumstances and considerations of fairness and natural justice permit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall not receive or accept as evidence anything that would be inadmissible in a court by reason of any privilege under the law of evidence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appearance</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A party to a proceeding before the Tribunal may appear in person or be represented by another person, including legal counsel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Private hearings</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Hearings shall be held in public. However, the Tribunal may hold all or any part of a hearing in private if it is of the opinion that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a public hearing would not be in the public interest;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>medical information about a person may be disclosed and the desirability of ensuring that, in the interests of that person, the information is not publicly disclosed outweighs the desirability of adhering to the principle that hearings be open to the public; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>confidential business information may be disclosed and the desirability of ensuring that the information is not publicly disclosed outweighs the desirability of adhering to the principle that hearings be open to the public.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Standard of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In any proceeding before the Tribunal, a party that has the burden of proof discharges it by proof on the balance of probabilities.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Text>The Tribunal, and each of its members, has all the powers of a commissioner under Part I of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Inquiries Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Text>A member who conducts a review shall provide a determination, and an appeal panel shall provide a decision, with reasons, in writing to all parties to a proceeding.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rules of Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>The Tribunal may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, make rules that are not inconsistent with this Act or any Act referred to in section 2 to govern the management of its affairs and the practice and procedure in connection with matters brought before it.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Costs</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Tribunal may award any costs, and may require the reimbursement of any expenses incurred in connection with a hearing, that it considers reasonable if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is seized of the matter for reasons that are frivolous or vexatious;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a party that files a request for a review or an appeal and does not appear at the hearing does not establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a party that is granted an adjournment of the hearing requested the adjournment without adequate notice to the Tribunal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recovery</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Costs awarded to the Minister of Transport, and expenses of that Minister or the Tribunal that are subject to reimbursement, under subsection (1) are a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Costs or expenses under subsection (1) that have not been paid may be certified by the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On production to the Federal Court, a certificate shall be registered. When it is registered, a certificate has the same force and effect as if it were a judgment obtained in the Federal Court for a debt of the amount specified in it and all reasonable costs and charges attendant on its registration, recoverable in that Court or in any other court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Proceedings to be recorded</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>Proceedings before the Tribunal shall be recorded, and the record shall show all evidence taken and all determinations, decisions and findings made in respect of the proceedings.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision on appeal final</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>A decision of an appeal panel of the Tribunal is final and binding on the parties to the appeal.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall, not later than June 30 in each fiscal year, submit to Parliament, through the member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this section, a report of its activities during the preceding fiscal year, and that Minister shall cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives it.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in sections 24 to 32.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>former Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ancien Tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>former Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Civil Aviation Tribunal established by subsection 29(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> as that Act read immediately before the coming into force of section 44.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>new Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>nouveau Tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>new Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada established by subsection 2(1).</Text></Definition></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>Wherever, in any Act of Parliament, in any instrument made under an Act of Parliament or in any contract, lease, licence or other document, a power, duty or function is vested in or is exercisable by the former Tribunal, the power, duty or function is vested in or is exercisable by the new Tribunal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Appropriations</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Any amount that is appropriated, for the fiscal year in which this section comes into force, by an appropriation Act based on the Estimates for that year for defraying the charges and expenses of the former Tribunal and that, on the day on which section 44 comes into force, is unexpended is deemed, on that day, to be an amount appropriated for defraying the charges and expenses of the new Tribunal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Members of Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Text>The Chairman, Vice-Chairman and other members of the former Tribunal immediately before the coming into force of section 44 shall, on the coming into force of that section, occupy the positions of Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson and members, respectively, with the new Tribunal until the expiry of the period of their appointment to the former Tribunal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Employment continued</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed as affecting the status of an employee who, immediately before the coming into force of section 44, occupied a position with the former Tribunal, except that each of those persons shall, on the coming into force of that section, occupy their position with the new Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, <DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>Every reference to the former Tribunal in any deed, contract, agreement or other document executed by the former Tribunal in its own name shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be read as a reference to the new Tribunal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>All rights and property of the former Tribunal and of Her Majesty in right of Canada that are under the administration and control of the former Tribunal and all obligations of the former Tribunal are transferred to the new Tribunal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Commencement of legal proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Text>Any action, suit or other legal proceeding in respect of an obligation or liability incurred by the former Tribunal may be brought against the new Tribunal in any court that would have had jurisdiction if the action, suit or other legal proceeding had been brought against the former Tribunal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of legal proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>Any action, suit or other legal proceeding to which the former Tribunal is a party that is pending in any court immediately before the day on which section 44 comes into force may be continued by or against the new Tribunal in the same manner and to the same extent as it could have been continued by or against the former Tribunal.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Proceedings relating to any matter before the former Tribunal on the coming into force of section 44, including any matter that is in the course of being heard by the former Tribunal, shall be continued by the new Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Application of provisions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless the Governor in Council, by order, directs that proceedings continued under this section are to be dealt with in accordance with the provisions of this Act, the proceedings shall be dealt with and determined in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> as that Act read immediately before the coming into force of section 44.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Directions re proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, direct that proceedings in respect of any class of matter referred to in subsection (1) in respect of which no decision or order is made on the coming into force of section 44 shall be discontinued or continued by the new Tribunal, as the case may be, on the terms and conditions specified in the order for the protection and preservation of the rights and interests of the parties.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-2</MarginalNote><TitleText>Aeronautics Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada established by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 4, s. 14</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Text>Sections 6.6 to 6.8 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Canadian aviation document</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>6.6</Label><Text>In sections 6.7 to 7.21, <DefinedTermEn>Canadian aviation document</DefinedTermEn> includes any privilege accorded by a Canadian aviation document.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Non-application of certain provisions</MarginalNote><Label>6.7</Label><Text>Sections 6.71 to 7.21 do not apply to a member of the Canadian Armed Forces acting in that capacity or to any other person in relation to a Canadian aviation document issued in respect of a military aircraft, military aerodrome or military facility.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Minister may refuse to issue or amend Canadian aviation document</MarginalNote><Label>6.71</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may refuse to issue or amend a Canadian aviation document on the grounds that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant is incompetent;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant or any aircraft, aerodrome, airport or other facility in respect of which the application is made does not meet the qualifications or fulfil the conditions necessary for the issuance or amendment of the document; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister is of the opinion that the public interest and, in particular, the aviation record of the applicant or of any principal of the applicant, as defined in regulations made under paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), warrant the refusal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall, by personal service or by registered or certified mail sent to their latest known address, notify the applicant or the owner or operator of the aircraft, aerodrome, airport or other facility, as the case may be, of a decision made under subsection (1). The notice shall be in a form prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council and, in addition to any other information that may be prescribed, shall indicate, as the case requires,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the nature of the incompetence of the applicant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the qualifications or conditions referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) that are not met or fulfilled, as the case may be;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the reasons for the Minister’s opinion referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>except in the case of a document or class of documents prescribed under paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is served or sent, on or before which the applicant, owner or operator may file a request for a review of the Minister’s decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>defining the word <DefinedTermEn>principal</DefinedTermEn>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing Canadian aviation documents, or classes of such documents, in respect of which a review of the Minister’s decision to refuse to issue or amend a document may not be requested.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>6.72</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to any regulations made under paragraph 6.71(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), an applicant, owner or operator who is served with or sent a notice under subsection 6.71(2) and who wishes to have the Minister’s decision reviewed shall, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application may allow, file a written request for a review of the decision with the Tribunal at the address set out in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal who conducts the review may determine the matter by confirming the Minister’s decision or by referring the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Suspensions, etc., generally</MarginalNote><Label>6.8</Label><Text>In addition to any ground referred to in any of sections 6.71, 6.9 to 7.1 and 7.21, the Minister may suspend, cancel or refuse to issue, amend or renew a Canadian aviation document in the circumstances and on the grounds prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>Subsection 6.9(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Holder, etc., not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(7.1)</Label><Text>In a review under this section, a holder, owner or operator referred to in subsection (1) is not required, and shall not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of Tribunal member</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>On a review under this section of a decision of the Minister to suspend or cancel a Canadian aviation document, the member of the Tribunal who conducts the review may determine the matter by confirming the Minister’s decision or substituting his or her own determination.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effective date of Minister’s decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Minister’s decision takes effect on the date of receipt of the notice under subsection (1) by the person on whom it is served or to whom it is sent, unless the notice indicates that the decision is to take effect on a later date.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 7(7) and (8) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of Tribunal member</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>On a review under this section of a decision of the Minister to suspend a Canadian aviation document, the member of the Tribunal who conducts the review may determine the matter by confirming the Minister’s decision or substituting his or her own determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Request for reconsideration of immediate threat</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Where</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no appeal from a determination under subsection (7) confirming the Minister’s decision is taken under section 7.2 within the time limited for doing so under that section, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an appeal panel has, on an appeal under section 7.2, confirmed the Minister’s decision under this section,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>the holder of the document or the owner or operator of any aircraft, airport or other facility in respect of which the document was issued may, in writing, request the Minister to reconsider whether the immediate threat to aviation safety referred to in subsection (1) that occasioned the suspension continues to exist or is likely to occur as described in that subsection.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 4, s. 15(1)</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 7.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Suspension, etc., on other grounds</MarginalNote><Label>7.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister decides to suspend, cancel or refuse to renew a Canadian aviation document on the grounds that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the holder of the document is incompetent,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the holder or any aircraft, airport or other facility in respect of which the document was issued ceases to meet the qualifications necessary for the issuance of the document or to fulfil the conditions subject to which the document was issued, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister is of the opinion that the public interest and, in particular, the aviation record of the holder of the document or of any principal of the holder, as defined in regulations made under paragraph 6.71(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), warrant it,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>the Minister shall, by personal service or by registered or certified mail sent to the holder or the owner or operator of the aircraft, airport or facility, as the case may be, at their latest known address, notify that person of the Minister’s decision.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 4, s. 15(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 7.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) of the Act is repealed.</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label /><Text /></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 7.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effective date of Minister’s decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Minister’s decision to suspend or cancel a Canadian aviation document takes effect on the date of receipt of the notice under subsection (1) by the person on whom it is served or to whom it is sent, unless the notice indicates that the decision is to take effect on a later date.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections 7.1(7) to (9) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of Tribunal member</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>On a review under this section of a decision of the Minister to suspend, cancel or refuse to renew a Canadian aviation document, the member of the Tribunal who conducts the review may determine the matter by confirming the Minister’s decision or by referring the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of decision pending reconsideration</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If a decision to suspend or cancel a Canadian aviation document is referred back to the Minister for reconsideration under subsection (7), the decision of the Minister remains in effect until the reconsideration is concluded. However, the member, after considering any representations made by the parties, may grant a stay of the decision until the reconsideration is concluded, if he or she is satisfied that granting a stay would not constitute a threat to aviation safety.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>Section 7.2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>7.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within thirty days after the determination,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person affected by the determination may appeal a determination made under subsection 6.72(4) or 7.1(7) to the Tribunal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person affected by the determination or the Minister may appeal a determination made under subsection 6.9(8) or 7(7) to the Tribunal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under subsection 6.72(4) or 7.1(7), dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under subsection 6.9(8) or 7(7), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of decision pending reconsideration</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a decision to suspend or cancel a Canadian aviation document is referred back to the Minister for reconsideration under paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the decision of the Minister remains in effect until the reconsideration is concluded. However, the appeal panel, after considering any representations made by the parties, may grant a stay of the decision until the reconsideration is concluded, if it is satisfied that granting a stay would not constitute a threat to aviation safety.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Default in payment</MarginalNote><Label>7.21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may suspend, or refuse to issue, amend or renew, a Canadian aviation document if a certificate under section 7.92, paragraph 8(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or subsection 8.1(4) has been issued to the Minister in respect of the applicant for, or the holder of, the document or in respect of the owner or operator of an aircraft, aerodrome, airport or other facility to which the document relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall, by personal service or by registered or certified mail sent to the applicant, holder, owner or operator, as the case may be, at their latest known address, notify that person of a decision made under subsection (1) and, in the case of a suspension, of the effective date of the suspension, which shall not be earlier than thirty days after the notice is served or sent.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 1, s. 5, c. 4, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>Sections 7.7 to 7.9 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of assessment of monetary penalty</MarginalNote><Label>7.7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister believes on reasonable grounds that a person has contravened a designated provision, the Minister may decide to assess a monetary penalty in respect of the alleged contravention, in which case the Minister shall, by personal service or by registered or certified mail sent to the person at their latest known address, notify the person of his or her decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice under subsection (1) shall be in a form prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council and shall, in addition to any other information that may be prescribed, indicate</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the designated provision that the Minister believes has been contravened;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to any regulations made under paragraph 7.6(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the amount that is determined by the Minister, in accordance with any guidelines that the Minister may make for the purpose, to be the amount that must be paid to the Minister as the penalty in the event that the person does not wish to appear before a member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct a review to make representations in respect of the alleged contravention; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is served or sent, on or before which, the penalty must be paid or a request for a review must be filed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Option</MarginalNote><Label>7.8</Label><Text>A person who has been served with or sent a notice under subsection 7.7(1) must either pay the amount of the penalty specified in the notice or file with the Tribunal a written request for a review of the facts of the alleged contravention or of the amount of the penalty.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of specified amount precludes further proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>7.9</Label><Text>If a person who is served with or sent a notice under subsection 7.7(1) pays the amount specified in the notice in accordance with the requirements set out in the notice, the Minister shall accept the amount as and in complete satisfaction of the amount of the penalty for the contravention by that person of the designated provision and no further proceedings under this Part shall be taken against the person in respect of that contravention.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review of determination</MarginalNote><Label>7.91</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is served with or sent a notice under subsection 7.7(1) and who wishes to have the facts of the alleged contravention or the amount of the penalty reviewed shall, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application may allow, file a written request for a review with the Tribunal at the address set out in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The burden of establishing that a person has contravened a designated provision is on the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who is alleged to have contravened a designated provision is not required, and shall not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>7.92</Label><Text>If a person fails to pay the amount of the penalty specified in a notice under subsection 7.7(1) within the time specified in the notice and does not file a request for a review under subsection 7.91(1), the person is deemed to have committed the contravention alleged in the notice, and the Minister may obtain from the Tribunal a certificate in a form prescribed by the Governor in Council that indicates the amount of the penalty specified in the notice.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Text>The portion of section 8 of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Determination by Tribunal member</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>If, at the conclusion of a review under section 7.91, the member of the Tribunal who conducts the review determines that</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1; 1992, c. 4, s. 22</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Text>Section 8.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person affected by the determination or the Minister may, within thirty days after the determination, appeal a determination made under section 8 to the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may dispose of the appeal by dismissing it or allowing it and, in allowing the appeal, the panel may substitute its decision for the determination appealed against.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where the appeal panel finds on an appeal that a person has contravened the designated provision, the panel shall without delay inform the person of the finding and, subject to any regulations made under paragraph 7.6(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), of the amount determined by the panel to be payable by the person in respect of the contravention and, where the amount is not paid to the Tribunal by or on behalf of the person within the time allowed by the Tribunal, the Tribunal shall issue to the Minister a certificate in a form prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council, setting out the amount required to be paid by the person.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Text>Subsection 8.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Registration of certificate</MarginalNote><Label>8.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the time limit for the payment of an amount determined by the Minister in a notice under subsection 7.7(1) has expired, the time limit for the request for a review under subsection 7.91(1) has expired, the time limit for an appeal under subsection 8.1(1) has expired, or an appeal taken under section 8.1 has been disposed of, on production in any superior court, a certificate issued under section 7.92, paragraph 8(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or subsection 8.1(4) shall be registered in the court. When it is registered, a certificate has the same force and effect, and proceedings may be taken in connection with it, as if it were a judgment in that court obtained by Her Majesty in right of Canada against the person named in the certificate for a debt of the amount set out in the certificate.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Text>Subsection 8.3(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of certain provisions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 7.1(3) to (8) and section 7.2 apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, in respect of a decision of the Minister referred to in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 33 (1st Supp.), s. 5; 1992, c. 1, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Text>Part IV of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “full opportunity” with “opportunity”</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by replacing the words “full opportunity” with the word “opportunity” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 6.9(7);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 7(6); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 7.1(6).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “audition” with “audience”</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The French version of the Act is amended by replacing the word “audition” with the word “audience” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 6.9(6) and (7);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 7(5) and (6); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 7.1(5) and (6).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-9</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Shipping Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>46.</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada established by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 6 (3rd Supp.), s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Text>Section 120 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Medical incapacity of certificate holder</MarginalNote><Label>120.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister believes on reasonable grounds that the holder of a certificate granted under this Part is incapacitated in respect of the performance of his or her duties as a certificated master or seaman by reason of not meeting the medical fitness standards prescribed under paragraph 110(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), the Minister may suspend the certificate until the Minister is satisfied that the certificate holder is no longer incapacitated.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable to suspension</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 504.1 to 505.2 apply in respect of a suspension under subsection (1) with any modifications that the circumstances require. However, subsections 505.1(4) and 505.2(3) apply as if the suspension were a suspension of a certificate under paragraph 504(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48.</Label><Text>Section 125 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable to suspensions and cancellations</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Sections 504.1 to 505.2 apply in respect of a suspension or cancellation under subsection (4) with any modifications that the circumstances require. However, subsections 505.1(4) and 505.2(3) apply as if the suspension or cancellation were a suspension or cancellation of a certificate under paragraph 504(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49.</Label><Text>Section 128 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable to suspensions and cancellations</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Sections 504.1 to 505.2 apply in respect of a suspension or cancellation under subsection (2) with any modifications that the circumstances require.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50.</Label><Text>Section 133 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable to suspensions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Sections 504.1 to 505.2 apply in respect of a suspension under subsection (3) with any modifications that the circumstances require. However, subsections 505.1(4) and 505.2(3) apply as if the suspension were a suspension of a certificate under paragraph 504(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 6 (3rd Supp.), s. 87(F); 1999, c. 19, ss. 15, 16</MarginalNote><Label>51.</Label><Text>The heading before section 504 and sections 504 and 505 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Tribunal Hearings Related to the Competency and Conduct of Officers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Suspension or cancellation of certificate</MarginalNote><Label>504.</Label><Text>With respect to a certificate granted by the Minister, or a certificate granted in any other country in so far only as concerns its validity in Canada, the Minister may suspend or cancel the certificate of competency or service of a master, mate or engineer if the Minister is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the master, mate or engineer is incompetent or is guilty of any act of misconduct, drunkenness or tyranny;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the master, mate or engineer on board a vessel that has contravened any of sections 5.3 to 5.5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Coastal Fisheries Protection Act</XRefExternal> knew, when the contravention occurred, that the vessel was committing the contravention;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the loss or abandonment of, or serious damage to, any ship or any loss of life was caused by the wrongful act or default of the master, mate or engineer;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the master, mate or engineer is guilty of a criminal offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the master or mate, in the case of collision between his or her vessel and another vessel, has failed without reasonable cause to comply with the requirements of section 568 with regard to rendering assistance or giving information.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice before suspension or cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>504.1</Label><Text>Before suspending or cancelling a certificate of competency or service, the Minister shall, by personal service or by registered or certified mail sent to the holder of the certificate at his or her latest known address, give the holder 30 days notice of the proposed suspension or cancellation. The notice shall be in a form prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council and shall indicate</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the grounds for the proposed suspension or cancellation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the address at which, and the date, being 30 days after the notice is given, on or before which, the holder may file a request for a review of the Minister’s decision.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>504.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may suspend or cancel a certificate of competency or service without giving notice under section 504.1 if, on <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application by the Minister, the Tribunal determines that compliance with that section is not in the interest of public safety.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision within 24 hours</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application by the Minister under subsection (1) shall be heard by a member of the Tribunal, sitting alone, whose determination shall be made within 24 hours after the application is filed with the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may appeal the determination to the Tribunal within 24 hours after the determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision within 48 hours</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal shall make a decision within 48 hours after the appeal is filed with the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice after suspension or cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>504.3</Label><Text>Unless a notice is given under section 504.1, immediately after suspending or cancelling a certificate, the Minister shall, by personal service or by registered or certified mail sent to the holder of the certificate at his or her latest known address, give the holder a notice in a form prescribed by regulation of the Governor in Council</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>confirming the suspension or cancellation and providing all relevant information concerning the grounds on which the Minister suspended or cancelled the certificate; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>indicating the address at which, and the date, being 30 days after the notice is given, on or before which, the holder may file a request for a review of the Minister’s decision.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>505.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The holder of a certificate may, on or before the date specified in a notice under section 504.1 or 504.3 or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review of the decision referred to in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of request</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The filing of a request for a review of a decision referred to in a notice under section 504.1 operates as a stay of the proposed suspension or cancellation until the matter is finally disposed of in accordance with section 505.1 or 505.2.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>505.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection 505(1), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the holder of the certificate of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the holder of the certificate with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In a review of a decision made under paragraph 504(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), the holder of the certificate is not required, and must not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The member may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a suspension or cancellation of a certificate under paragraph 504(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), confirm the Minister’s decision or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a suspension or cancellation of a certificate under paragraph 504(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), confirm the Minister’s decision or substitute his or her own determination.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>505.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The holder of a certificate may appeal a determination made under paragraph 505.1(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), and the holder of a certificate or the Minister may appeal a determination made under paragraph 505.1(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), to the Tribunal within 30 days after the determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under paragraph 505.1(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under paragraph 505.1(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Endorsements</MarginalNote><Label>505.3</Label><Text>A reference to a certificate in sections 504 to 505.2 includes a reference to an endorsement of that certificate.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 10</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Transportation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>52.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 180(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 7.8 to 8.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> apply to the contravention of a provision, requirement or condition designated under section 177, with any modifications that are necessary, and a reference in any of those provisions or in any document issued under any of those provisions to</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 180(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>“Minister” shall be read as a reference to the Agency or, in any provision other than section 7.9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, to a person designated by the Agency;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>Financial Administration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>53.</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out, in column I, the reference to</Text><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civil Aviation Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal de l’aviation civile</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>and the corresponding reference in column II to the “Minister of Transport”.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>54.</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the Act is amended by adding, in alphabetical order in column I, a reference to</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal d’appel des transports du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>and a corresponding reference in column II to the “Minister of Transport”.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Marine Transportation Security Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 40</MarginalNote><Label>55.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>screening officer</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Transportation Security Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>screening officer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>agent de contrôle</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>screening officer</DefinedTermEn> means a person designated by the Minister under section 19.1 as a screening officer for the purposes of this Act;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada established by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>56.</Label><Text>Sections 5 and 6 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations respecting security</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the security of marine transportation, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for preventing unlawful interference with marine transportation and ensuring that appropriate action is taken where that interference occurs or could occur;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring or authorizing screening for the purpose of protecting persons, goods, vessels and marine facilities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the establishment of restricted areas;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the keeping and preservation of records and documents relating to the security of marine operations, including copies of the regulations, security measures and security rules;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for requiring the records and documents to be filed with the Minister or provided on request; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the protection, preservation and return of any evidence that has been seized under this Act without a warrant or any vessel that has been detained under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences relating to the regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes a regulation made under subsection (1) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual, to a fine not exceeding $5,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation, to a fine not exceeding $100,000.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notices and service of documents</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the form and manner of giving notice under this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the service of documents required or authorized to be served under this Act, including the manner of serving them, the proof of their service and the circumstances under which they are deemed to have been served.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>57.</Label><Text>Section 19 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>designation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 19.1 to 19.8, <DefinedTermEn>designation</DefinedTermEn> includes any privilege accorded by a designation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of screening officers</MarginalNote><Label>19.1</Label><Text>The Minister may designate persons or classes of persons to act as screening officers for the purposes of this Act or any of its provisions.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Refusal to designate, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>19.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may refuse to designate a person as a screening officer under section 19.1, or may suspend, cancel or refuse to renew the designation of a person as a screening officer, if the Minister is of the opinion that the person is incompetent, does not meet the qualifications or fulfil the conditions required for the designation or ceases to meet the qualifications or fulfil the conditions of the designation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension or cancellation of designation for contraventions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may suspend or cancel the designation of a person as a screening officer if the Minister is of the opinion that the person has contravened this Act or any regulation, security measure or security rule, or any condition referred to in subsection 10(6).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension for immediate threat</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may suspend the designation of a person as a screening officer if the Minister is of the opinion that the exercise by the person of the functions of a screening officer constitutes, or is likely to constitute, an immediate threat to marine transportation security.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>19.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister decides to refuse to designate a person as a screening officer or decides to suspend, cancel or refuse to renew a person’s designation as a screening officer, the Minister shall notify the person of that decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice under subsection (1) shall include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the grounds for the Minister’s decision; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is given, on or before which, the person may file a request for a review of the decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effective date of suspension or cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In the case of a suspension or cancellation, the effective date of the decision shall not be earlier than</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under subsection 19.2(1) or (3), the day that the notice was received by the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under subsection 19.2(2), the thirtieth day after the notice is given.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>19.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person affected by a decision of the Minister under section 19.2 may, on or before the date specified in the notice under subsection 19.3(1) or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review of the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of request</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A request under subsection (1) for a review of a decision of the Minister does not operate as a stay of the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On application in writing by the person affected by a decision made under subsection 19.2(2), after giving any notice to the Minister that is, in the member’s opinion, necessary and after considering any representations made by the parties, a member of the Tribunal assigned for the purpose may grant a stay of the decision until the review is completed, unless he or she is of the opinion that granting a stay would constitute a threat to marine transportation security.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>19.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection 19.4(1), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In a review of a decision made under subsection 19.2(2), the person who filed the request for the review is not required, and shall not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The member may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under subsection 19.2(1) or (3), confirm the decision or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under subsection 19.2(2), confirm the decision or substitute his or her own determination.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>19.6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within thirty days after the determination,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person affected by the determination may appeal a determination made under paragraph 19.5(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to the Tribunal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person affected by the determination or the Minister may appeal a determination made under paragraph 19.5(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to the Tribunal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under paragraph 19.5(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under paragraph 19.5(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision to remain in effect pending reconsideration</MarginalNote><Label>19.7</Label><Text>If a matter is referred back to the Minister for reconsideration under paragraph 19.5(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 19.6(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the decision of the Minister under subsection 19.2(1) or (3) to suspend or cancel a designation remains in effect until the reconsideration is concluded. However, the member who made the determination or the appeal panel, after considering any representations made by the parties, may grant a stay of a decision under subsection 19.2(1) to suspend or cancel a designation until the reconsideration is concluded, if the member or panel is satisfied that granting a stay would not constitute a threat to marine transportation security.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Reconsideration</MarginalNote><Label>19.8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the case of a decision made under subsection 19.2(3), if the appeal panel has, on an appeal under section 19.6, dismissed the appeal or if the Minister has, after reconsidering the matter pursuant to paragraph 19.5(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 19.6(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), confirmed the suspension, the person affected by the decision may, in writing, request the Minister to reconsider whether the exercise by the person of the functions of a screening officer continues to constitute, or is likely to continue to constitute, an immediate threat to marine transportation security.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the receipt of a request by a person under subsection (1), the Minister shall without delay conduct the reconsideration and inform the person of his or her decision regarding the request. Sections 19.3 to 19.7 apply in respect of that decision with any modifications that are necessary.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>58.</Label><Text>Subsection 28(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exploitant du bâtiment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>L’exploitant d’un bâtiment peut être déclaré coupable d’une infraction à la présente loi, en rapport avec ce bâtiment, commise par une autre personne, que celle-ci ait été ou non identifiée, poursuivie ou déclarée coupable, à moins que, lors de l’infraction, le bâtiment n’ait été en la possession d’une autre personne sans son consentement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>59.</Label><Text>Section 32 of the Act and the headings before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ADMINISTRATIVE PENALTIES</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>violation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>In sections 33 to 51, <DefinedTermEn>violation</DefinedTermEn> means a contravention of a provision that is designated as a violation by the regulations.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Assurances of Compliance and Notices of Violation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>If reasonable grounds to believe a violation</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that a person has committed a violation, the Minister may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enter into an assurance of compliance with the person that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>identifies the violation and provides that the person will comply with the provision to which the violation relates within the period, and be subject to the terms and conditions, specified in the assurance,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>sets out the amount and form of any security that, pending compliance with the assurance, must be deposited with the Minister, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>sets out the penalty, fixed by or within the range fixed by the regulations, that the person would have been liable to pay for the violation if the assurance had not been entered into; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>issue, and cause to be served on the person, a notice of violation that names the person, identifies the violation and sets out</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the penalty, fixed by or within the range fixed by the regulations, that the person is liable to pay for the violation,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the period, being thirty days after notice is served, within which the penalty must be paid or a review must be requested, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>particulars of the manner in which, and the address at which, the penalty must be paid or a review requested.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension of period</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may extend the period specified under subparagraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) if the Minister is satisfied that the person is unable to comply with the assurance of compliance for reasons beyond the person’s control.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Short-form descriptions in notices of violation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may establish, in respect of each violation, a short-form description to be used in notices of violation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deemed violation</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who enters into an assurance of compliance under paragraph 33(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is, unless a review is requested under subsection (2), deemed to have committed the violation in respect of which the assurance was entered into.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who enters into an assurance of compliance may, within forty-eight hours after the assurance is signed, unless a notice of default is served within that period under subsection 36(1), file a request with the Tribunal for a review of the facts of the violation, in which case the assurance is deemed to be a notice of violation and a review under subsection 39(1) of the facts of the violation and of the amount of the penalty is deemed to have been requested.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>When assurance of compliance complied with</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>If the Minister is satisfied that an assurance of compliance under paragraph 33(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) has been complied with, the Minister shall cause a notice to that effect to be served on the person and, on the service of the notice,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no further proceedings may be taken against the person with respect to the violation in respect of which the assurance was entered into; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any security deposited under subparagraph 33(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) must be returned to the person.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>When assurance of compliance not complied with</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister is of the opinion that a person who has entered into an assurance of compliance has not complied with it, the Minister may cause a notice of default to be served on the person to the effect that, unless a member determines under section 37, or an appeal panel decides under section 40, that the assurance has been complied with,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person is liable to pay double the amount of the penalty set out in the assurance; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the security deposited under subparagraph 33(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) is forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice under subsection (1) shall include the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is served, on or before which, a request for a review may be filed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No set-off</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the service of a notice of default, the person served has no right of set-off against any amount spent by the person under the assurance of compliance.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is served with a notice under subsection 36(1) may, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The burden is on the Minister to establish that the person did not comply with the assurance of compliance referred to in the notice. The person is not required, and shall not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain defences not available</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person does not have a defence by reason that the person exercised all due diligence to comply with the assurance of compliance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The member may confirm the Minister’s decision or determine that the person has complied with the assurance of compliance.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Return of security</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>Any security deposited under subparagraph 33(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) shall be returned to the person if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person pays double the amount of the penalty set out in the assurance of compliance in accordance with a notice under subsection 36(1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a member determines under subsection 37(6), or an appeal panel decides under subsection 40(3), that the assurance has been complied with.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of violation</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person served with a notice of violation under paragraph 33(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay the amount of the penalty; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within thirty days after being served or any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file with the Tribunal a written request for a review of the facts of the violation or the amount of the penalty.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When review not requested</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a review of the facts of the violation is not requested, the person is deemed to have committed the violation in respect of which the notice was served.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The burden is on the Minister to establish that the person committed the violation referred to in the notice. The person is not required, and shall not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The member may confirm the Minister’s decision or, subject to any regulations made under paragraph 51(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), substitute his or her own determination.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister or the person who requested the review of the decision may appeal a determination made under subsection 37(6) or 39(6) to the Tribunal within thirty days after the determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under subsection 37(6), dismiss the appeal or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under subsection 39(6), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and, subject to regulations made under paragraph 51(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), substitute its own decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Choice of Proceedings</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>How contravention may be proceeded with</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Text>If a contravention can be proceeded with as a violation or as an offence, the Minister may commence proceedings in respect of that contravention as a violation or recommend that it be proceeded with as an offence, but it may be proceeded with only as one or the other.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Recovery of Debts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Debts due to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Text>The following amounts constitute debts due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in a court of competent jurisdiction:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless a review of the amount of a penalty is requested under subsection 39(1), the amount of the penalty, from the time the notice of violation that sets out the penalty is served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of a penalty set out in a notice of default referred to in subsection 36(1), from the time the notice under that subsection is served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of a penalty determined by a member under section 39, or decided by an appeal panel under section 40, from the time of the respective determination or decision; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of any reasonable expenses incurred in attempting to recover an amount referred to in any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All or part of a debt referred to in section 42 in respect of which there is a default of payment may be certified by the Minister or the Tribunal, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On production to the Federal Court, a certificate shall be registered. When it is registered, a certificate has the same force and effect, and proceedings may be taken in connection with it, as if it were a judgment obtained in that Court for a debt of the amount specified in it and all reasonable costs and charges attendant on its registration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Rules of Law about Violations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Violations are not offences</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a violation is not an offence and, accordingly, section 126 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> does not apply.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Defence</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, no person is liable for the commission of a violation if the person exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Violation by employee or agent</MarginalNote><Label>46.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person is liable for a violation committed by their employee or agent, whether or not the employee or agent has been identified or proceeded against under sections 33 to 43.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Liability of operator of a vessel</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The operator of a vessel is liable for a violation committed in relation to the vessel by another person, whether or not the other person has been identified or proceeded against under sections 33 to 43 unless, at the time of the violation, the vessel was in the possession of another person without the operator’s consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Liability of operator of marine facility</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The operator of a marine facility is liable for a violation committed with their consent by another person in relation to the facility, whether or not the other person has been identified or proceeded against under sections 33 to 43.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Officers, etc., of corporation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An officer, director or agent of a corporation that commits a violation under this Act is a party to and liable for the violation if he or she directed, authorized, assented to, acquiesced in or participated in the commission of the violation, whether or not the corporation has been identified or proceeded against under sections 33 to 43.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Notations removed</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Unless the Minister is of the opinion that it is not in the public interest to do so, five years after the last day on which any of the following events occurs, the Minister is to remove every notation of violation or default, and every suspension or cancellation of the designation of or refusal to designate or to renew the designation of a person as a screening officer on prescribed grounds, from any records that the Minister may keep respecting the person:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>payment by the person of every penalty that the person is liable to pay after a notice of violation, a notice of default, a determination of a member of the Tribunal on review or a decision of an appeal panel of the Tribunal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the suspension or cancellation of the designation of, or the refusal to designate or to renew the designation of, the person as a screening officer under section 19.2.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty to notify</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When the Minister is of the opinion that removal of a notation is not in the public interest, the Minister shall give notice of that fact to the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A notice under subsection (2) shall provide all relevant information concerning the grounds on which the Minister has refused to remove the notation and shall include the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is served, on or before which, a request for a review may be filed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections 37(1) to (3) apply in respect of a refusal to remove a notation, with any modifications that the circumstances require.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review may confirm the Minister’s decision or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The person may, within thirty days after a determination is made under subsection (5), appeal the determination to the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the person does not appear at the review hearing, the person is not entitled to appeal a determination unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Public record</MarginalNote><Label>48.</Label><Text>The Minister shall keep a public record of notations of violations or default that appear on any record that the Minister may keep respecting persons under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>49.</Label><Text>No notice of violation may be issued more than two years after the Minister becomes aware of the violation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>50.</Label><Text>A document that purports to have been issued by the Minister and certifies the day on which the Minister became aware of a violation is evidence, without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the document, that the Minister became aware of the violation on that day.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>51.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating, as a violation that may be proceeded with in accordance with sections 33 to 46, 49 and 50, the contravention of a provision that is an offence under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating violations that, if continued on more than one day, constitute a separate violation for each day on which they are continued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating violations that may be proceeded with by issuing notices of violation and fixing a penalty or a range of penalties in respect of each such violation, up to a maximum of $25,000 but in any event not greater than the maximum fine that would be payable if the violation were proceeded with by way of summary conviction; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing anything that by subsections 33 to 50 is to be prescribed.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 30</MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Sector Compensation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>60.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following under the heading “Other Portions of the Public Service”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civil Aviation Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal de l’aviation civile</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>61.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “Other Portions of the Public Service”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal d’appel des transports du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-35</MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Service Staff Relations Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>SOR/88-105</MarginalNote><Label>62.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Civil Aviation Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal de l’aviation civile</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>63.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal d’appel des transports du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 32 (4th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Railway Safety Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>64.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Safety Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada established by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 4(5) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Manner of filing or sending notices and documents</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>With the exception of a notice or document sent to or by the Tribunal, for the purposes of this Act, a notice or document must be filed with, or sent to, a person</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>65.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 27:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Refusal to designate etc.</MarginalNote><Label>27.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may refuse to designate a person as a screening officer under section 27 or may suspend, cancel or refuse to renew the designation of a person as a screening officer if the Minister is of the opinion that the person is incompetent, does not meet the qualifications or fulfil the conditions required for the designation or ceases to meet the qualifications or fulfil the conditions of the designation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension or cancellation of designation for offences</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may suspend or cancel the designation of a person as a screening officer if the Minister is of the opinion that the person has committed an offence within the meaning of section 41.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspension of designation for immediate threat</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may suspend the designation of a person as a screening officer if the Minister is of the opinion that the exercise by the person of the functions of a screening officer constitutes, or is likely to constitute, an immediate threat to railway security.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>27.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister decides to refuse to designate a person as a screening officer or decides to suspend, cancel or refuse to renew the designation of a person as a screening officer, the Minister shall notify the person of that decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice under subsection (1) shall include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the grounds for the Minister’s decision; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is sent, on or before which, the person may file a request for a review of the decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effective date of suspension or cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In the case of a suspension or cancellation, the effective date of the decision shall not be earlier than</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under subsection 27.1(1) or (3), the day that the notice was received by the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under subsection 27.1(2), the thirtieth day after the notice is sent.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>27.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person affected by a decision of the Minister under section 27.1 may, on or before the date specified in the notice under subsection 27.2(1) or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review of the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of request</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A request under subsection (1) for a review of a decision of the Minister does not operate as a stay of the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On application in writing by the person affected by a decision made under subsection 27.1(2), after giving any notice to the Minister that is, in the member’s opinion, necessary and after considering any representations made by the parties, a member of the Tribunal assigned for the purpose may grant a stay of the decision until the review is completed, unless he or she is of the opinion that granting a stay would constitute a threat to railway security.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>27.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection 27.3(1), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In a review of a decision made under subsection 27.1(2), the person who filed the request for the review is not required, and shall not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The member may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under subsection 27.1(1) or (3), confirm the decision or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under subsection 27.1(2), confirm the decision or substitute his or her own determination.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>27.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within thirty days after the determination,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person affected by the determination may appeal a determination made under paragraph 27.4(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to the Tribunal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person affected by the determination or the Minister may appeal a determination made under paragraph 27.4(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to the Tribunal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under paragraph 27.4(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under paragraph 27.4(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision to remain in effect pending reconsideration</MarginalNote><Label>27.6</Label><Text>If a matter is referred back to the Minister for reconsideration under paragraph 27.4(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 27.5(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the decision of the Minister under subsection 27.1(1) or (3) to suspend or cancel a designation remains in effect until the reconsideration is completed. However, the member who made the determination or the appeal panel, after considering any representations made by the parties, may grant a stay of a decision under subsection 27.1(1) to suspend or cancel a designation until the reconsideration is completed, if the member or panel is satisfied that granting a stay would not constitute a threat to railway security.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Reconsideration</MarginalNote><Label>27.7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the case of a decision made under subsection 27.1(3), if the appeal panel has, on an appeal under section 27.5, dismissed the appeal or if the Minister has, after reconsidering the matter pursuant to paragraph 27.4(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 27.5(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), confirmed the suspension, the person affected by the decision may, in writing, request the Minister to reconsider whether the exercise by the person of the functions of a screening officer continues to constitute, or is likely to continue to constitute, an immediate threat to railway security.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request by a person under subsection (1), the Minister shall without delay conduct the reconsideration and inform the person of his or her decision regarding the request. Sections 27.2 to 27.6 apply in respect of that decision, with any modifications that are necessary.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>designation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>27.8</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 27.1 to 27.7, <DefinedTermEn>designation</DefinedTermEn> includes any privilege accorded by a designation.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>66.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 31 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>A notice under subsections (1) to (3) that contains an order shall indicate the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is sent, on or before which, the recipient of the notice may file a request for a review of the order of the railway safety inspector.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 31(9) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reviewable order</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The alteration of an order under subsection (8) is an order that is reviewable under sections 31.1 to 31.5.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>67.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 31:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review of order of railway safety inspector</MarginalNote><Label>31.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person, including a railway company, who is sent a notice under section 31 that contains an order may, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review of the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal shall without delay appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The member may confirm the order or refer the matter to the Minister for consideration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>31.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The person who requested the review under section 31.1 may, within thirty days after the determination, appeal a determination made under subsection 31.1(4) to the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the person does not appear at the review hearing, the person is not entitled to appeal a determination unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may dismiss the appeal or refer the matter to the Minister for consideration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No stay of order</MarginalNote><Label>31.3</Label><Text>An order of a railway safety inspector shall not be stayed pending a review under section 31.1, an appeal under section 31.2 or consideration by the Minister under subsection 31.1(4) or 31.2(3).</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consideration by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>31.4</Label><Text>If a matter is referred to the Minister under subsection 31.1(4) or 31.2(3), or if the Minister on his or her own initiative decides to review an order of a railway safety inspector, the Minister may confirm the order, or may, by order, alter or revoke the order of the railway safety inspector. For greater certainty, the Minister’s order may be made an order of the Federal Court or of any superior court under section 34.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>When alteration or revocation effective</MarginalNote><Label>31.5</Label><Text>An alteration or revocation under section 31.4 has effect when the railway company or other person to whom notice of the order under section 31 was sent receives notice of the alteration or revocation.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 9, s. 25</MarginalNote><Label>68.</Label><Text>Subsection 32(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order contained in a notice under subsection (1), (3) or (3.1) takes effect on the date of receipt of the notice. The notice shall indicate the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is sent, on or before which, the recipient of the notice may file a request for a review of the order.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>69.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 32:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>32.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person, including a railway company, who is sent a notice under section 32 that contains an order may, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review of the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall notify the Minister and the person who filed the request of the time and place in writing. In the case of a request for review of an order made under subsection 32(3), the Tribunal shall do so without delay.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person who filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In a review of an order made under subsection 32(3), a person who the Minister is of the opinion has contravened a regulation made under section 24 is not required, and shall not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The member may confirm the order or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>32.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The person who requested the review under section 32.1 may, within thirty days after the determination, appeal a determination made under subsection 32.1(5) to the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the person does not appear at the review hearing, the person is not entitled to appeal a determination unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Stay of order</MarginalNote><Label>32.3</Label><Text>If a request for review is filed, an order made under subsection 32(1) or (3.1) shall be stayed until the matter is finally disposed of in accordance with section 32.1, 32.2 or 32.4. However, an order made under subsection 32(3) shall not be stayed pending a review under section 32.1, an appeal under section 32.2 or reconsideration by the Minister under subsection 32.1(5) or 32.2(3).</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Reconsideration by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>32.4</Label><Text>If a matter is referred back to the Minister under subsection 32.1(5) or 32.2(3), the Minister may confirm the order, or may, by order, alter or revoke the order. For greater certainty, the Minister’s order may be made an order of the Federal Court or of any superior court under section 34.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>When alteration or revocation effective</MarginalNote><Label>32.5</Label><Text>An alteration or revocation under section 32.4 has effect when the railway company or other person to whom notice of the order under section 32 was sent receives notice of the alteration or revocation.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 9, s. 33</MarginalNote><Label>70.</Label><Text>Paragraph 46(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>orders and notices sent under sections 31 to 32.5;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Amendment to This Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Amendment to this Act</MarginalNote><Label>71.</Label><Text>If Bill C-14, introduced in the first session of the 37th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the coming into force of section 1 of that Act, subsection 2(2) of this Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction generally</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tribunal has jurisdiction in respect of reviews and appeals as expressly provided for under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Transportation Security Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Safety Act</XRefExternal> and any other federal Act regarding transportation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Bill C-14</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-14</MarginalNote><Label>72.</Label><Text>If Bill C-14, introduced in the first session of the 37th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal> (referred to in this section as the “other Act”), receives royal assent, then, on the coming into force of section 2 of this Act,</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>adjudicator</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the other Act is repealed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 2 of the other Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada established by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 15 of the other Act and the heading before it are repealed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subparagraph 16(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)(ii) of the French version of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>le capitaine ou le membre de l’équipage a été déclaré coupable d’une infraction liée à l’exécution de ses fonctions sur un bâtiment ou a commis une violation pour laquelle un procès-verbal a été dressé en vertu de l’alinea 229(1)<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 16(5) and (6) of the other Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice after refusal to issue</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister of Transport must, immediately after refusing to issue a Canadian maritime document, give the applicant a notice</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>confirming the refusal and providing all relevant information concerning the grounds on which the Minister has refused to issue the document; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>indicating, in the case of a refusal to issue a document under Part 3 (Personnel) on the grounds set out in paragraph (4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is given, on or before which, the applicant may file a request for a review of the Minister’s decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the other Act is amended by adding the following after section 16:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>16.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An applicant who receives a notice under subsection 16(5) may, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review of the decision if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the request is in respect of a Canadian maritime document that is issued under Part 3 (Personnel); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the grounds for refusing to issue the document are set out in paragraph 16(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal must appoint a time and place for the review and must notify the Minister of Transport and the applicant of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review must provide the Minister of Transport and the applicant with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In a review of a decision made under subparagraph 16(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)(ii) on the ground that an applicant has committed a violation in respect of which a notice of violation has been issued to the applicant, the applicant is not required, and must not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter before the matter that gave rise to the issue of the notice has been disposed of in accordance with sections 232 to 232.2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The member may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under paragraph 16(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), confirm the decision or substitute his or her own determination; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in any other case, confirm the decision or refer the matter back to the Minister of Transport for reconsideration.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 20 of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Suspension, cancellation and refusal to renew</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to section 20.1, the Minister of Transport may suspend, cancel or refuse to renew a Canadian maritime document if the Minister is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the requirements for the issuance of the document are no longer met;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a term or condition attached to the document has been contravened;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the document was obtained by any fraudulent or improper means or a misrepresentation of any material fact;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the holder of the document has not paid a fine or penalty imposed on them under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the holder of the document has contravened a provision of this Act or the regulations that the Minister is responsible for administering;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a Canadian maritime document issued under Part 3 (Personnel) to a master or crew member,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the master or crew member is incompetent or has committed an act of misconduct,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the master or crew member was on board a vessel that contravened any of sections 5.3 to 5.5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Coastal Fisheries Protection Act</XRefExternal> and knew, when the contravention occurred, that the vessel was committing the contravention, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the master or crew member has been found guilty of an offence related to their duties on a vessel; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a refusal to renew,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the applicant has not paid a fee set under paragraph 35(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) in respect of the issuance of the document, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Minister is of the opinion that the public interest and, in particular, the record of the applicant or of a principal of the applicant warrant it.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of document</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a Canadian maritime document is suspended or cancelled, the person who held it shall return it on demand to the Minister of Transport.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice before suspension or cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>20.1</Label><Text>The Minister of Transport must, before suspending or cancelling a Canadian maritime document issued under Part 3 (Personnel), give the holder 30 days notice of the proposed suspension or cancellation. The notice must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide the holder with all relevant information concerning the grounds on which the Minister proposes to suspend or cancel the document; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>indicate, in the case of a proposed suspension or cancellation of a document on the grounds referred to in paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) or subparagraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)(ii), the address at which, and the date, being 30 days after the notice is given, on or before which, the applicant may file a request for a review of the Minister’s decision.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>20.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Transport may suspend or cancel a Canadian maritime document issued under Part 3 (Personnel) without complying with section 20.1 if, on <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application by the Minister, the Tribunal determines that compliance with that section is not in the interest of public safety.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision within 24 hours</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application by the Minister of Transport under subsection (1) must be heard by a member of the Tribunal, sitting alone, whose determination shall be made within 24 hours after the application is filed with the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister of Transport may, within 24 hours after the determination, appeal the determination to the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision within 48 hours</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal shall make a decision within 48 hours after the appeal is filed with the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice after suspension, cancellation or refusal to renew</MarginalNote><Label>20.3</Label><Text>Except where notice of a proposed suspension or cancellation of a Canadian maritime document is given under section 20.1, the Minister of Transport must, immediately after suspending, cancelling or refusing to renew a Canadian maritime document, give the holder a notice that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>confirms the suspension, cancellation or refusal and provides all relevant information concerning the grounds on which the Minister suspended, cancelled or refused to renew the document; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>indicates, in the case of the suspension or cancellation of, or the refusal to renew, a document on the grounds referred to in paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) or subparagraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)(ii), the address at which, and the date, being 30 days after the notice is given, on or before which, the applicant may file a request for a review of the Minister’s decision.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>20.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the holder of a Canadian maritime document that is referred to in a notice under section 20.1 or 20.3 may, within the time specified in the notice or any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review of the decision referred to in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A request for a review must not be filed with, or accepted by, the Tribunal if the grounds for suspending, cancelling or refusing to renew the document are set out in paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or subparagraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)(i).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of request</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The filing of a request for a review in respect of a notice under section 20.1 operates as a stay of the proposed suspension or cancellation until the matter is finally disposed of in accordance with this section or section 20.5.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal must appoint a time and place for the review and must notify the Minister of Transport and the holder of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review must provide the Minister of Transport and the holder with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In a review of a decision made under paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), the holder is not required, and must not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The member may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a decision made under paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) or subparagraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(ii) or (iii), confirm the Minister of Transport’s decision or substitute his or her own determination; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in any other case, confirm the Minister of Transport’s decision or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>20.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The applicant for, or holder of, a Canadian maritime document may appeal to the Tribunal a determination made under subsection 16.1(5) or 20.4(7), and the Minister of Transport may appeal to the Tribunal a determination made under paragraph 16.1(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 20.4(7)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>). The time limit for making an appeal is 30 days after the determination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under paragraph 16.1(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 20.4(7)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision; or</Text></Paragraph><?Pub _bookmark Command="[Quick Mark]"?><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under paragraph 16.1(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or 20.4(7)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister of Transport for reconsideration.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs 35(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the other Act are repealed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 229(1) of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><Label>229.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that a person or vessel has committed a violation, the Minister may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enter into an assurance of compliance with the person or vessel that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>identifies the violation and provides that the person or vessel will comply with the provision to which the violation relates within the period, and be subject to the terms and conditions, specified in the assurance,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>sets out the amount and form of any security that, pending compliance with the assurance, must be deposited with the Minister, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>sets out the penalty, fixed by or within the range fixed by the regulations made under this Part, for the violation that the person or vessel would have been liable to pay if the assurance had not been entered into; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>issue, and cause to be served on the person or vessel, a notice of violation that names the person or vessel, identifies the violation and sets out</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the penalty, fixed by or within the range fixed by the regulations made under this Part, for the violation that the person or vessel is liable to pay,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the period, being thirty days after the notice is served, within which the penalty must be paid or a review of the notice requested, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>particulars of the manner in which, and the address at which, the penalty must be paid or a review requested.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 229(3) of the French version of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Description abrégée</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Il peut établir, pour toute violation, une description abrégée à utiliser dans les procès-verbaux.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 230 to 232 of the other Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Deemed violation</MarginalNote><Label>230.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who, or vessel that, enters into an assurance of compliance is, unless a review is requested under subsection (2), deemed to have committed the violation in respect of which the assurance was entered into.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who, or vessel that, enters into an assurance of compliance may, within 48 hours after the assurance is signed, unless a notice of default is served within that period under section 231.1, request a review of the facts of the violation, in which case the assurance is deemed to be a notice of violation and a review under paragraph 232(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the facts of the violation and the amount of the penalty is deemed to have been requested.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>When assurance of compliance complied with</MarginalNote><Label>231.</Label><Text>If the Minister is satisfied that an assurance of compliance has been complied with, the Minister must cause a notice to that effect to be served on the person or vessel and, on the service of the notice,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no further proceedings may be taken against the person or vessel with respect to the violation in respect of which the assurance was entered into; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any security deposited under subparagraph 229(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) must be returned to the person or vessel.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>When assurance of compliance not complied with</MarginalNote><Label>231.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister is of the opinion that a person who, or vessel that, has entered into an assurance of compliance has not complied with it, the Minister may cause a notice of default to be served on the person or vessel to the effect that, unless a member determines under section 231.2, or an appeal panel decides under section 232.2, that the assurance has been complied with,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person or vessel is liable to pay double the amount of the penalty set out in the assurance; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the security deposited under subparagraph 229(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) is forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice under subsection (1) must include the address at which, and the date, being 30 days after the notice is served, on or before which, a request for a review may be filed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No set-off</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the service of a notice of default, the person or vessel served has no right of set-off against any amount spent by the person or vessel under the assurance of compliance.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>231.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person or vessel served with a notice under subsection 231.1(1) may, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (1), the Tribunal must appoint a time and place for the review and must notify the Minister and the person who, or vessel that, filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review must provide the Minister and the person or vessel with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The burden is on the Minister to establish that the person or vessel did not comply with the assurance of compliance referred to in the notice. The person is not required, and must not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain defences not available</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person or vessel named in a notice of default does not have a defence by reason that the person or vessel exercised due diligence to comply with the assurance of compliance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The member may confirm the Minister’s decision or determine that the person or vessel has complied with the assurance of compliance.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Return of security</MarginalNote><Label>231.3</Label><Text>Any security deposited under subparagraph 229(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) must be returned to the person or vessel if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person or vessel pays double the amount of the penalty set out in the assurance of compliance in accordance with a notice of default under section 231.1; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a member determines under section 231.2, or an appeal panel decides under section 232.2, that the assurance of compliance has been complied with.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of violation</MarginalNote><Label>232.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person or vessel served with a notice of violation under paragraph 229(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay the amount of the penalty; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within thirty days after being served or any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file with the Tribunal a written request for a review of the facts of the violation or the amount of the penalty.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When review not requested</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a review of the facts of the violation is not requested, the person or vessel is deemed to have committed the violation in respect of which the notice was served.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>232.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under paragraph 232(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the Tribunal must appoint a time and place for the review and must notify the Minister and the person who, or vessel that, filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review must provide the Minister and the person or vessel with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The burden is on the Minister to establish that the person or vessel committed the violation referred to in the notice. The person is not required, and must not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The member may confirm the Minister’s decision or, subject to any regulations made under paragraph 244(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), substitute his or her own determination.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>232.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister or the person who, or vessel that, requested the review may, within 30 days after the determination, appeal a determination made under subsection 231.2(6) or 232.1(4) to the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Tribunal assigned to hear the appeal may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under subsection 231.2(6), dismiss the appeal or allow the appeal and substitute its own decision; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination made under subsection 232.1(4), dismiss the appeal, or allow the appeal and, subject to regulations made under paragraph 244(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), substitute its own decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 234 of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Debts due to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>234.</Label><Text>The following amounts constitute debts due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in a court of competent jurisdiction:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless a review of the amount of the penalty is requested under paragraph 232(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the amount of a penalty set out in a notice of violation, from the time the notice is served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount that a notice of default served under subsection 231.1(1) provides that a person is liable to pay, from the time the notice is served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of a penalty determined by a member after a review under section 232.1, or decided by an appeal panel after an appeal under section 232.2, from the time of the respective determination or decision; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of any reasonable expenses incurred in attempting to recover an amount referred to in any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 235(1) of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>235.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All or part of a debt referred to in section 234 in respect of which there is a default of payment may be certified by the Minister or the Tribunal, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 239(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person or vessel pays every penalty that the person or vessel is liable to pay after a notice of violation, a notice of default, a determination of a member of the Tribunal on review or a decision of an appeal panel of the Tribunal;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 239(3) of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A notice under subsection (2) must include the address at which, and the date, being thirty days after the notice is served, on or before which, a request for a review may be filed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The person or vessel may, on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Tribunal on application allows, file a written request for a review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>On receipt of a request filed under subsection (4), the Tribunal must appoint a time and place for the review and must notify the Minister and the person who, or vessel that, filed the request of the time and place in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The member of the Tribunal assigned to conduct the review must provide the Minister and the person who, or vessel that, filed the request with an opportunity consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The member may confirm the Minister’s decision or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The person who, or vessel that, requested the review may, within 30 days after the determination, appeal a determination made under subsection (7) to the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If the person or vessel does not appear at the review hearing, the person or vessel is not entitled to appeal a determination unless the person or vessel establishes that there was sufficient reason to justify the absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>The appeal panel assigned to hear the appeal may dismiss the appeal or refer the matter back to the Minister for reconsideration.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 244(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) of the other Act is repealed.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>73.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, other than sections 71 and 72, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>