<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-17</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Budget Implementation Act, 1997 and the Financial Administration Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Budget Implementation Act, 1997 and the Financial Administration Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Budget Implementation, 1997 and Financial Administration</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2001</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2001-6-14">90145</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 1997</XRefExternal> implement certain of the Government of Canada’s commitments regarding the Canada Foundation for Innovation that were announced in the Economic Statement and Budget Update of October 18, 2000.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Funding for the Foundation will include operation and maintenance costs of research infrastructure, as well as the purchasing of access to world-leading research facilities located outside Canada and to major international collaborative research projects.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Also, a further $750,000,000 is provided to the Foundation — beyond the $500,000,000 provided for in the Economic Statement and Budget Update of October 18, 2000 — for a total amount of $1,250,000,000.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended to clarify that Parliament must provide explicit authority for any borrowing by or on behalf of the Crown. Two new kinds of regulations are made possible — regulations deeming certain transactions to be a borrowing of money, and regulations imposing a requirement that a money-borrowing transaction be authorized by the Minister of Finance. The Minister of Finance is empowered to authorize such transactions, subject to any terms and conditions that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is also amended to correct an oversight under which the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board was inadvertently removed from the list of Crown Corporations that are exempt from the application of Divisions I to IV of Part X of that Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 26</MarginalNote><TitleText>BUDGET IMPLEMENTATION ACT, 1997</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>eligible project</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 1997</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>eligible project</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>travaux admissibles</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible project</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a project carried on, or to be carried on, by an eligible recipient for the modernization, acquisition, development, operation or maintenance of research infrastructure by the recipient in Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the purchasing by an eligible recipient of access to a world-leading research facility located outside Canada or to a major international collaborative research project, including the purchasing of such access by means of a contribution toward a portion of capital costs.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Objects and purposes of foundation</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The objects and purposes of the foundation are to make grants to eligible recipients for eligible projects to increase Canada’s capability of carrying on high quality research.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 94:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>$1,250,000,000 granted</MarginalNote><Label>95.</Label><Text>From and out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund there may, on the requisition of the Minister of Finance, be paid and applied a sum of one billion, two hundred and fifty million dollars for the fiscal year beginning on April 1, 2000, for payment to the Canada Foundation for Innovation for its use.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 26, s. 21(E)</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Section 43 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Borrowing of money</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any statement in any other Act of Parliament to the effect that this Act or any portion or provision of it does not apply, no money shall be borrowed by or on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada except as provided by or under</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other Act of Parliament that expressly authorizes the borrowing of money; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other Act of Parliament that provides for the borrowing of money from Her Majesty in right of Canada or of a province.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Issuing of securities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No securities shall be issued by or on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada without the authority of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 60(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>deeming a specified transaction or a transaction of a specified class, including the issuance of securities, to be a transaction to borrow money for the purposes of subsection 43(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>notwithstanding any right provided by or under any other Act of Parliament to borrow money without the Minister’s authorization, requiring the Minister’s authorization in respect of a specified transaction to borrow money or a transaction of a specified class to borrow money.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 60 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister’s authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a regulation is made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), the Minister may authorize, subject to any terms and conditions that the Minister considers appropriate,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the specified transaction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a particular transaction named by the Minister within the specified class;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>transactions of a particular subclass described by the Minister within the specified class; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>transactions of the specified class.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 17, s. 31</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 85(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exempted Crown corporations</MarginalNote><Label>85.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Divisions I to IV do not apply to the Bank of Canada, the Canada Council, the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board, the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, the Canadian Film Development Corporation, the International Development Research Centre or the National Arts Centre Corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) is deemed to have come into force on December 31, 1998.</Text></Subsection><?Pub Caret?></Section></Body></Bill>