<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>S-10</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Parliament of Canada Act (Parliamentary Poet Laureate)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Parliament of Canada Act (Parliamentary Poet Laureate), An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Parliament of Canada Act (Parliamentary Poet Laureate)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>36</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2001</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2001-12-18">36000</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment creates the position of Parliamentary Poet Laureate.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-1</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 75:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Parliamentary Poet Laureate</MarginalNote><Label>75.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is hereby established the position of Parliamentary Poet Laureate, the holder of which is an officer of the Library of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Selection</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons, acting together, shall select the Parliamentary Poet Laureate from a list of three names submitted in confidence by a committee chaired by the Parliamentary Librarian and also composed of the National Librarian, the National Archivist of Canada, the Commissioner of Official Languages for Canada, and the Chair of the Canada Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Term</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Parliamentary Poet Laureate holds office for a term not exceeding two years, at the pleasure of the Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons acting together.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Roles and responsibilities</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Parliamentary Poet Laureate may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>write poetry, especially for use in Parliament on occasions of state;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sponsor poetry readings;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>give advice to the Parliamentary Librarian regarding the collection of the Library and acquisitions to enrich its cultural holdings; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>perform such other related duties as are requested by either Speaker or the Parliamentary Librarian.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>