<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-23</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Customs Act and to make related amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Customs Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Customs</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2001</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>25</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2001</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2001-10-25">90147</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to modernize the customs administration by</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for the expedited movement of persons and goods into Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for streamlined clearance procedures for low risk passengers by pre-arrival risk assessment of passenger information;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for new requirements in respect of the provision of information obtained under that Act;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing for monetary penalties in respect of designated contraventions;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>extending the time for requesting reviews and appeals beyond current time limits;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>harmonizing provisions for the collection of amounts owing under that Act with those of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>making technical and housekeeping amendments; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>making related amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><?Pub Caret1?><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>CUSTOMS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 147(1)</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>release</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> means an individual, a partnership, a corporation, a trust, the estate of a deceased individual or a body that is a society, a union, a club, an association, a commission or other organization of any kind;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>régle­mentaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of a form or the manner of filing a form, authorized by the Minister,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of the information to be provided on or with a form, specified by the Minister, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in any other case, prescribed by regulation or determined in accordance with rules prescribed by regulation;</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>release</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>dédouane­ment</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>release</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of goods, to authorize the removal of the goods from a customs office, sufferance warehouse, bonded warehouse or duty free shop for use in Canada, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of goods to which paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) applies, to receive the goods at the place of business of the importer, owner or consignee;</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>data</DefinedTermEn> means representations, in any form, of information or concepts;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>document</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn> means any material on which data are recorded or marked and which is capable of being read or understood by a person or a computer system or other device;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Electronic records</MarginalNote><Label>(1.3)</Label><Text>Every person required by this Act to keep records who does so electronically shall retain them in an electronically readable format for the prescribed retention period.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 123(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Attributions du commissaire</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Les attributions conférées au commissaire par la présente loi peuvent être exercées par toute personne qu’il autorise à agir ainsi ou par tout agent appartenant à une catégorie d’agents qu’il autorise à agir ainsi. Les attributions ainsi exercées sont réputées l’avoir été par le commissaire.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 2(1)</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 3.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Interest to be compounded</MarginalNote><Label>3.1</Label><Text>Interest shall be computed at a prescribed rate or at a specified rate and compounded daily and, if interest is computed in respect of an amount under a provision of this Act and is unpaid on the day it would, but for this section, have ceased to be computed under that provision, interest at the specified rate shall be computed and compounded daily on that unpaid interest from that day to the day it is paid and shall be paid as that provision required the amount to be paid.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>Subsection 3.3(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Waiver of penalty or interest</MarginalNote><Label>3.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister or any officer designated by the Minister for the purposes of this section may at any time waive or cancel all or any portion of any penalty or interest otherwise payable by a person under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply if measures may be taken under section 127.1, a request under section 129 is made or the time for making a request set out in that section has not expired.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 3.4:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Payment of Large Amounts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Where excess amount to be paid</MarginalNote><Label>3.5</Label><Text>Except in the circumstances that the Minister may specify, every person who makes a payment of any amount under this Act shall, if the amount exceeds the amount specified by the Minister, make the payment to the account of the Receiver General in the prescribed manner and within the prescribed time at</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a bank;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a credit union;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a corporation authorized by an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province to carry on the business of offering its services as a trustee to the public; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a corporation authorized by an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province to accept deposits from the public and that carries on the business of lending money on the security of real property or immovables or of investing in mortgages or hypothecary claims on immovables.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 4:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Undertakings</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Text>In the case of goods to which paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) applies, the Minister may accept from an importer or transporter an undertaking to assume obligations in relation to compliance with this Act and the regulations.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 7:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Provision of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to provide accurate information</MarginalNote><Label>7.1</Label><Text>Any information provided to an officer in the administration or enforcement of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or under any other Act of Parliament that prohibits, controls or regulates the importation or exportation of goods, shall be true, accurate and complete.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Section 8 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Declaration</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>The Minister may include on any form a declaration, to be signed by the person completing the form, declaring that the information given by that person on the form is true, accurate and complete.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 148</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 8.1(7) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Imprimés en preuve</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Pour l’application de la présente loi et du <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tarif des douanes</XRefExternal>, un document présenté par le ministre, paraissant être l’imprimé d’un formulaire reçu en application du present article, est admissible en preuve et établit, sauf preuve contraire, la production ou la fourniture du formulaire en application du présent article.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 148</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 8.1(8) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations in respect of electronic systems or any other technology to be used in the administration of this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, including regulations respecting</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Subsection 9(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Records</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an officer so requests, a customs broker shall make available to the officer, within the time specified by the officer, any records that the customs broker is required by the regulations to keep.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 11(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Presentation of persons on arrival in Canada</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, every person arriving in Canada shall, except in such circumstances and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, enter Canada only at a customs office designated for that purpose that is open for business and without delay present himself or herself to an officer and answer truthfully any questions asked by the officer in the performance of his or her duties under this or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to any person who has presented himself or herself outside Canada at a customs office designated for that purpose and has not subsequently stopped at any other place prior to his or her arrival in Canada unless an officer requires that person to present himself or herself to the officer.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 11 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — alternative manner</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to a person who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>holds an authorization issued by the Minister under subsection 11.1(1) to present himself or herself in a prescribed alternative manner and who has presented himself or herself in the manner authorized for that person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is a member of a prescribed class of persons authorized by regulations made under subsection 11.1(3) to present himself or herself in a prescribed alternative manner and who has presented himself or herself in the manner authorized for that class.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of officer</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding that a person holds an authorization under subsection 11.1(1) or is authorized under the regulations made under subsection 11.1(3), an officer may require a person to present himself or herself in accordance with subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 11:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Minister may authorize</MarginalNote><Label>11.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, the Minister may issue to any person an authorization to present himself or herself in an alternative manner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment, etc., of authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, subject to the regulations, amend, suspend, renew, cancel or reinstate an authorization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing classes of persons who may be authorized to present themselves in alternative manners;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting alternative manners of presentation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the requirements and conditions that are to be met before authorizations may be issued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the terms and conditions of authorizations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the amendment, suspension, renewal, cancellation or reinstatement of authorizations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting fees or the manner of determining fees to be paid for authorizations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of customs controlled areas</MarginalNote><Label>11.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may designate an area as a customs controlled area for the purposes of this section and sections 11.3 to 11.5 and 99.2 and 99.3.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment, etc. of designation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may amend, cancel or reinstate at any time a designation made under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Entry prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>11.3</Label><Text>No owner or operator of a facility where a customs controlled area is located shall grant or allow to be granted access to the customs controlled area to any person unless the person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has been authorized by the Minister in accordance with regulations made under section 11.5; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is a prescribed person or a member of a prescribed class of persons.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Presentation and reporting</MarginalNote><Label>11.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), every person leaving a customs controlled area, other than for the purpose of boarding a flight with a destination outside Canada, shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>present himself or herself in the prescribed manner to an officer and identify himself or herself;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>report in the prescribed manner and make available to the officer any goods that he or she has acquired through any means while in the customs controlled area; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>answer truthfully any questions asked by an officer in the performance of his or her duties under this or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application of subsection (1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>persons who are required to present themselves under section 11 or report goods under section 12; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribed persons or members of prescribed classes of persons in prescribed circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>11.5</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the authorization of persons under paragraph 11.3(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing persons or classes of persons who may be granted access under paragraph 11.3(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the circumstances in which an authorization under paragraph 11.3(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) may be amended, suspended, renewed, cancelled or reinstated;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the manner in which a person must present himself or herself under paragraph 11.4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and report goods under paragraph 11.4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing for the purposes of paragraph 11.4(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) persons or classes of persons who are exempt from the requirements imposed by subsection 11.4(1) and the circumstances in which they are exempted.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>Paragraph 12(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of goods in the actual possession of a person arriving in Canada, or that form part of the person’s baggage where the person and the person’s baggage are being carried on board the same conveyance, by that person or, in prescribed circumstances, by the person in charge of the conveyance;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to answer questions and present goods</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Every person who reports goods under section 12 inside or outside Canada or is stopped by an officer in accordance with section 99.1 shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>answer truthfully any question asked by an officer with respect to the goods; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if an officer so requests, present the goods to the officer, remove any covering from the goods, unload any conveyance or open any part of the conveyance, or open or unpack any package or container that the officer wishes to examine.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Text>Subsection 17(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rates of duties</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to this Act, the rates of duties on imported goods shall be the rates applicable to the goods at the time they are accounted for under subsection 32(1), (2) or (5) or, where goods have been released in the circumstances set out in paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), at the time of release.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 18(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Liability of person reporting goods short landed</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and 20(2.1), any person who reports goods under section 12, and any person for whom that person acts as agent or employee while so reporting, are jointly and severally or solidarily liable for all duties levied on the goods unless one or the other of them proves, within the time that may be prescribed, that the duties have been paid or that the goods</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 19(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Disposition of goods before release</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to section 20, any person who is authorized by an officer or by any prescribed means to do so may</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 19 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorization to deliver goods</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>In prescribed circumstances and under prescribed conditions, a person may be authorized by an officer or by any prescribed means to deliver goods or cause them to be delivered to the place of business of the importer, owner or consignee.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 3(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 19(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Movement and storage of goods</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to section 20, where goods that have been reported under section 12 have been described in the prescribed form at a customs office designated for that purpose, any person who is authorized by an officer or by any prescribed means to do so may</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 20(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Liability of transporter</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2.1), every person who transports or causes to be transported within Canada goods, other than goods to which paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) applies, that have been imported but have not been released is liable for all duties on the goods unless the person proves, within the time that may be prescribed, that the goods were</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 20 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If a person transports within Canada goods to which paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) applies, which the person is required to report under section 12 but which have not been released, the person is liable for all duties on the goods unless the person proves, within the time that may be prescribed, that the goods were</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>destroyed while being transported;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>received in a customs office, bonded warehouse or duty free shop;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the goods are designated as ships’ stores by regulations made under paragraph 99(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, received on board a conveyance of a class prescribed under that paragraph for use on the conveyance in accordance with regulations made under that paragraph;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>exported; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>received at the place of business of the importer, owner or consignee.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 5</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>Subsection 22(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Records</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the following persons shall keep the prescribed records at their place of business in Canada or at any other place that the Minister may designate, for the prescribed period and in the prescribed manner, and shall on the request of an officer make them available to the officer, within the time specified by the officer, and answer truthfully any questions asked by the officer about those records:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who transports or causes to be transported goods into Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who transports or causes to be transported within Canada goods that have been imported but have not been released.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 168</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 28(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Liability of operator</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1.2), the operator of a sufferance warehouse, bonded warehouse or duty free shop is liable for all duties or taxes levied under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or any other law relating to customs on goods that have been received in that warehouse or shop unless the operator proves that the goods</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 72(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 28(1.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — certain goods</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>This section does not apply to goods to which paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) applies.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 72(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 28(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition <DefinedTermEn>duties</DefinedTermEn> does not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>duties</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) does not apply for the purposes of subsections (1) and (2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>Section 31 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Release</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>Subject to section 19, no goods shall be removed from a customs office, sufferance warehouse, bonded warehouse or duty free shop by any person other than an officer in the performance of his or her duties under this or any other Act of Parliament unless the goods have been released by an officer or by any prescribed means.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Subsections 32(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Release prior to accounting</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In prescribed circumstances and under prescribed conditions, goods may be released prior to the accounting required under subsection (1) if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the importer or owner of the goods makes an interim accounting in the prescribed manner and form and containing the prescribed information, or in the form and containing the information that is satisfactory to the Minister; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the goods have been authorized by an officer or by any prescribed means for delivery to, and have been received at, the place of business of the importer, owner or consignee of the goods.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accounting after release</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If goods are released under subsection (2), they shall be accounted for within the prescribed time and in the manner described in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) by, in the case of goods to which paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) applies, the person who made the interim accounting under that paragraph in respect of the goods and, in the case of goods to which paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) applies, by the importer or owner of the goods.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 152</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>Subsection 32.2(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Diversions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The obligation under this section to make a correction to a declaration of tariff classification includes an obligation to correct a declaration of tariff classification that is rendered incorrect by a failure, after the goods are accounted for under subsection 32(1), (3) or (5) or, in the case of prescribed goods, after the goods are released without accounting, to comply with a condition imposed under a tariff item in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> or under any regulations made under that Act in respect of a tariff item in that List.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 32.2:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Diversion of goods used as ships’ stores</MarginalNote><Label>32.3</Label><Text>If goods are removed or caused to be removed for use as ships’ stores under paragraph 19(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), and the goods are subsequently diverted to another use, the person who diverted the goods shall, at the time of the diversion,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>report the diversion to an officer at a customs office;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>account for the goods in the prescribed manner and in the prescribed form containing the prescribed information; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay as duties on the goods an amount equal to the amount of duties that would be payable on like goods imported in like condition at the time of the diversion.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 153</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>Section 33.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Section 33.3 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1); 1994, c. 47, s. 70; 1995, c. 41, s. 9; 1997, c. 36, s. 154</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Text>Section 33.4 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Interest</MarginalNote><Label>33.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), any person who is liable to pay an amount of duties in respect of imported goods shall pay, in addition to the amount, interest at the specified rate for the period beginning on the first day after the day the person became liable to pay the amount and ending on the day the amount has been paid in full, calculated on the outstanding balance of the amount.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When duties deemed payable</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), any duties in respect of goods payable under paragraph 59(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 65(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of this Act or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> are deemed to have become payable on the day duties became payable in respect of the goods under this Part or that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest-free period</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an amount of duties in respect of goods that is payable by a person under paragraph 59(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 65(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) in accordance with a determination, re-determination or further re-determination made under this Act is paid by the person or if an amount of duties in respect of goods that is payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> in accordance with a determination or re-determination made under that Act is paid by the importer in Canada within thirty days after the day the determination, re-determination or further re-determination, as the case may be, is made (in this subsection referred to as the “decision day”), interest is not payable under subsection (1) on the amount for the period beginning on the day after the decision day and ending on the day the amount is paid.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>Section 33.6 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 33.7(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person accounts for the goods within the extended time, no penalty shall be imposed under section 109.1; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 33.7(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person pays that amount within the time as so extended, subsection 33.4(1) shall apply in respect of that amount as if the time had not been so extended, but interest payable under that subsection in respect of that amount shall be computed at the prescribed rate rather than at the specified rate; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>Section 33.8 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 44, s. 83</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 35.02(1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 44, s. 83</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 35.02(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 44, s. 83</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 35.02(4) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Goods imported from a NAFTA country</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a person imports goods of a prescribed class from a NAFTA country, that person is not liable to a penalty under section 109.1 unless</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 44, s. 83</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 35.02(5) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 44, s. 85; 1995, c. 41, s. 15; 1997, c. 36, s. 159</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>Subsections 40(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Importers’ records</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who imports goods or causes goods to be imported for sale or for any industrial, occupational, commercial, institutional or other like use or any other use that may be prescribed shall keep at the person’s place of business in Canada or at any other place that may be designated by the Minister any records in respect of those goods in any manner and for any period of time that may be prescribed and shall, where an officer so requests, make them available to the officer, within the time specified by the officer, and answer truthfully any questions asked by the officer in respect of the records.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister’s request</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, in the opinion of the Minister, a person has not kept records in accordance with subsection (1), the Minister may request that person to comply with that subsection in respect of the records.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirement to keep records</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The following persons shall keep at their place of business or at any other place that may be designated by the Minister the prescribed records with respect to the prescribed goods, in the manner and for the period that may be prescribed, and shall, where an officer requests, make them available to the officer, within the time specified by the officer, and answer truthfully any questions asked by the officer in respect of the records:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who is granted a licence under section 24;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who receives goods authorized for delivery to the person’s place of business in the circumstances set out in paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who is authorized under paragraph 32(6)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or subsection 32(7) to account for goods;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who is granted a certificate under section 90 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who is granted a licence under section 91 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Text>Section 42 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>dwelling-house</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>dwelling-house</DefinedTermEn> means the whole or any part of a building or structure that is kept or occupied as a permanent or temporary residence, and includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a building within the curtilage of a dwelling-house that is connected to it by a doorway or by a covered and enclosed passageway; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a unit that is designed to be mobile and to be used as a permanent or temporary residence and that is being used as such a residence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inspections</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer, or an officer within a class of officers, designated by the Minister for the purposes of this section, may at all reasonable times, for any purpose related to the administration or enforcement of this Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>inspect, audit or examine any record of a person that relates or may relate to the information that is or should be in the records of the person or to any amount paid or payable under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>examine property in an inventory of a person and any property or process of, or matter relating to, the person, an examination of which may assist the officer in determining the accuracy of the inventory of the person or in ascertaining the information that is or should be in the records of the person or any amount paid or payable by the person under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (3), enter any premises or place where any business is carried on, any property is kept, anything is done in connection with any business or any records are or should be kept; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require the owner or manager of the property or business and any other person on the premises or place to give the officer all reasonable assistance and to answer truthfully any question, and, for that purpose, require the owner, manager or other person designated by the owner or manager to attend at the premises or place with the officer.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prior authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If any premises or place referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) is a dwelling-house, an officer may not enter that dwelling-house without the consent of the occupant except under the authority of a warrant under subsection (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application by the Minister, a judge may issue a warrant authorizing an officer to enter a dwelling-house subject to the conditions that may be specified in the warrant, if the judge is satisfied by information on oath that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>there are reasonable grounds to believe that the dwelling-house is a premises or place referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>entry into the dwelling-house is necessary; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>entry into the dwelling-house has been, or there are reasonable grounds to believe that entry into the dwelling-house will be, refused.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other access to document</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the judge is not satisfied that entry into that dwelling-house is necessary for any purpose relating to the administration or enforcement of this Act but is satisfied that access to a document or property that is or should be kept in the dwelling-house has been or may be expected to be refused, the judge may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>order the occupant of the dwelling-house to provide the officer with reasonable access to any document or property; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make any other order that is appropriate in the circumstances to carry out the purposes of this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 160</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>Section 42.01 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Methods of verification</MarginalNote><Label>42.01</Label><Text>An officer, or an officer within a class of officers, designated by the Minister for the purposes of this section may conduct a verification of origin (other than a verification of origin referred to in section 42.1), verification of tariff classification or verification of value for duty in respect of imported goods in the manner that is prescribed and may for that purpose at all reasonable times enter any prescribed premises.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 163</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 42.3(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prise d’effet de la révision ou du réexamen</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sous réserve du paragraphe (4), si, à la suite de la révision ou du réexamen, en application du paragraphe 59(1), de l’origine de marchandises qui font l’objet d’une demande visant l’obtention du traitement tarifaire préférentiel de l’ALÉNA ou de celui de l’ALÉCC et dont la vérification de l’origine est prévue par la présente loi, celles-ci ne peuvent pas bénéficier du traitement tarifaire préférentiel demandé pour le motif que le classement tarifaire ou la valeur d’une matière ou d’un matériel ou de plusieurs matières ou matériels utilisés pour la production de ces marchandises diffère du classement ou de la valeur correspondants de ces matières ou matériels dans le pays d’exportation — pays ALÉNA ou Chili —, la prise d’effet de la révision ou du réexamen est subordonnée à leur notification à l’importateur et à la personne qui a rempli et signé le certificat d’origine des marchandises.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 163</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 42.3(4) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report de la date de prise d’effet</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>La date de prise d’effet de la révision ou du réexamen de l’origine visé au paragraphe (2) est reportée pour une période maximale de quatre-vingt-dix jours, si le ministre est convaincu que l’importateur des marchandises ou la personne qui a rempli et signé le certificat d’origine de celles-ci a démontré qu’il s’est fondé de bonne foi, à son détriment, sur le classement tarifaire ou la détermination de la valeur des matières ou matériels visés à ce paragraphe effectués par l’administration douanière du pays ALÉNA d’exportation des marchandises ou du Chili, selon le cas.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 30, s. 160</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>Subsection 43(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Production of records</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, for any purpose related to the administration or enforcement of this Act, including the collection of any amount owing under this Act by any person, by notice served personally or sent by registered or certified mail, require any person to provide any record at a place specified by the Minister and within any reasonable time that may be stipulated in the notice.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36.</Label><Text>Subsection 43.1(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), by adding the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the tariff classification of the goods.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37.</Label><Text>Subsection 51(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>time of importation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>time of importation</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of goods other than those to which paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) applies, the date on which an officer authorizes the release of the goods under this Act or the date on which their release is authorized by any prescribed means; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of goods to which paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) applies, the date on which the goods are received at the place of business of the importer, owner or consignee.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38.</Label><Text>Section 54 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Marchandises exportées au Canada en passant par un autre pays</MarginalNote><Label>54.</Label><Text>Pour l’application des articles 45 à 55, les marchandises provenant d’un pays qui sont exportées au Canada en passant par un autre pays sont considérées, sous réserve des conditions réglementaires, comme ayant été expédiées directement au Canada à partir du premier pays.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 165</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 57.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Marking determination</MarginalNote><Label>57.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any officer, or any officer within a class of officers, designated by the Minister for the purposes of this section may, at or before the time goods imported from a NAFTA country are accounted for under subsection 32(1), (3) or (5), in the prescribed manner and subject to the prescribed conditions, make a determination as to whether the goods have been marked in the manner referred to in section 35.01.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 165</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 57.01(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Décision présumée</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Dans le cas où l’agent ne rend pas sa décision au plus tard au moment de la déclaration en détail des marchandises prévue aux paragraphes 32(1), (3) ou (5), celles-ci sont réputées marquées conformément à l’article 35.01 sur le fondement des déclarations faites par l’auteur de la déclaration en détail.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Text>Paragraph 57.1(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the tariff classification of imported goods is to be determined in accordance with sections 10 and 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, unless otherwise provided in that Act; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 59(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a determination under section 57.01 or 58, re-determine the origin, tariff classification, value for duty or marking determination of any imported goods at any time within</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 59(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice requirement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer who makes a determination under subsection 57.01(1) or 58(1) or a re-determination or further re-determination under subsection (1) shall without delay give notice of the determination, re-determination or further re-determination, including the rationale on which it is made, to the prescribed persons.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 59(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment or refund</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every prescribed person who is given notice of a determination, re-determination or further re-determination under subsection (2) shall, in accordance with that decision,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay any amount owing, or additional amount owing, as the case may be, as duties in respect of the goods or, if a request is made under section 60, pay that amount or give security satisfactory to the Minister in respect of that amount and any interest owing or that may become owing on that amount; or</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 59(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amounts payable immediately</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any amount owing by or to a person under subsection (3) or 66(3) in respect of goods, other than an amount in respect of which security is given, is payable immediately, whether or not a request is made under section 60.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 60(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Request for re-determination or further re-determination</MarginalNote><Label>60.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person to whom notice is given under subsection 59(2) in respect of goods may, within ninety days after the notice is given, request a re-determination or further re-determination of origin, tariff classification, value for duty or marking. The request may be made only after all amounts owing as duties and interest in respect of the goods are paid or security satisfactory to the Minister is given in respect of the total amount owing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person may request a review of an advance ruling made under section 43.1 within ninety days after it is given to the person.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 60(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>la confirmation, la modification ou l’annulation de la décision anticipée;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 60(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>re-determine or further re-determine the marking determination.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 60:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time to make a request</MarginalNote><Label>60.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If no request is made under section 60 within the time set out in that section, a person may make an application to the Commissioner for an extension of the time within which the request may be made, and the Commissioner may extend the time for making the request.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must set out the reasons why the request was not made on time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>How application made</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The application must be made to the Commissioner in the prescribed manner and form and contain the prescribed information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties of Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On receipt of an application, the Commissioner must, without delay, consider it and notify the person making the application, in writing, of the Commissioner’s decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Date of request</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the Commissioner grants the application, the request is valid as of the date of the Commissioner’s decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for granting application</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>No application may be granted unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application is made within one year after the expiry of the time set out in section 60; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person making the application demonstrates that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within the time set out in section 60, the person was unable to act or to give a mandate to act in the person’s name or the person had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to make a request,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the application was made as soon as circumstances permitted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time by Canadian International Trade Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>60.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who has made an application under section 60.1 may apply to the Canadian International Trade Tribunal to have the application granted after either</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Commissioner has refused the application; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ninety days have elapsed after the application was made and the Commissioner has not notified the person of the Commissioner’s decision.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>If paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) applies, the application under this subsection must be made within ninety days after the application is refused.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>How application made</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must be made by filing with the Commissioner and the Secretary of the Canadian International Trade Tribunal a copy of the application referred to in section 60.1 and, if notice has been given under subsection 60.1(4), a copy of the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of Canadian International Trade Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Canadian International Trade Tribunal may dispose of an application by dismissing or granting it and, in granting an application, it may impose any terms that it considers just or order that the request be deemed to be a valid request as of the date of the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When application to be granted</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No application may be granted under this section unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application under subsection 60.1(1) was made within one year after the expiry of the time set out in section 60; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person making the application demonstrates that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within the time set out in section 60, the person was unable to act or to give a mandate to act in the person’s name or the person had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to make a request,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the application was made as soon as circumstances permitted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 61(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>at any time, if the person who is given notice of a marking determination under section 57.01 or of a re-determination under paragraph 59(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) fails to comply with any provision of this Act or the regulations or commits an offence under this Act in respect of the goods,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 16(1)</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 65(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>soit verser tout complément de droits dû sur les marchandises ou, si appel a été interjeté en vertu de l’article 67, payer cette somme ou donner la garantie, jugée satisfaisante par le ministre, du versement de ce complément et des intérêts échus ou à échoir sur ce complément;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 16(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 65(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amount owing or refund payable immediately</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any amount owing by or to a person under subsection (1) or 66(3) of this Act or as a result of a determination or re-determination under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> in respect of goods, other than an amount in respect of which security is given, is payable immediately, whether or not an appeal is taken under section 67 of this Act or subsection 61(1) of that Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46.</Label><Text>Section 65.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — marking determinations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>This section does not apply to a marking determination.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 168</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 66(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Interest on payments</MarginalNote><Label>66.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the amount paid by a person on account of duties expected to be owing under paragraph 59(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or 65(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of this Act or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> exceeds the amount of duties, if any, owing as a result of a determination, re-determination or further re-determination, the person shall be paid, in addition to the excess amount, interest at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the first day after the day the amount was paid and ending on the day the determination, re-determination or further re-determination, as the case may be, was made, calculated on the excess amount.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 168</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 66(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest on refunds</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who is given a refund under paragraph 59(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or 65(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of this Act or under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> of an amount paid shall be given, in addition to the refund, interest at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the first day after the day the amount was paid and ending on the day the refund is given, calculated on the amount of the refund.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 169; 1999, c. 17, par. 127(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>48.</Label><Text>Subsection 67(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Appel devant le Tribunal canadien du commerce extérieur</MarginalNote><Label>67.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Toute personne qui s’estime lésée par une décision du commissaire rendue conformément aux articles 60 ou 61 peut en interjeter appel devant le Tribunal canadien du commerce extérieur en déposant par écrit un avis d’appel auprès du commissaire et du secrétaire de ce Tribunal dans les quatre-vingt-dix jours suivant la notification de l’avis de décision.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 67:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time to appeal</MarginalNote><Label>67.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If no notice of appeal has been filed within the time set out in section 67, a person may make an application to the Canadian International Trade Tribunal for an order extending the time within which a notice of appeal may be filed, and the Tribunal may make an order extending the time for appealing and may impose any terms that it considers just.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must set out the reasons why the notice of appeal was not filed on time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>How application made</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The application must be made by filing with the Commissioner and the Secretary of the Canadian International Trade Tribunal the application accompanied by the notice of appeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for granting application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No order may be made under this section unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application is made within one year after the expiry of the time set out in section 67; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person making the application demonstrates that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within the time set out in section 67 for appealing, the person was unable to act or to give a mandate to act in the person’s name or the person had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to appeal,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the application was made as soon as circumstances permitted, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>there are reasonable grounds for the appeal.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 19(1)</MarginalNote><Label>50.</Label><Text>Subsection 69(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Remboursement en cas d’appel</MarginalNote><Label>69.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>La personne qui interjette appel, en vertu des articles 67 ou 68, d’une décision portant sur des marchandises, après avoir versé une somme à titre de droits et d’intérêts sur celles-ci, et qui donne la garantie, jugée satisfaisante par le ministre, du versement de la partie impayée des droits et intérêts dus sur les marchandises et de tout ou partie de la somme versée à titre de droits et d’intérêts (sauf les intérêts payés en raison du non-paiement de droits dans le délai prévu au paragraphe 32(5) ou à l’article 33) sur les marchandises, est remboursée de tout ou partie de la somme versée pour laquelle la garantie a été donnée.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 74(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>d’une part, le réclamant donne à l’agent toute possibilité d’examiner les marchandises en cause ou, d’une façon générale, d’apprécier les motifs de la réclamation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 74 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Refund without application</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister, within four years after goods are accounted for under subsection 32(1), (3) or (5), may refund all or part of duties paid on imported goods without application by the person who paid them if it is determined that the duties were overpaid or paid in error in any of the circumstances set out in</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), only to the extent that the refund is not based on tariff classification, value for duty or origin of the goods.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties that may not be refunded</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The duties that may be refunded under subsection (6) do not include duties or taxes levied under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or a surtax or temporary duty imposed under Division 4 of Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of refund</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>A person of a prescribed class may apply, within four years after goods are accounted for under subsection 32(1), (3) or (5), in prescribed circumstances and under prescribed conditions, the amount of any refund to which they are entitled under this section to the payment of any amount for which they are liable or may become liable under this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52.</Label><Text>Subsection 76(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Marchandises défectueuses</MarginalNote><Label>76.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sous réserve des règlements pris en vertu de l’article 81, le ministre peut, dans les circonstances prévues par règlement, accorder à une personne le remboursement de tout ou partie des droits qu’elle a payés sur des marchandises importées qui, d’une part, sont défectueuses, de qualité inférieure à celle pour laquelle il y a eu paiement ou différentes des marchandises commandées et, d’autre part, après leur importation, ont, sans frais pour Sa Majesté du chef du Canada, été aliénées conformément à des modalités acceptées par le ministre, ou ont été exportées.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 20(1); 1997, c. 36, s. 178</MarginalNote><Label>53.</Label><Text>Section 80 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Interest on refunds</MarginalNote><Label>80.</Label><Text>Any person who is granted a refund of duties under section 74, 76 or 79 shall be granted, in addition to the refund, interest on the refund at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the ninety-first day after the day an application for the refund is received in accordance with paragraph 74(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and ending on the day the refund is granted.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 180</MarginalNote><Label>54.</Label><Text>Subsection 80.2(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Excess to be repaid — paragraph 74(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an abatement or refund is granted to a person under paragraph 74(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) and the goods are sold or otherwise disposed of or are subsequently used in a manner that fails to comply with a condition imposed under a tariff item in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, or under any regulations made under that Act in respect of a tariff item in that List, the person who was granted the refund or abatement shall, within ninety days after the failure to comply,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>report the failure to an officer at a customs office; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay to Her Majesty in right of Canada any amount to which they are not entitled, together with any interest that was granted to the person under section 80 or 80.1 on that amount.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>55.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 95(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>à la demande de l’agent, lui présenter les marchandises et les déballer, ainsi que décharger les moyens de transport et en ouvrir les parties, ouvrir ou défaire les colis et autres contenants que l’agent veut examiner.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 95(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Written report</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If goods are required to be reported in writing, they shall be reported in the prescribed form containing the prescribed information or in such form containing such information as is satisfactory to the Minister.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 14, s. 44</MarginalNote><Label>56.</Label><Text>Subsection 97.1(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Modification du certificat</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>La personne qui a rempli et signé le certificat et qui a des motifs de croire que celui-ci contient des renseignements inexacts communique sans délai à tout destinataire du certificat les renseignements corrigés.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 14, s. 45</MarginalNote><Label>57.</Label><Text>Subsection 97.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exporters’ or producers’ records</MarginalNote><Label>97.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who exports goods or causes them to be exported for sale or for any industrial, occupational, commercial, institutional or other like use or any other use that may be prescribed, and every other person who has completed and signed a certificate in accordance with subsection 97.1(1), shall keep at the person’s place of business in Canada or at any other place that may be designated by the Minister any records in respect of those goods in the manner and for the period that may be prescribed and shall, if an officer requests, make them available to the officer, within the time specified by the officer, and answer any questions asked by the officer in respect of the records.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>58.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 97.2:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><Label>PART V.1</Label><TitleText>COLLECTIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>97.21</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in this Part.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>debtor</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>débiteur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>debtor</DefinedTermEn> means a person liable to pay an amount owing or payable in accordance with this Act.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>juge</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn> means a judge of a superior court having jurisdiction in the province where a matter arises or a judge of the Federal Court.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>receiver</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>séquestre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>receiver</DefinedTermEn> means a person who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under the authority of a debenture, bond or other debt security, a court order or an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province, is empowered to operate or manage a business or a property of another person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is appointed by a trustee under a trust deed in respect of a debt security to exercise the authority of the trustee to manage or operate a business or a property of the debtor under the debt security;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is appointed by a bank to act as agent of the bank in the exercise of the authority of the bank under subsection 426(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bank Act</XRefExternal> in respect of property of another person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is appointed as a liquidator to liquidate the assets of a corporation or to wind up the affairs of a corporation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is appointed as a committee, guardian or curator with authority to manage and care for the affairs and assets of an individual who is incapable of managing those affairs and assets.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedDefinition><Text>It includes a person who is appointed to exercise the authority of a creditor under a debenture, bond or other debt security to operate or manage a business or a property of another person. However, if a person is so appointed it does not include that creditor.</Text></ContinuedDefinition></Definition></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Debts to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>97.22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3), any duties, fee, charge or other amount owing or payable under this Act is a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada from and after the time such amount should have been paid, and any person from whom the amount is owing shall, after a notice of arrears is sent by mail addressed to the person at their latest known address or delivered to that address, pay the amount owing as indicated in the notice or appeal the notice under section 97.23.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Penalty or ascertained forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any amount of money demanded as a penalty in a notice of assessment served under section 109.3 and any interest payable under section 109.5 or any amount of money demanded in a notice under section 124 and any interest payable under subsection 124(6), from and after the time of service, is a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada from the person on whom the notice is served and the person shall pay that amount or, within ninety days after the time of service, request a decision of the Minister under section 131.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amounts demanded by the Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any amount of money demanded under paragraph 133(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (1.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and any interest payable under subsection 133(7), from and after the time notice is served under subsection 131(2), is a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada from the person who requested the decision and the person shall pay the amount so demanded or, if the person appeals the decision of the Minister under section 135, give security satisfactory to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court costs</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If an amount is payable by a person to Her Majesty in right of Canada because of an order, judgment or award of a court in respect of the costs of litigation relating to a matter to which this Act applies, sections 97.24, 97.26, 97.28 and 97.3 to 97.33 apply to the amount as if the amount were a debt owing by the person to Her Majesty on account of duties payable by the person under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Any amount payable under this Act is recoverable in the Federal Court or any other court of competent jurisdiction or in any other manner provided under this Part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest on judgments</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If a judgment is obtained for any amount payable under this Act, including a certificate registered under section 97.24, the provisions of this Act under which interest is payable for failure to pay the amount apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, to a failure to pay the judgment debt, and the interest is recoverable in the same manner as the judgment debt.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>97.23</Label><Text>A person to whom a notice is sent or delivered under subsection 97.22(1) may, within thirty days after that notice is sent, appeal the notice by way of an action in the Federal Court in which the person is the plaintiff and the Minister is the defendant if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no appeal is or was available to that person under section 67 or 68 in respect of the same matter; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the notice is not in respect of an amount assessed under section 97.44.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Certificates, Liens and Set-off</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>97.24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any debt, or any part of a debt, due to Her Majesty in right of Canada under this Act may be certified by the Minister as an amount payable by the debtor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration in court</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On production to the Federal Court, the certificate must be registered in the Court. When it is registered, it has the same force and effect, and all proceedings may be taken, as if the certificate were a judgment obtained in the Court for a debt of the amount specified in the certificate and interest on the amount as provided under this Act. For the purposes of any such proceedings, the certificate is a judgment of the Court against the debtor and enforceable as such.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Costs</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>All reasonable costs and charges for the registration of the certificate or in respect of any proceedings taken to collect the amount certified are recoverable in the same way as if they had been certified in the certificate registered under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protected interest in property</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A memorial may be recorded for the purpose of creating a protected interest in property in a province or an interest in such property held by the debtor in the same manner as a document evidencing the following may be recorded in accordance with the law of the province:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a judgment of the superior court of the province against a person for a debt owing by the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an amount payable by a person in the province in respect of a debt owing to Her Majesty in right of the province.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Creation of protected interest</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The effect of recording a memorial is, in the same manner and to the same extent as if the memorial were a document evidencing a judgment or an amount referred to in subsection (4), to create a protected interest in the property of the debtor in the province, or in any interest in that property, held by the debtor or to otherwise bind that property or interest in the property. The protected interest created is subordinate to any protected interest in respect of which all steps necessary to make it effective against other creditors were taken before the time the memorial was recorded.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proceedings in respect of memorial</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If a memorial is recorded in a province, proceedings may be taken, in the same manner and to the same extent as if the memorial were a document evidencing a judgment or an amount referred to in subsection (4), in the province in respect of the memorial, including proceedings</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to enforce payment of the amount evidenced by the memorial, interest on the amount and all costs and charges paid or incurred in respect of the recording of the memorial and proceedings taken to collect the amount;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to renew or otherwise prolong the effectiveness of the recording of the memorial;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to cancel or withdraw the memorial wholly or in respect of any of the property or interests affected by the memorial; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to postpone the effectiveness of the recording of the memorial in favour of any protected interest that has been or is intended to be recorded in respect of any property or interest affected by the memorial.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Federal Court may make order, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If in any proceeding or as a condition precedent to any proceeding referred to in subsection (6) any order, consent or ruling is required under the law of a province to be made or given by the superior court of the province or by a judge or official of the court, a like order, consent or ruling may be made or given by the Federal Court or by a judge or official of the Federal Court and, when so made or given, has the same effect for the purposes of the proceeding as if it were made or given by the superior court of the province or by a judge or official of the court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Presentation of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If a memorial, or a document relating to it, is presented for recording, for the purpose of any proceeding referred to in subsection (6), to any official in the land, personal property or other registry system of a province, it is to be accepted for recording in the same manner and to the same extent as if the memorial or document were a document evidencing a judgment or an amount referred to in subsection (4) for the purpose of a like proceeding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Access for recording</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If access is sought to any person, place or thing in a province for the purpose of recording a memorial, or a document relating to it, the access must be granted in the same manner and to the same extent as if the memorial or document were a document evidencing a judgment or an amount referred to in subsection (4) for the purpose of a like proceeding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence deemed to have been provided</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>If a memorial or document is issued by the Federal Court or signed or certified by a judge or official of the Court, any affidavit, declaration or other evidence required under the law of the province to be provided with or to accompany the memorial or document in the proceeding is deemed to have been provided with or to have accompanied the memorial or document as so required.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — sale, etc., without consent</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Despite any law of Canada or of a province, no sheriff or other person may, without the written consent of the Minister, sell or otherwise dispose of any property or publish any notice or otherwise advertise in respect of any sale or other disposition of any property pursuant to any process issued or protected interest created in any proceeding to collect an amount certified in a certificate, any interest on the amount and any costs.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent consent</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (11), if the Minister’s consent is subsequently given, any property that would have been affected by a process or protected interest referred to in that subsection had the Minister’s consent been given at the time the process was issued or the protected interest was created is bound, seized, attached, charged or otherwise affected as if that consent had been given at the time the process was issued or the protected interest was created, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Completion of notices, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>If information required to be set out by any sheriff or other person in a minute, notice or document required to be completed for any purpose cannot, because of subsection (11), be so set out, the sheriff or other person must complete the minute, notice or document to the extent possible without that information and, when the consent of the Minister is given, a further minute, notice or document setting out all the information is to be completed for the same purpose. The sheriff or other person is deemed to have complied with any law or rule of court requiring the information to be set out in the minute, notice or document.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application for an order</MarginalNote><Label>(14)</Label><Text>A sheriff or other person who is unable, because of subsection (11) or (13), to comply with any law or rule of court is bound by any order made by a judge of the Federal Court, on an <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application by the Minister, for the purpose of giving effect to the proceeding or protected interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Secured claims</MarginalNote><Label>(15)</Label><Text>A protected interest that is registered in accordance with subsection 87(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> is deemed to be a claim that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is secured by a security and that, subject to subsection 87(2) of that Act, ranks as a secured claim under that Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is referred to in paragraph 86(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Details in certificates and memorials</MarginalNote><Label>(16)</Label><Text>Despite any law of Canada or of a province, in any certificate in respect of a debtor, in any memorial evidencing the certificate or in any writ or document issued for the purpose of collecting an amount certified, it is sufficient for all purposes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to set out, as the amount payable by the debtor, the total of amounts payable by the debtor without setting out the separate amounts making up that total; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to refer to the rate of interest to be charged on the separate amounts making up the amount payable in general terms as interest at the rate prescribed under this Act applicable from time to time on amounts payable to the Receiver General, without indicating the specific rates of interest to be charged on each of the separate amounts or to be charged for any particular period of time.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(17)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>memorial</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>extrait</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>memorial</DefinedTermEn> means a document issued by the Federal Court evidencing a certificate registered under subsection (2) in respect of a debtor and includes a writ of that Court issued pursuant to the certificate or any notification of the document or writ.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>protected interest</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>droit garanti</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>protected interest</DefinedTermEn> means a charge, lien, prior claim, priority on or binding interest in property.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>enregistrement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a memorial, means to file, register or otherwise record the memorial.</Text></Definition></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Detention of and lien on imported or exported goods</MarginalNote><Label>97.25</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any goods reported for exportation under section 95 or imported by or on behalf of a debtor are subject to a lien for the amount owed by the debtor and may be detained by an officer at the expense of the debtor until that amount is paid.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conveyances</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any conveyance used for the importation of goods in respect of which a notice under section 109.3 has been served is subject to a lien for the amount owed by the debtor and may be detained by an officer at the expense of the person on whom the notice was served until the amount set out in the notice is paid.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sale of detained goods</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister, on giving 30 days notice in writing to the debtor at the debtor’s latest known address, may direct that any goods imported or reported for exportation by or on behalf of the debtor, or any conveyance, that has been detained be sold by public auction or public tender or by the Minister of Public Works and Government Services under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Surplus Crown Assets Act</XRefExternal>, subject to such regulations as may be made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proceeds of sale</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The proceeds of any sale shall be applied to amounts owed by the debtor, any expenses incurred by Her Majesty in right of Canada in respect of the goods sold and any duties on the goods and the surplus, if any, shall be paid to the debtor.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Set-off</MarginalNote><Label>97.26</Label><Text>The Minister may require that an amount specified by the Minister be deducted from or set-off against an amount that is or may become payable to a debtor by Her Majesty in Right of Canada. If an amount payable to a person under a provision of this Act has at any time been deducted or set-off, the amount is deemed to have been paid to the debtor at that time under that provision and to have been paid by the debtor at that time on account of the debt to Her Majesty.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Refund may be applied against liabilities</MarginalNote><Label>97.27</Label><Text>The Minister may, if a person is or is about to become liable to make any payment to Her Majesty in right of Canada or in right of a province, apply the amount of any drawback, refund or relief granted under section 74 or 76 of this Act or section 89, 101 or 113 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> to that other liability and notify the person of that action.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Garnishment and Non-arm’s Length Transfers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Garnishment — general</MarginalNote><Label>97.28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister has knowledge or suspects that a person is or will be, within one year, liable to make a payment to a debtor, the Minister may, by notice in writing, require the person to pay without delay, if the moneys are immediately payable, and, in any other case, as and when the moneys become payable, the moneys otherwise payable to the debtor in whole or in part to the Receiver General on account of the debtor’s liability under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Garnishment — institutions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by notice in writing, require the following institutions or persons to pay in whole or in part to the Receiver General on account of a debtor’s liability the moneys that would otherwise be loaned, advanced or paid if the Minister has knowledge or suspects that within ninety days</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a bank, credit union, trust company or other similar person (in this section referred to as the “institution”) will loan or advance moneys to, or make a payment on behalf of, or make a payment in respect of a negotiable instrument issued by, a debtor who is indebted to the institution and who has granted security in respect of the indebtedness; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person, other than an institution, will loan or advance moneys to, or make a payment on behalf of, a debtor who the Minister knows or suspects</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is employed by, or is engaged in providing services or property to, that person or was or will be, within ninety days, so employed or engaged, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if that person is a corporation, is not dealing at arm’s length with that person.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>Any moneys so paid to the Receiver General are deemed to have been loaned, advanced or paid to the debtor.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of receipt</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A receipt issued by the Minister for moneys paid as required under this section is a good and sufficient discharge of the original liability to the extent of the payment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Periodic payments</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Minister has, under this section, required a person to pay to the Receiver General on account of the liability under this Act of a debtor moneys otherwise payable by the person to the debtor as interest, rent, remuneration, a dividend, an annuity or other periodic payment, the requirement applies to all such payments to be made by the person to the debtor until the liability under this Act is satisfied, and operates to require payments to the Receiver General out of each such payment of such amount as is required by the Minister in a notice in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Failure to comply</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with a requirement under subsection (1) or (4) is liable to pay to Her Majesty in right of Canada an amount equal to the amount that the person was required under that subsection to pay to the Receiver General.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Failure to comply — institutions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Every institution or person that fails to comply with a requirement under subsection (2) is liable to pay to Her Majesty in right of Canada an amount equal to the lesser of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the total of moneys loaned, advanced or paid to the debtor, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount that the institution or person was required under that subsection to pay to the Receiver General.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Service</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If a person carries on business under a name or style other than the person’s own name, notification to the person of a requirement under subsection (1) or (2) may be addressed to the name or style under which the person carries on business and, in the case of personal service, is validly served if it is left with an adult person employed at the place of business of the addressee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Service — partnerships</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If persons carry on business in partnership, notification to the persons of a requirement under subsection (1) or (2) may be addressed to the partnership name and, in the case of personal service, is deemed to be validly served if it is served on one of the partners or left with an adult person employed at the place of business of the partnership.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of payment as required</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If an amount that would otherwise have been payable to or on behalf of a debtor is paid by a person to the Receiver General pursuant to a notice served on the person under this section or pursuant to an assessment under section 97.44, the person is deemed, for all purposes, to have paid the amount to or on behalf of the debtor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application to Her Majesty in right of a province</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Provisions of this Part that provide that a person who has been required by the Minister to pay to the Receiver General an amount that would otherwise be loaned, advanced or paid to a debtor who is liable to make a payment under this Act apply to Her Majesty in right of a province.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Liability — non-arm’s length transfers</MarginalNote><Label>97.29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person transfers property, either directly or indirectly, by means of a trust or by any other means, to the transferor’s spouse or common-law partner or an individual who has since become the transferor’s spouse or common-law partner, an individual who was under eighteen years of age, or another person with whom the transferor was not dealing at arm’s length, the transferee and transferor are jointly and severally or solidarily liable to pay an amount equal to the lesser of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount determined by the formula</Text><FormulaGroup><Formula><FormulaText>A – B</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>A</FormulaTerm><Text>is the amount, if any, by which the fair market value of the property at the time of transfer exceeds the fair market value at that time of the consideration given by the transferee for the transfer of the property, and</Text></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>B</FormulaTerm><Text>is the amount, if any, by which the amount assessed the transferee under subsection 325(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> and subsection 160(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> in respect of the property exceeds the amount paid by the transferor in respect of the amount so assessed, and</Text></FormulaDefinition></FormulaGroup></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the total of all amounts each of which is</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an amount that the transferor is liable to pay under this Act, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>interest or a penalty for which the transferor is liable as of the time of transfer.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>However, nothing in this subsection limits the liability of the transferor under any other provision of this Act.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fair market value of undivided interest</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of this section, the fair market value at any time of an undivided interest in a property, expressed as a proportionate interest in that property, is, subject to subsection (4), equal to the same proportion of the fair market value of that property at that time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rules applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a transferor and transferee have, under subsection (1), become jointly and severally or solidarily liable in respect of all or part of the liability of the transferor under this Act, the following rules apply:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a payment by the transferee on account of the transferee’s liability discharges, to the extent of the payment, the joint liability; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a payment by the transferor on account of the transferor’s liability discharges the transferee’s liability only to the extent that the payment operates to reduce the transferor’s liability to an amount less than the amount in respect of which the transferee was made jointly and severally or solidarily liable.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfers to spouse or common-law partner</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), if at any time a debtor transfers property to the debtor’s spouse or common-law partner under a decree, order or judgment of a competent tribunal or under a written separation agreement and, at that time, the debtor and the debtor’s spouse or common-law partner were separated and living apart as a result of the breakdown of their marriage or common-law partnership (as defined in subsection 248(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>), for the purposes of paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the fair market value at that time of the property so transferred is deemed to be nil. However, nothing in this subsection limits the liability of the debtor under any other provision of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Related persons</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>related persons are deemed not to deal with each other at arm’s length, and it is a question of fact whether persons not related to each other were, at any particular time, dealing with each other at arm’s length;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>persons are related to each other if they are related persons within the meaning of subsections 251(2) to (6) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, except that references in those subsections to “corporation” are to be read as references to “corporation or partnership”, and references in those subsections to “shares” or “shareholders” are, in respect of a partnership, to be read as references to “rights” or “partners”, respectively; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a member of a partnership is deemed to be related to the partnership.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>common-law partner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>conjoint de fait</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>common-law partner</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 248(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> except that references to “taxpayer” in that definition are to be read as references to “debtor”.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>common-law partnership</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>union de fait</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>common-law partnership</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 248(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>property</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>bien</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>property</DefinedTermEn> includes money.</Text></Definition></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Acquisition of Property and Seizures</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Acquisition of debtor’s property</MarginalNote><Label>97.3</Label><Text>For the purpose of collecting amounts owed by a debtor, the Minister may purchase or otherwise acquire any interest in the debtor’s property that the Minister is given a right to acquire in legal proceedings or under a court order or that is offered for sale or redemption, and may dispose of any interest so acquired in any manner that the Minister considers reasonable.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Moneys seized from debtor</MarginalNote><Label>97.31</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister has knowledge or suspects that a person is holding moneys that were seized by a police officer, in the course of administering or enforcing the criminal law of Canada, from a debtor and that are restorable to the debtor, the Minister may, by notice in writing, require that person to turn over the moneys otherwise restorable to the debtor, in whole or in part, to the Receiver General on account of the debtor’s liability under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Receipt</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A receipt issued for moneys turned over is a good and sufficient discharge of the requirement to restore the moneys to the debtor to the extent of the amount so turned over.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Seizure of chattels</MarginalNote><Label>97.32</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person fails to pay an amount as required under this Act, the Minister may give thirty days notice to the person by registered or certified mail addressed to the person at their latest known address of the Minister’s intention to direct that the person’s goods and chattels be seized and sold. If the person fails to make the payment before the expiration of the thirty days, the Minister may issue a certificate of the failure and direct that the person’s goods and chattels be seized.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sale of seized property</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Seized property must be kept for ten days at the expense and risk of the owner and, if the owner does not pay the amount due together with all expenses within the ten days, the property seized shall be sold by public auction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of sale</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Except in the case of perishable goods, notice of the sale setting out the time and place of the sale together with a general description of the property to be sold must be published, a reasonable time before the goods are sold, in one or more newspapers of general local circulation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Surplus</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any surplus resulting from a sale, after deduction of the amount owing and all expenses, must be paid or returned to the owner of the property seized.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption from seizure</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Goods and chattels of any person that would be exempt from seizure under a writ of execution issued out of a superior court of the province in which the seizure is made are exempt from seizure under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Person leaving Canada</MarginalNote><Label>97.33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister suspects that a person who is liable to pay an amount under this Act or would be so liable if the time for payment of the amount had arrived has left or is about to leave Canada, the Minister may, before the day otherwise fixed for payment, by notice in writing, demand payment of the amount. Despite any other provision of this Act, the person shall pay the amount immediately.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Failure to pay</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person fails to pay an amount as required, the Minister may direct that the goods and chattels of the person be seized and subsections 97.32(2) to (5) apply.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Collection Restrictions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Collection action delayed</MarginalNote><Label>97.34</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person is liable for the payment of an amount under this Act, if an amount is demanded in a notice served under section 109.3 or 124, or if an amount is demanded under paragraph 133(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or subsection 133(1.1) in a notice served under subsection 131(2), the Minister must not, for the purpose of collecting the amount, take the following actions until the ninety-first day after the day notice is given to the debtor:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>commence legal proceedings in a court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>certify the amount under section 97.24;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require the retention of the amount by way of deduction or set-off under section 97.26;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require a person or institution to make a payment under section 97.28;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require a person to turn over moneys under subsection 97.31(1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>give a notice, issue a certificate or make a direction under subsection 97.32(1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal to Federal Court</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person has appealed a decision of the Minister to the Federal Court under section 97.23 or 135, the Minister must not take any action described in subsection (1) to collect the amount in controversy before the date of the decision of the Court or the day on which the person discontinues the appeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reference to Canadian International Trade Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Commissioner has referred a question to the Canadian International Trade Tribunal under section 70, the Minister must not take any action described in subsection (1) to collect the amount in controversy before the day on which the question is determined by the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a person has made a request under section 60 or 129 or has appealed under section 67 or 68 and the person agrees in writing with the Minister to delay proceedings on the request or appeal, as the case may be, until judgment has been given in another action before the Federal Court, the Canadian International Trade Tribunal or the Supreme Court of Canada, in which action the issue is the same or substantially the same as that raised in the request or appeal of the person, the Minister may take any of the actions described in subsection (1) for the purpose of collecting the amount payable, or a part of the amount payable, determined in a manner consistent with the decision or judgment in the other action at any time after the Minister notifies the person in writing that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the decision of the Canadian International Trade Tribunal or Federal Court in that action has been mailed to the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>judgment has been pronounced by the Federal Court of Appeal in that action; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>judgment has been delivered by the Supreme Court of Canada in that action.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of taking security</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister must not, for the purpose of collecting an amount payable, or a part of an amount payable, under this Act, take any of the actions described in subsection (1) if a person has given security to the Minister when requesting or appealing from a decision of the Commissioner or Minister.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization to proceed immediately</MarginalNote><Label>97.35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 97.34, if, on <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application by the Minister, a judge is satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to believe that the collection of all or any part of an amount assessed or demanded under this Act would be jeopardized by a delay in the collection of that amount, the judge shall, on any terms that the judge considers reasonable in the circumstances, authorize the Minister to immediately take any action described in that section to collect the amount.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice not sent</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An authorization may be granted by a judge notwithstanding that a notice in respect of the amount has not been sent to the debtor at or before the time the application is made if the judge is satisfied that the receipt of the notice by the debtor would likely further jeopardize the collection of the amount and, for the purposes of sections 97.22, 97.24, 97.26, 97.28, 97.31 and 97.32, the amount in respect of which an authorization is granted is deemed to be an amount payable under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Affidavits</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Statements contained in an affidavit filed in the context of an application made under this section may be based on belief but must include the grounds for the belief.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Service of authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An authorization must be served by the Minister on the debtor within 72 hours after it is granted, except if the judge orders the authorization to be served at some other time specified in the authorization, and, if a notice has not been sent to the debtor at or before the time of the application, the notice is to be served together with the authorization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>How service effected</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Service on a debtor must be effected by personal service or in accordance with the directions of a judge.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application to judge for direction</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If service on a debtor cannot reasonably otherwise be effected as and when required under this section, the Minister may, as soon as is practicable, apply to a judge for further direction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review of authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If a judge of a court has granted an authorization, the debtor may, on six clear days notice to the Deputy Attorney General of Canada, apply to a judge of the court to review the authorization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation period for review application</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>An application under subsection (7) must be made</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within thirty days after the day on which the authorization was served on the debtor in accordance with this section; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within any further time that a judge may allow, on being satisfied that the application was made as soon as was practicable.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hearing <Language xml:lang="la">in camera</Language></MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An application may, on request of the debtor, be heard <Language xml:lang="la">in camera</Language>, if the debtor establishes to the satisfaction of the judge that the circumstances of the case justify <Language xml:lang="la">in camera</Language> proceedings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of application</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>On an application, the judge is to determine the question summarily and may confirm, set aside or vary the authorization and make any other order that the judge considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directions</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>If any question arises as to the course to be followed in connection with anything done or being done under this section and there is no direction in this section in respect of the matter, a judge may give any direction in respect of the matter that, in the opinion of the judge, is appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No appeal from review order</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>No appeal lies from an order of a judge made under subsection (10).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Trustees, Receivers and Personal Representatives</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Bankruptcies</MarginalNote><Label>97.36</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following rules apply to a person who is a bankrupt:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the trustee in bankruptcy is the agent of the bankrupt and any act performed by the trustee in the administration of the estate of the bankrupt or in the carrying on of any business of the bankrupt is deemed to have been made by the trustee as agent of the bankrupt;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the estate of the bankrupt is not a trust or an estate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the property and money of the bankrupt immediately before the day of the bankruptcy does not pass to or vest in the trustee in bankruptcy on the receiving order being made or the assignment in bankruptcy being filed but remains vested in the bankrupt;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the trustee in bankruptcy, and not the bankrupt, is liable for the payment of all amounts (other than amounts that relate solely to activities in which the bankrupt begins to engage on or after the day of the bankruptcy and to which the bankruptcy does not relate) that become payable by the bankrupt under this Act during the period beginning on the day immediately after the day the trustee became the trustee in bankruptcy of the bankrupt and ending on the day the discharge of the trustee is granted under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal>, except that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the trustee is liable for the payment of amounts that became payable by the bankrupt after the day of the bankruptcy only to the extent of the property and money of the bankrupt in possession of the trustee available to satisfy the liability, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the trustee is not liable for the payment of any amount for which a receiver is liable under section 97.37,</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if, on or after the day of bankruptcy, the bankrupt begins to engage in particular activities to which the bankruptcy does not relate, the particular activities are deemed to be separate from the activities of the person to which the bankruptcy relates as though the particular activities were activities of a separate person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), the trustee in bankruptcy shall perform all the obligations under this Act of the bankrupt in respect of the activities of the bankrupt to which the bankruptcy relates for the period beginning on the day immediately after the day of bankruptcy and ending on the day the discharge of the trustee is granted under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), if the bankrupt has not on or before the day of bankruptcy fulfilled all of their obligations under this Act in respect of any activities of the bankrupt on or before the day of bankruptcy, the trustee in bankruptcy shall fulfil those obligations, unless the Minister waives in writing the requirement for the trustee to do so;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if there is a receiver with authority in respect of a business, a property, affairs or assets of the bankrupt, the trustee in bankruptcy is not required to perform the obligations of the bankrupt under this Act to the extent that the receiver is required under section 97.37 to perform those obligations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the property and money held by the trustee in bankruptcy for the bankrupt on the day an order of absolute discharge of the bankrupt is granted under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> does not pass to the bankrupt on the order being granted but is held by and vested in the bankrupt continuously since the day it was acquired by the bankrupt or the trustee, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>bankrupt</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>bankrupt</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>97.37</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>business</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>entreprise</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>business</DefinedTermEn> includes a part of a business.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>relevant assets</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>actif pertinent</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>relevant assets</DefinedTermEn> of a receiver means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the receiver’s authority relates to all the properties, businesses, affairs and assets of a person, all those properties, businesses, affairs and assets; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the receiver’s authority relates to only part of the properties, businesses, affairs or assets of a person, that part of the properties, businesses, affairs or assets, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Receivers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The following rules apply to a receiver who on a particular day is vested with the authority to manage, operate, liquidate or wind up any business or property, or to manage and care for the affairs and assets, of a person:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the receiver is an agent of the person and any act performed by the receiver in respect of the relevant assets of the receiver is deemed to have been performed, as the case may be, by the receiver as agent on behalf of the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the receiver is not a trustee of the estate of the person or any part of the estate of the person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the relevant assets of the receiver are a part and not all of the person’s businesses, properties, affairs or assets, the relevant assets of the receiver are deemed to be, throughout the period during which the receiver is acting as receiver of the person, separate from the remainder of the businesses, properties, affairs or assets of the person as though the relevant assets were businesses, properties, affairs or assets, as the case may be, of a separate person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person and the receiver are jointly and severally or solidarily liable for the payment of all amounts that become payable by the person under this Act before or during the period during which the receiver is acting as receiver of the person to the extent that the amounts can reasonably be considered to relate to the relevant assets of the receiver or to the businesses, properties, affairs or assets of the person that would have been the relevant assets of the receiver if the receiver had been acting as receiver of the person at the time the amounts became payable except that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the receiver is liable for the payment of amounts that became payable before that period only to the extent of the property and money of the person in possession or under the control and management of the receiver after</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>satisfying the claims of creditors whose claims ranked, on the particular day, in priority to the claim of the Crown in respect of the amounts, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>paying any amounts that the receiver is required to pay to a trustee in bankruptcy of the person, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the payment by the person or the receiver of an amount in respect of the liability discharges the joint liability to the extent of that amount;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the receiver shall perform all the obligations, in respect of the relevant assets of the receiver for the period during which the receiver is acting as receiver, that are required under this Act to be performed by the person, as if the relevant assets were the only properties, businesses, affairs and assets of the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person has not on or before the particular day fulfilled their obligations under this Act before the period during which the receiver was acting as receiver, the receiver shall fulfil those obligations for that period that relate to the businesses, properties, affairs or assets of the person that would have been the relevant assets of the receiver if the receiver had been acting as receiver of the person during that period, unless the Minister waives in writing the requirement for the receiver to do so.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>97.38</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section and in section 97.39.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>trust</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fiducie</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>trust</DefinedTermEn> includes the estate of a deceased individual.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>trustee</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fiduciaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>trustee</DefinedTermEn> includes the personal representative of a deceased individual, but does not include a receiver.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Trustee’s liability</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), each trustee of a trust is liable to satisfy every obligation imposed on the trust under this Act, whether the obligation was imposed during or before the period during which the trustee acts as trustee of the trust, but the satisfaction of an obligation of a trust by one of the trustees of the trust discharges the liability of all other trustees of the trust to satisfy that obligation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Joint and several or solidary liability</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A trustee of a trust is jointly and severally or solidarily liable with the trust and each of the other trustees, if any, for the payment of all amounts that become payable by the trust under this Act before or during the period during which the trustee acts as trustee of the trust except that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the trustee is liable for the payment of amounts that became payable before that period only to the extent of the property and money of the trust under the control of the trustee; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the payment by the trust or the trustee of an amount in respect of the liability discharges the joint liability to the extent of that amount.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in writing, waive the requirement for the personal representative of a deceased individual to fulfil the obligations under this Act in respect of the activities of the deceased individual that occurred on or before the day the individual died.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Activities of a trustee</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, if a person acts as trustee of a trust, anything done by the person in the person’s capacity as trustee of the trust is deemed to have been done by the trust and not by the person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>representative</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>97.39</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>representative</DefinedTermEn> means a person, other than a trustee in bankruptcy or a receiver, who is administering, winding up, controlling or otherwise dealing with any property, business, commercial activity or estate of another person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificates for receivers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every receiver shall, before distributing to any person any property or money under the control of the receiver in the receiver’s capacity as receiver, obtain a certificate from the Minister certifying that the following amounts have been paid or security for the payment of the amounts has been accepted by the Minister:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>amounts that the person is or can reasonably be expected to become liable to pay under this Act at or before the time the distribution is made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>amounts that the receiver is or can reasonably be expected to become liable to pay in the receiver’s capacity as receiver.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificates for representatives</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every representative shall, before distributing to any person any property or money under the control of the representative in the representative’s capacity as representative, obtain a certificate from the Minister certifying that the following amounts have been paid or that security for the payment of the amounts has been accepted by the Minister:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>amounts that the person is or can reasonably be expected to become liable to pay under this Act at or before the time the distribution is made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>amounts that the representative is or can reasonably be expected to become liable to pay in the representative’s capacity as representative.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Liability for failure to obtain certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any receiver or representative who distributes property or money without obtaining a certificate in respect of the amounts referred to in subsection (2) or (3) is personally liable for the payment of those amounts to the extent of the value of the property or money so distributed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amalgamations and Windings-up</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Amalgamations</MarginalNote><Label>97.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If two or more corporations (in this section each referred to as a “predecessor”) are merged or amalgamated to form one corporation (in this section referred to as the “new corporation”), the new corporation is, for the purposes of this Act, deemed to be a separate person from each of the predecessors and the same corporation as, and a continuation of, each predecessor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to the merger or amalgamation of two or more corporations that is the result of the acquisition of property of one corporation by another corporation pursuant to the purchase of the property by the other corporation or as the result of the distribution of the property to the other corporation on the winding-up of the corporation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Winding-up</MarginalNote><Label>97.41</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, if at any time a particular corporation is wound up and not less than 90% of the issued shares of each class of the capital stock of the particular corporation were, immediately before that time, owned by another corporation, the other corporation is deemed to be the same corporation as, and a continuation of, the particular corporation.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Partnerships</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Partnerships</MarginalNote><Label>97.42</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, anything done by a person as a member of a partnership is deemed to have been done by the partnership in the course of the partnership’s activities and not to have been done by the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Joint and several or solidary liability</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A partnership and each member or former member (each of which is referred to in this subsection as the “member”) of the partnership (other than a member which is a limited partner and is not a general partner) are jointly and severally or solidarily liable for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the payment of all amounts that become payable by the partnership under this Act before or during the period during which the member is a member of the partnership or, if the member was a member of the partnership at the time the partnership was dissolved, after the dissolution of the partnership, except that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the member is liable for the payment of amounts that become payable before that period only to the extent of the property and money that is regarded as property or money of the partnership in accordance with the laws of the province governing the partnership, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the payment by the partnership or by any member of the partnership of an amount in respect of the liability discharges the joint liability to the extent of that amount; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>all other obligations under this Act that arose before or during the period for which the partnership is liable or, if the member was a member of the partnership at the time the partnership was dissolved, the obligations that arose upon or as a consequence of the dissolution.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Unincorporated Bodies</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Compliance by unincorporated bodies</MarginalNote><Label>97.43</Label><Text>If any amount is required to be paid or any other thing is required to be done under this Act by a person (in this section referred to as the “body”) that is not an individual, corporation, partnership, trust or estate, the following persons are jointly and severally or solidarily liable to pay that amount or to comply with the requirement:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>every member of the body holding office as president, chairperson, treasurer, secretary or similar officer of the body;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if there are no members referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), every member of any committee having management of the affairs of the body; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if there are no members referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), every member of the body.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>The payment of the amount or the fullfilment of the requirement by a member is deemed to be compliance with the requirement.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Assessments, Objections and Appeals</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Assessments</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Assessments — garnishments and non-arms length transfers</MarginalNote><Label>97.44</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may assess any amount that a person is liable to pay</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under section 97.28, before the expiry of four years after the notice from the Minister requiring the payment is issued to the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under section 97.29, at any time.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>The Minister may reassess the amount or make an additional assessment.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person has been assessed an amount under subsection (1), the person shall pay, in addition to the amount, interest at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the first day after the day the amount was assessed and ending on the day the amount is paid.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) does not apply in respect of a reassessment of a person made</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to give effect to a decision on an objection or appeal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with the consent in writing of the person to dispose of an appeal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When assessment may be made</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An assessment under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) may be made at any time if the person to be assessed has</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>made a misrepresentation that is attributable to the person’s neglect, carelessness or wilful default;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>committed fraud in supplying, or failing to supply, any information under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>filed a waiver under subsection (5) that is in effect at that time.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Any person may, within the time otherwise limited by paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) for assessing the person, waive the application of that paragraph by filing with the Minister a waiver in the prescribed form specifying the matter in respect of which the person waives the application of that paragraph.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Revoking waiver</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Any person who files a waiver may revoke the waiver on six months notice to the Minister by filing with the Minister a notice of revocation of the waiver in the prescribed form.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Liability not affected</MarginalNote><Label>97.45</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Liability under this Part to pay any amount is not affected by an incorrect or incomplete assessment or by the fact that no assessment has been made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Assessment deemed valid</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to being reassessed or vacated as a result of an objection or appeal under this Part, an assessment is valid and binding, despite any error, defect or omission in the assessment or in any proceeding under this Part relating to it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Irregularities</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An appeal from an assessment must not be allowed by reason only of an irregularity, informality, omission or error on the part of any person in the observation of any directory provision of this Part.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of assessment</MarginalNote><Label>97.46</Label><Text>After making an assessment, the Minister must send to the person assessed a notice of assessment.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Assessment before collection</MarginalNote><Label>97.47</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may not collect an amount under section 97.44 unless that amount has been assessed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment of remainder</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An amount that is unpaid by a person and the subject of a notice of assessment is payable immediately by the person to the Receiver General.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Security if objection or appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a person objects to or appeals from an assessment under this Part, the Minister shall accept security, in an amount and a form satisfactory to the Minister, given by or on behalf of the person, for the payment of any amount that is in controversy.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Objections and Appeals</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Objection to assessment</MarginalNote><Label>97.48</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any person who has been assessed under section 97.44 and who objects to the assessment may, within ninety days after the day notice of the assessment is sent to the person, file with the Minister a notice of objection in the prescribed form and manner setting out the reasons for the objection and all relevant facts.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Issues to be decided</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person objects to an assessment, the notice of objection must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>reasonably describe each issue to be decided;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify in respect of each issue the relief sought, expressed as the change in any amount that is relevant for the purposes of the assessment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide the facts and reasons relied on by the person in respect of each issue.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Late compliance</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a notice of objection filed by a person to whom subsection (2) applies does not include the information required by paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) in respect of an issue to be decided that is described in the notice, the Minister may in writing request the person to provide the information, and those paragraphs are deemed to have been complied with in respect of the issue if, within 60 days after the request is made, the person submits the information in writing to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation on objections</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a person has filed a notice of objection to an assessment and the Minister makes a particular assessment under subsection (8) pursuant to the notice of objection or in accordance with an order of a court vacating, varying or restoring an assessment or referring an assessment back to the Minister for reconsideration and reassessment, the person may object to the particular assessment in respect of an issue</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>only if the person complied with subsection (2) in the notice with respect to that issue; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>only with respect to the relief sought in respect of that issue as specified by the person in the notice.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of subsection (4)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If a person has filed a notice of objection to an assessment (in this subsection referred to as the “earlier assessment”) and the Minister makes a particular assessment under subsection (8) pursuant to the notice of objection, subsection (4) does not limit the right of the person to object to the particular assessment in respect of an issue that was part of the particular assessment and not a part of the earlier assessment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation on objections</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), no objection may be made by a person in respect of an issue for which the right of objection has been waived in writing by the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Acceptance of objection</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Minister may accept a notice of objection even if it was not filed in the prescribed manner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consideration of objection</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>On receipt of a notice of objection, the Minister must, without delay, reconsider the assessment and vacate or confirm the assessment or make a reassessment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiving reconsideration</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If, in a notice of objection, a person who wishes to appeal directly to the Tax Court of Canada requests the Minister not to reconsider the assessment objected to, the Minister may confirm the assessment without reconsideration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>After reconsidering or confirming an assessment, the Minister must send to the person objecting a notice of the Minister’s decision by registered or certified mail.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal to the Tax Court of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>97.49</Label><Text>If a person files a notice of objection to an assessment and the Minister sends to the person a notice of a reassessment or an additional assessment, in respect of any matter dealt with in the notice of objection, the person may, within ninety days after the day the notice of reassessment or additional assessment was sent by the Minister,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>appeal to the Tax Court of Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if an appeal has already been instituted in respect of the matter, amend the appeal by joining to it an appeal in respect of the reassessment or additional assessment in any manner and on any terms that the Court directs.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>97.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If no objection to an assessment is filed under section 97.48, within the time limit otherwise provided, a person may make an application to the Minister to extend the time for filing a notice of objection and the Minister may grant the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must set out the reasons why the notice of objection was not filed within the time otherwise limited by this Part for doing so.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>How application made</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The application must be made by delivering or mailing the application and a copy of the notice of objection to the Chief of Appeals in a Tax Services Office or Taxation Centre of the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may accept the application even if it was not delivered or mailed to the person or place specified in subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>On receipt of the application, the Minister must, without delay, consider it, and notify the person of his or her decision by registered or certified mail.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Date of objection if application granted</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the application is granted, the notice of objection is deemed to have been filed on the day the decision of the Minister is mailed to the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When order to be made</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>No application may be granted under this section unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application is made within one year after the expiration of the time otherwise limited by this Part for objecting; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person demonstrates that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within the time otherwise limited by this Part for objecting, the person was unable to act or to give a mandate to act in the person’s name, or the person had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to object to the assessment,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the application was made as soon as circumstances permitted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time by Tax Court of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>97.51</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who has made an application under section 97.5 may apply to the Tax Court of Canada to have the application granted after either</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister has refused the application; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ninety days have elapsed after service of the application and the Minister has not notified the person of the Minister’s decision.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>If paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) applies, the application under this subsection must be made within thirty days after the application is refused.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>How application made</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must be made by filing in the Registry of the Tax Court of Canada, in accordance with the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, three copies of the documents filed under subsection 97.5(3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copy to the Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After receiving the application, the Tax Court of Canada must send a copy of it to the office of the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of Court</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Tax Court of Canada may dispose of the application by dismissing or granting it. If the Court grants the application, it may impose any terms that it considers just or order that the notice of objection be deemed to be a valid objection as of the date of the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When application to be granted</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No application may be granted under this section unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application was made under subsection 97.5(1) within one year after the expiration of the time set out in this Part for objecting; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person demonstrates that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within the time otherwise limited by this Part for objecting, the person was unable to act or to give a mandate to act in the person’s name, or the person had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to object to the assessment,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the application was made under subsection 97.5(1) as soon as circumstances permitted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time to appeal</MarginalNote><Label>97.52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If no appeal to the Tax Court of Canada has been taken under section 97.53 within the time set out in that section, a person may make an application to the Court for an order extending the time within which an appeal may be made, and the Court may make an order extending the time for appealing and may impose any terms that it considers just.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must set out the reasons why the appeal was not taken on time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>How application made</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The application must be made by filing in the Registry of the Tax Court of Canada, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, three copies of the application together with three copies of the notice of appeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copy to Deputy Attorney General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>After receiving the application, the Tax Court of Canada must send a copy of the application to the office of the Deputy Attorney General of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When order to be made</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No order may be made under this section unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application was made within one year after the expiration of the time otherwise limited by this Part for appealing; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person demonstrates that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within the time otherwise limited by this Part for appealing, the person was unable to act or to give a mandate to act in the person’s name, or the person had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to appeal,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the application was made as soon as circumstances permitted, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>there are reasonable grounds for appealing from an assessment.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>97.53</Label><Text>A person who has filed a notice of objection to an assessment under this Part may appeal to the Tax Court of Canada to have the assessment vacated or a reassessment made after either</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister has confirmed the assessment or has reassessed; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>180 days have elapsed after the filing of the notice of objection and the Minister has not notified the person that the Minister has vacated or confirmed the assessment or has reassessed.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>If paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) applies, an application to appeal under this section must be made within ninety days after the day notice is sent to the person under subsection 97.48(10).</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation on appeals to the Tax Court of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>97.54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 97.49 and 97.53, a person may appeal to the Tax Court of Canada only with respect to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an issue in respect of which the person has complied with subsection 97.48(2) in the notice of objection; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an issue described in subsection 97.48(5) if the person was not required to file a notice of objection to the assessment that gave rise to the issue.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>If paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) applies, the person may appeal only with respect to the relief sought in respect of the issue specified by the person in the notice.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite sections 97.49 and 97.53, a person may not appeal to the Tax Court of Canada to have an assessment vacated or varied in respect of an issue for which the right of objection or appeal has been waived in writing by the person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Institution of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>97.55</Label><Text>An appeal to the Tax Court of Canada under this Part, other than one referred to in section 18.3001 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, must be taken in the manner set out in that Act or in any rules made under that Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>97.56</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an appeal referred to in section 18.3001 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is made to the Tax Court of Canada, the Court must immediately send a copy of the notice of appeal to the office of the Commissioner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice, etc., forwarded to Tax Court of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Immediately after receiving notice of an appeal, the Commissioner must forward to the Tax Court of Canada and the appellant copies of all applications, notices of assessment, notices of objection and notifications, if any, that are relevant to the appeal. Once forwarded, the copies form part of the record before the Tax Court of Canada and are evidence of the existence of the documents and of the making of the statements contained in them.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>97.57</Label><Text>The Tax Court of Canada may dispose of an appeal from an assessment by dismissing or allowing it. If the appeal is allowed, the Court may vacate the assessment or refer it back to the Minister for reconsideration and reassessment.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>References to Tax Court of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>97.58</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister and another person agree in writing that a question arising under this Part, in respect of any assessment or proposed assessment, should be determined by the Tax Court of Canada, that question shall be determined by that Court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time during consideration not to count</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The time between the day proceedings are taken in the Tax Court of Canada to have a question determined and the day the question is finally determined must not be counted in the calculation of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the four-year period referred to in paragraph 97.44(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the time for service of a notice of objection to an assessment under section 97.48; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the time within which an appeal may be instituted under section 97.53.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 97.21 to 97.58 of the Act, as enacted by subsection (1), apply to amounts that are payable after this Act is assented to, regardless of when the amounts became payable.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>59.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 99(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>tant qu’il n’y a pas eu dédouanement, examiner toutes marchandises importées et en ouvrir ou faire ouvrir tous colis ou contenants, ainsi qu’en prélever des échantillons en quantités raisonnables;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 99(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at any time up to the time of release, examine any mail that has been imported and, subject to this section, open or cause to be opened any such mail that the officer suspects on reasonable grounds contains any goods referred to in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, or any goods the importation of which is prohibited, controlled or regulated under any other Act of Parliament, and take samples of anything contained in such mail in reasonable amounts;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 99(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>tant qu’il n’y a pas eu exportation, examiner toutes marchandises déclarées conformément à l’article 95 et en ouvrir ou faire ouvrir tous colis ou contenants, ainsi qu’en prélever des échantillons en quantités raisonnables;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 99(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at any time up to the time of exportation, examine any mail that is to be exported and, subject to this section, open or cause to be opened any such mail that the officer suspects on reasonable grounds contains any goods the exportation of which is prohibited, controlled or regulated under any Act of Parliament, and take samples of anything contained in such mail in reasonable amounts;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1988, c. 65, s. 79</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 99(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>examiner les marchandises au sujet desquelles il soupçonne, pour des motifs raisonnables, qu’il y a eu une erreur de classement tarifaire, de valeur en douane ou d’indication quantitative dans la déclaration en détail ou la déclaration provisoire dont elles ont fait l’objet conformément à l’article 32 ou pour lesquelles est demandé un remboursement ou un drawback en vertu de la présente loi ou du Tarif des douanes, ainsi qu’en prélever des échantillons en quantités raisonnables;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>examiner les marchandises au sujet desquelles il soupçonne, pour des motifs raisonnables, qu’il y a eu une erreur sur leur origine dans la déclaration en détail ou la déclaration provisoire dont elles ont fait l’objet conformément à l’article 32, ainsi qu’en prélever des échantillons en quantités raisonnables;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>examiner les marchandises dont il soupçonne, pour des motifs raisonnables, qu’elles ont donné ou pourraient donner lieu à une infraction soit à la présente loi, soit à toute autre loi fédérale à l’égard de laquelle il a des fonctions d’exécution ou de contrôle d’application, soit aux règlements d’application de ces lois, ainsi qu’en ouvrir ou faire ouvrir tous colis ou contenants;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>s’il soupçonne, pour des motifs raisonnables, qu’un moyen de transport ou que les marchandises se trouvant à son bord ont donné ou pourraient donner lieu à une infraction visée à l’alinéa <Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), immobiliser le moyen de transport, monter à son bord et le fouiller, examiner les marchandises et en ouvrir ou faire ouvrir tous colis ou contenants, ainsi que faire conduire le moyen de transport à un bureau de douane ou à tout autre lieu indiqué pour ces opérations.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsections 99(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception for mail</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer may not open or cause to be opened any mail that is being imported or exported and that weighs thirty grams or less unless the person to whom it is addressed consents or the person who sent it has completed and attached to the mail a label in accordance with article RE 601 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Letter Post Regulations</XRefExternal> of the Universal Postal Convention.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception for mail</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An officer may cause imported mail, or mail that is being exported, that weighs thirty grams or less to be opened in his or her presence by the person to whom it is addressed, the person who sent it or a person authorized by either of those persons.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>60.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 99:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Power to stop</MarginalNote><Label>99.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an officer has reasonable grounds to suspect that a person has entered Canada without presenting himself or herself in accordance with subsection 11(1), the officer may stop that person within a reasonable time after the person has entered Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of officer</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer who stops a person referred to in subsection (1) may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>question the person; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of goods imported by that person, examine them, cause to be opened any package or container of the imported goods and take samples of them in reasonable amounts.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Search of persons</MarginalNote><Label>99.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An officer may search any person leaving a customs controlled area, other than a prescribed person or a member of a prescribed class of persons who may be searched under subsection (2), if the officer suspects on reasonable grounds that the person has secreted on or about their person anything in respect of which this Act or the regulations have been or might be contravened, anything that would afford evidence with respect to a contravention of this Act or the regulations or any goods the importation or exportation of which is prohibited, controlled or regulated under this or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Search of prescribed persons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer may, in accordance with the regulations, search any prescribed person or member of a prescribed class of persons leaving a customs controlled area.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person taken before senior officer</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An officer who is about to search a person under this section shall, on the request of the person, immediately take that person before the senior officer at the place where the search is to be conducted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review by senior officer</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A senior officer before whom a person is taken by an officer shall, if the senior officer agrees with the officer that under subsection (1) or (2), as the case may be, the person may be searched, direct that the person be searched or, if the senior officer does not so agree, discharge the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitations on searches</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person may be searched by an officer who is not of the same sex and, if there is no officer of the same sex at the place at which the search is to be conducted, an officer may authorize any suitable person of the same sex to conduct the search.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Non-intrusive examination of goods</MarginalNote><Label>99.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An officer may, in accordance with the regulations and without individualized suspicion, conduct a non-intrusive examination of goods in the custody or possession of a person leaving a customs controlled area.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other examination of goods</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer may examine any goods in the custody or possession of a person leaving a customs controlled area and open or cause to be opened any baggage, package or container and take samples of the goods in reasonable amounts, if the officer suspects on reasonable grounds that this Act or any other Act of Parliament administered or enforced by the officer or any regulations made under it have been or might be contravened in respect of the goods.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Examination of abandoned goods</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An officer may, at any time, open or cause to be opened, inspect and detain any baggage, package or container found abandoned in a customs controlled area.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>99.4</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing persons or classes of persons who may be searched under subsection 99.2(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting, for the purposes of subsection 99.2(2), the circumstances and manner in which searches are to be conducted and the types of searches that may be conducted; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting, for the purposes of subsection 99.3(1), the manner in which examinations are to be conducted and the machines, instruments, devices or other apparatuses or classes of machines, instruments, devices or apparatuses that may be used to conduct examinations.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 25(1); 1995, c. 41, ss. 27, 28; 1999, c. 17, s. 124</MarginalNote><Label>61.</Label><Text>Sections 107 and 108 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>107.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>customs information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>renseignement douanier</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>customs information</DefinedTermEn> means information of any kind and in any form that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>relates to one or more persons and is obtained by or on behalf of the Minister for the purposes of this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is prepared from information described in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>official</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fonctionnaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>official</DefinedTermEn> means a person who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is or was employed in the service of Her Majesty in right of Canada or of a province;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>occupies or occupied a position of responsibility in the service of Her Majesty in right of Canada or of a province; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is or was engaged by or on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada or of a province.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>specified person</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>personne déterminée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>specified person</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is employed in the service of, who occupies a position of responsibility in the service of, or who is engaged by or on behalf of, Her Majesty in right of Canada to carry out the provisions of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal>. It includes a person who was formerly so employed or engaged or who formerly occupied such a position.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition — provision or use of customs information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except as authorized under this section, no person shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>knowingly provide, or allow to be provided, to any person any customs information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>knowingly allow any person to have access to any customs information; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>knowingly use customs information.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorized use of customs information by official</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An official may use customs information for the purposes of administering or enforcing this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Imports Measures Act</XRefExternal> or Part 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) Act</XRefExternal> or for any purpose set out in subsection (4), (5) or (7).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorized provision of information</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An official may provide, allow to be provided or provide access to customs information if the information</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>will be used solely in or to prepare for criminal proceedings commenced under an Act of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>will be used solely in or to prepare for any legal proceedings relating to the administration or enforcement of an international agreement relating to trade, this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal>, any other Act of Parliament or law of a province that provides for the imposition or collection of a tax or duty or Part 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) Act</XRefExternal>, before</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a court of record, including a court of record in a jurisdiction outside Canada,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an international organization, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a dispute settlement panel or an appellate body created under an international agreement relating to trade;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may reasonably be regarded as necessary solely for a purpose relating to the administration or enforcement of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or Part 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) Act</XRefExternal> by an official of the Agency;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may reasonably be regarded as necessary solely for a purpose relating to the administration or enforcement of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal> by a member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may reasonably be regarded as necessary solely for a purpose relating to the life, health or safety of an individual or to the environment in Canada or any other country;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>will be used solely for a purpose relating to the supervision, evaluation or discipline of a specified person by Her Majesty in right of Canada in respect of a period during which the person was employed or engaged by, or occupied a position of responsibility in the service of, Her Majesty in right of Canada to administer or enforce this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or Part 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) Act</XRefExternal> to the extent that the information is relevant for that purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is reasonably regarded by the official to be information that does not directly or indirectly identify any person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is reasonably regarded by the official to be information relating to the national security or defence of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provision of information to certain persons</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An official may provide, allow to be provided or provide access to customs information to the following persons:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a peace officer having jurisdiction to investigate an alleged offence under any Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province subject to prosecution by indictment, the Attorney General of Canada and the Attorney General of the province in which proceedings in respect of the alleged offence may be taken, if that official believes on reasonable grounds that the information relates to the alleged offence and will be used in the investigation or prosecution of the alleged offence, solely for those purposes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person that is otherwise legally entitled to the information by reason of an Act of Parliament, solely for the purposes for which that person is entitled to the information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official solely for the purposes of developing, administering or enforcing an Act of Parliament or developing or implementing a policy related to an Act of Parliament if the information relates to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>goods, the importation, exportation or in-transit movement of which is or may be prohibited, controlled or regulated under that Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a person who that official has reasonable grounds to believe may have committed an offence under that Act in respect of goods imported or exported by that person, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>goods that may be evidence of an offence under that Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official, solely for the purpose of administering or enforcing an Act of the legislature of a province, if the information relates to goods that are subject to import, in-transit or export controls or taxation upon importation into the province under that Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official of a participating province, as defined in subsection 123(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, or an official of the province of Quebec, if the information relates to the administration or enforcement of Part IX of that Act in that province, solely for that purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official solely for the purpose of the formulation or evaluation of fiscal or trade policy or the development of a remission order under an Act of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official solely for the purpose of setting off, against any sum of money that may be due to or payable by Her Majesty in right of Canada, a debt due to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>Her Majesty in right of Canada, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Her Majesty in right of a province on account of taxes payable to the province if an agreement exists between Canada and the province under which Canada is authorized to collect taxes on behalf of the province;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>counsel, as defined in subsection 84(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal>, in accordance with subsection 84(3) of that Act and subject to subsection 84(3.1) of that Act, except that the word “information” in those subsections is to be read as a reference to the words “customs information”;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official of the Department of Human Resources Development solely for the purpose of administering or enforcing the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, if the information relates to the movement of people into and out of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official of the Department of Citizenship and Immigration solely for the purpose of administering or enforcing the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration Act</XRefExternal>, if the information relates to the movement of people into and out of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official of the Financial Transactions and Reports Analysis Centre of Canada solely for the purpose of administering or enforcing the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person solely for the purpose of determining any entitlement, liability or obligation of the person under this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> including the person’s entitlement to any refund, relief, drawback or abatement under those Acts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any person, if the information is required to comply with a subpoena or warrant issued or an order made by a court of record in Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any person, if the information is required to comply with a subpoena or warrant issued or an order made by a court of record outside of Canada, solely for the purposes of criminal proceedings; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribed persons or classes of persons, in prescribed circumstances for prescribed purposes, solely for those purposes.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provision of customs information by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister may provide, allow to be provided or provide access to customs information to any person if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the information may not otherwise be provided, allowed to be provided or provided access to under this section and, in the Minister’s opinion, the public interest in providing the information clearly outweighs any invasion of privacy, or any material financial loss or prejudice to the competitive position of the person to whom the information relates, that could result from the provision of the information; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the Minister’s opinion, providing the information would clearly benefit the individual to whom the information relates.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notification of Privacy Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If customs information provided under subsection (6) is personal information within the meaning of section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister must notify, in writing, the Privacy Commissioner appointed under section 53 of that Act of any provision of personal information under that subsection before its provision if reasonably practicable or, in any other case, without delay after the provision. The Privacy Commissioner may, if the Privacy Commissioner considers it appropriate, notify the individual to whom the information relates of the provision of the information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Providing customs information to other governments</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Customs information may be provided by any person to an official or any other person employed by or representing the government of a foreign state, an international organization established by the governments of states, a community of states, or an institution of any such government or organization, in accordance with an international convention, agreement or other written arrangement between the Government of Canada or an institution of the Government of Canada and the government of the foreign state, the organization, the community or the institution, solely for the purposes set out in that arrangement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure of customs information to certain persons</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An official may provide, allow to be provided or provide access to customs information relating to a particular person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to that particular person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to a person authorized to transact business under this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> as that particular person’s agent, at the request of the particular person and on receipt of such fee, if any, as is prescribed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with the consent of that particular person, to any other person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament or other law, no official may be required, in connection with any legal proceedings, to give or produce evidence relating to any customs information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Measures to protect customs information</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>The person presiding at a legal proceeding relating to the supervision, evaluation or discipline of a specified person may order any measure that is necessary to ensure that customs information is not used or provided to any person for any purpose not relating to that proceeding, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>holding a hearing <Language xml:lang="la">in camera</Language>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>banning the publication of the information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>concealing the identity of the person to whom the information relates; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sealing the records of the proceeding.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal from order to disclose customs information</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>An order or direction that is made in the course of or in connection with any legal proceeding and that requires an official to give or produce evidence relating to customs information may, by notice served on all interested parties, be immediately appealed by the Minister or by the person against whom the order or direction is made</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the court of appeal of the province in which the order or direction is made, in the case of an order or direction made by a court or other tribunal established under the laws of the province, whether or not that court or tribunal is exercising a jurisdiction conferred by the laws of Canada; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the Federal Court of Appeal, in the case of an order or direction made by a court or other tribunal established under the laws of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>The court to which the appeal is taken may allow the appeal and quash the order or direction appealed from or may dismiss the appeal. The rules of practice and procedure from time to time governing appeals to the courts apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, in respect of the appeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Stay</MarginalNote><Label>(14)</Label><Text>An appeal stays the operation of the order or direction appealed from until judgment in the appeal is pronounced.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(15)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations prescribing the circumstances in which fees may be charged for providing or providing access to customs information or making or certifying copies of information and the amount of any such fees.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Passenger information</MarginalNote><Label>107.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, under prescribed circumstances and conditions, require any prescribed person or prescribed class of persons to provide, or provide access to, prescribed information about any person on board a conveyance in advance of the arrival of the conveyance in Canada or within a reasonable time after that arrival.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any person who is required under subsection (1) to provide, or provide access to, prescribed information shall do so despite any restriction under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> on the disclosure of such information.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 41, s. 29; 1997, c. 36, ss. 182, 183</MarginalNote><Label>62.</Label><Text>Sections 109.1 and 109.11 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Designated provisions</MarginalNote><Label>109.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with any provision of an Act or a regulation designated by the regulations made under subsection (3) is liable to a penalty of not more than twenty-five thousand dollars, as the Minister may direct.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Failure to comply</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with any term or condition of a licence issued under this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> or any obligation undertaken under section 4.1 is liable to a penalty of not more than twenty-five thousand dollars, as the Minister may direct.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation by regulation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating any provisions of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or of any regulation made under any of those Acts; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing short-form descriptions of the provisions designated under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and providing for the use of those descriptions.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 80; 1995, c. 41, s. 30</MarginalNote><Label>63.</Label><Text>Section 109.3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Assessment</MarginalNote><Label>109.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A penalty to which a person is liable under section 109.1 or 109.2 may be assessed by an officer and, if an assessment is made, an officer shall serve on the person a written notice of that assessment by sending it by registered or certified mail or delivering it to the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation on assessment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person shall not be assessed penalties under both sections 109.1 and 109.2 in respect of the same contravention of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or the regulations made under those Acts.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Penalty in addition to other sanction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An assessment under subsection (1) may be made in addition to a seizure under this Act or a demand for payment under section 124, in respect of the same contravention of this Act or the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sufficiency of short-form description</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The use on a notice of assessment of a short-form description established under paragraph 109.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or of a description that deviates from that description without affecting its substance is sufficient for all purposes to describe the contravention.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 80</MarginalNote><Label>64.</Label><Text>Section 109.5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Interest on penalties</MarginalNote><Label>109.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), a person on whom a notice of assessment of a penalty has been served under section 109.3 shall pay, in addition to the penalty, interest at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the day after the notice was served on the person and ending on the day the penalty has been paid in full, calculated on the outstanding balance of the penalty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Interest is not payable if the penalty is paid in full by the person within thirty days after the date of the notice of assessment.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>65.</Label><Text>Section 115 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Copies of records</MarginalNote><Label>115.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If any record is examined or seized under this Act, the Minister, or the officer by whom it is examined or seized, may make or cause to be made one or more copies of it, and a copy purporting to be certified by the Minister or a person authorized by the Minister is admissible in evidence and has the same probative force as the original would have if it had been proved in the ordinary way.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Detention of records seized</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No record that has been seized as evidence under this Act shall be detained for a period of more than three months unless, before the expiration of that period,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person from whom it was seized agrees to its further detention for a specified period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a justice of the peace is satisfied on application that, having regard to the circumstances, its further detention for a specified period is warranted and he or she so orders; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>judicial proceedings are instituted in which the seized record may be required.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>66.</Label><Text>Section 123 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Review of forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>123.</Label><Text>The forfeiture of goods or conveyances seized under this Act or any money or security held as forfeit in lieu of such goods or conveyances is final and not subject to review or to be restrained, prohibited, removed, set aside or otherwise dealt with except to the extent and in the manner provided by sections 127.1 and 129.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>67.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 124 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Value of exported goods</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Sections 117 and 119 and subsection (2) apply to a contravention of this Act or the regulations in respect of goods that have been or are about to be exported, except that the references to “value for duty of the goods” in those provisions are to be read as references to “value of the goods”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Value of goods</MarginalNote><Label>(4.2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (4.1), the expression “value of the goods” means the total of all payments made or to be made by the purchaser of the goods to or for the benefit of the vendor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Value of goods set by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(4.3)</Label><Text>If the value of the goods cannot be determined under subsection (4.2), the Minister may determine that value.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 124 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A person on whom a notice of ascertained forfeiture has been served shall pay, in addition to the amount set out in the notice, interest at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the day after the notice was served and ending on the day the amount is paid in full, calculated on the outstanding balance. However, interest is not payable if the amount is paid in full within thirty days after the date of the notice.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 81</MarginalNote><Label>68.</Label><Text>Section 127 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Review of ascertained forfeiture or penalty assessment</MarginalNote><Label>127.</Label><Text>The debt due to Her Majesty as a result of a notice served under section 109.3 or a demand under section 124 is final and not subject to review or to be restrained, prohibited, removed, set aside or otherwise dealt with except to the extent and in the manner provided by sections 127.1 and 129.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Corrective measures</MarginalNote><Label>127.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister, or any officer designated by the Minister for the purposes of this section, may cancel a seizure made under section 110, cancel or reduce a penalty assessed under section 109.3 or an amount demanded under section 124 or refund an amount received under any of sections 117 to 119 within thirty days after the seizure, assessment or demand, if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister is satisfied that there was no contravention; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>there was a contravention but the Minister considers that there was an error with respect to the amount assessed, collected, demanded or taken as security and that the amount should be reduced.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an amount is returned to a person under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the person shall be given interest on that amount at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the day after the amount was originally paid by that person and ending on the day it was returned.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 82</MarginalNote><Label>69.</Label><Text>Subsection 129(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Request for Minister’s decision</MarginalNote><Label>129.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following persons may, within ninety days after the date of a seizure or the service of a notice, request a decision of the Minister under section 131 by giving notice in writing, or by any other means satisfactory to the Minister, to the officer who seized the goods or conveyance or served the notice or caused it to be served, or to an officer at the customs office closest to the place where the seizure took place or closest to the place from where the notice was served:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any person from whom goods or a conveyance is seized under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any person who owns goods or a conveyance that is seized under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any person from whom money or security is received pursuant to section 117, 118 or 119 in respect of goods or a conveyance seized under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any person on whom a notice is served under section 109.3 or 124.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>70.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 129:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>129.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If no request for a decision of the Minister is made under section 129 within the time provided in that section, a person may apply in writing to the Minister for an extension of the time for making the request and the Minister may grant the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application must set out the reasons why the request was not made on time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof of application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The burden of proof that an application has been made under subsection (1) lies on the person claiming to have made it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister must, without delay after making a decision in respect of an application, notify the applicant in writing of the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for granting application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The application may not be granted unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is made within one year after the expiration of the time provided in section 129; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant demonstrates that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within the time provided in section 129, the applicant was unable to request a decision or to instruct another person to request a decision on the applicant’s behalf or the applicant had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to request a decision,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the application was made as soon as circumstances permitted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time by Federal Court</MarginalNote><Label>129.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person may apply to the Federal Court to have their application under section 129.1 granted if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister dismisses that application; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ninety days have expired after the application was made and the Minister has not notified the person of a decision made in respect of it.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>If paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) applies, the application under this subsection must be made within ninety days after the application is dismissed.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application process</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must be made by filing a copy of the application made under section 129.1, and any notice given in respect of it, with the Minister and the Administrator of the Court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of the Court</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Court may grant or dismiss the application and, if it grants the application, may impose any terms that it considers just or order that the request under section 129 be deemed to have been made on the date the order was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for granting application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The application may not be granted unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application under subsection 129.1(1) was made within one year after the expiration of the time provided in section 129; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person making the application demonstrates that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>within the time provided in section 129 for making a request for a decision of the Minister, the person was unable to act or to instruct another person to act in the person’s name or had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to request a decision,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the application was made as soon as circumstances permitted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>71.</Label><Text>Subsection 130(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Evidence may be given under subsection (2) by affidavit made before any person authorized by an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province to administer oaths or take affidavits.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 84</MarginalNote><Label>72.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 131(1) of the Act is amended by adding the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and by replacing paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a penalty assessed under section 109.3 against a person for failure to comply with subsection 109.1(1) or (2) or a provision that is designated under subsection 109.1(3), whether the person so failed to comply.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 131 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A person on whom a notice is served under section 130 may notify the Minister, in writing, that the person will not be furnishing evidence under that section and authorize the Minister to make a decision without delay in the matter.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 85</MarginalNote><Label>73.</Label><Text>Paragraph 132(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>where, as a result of a decision made by the Minister under paragraph 131(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), the Minister decides that a penalty that was assessed under section 109.3 is not justified by the facts or the law, the Minister shall forthwith cancel the assessment of the penalty and authorize the return of any money paid on account of the penalty and any interest that was paid under section 109.5 in respect of the penalty.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 86(2)</MarginalNote><Label>74.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 133(1.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>If the Minister decides under paragraph 131(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) that the person failed to comply, the Minister may, subject to any terms and conditions that the Minister may determine,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>remit any portion of the penalty assessed under section 109.3; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>demand that an additional amount be paid.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>If an additional amount is demanded, the total of the amount assessed and the additional amount may not exceed the maximum penalty that could be assessed under section 109.3.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 25, s. 86(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 133(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If an amount of money is demanded under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (1.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the person to whom the demand is made shall pay the amount demanded together with interest at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the day after the notice is served under subsection 131(2) and ending on the day the amount has been paid in full, calculated on the outstanding balance of the amount. However, interest is not payable if the amount demanded is paid in full within thirty days after the notice is served.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 1, s. 62, c. 51, s. 45; 1998, c. 30, par. 14(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>); 1999, c. 3, s. 60, c. 17, par. 127(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>75.</Label><Text>Sections 138 and 139 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Third party claims</MarginalNote><Label>138.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If goods or a conveyance is seized as forfeit under this Act or if a conveyance is detained under subsection 97.25(2), any person, other than the person in whose possession it was when seized or detained, who claims an interest in it as owner, mortgagee, hypothecary creditor, lien-holder or holder of any like interest may, within ninety days after the seizure or detention, apply for a decision by the Minister under section 139.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person may apply for a decision by giving notice in writing to the officer who seized or detained the goods or conveyance or to an officer at the customs office closest to the place where the seizure or detention took place.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof of application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The burden of proof that an application has been made under subsection (1) lies on the person claiming to have made it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provision of evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person who applies under subsection (1) must provide evidence that relates to their interest in the seized or detained goods or conveyance and any other evidence requested by the Minister in respect of that interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Manner of giving evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Evidence may be given under subsection (4) by affidavit made before any person authorized by an Act of Parliament or of the legislature of a province to administer oaths or take affidavits.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Late applications</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister may accept an application made within one year after the expiration of the ninety days referred to in subsection (1) by a person who has not claimed an interest in the seized or detained goods or conveyance within those ninety days.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for late applications</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>When making an application under subsection (6), the person must demonstrate to the Minister that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within the time provided in subsection (1) for making an application the person</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>was unable to act or to instruct another person to act in the person’s name, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>had a <Language xml:lang="la">bona fide</Language> intention to apply under that subsection;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it would be just and equitable to grant the application; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application was made as soon as circumstances permitted.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>139.</Label><Text>The Minister must decide an application made under section 138 without delay and, if the Minister is satisfied that the following conditions are met, must make a determination that the applicant’s interest in the goods or conveyance is not affected by the seizure or detention and as to the nature and extent of the applicant’s interest at the time of the contravention or use:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant acquired the interest in good faith before the contravention or use;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant is innocent of any complicity or collusion in the contravention or use; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant exercised all reasonable care in respect of any person permitted to obtain possession of the goods or conveyance in order to satisfy the applicant that it was not likely to be used in a contravention or, if the applicant is a mortgagee, hypothecary creditor or lien-holder, the applicant exercised that care in relation to the mortgagor, hypothecary debtor or lien-giver.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>139.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who makes an application under section 138 may, within ninety days after being notified of the decision, apply for an order under this section by giving notice in writing to the court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of <DefinedTermEn>court</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>court</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the Province of Ontario, the Superior Court of Justice;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the Province of Quebec, the Superior Court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the Provinces of Nova Scotia and British Columbia, the Yukon Territory and the Northwest Territories, the Supreme Court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the Provinces of New Brunswick, Manitoba, Saskatchewan and Alberta, the Court of Queen’s Bench;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the Provinces of Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland, the Trial Division of the Supreme Court; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in Nunavut, the Nunavut Court of Justice.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Date of hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A judge of the court must fix a day, not less than thirty days after the application has been made, for the hearing of the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The applicant, no later than fifteen days before the day fixed for the hearing, must serve notice of the application and of the hearing on the Minister, or an officer designated by the Minister for the purposes of this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Service by registered mail</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Service of the notice is sufficient if it is sent by registered mail addressed to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The applicant is entitled to an order declaring that the applicant’s interest is not affected by the seizure or detention and declaring the nature and extent of the applicant’s interest at the time of the contravention or use if, on the hearing of the application, the court is satisfied that the applicant</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>acquired the interest in good faith prior to the contravention or use;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is innocent of any complicity or collusion in the contravention or use; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>exercised all reasonable care in respect of any person permitted to obtain possession of the goods or conveyance in order to satisfy the applicant that it was not likely to be used in a contravention or, if the applicant is a mortgagee, hypothecary creditor or lien-holder, that the applicant exercised that care in relation to the mortgagor, hypothecary debtor or lien-giver.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>76.</Label><Text>Subsection 140(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>140.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who makes an application under section 139.1 or the Crown may appeal to the court of appeal from an order made under that section and the appeal shall be asserted, heard and decided according to the ordinary procedure governing appeals to the court of appeal from orders or judgments of a court.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, par. 127(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>77.</Label><Text>Section 141 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Goods or conveyance given to applicant</MarginalNote><Label>141.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner, on application by a person whose interest in a conveyance detained under subsection 97.25(2) or in goods or a conveyance seized as forfeit under this Act has been determined under section 139 or ordered under section 139.1 or 140 to be unaffected by the seizure or detention, shall direct that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of goods or a conveyance the forfeiture of which has become final, the goods or conveyance, as the case may be, be given to the applicant; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a conveyance detained under subsection 97.25(2), the conveyance be given to the applicant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amount paid if goods or conveyance sold</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>If goods or a conveyance that is to be given to the applicant has been sold or disposed of, an amount calculated on the basis of the interest of the applicant in the goods or conveyance at the time of the contravention or use, as determined under section 139 or ordered under section 139.1 or 140, shall be paid to the applicant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit on amount paid</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The total amount paid under subsection (1.1) in respect of goods or a conveyance shall, if the goods or conveyance was sold or otherwise disposed of under this Act, not exceed the proceeds of the sale or disposition, if any, less any costs incurred by Her Majesty in respect of the goods or conveyance, and, if there are no proceeds of disposition, no payment shall be made pursuant to subsection (1.1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 8, s. 50; 1992, c. 28, s. 28; 1993, c. 25, s. 87; 2000, c. 30, s. 161(1)</MarginalNote><Label>78.</Label><Text>The heading before section 143 and sections 143 to 147 of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>79.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 148:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Members of partnerships</MarginalNote><Label>148.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a reference in any notice or other document to the firm name of a partnership is to be read as a reference to all the members of the partnership; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any notice or other document is deemed to have been provided to each member of a partnership if the notice or other document is mailed to, served on or otherwise sent to the partnership</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>at its latest known address or place of business, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>at the latest known address</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>if it is a limited partnership, of any member of the limited partnership whose liability as a member is not limited, or</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>in any other case, of any member of the partnership.</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Members of unincorporated bodies</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a reference in any notice or other document to the firm name of an unincorporated body is to be read as a reference to all the members of the body; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any notice or other document is deemed to have been provided to each member of an unincorporated body if the notice or other document is mailed to, served on or otherwise sent to the body at its latest known address or place of business.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>80.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 149:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Proof of no appeal</MarginalNote><Label>149.1</Label><Text>An affidavit of an officer, sworn before a commissioner or other person authorized to take affidavits, setting out that the officer has charge of the appropriate records and has knowledge of the practice of the Agency and that an examination of the records shows that a notice of assessment under Part V.1 was mailed or otherwise sent to a person under this Act and that, after careful examination and search of the records, the officer has been unable to find that a notice of objection or of appeal from the assessment was received within the time allowed for the notice, is evidence of the statements contained in the affidavit.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Objection or appeal</MarginalNote><Label>149.2</Label><Text>If a person who is required under this Act to keep records serves a notice of objection or is a party to an appeal or reference under Part V.1, the person shall retain, until the objection, appeal or reference and any appeal from it is finally disposed of, every record that pertains to the subject-matter of the objection, appeal or reference.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 44, s. 106; 1997, c. 36, s. 191</MarginalNote><Label>81.</Label><Text>Section 159.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Offences re marking of goods</MarginalNote><Label>159.1</Label><Text>No person shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fail to mark imported goods in the manner referred to in section 35.01;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>mark imported goods in a deceptive manner so as to mislead another person as to the country of origin or geographic origin of the goods; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with intent to conceal the information given by or contained in the mark, alter, deface, remove or destroy a mark on imported goods made as required by the regulations made under subsection 19(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 44, s. 107</MarginalNote><Label>82.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 160 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>General offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>160.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 11, 12, 13, 15 or 16, subsection 20(1), section 31 or 40, subsection 43(2), 95(1) or (3), 103(3) or 107(2) or section 153, 155, 156 or 159.1 or commits an offence under section 159 or knowingly contravenes an order referred to in subsection 107(11)</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 160 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court order — subsection 43(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person has been convicted by a court of an offence under subsection (1) for a contravention of subsection 43(2), the court may make any order that it considers appropriate in order to enforce compliance with that subsection.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>83.</Label><Text>Section 161 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Summary conviction offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>161.</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes any of the provisions of this Act not otherwise provided for in section 160 is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine of not more than twenty-five thousand dollars and not less than one thousand dollars or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to both fine and imprisonment.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 7, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>84.</Label><Text>Subsections 163.5(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of designated officers</MarginalNote><Label>163.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In addition to the powers conferred on an officer for the enforcement of this Act, a designated officer who is at a customs office and is performing the normal duties of an officer or is acting in accordance with section 99.1 has, in relation to a criminal offence under any other Act of Parliament, the powers and obligations of a peace officer under sections 495 to 497 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, and subsections 495(3) and 497(3) of that Act apply to the designated officer as if he or she were a peace officer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Impaired driving offences</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A designated officer who is at a customs office and is performing the normal duties of an officer or is acting in accordance with section 99.1 has the powers and obligations of a peace officer under sections 254 and 256 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> and may, on demanding samples of a person’s blood or breath under subsection 254(3) of that Act, require that the person accompany the officer, or a peace officer referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>peace officer</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of that Act, for the purpose of taking the samples.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>85.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 164(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring, in any circumstances that may be prescribed, the owner or person in charge of a conveyance to give advance notice of the time and place of its arrival in Canada and any other information relating to its passengers and goods or its movement inside or outside Canada that may be prescribed, and prescribing the time within which and the manner in which the notice is to be given;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring the payment of costs incurred for the inspection of records held in a place outside of Canada and respecting the manner of determining those costs and the time and manner in which the costs must be paid;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 30(3); 1994, c. 47, s. 72; 1997, c. 14, ss. 47(2), (3)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 164(3) and (4) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>RELATED AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>86.</Label><Text>Schedule II to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by replacing the reference to “section 107” opposite the reference to “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>” with a reference to “sections 107 and 107.1”.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-10</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Post Corporation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>87.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 42 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Post Corporation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Submission of exported mail to customs officer</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>On request of a customs officer, all mail leaving Canada for a place outside Canada that contains or is suspected to contain anything the exportation of which is prohibited, controlled, regulated or subject to reporting under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> or any other Act of Parliament shall be submitted by the Corporation to the customs officer.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 42(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mail subject to customs laws</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A customs officer shall deal with mail submitted to him or her under this section in accordance with the laws relating to customs and the importation and exportation of goods and, subject to those laws, shall deliver it to the addressee, on payment of any postage due, or return it to the Corporation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36</MarginalNote><TitleText>Customs Tariff</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>88.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 123(1) to (3) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Intérêts</MarginalNote><Label>123.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Quiconque est astreint, en application du paragraphe 114(1), à payer une somme, sauf pour des droits perçus au titre de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les mesures spéciales d’importation</XRefExternal>, paie, en plus de cette somme, des intérêts au taux déterminé, calculés sur les arriérés pour la période commençant le lendemain de l’octroi du remboursement ou du drawback et se terminant le jour de son paiement intégral.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Intérêts : contraventions ou réaffectations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sous réserve du paragraphe (4), quiconque est astreint, en application des paragraphes 118(1) ou (2), à payer une somme, sauf pour des droits perçus au titre de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les mesures spéciales d’importation</XRefExternal>, paie, en plus de cette somme, des intérêts au taux qui est déterminé, calculés sur les arriérés pour la période commençant le jour où la somme devient exigible et se terminant le jour de son paiement intégral.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Intérêts : sous-produits ou résidus ou déchets vendables</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Sous réserve du paragraphe (4), quiconque est astreint, en application des articles 121 ou 122, à payer une somme, sauf pour des droits perçus au titre de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les mesures spéciales d’importation</XRefExternal>, paie, en plus de cette somme, des intérêts au taux qui est déterminé, calculés sur les arriérés pour la période commençant le lendemain de la production des sous-produits ou des résidus ou déchets vendables et se terminant le jour de son paiement intégral.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 123(5) and (6) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Computation of interest on certain duties</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who is liable under paragraph 118(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or section 121 or 122 to pay an amount in respect of duty levied under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> shall pay interest at the specified rate for the period beginning on the ninety-first day after the day the amount became payable and ending on the day the amount is paid in full, calculated on the amount of the balance outstanding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Computation of interest on certain duties</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A person who is liable under section 98, subsection 114(1) or paragraph 118(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to repay the amount of a drawback or relief in respect of duty levied under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> and any interest on the drawback shall pay, in addition to those amounts, interest at the specified rate for the period beginning on the first day after the day the drawback was granted or the person failed to comply with a condition to which the relief was subject, as the case may be, and ending on the day those amounts are repaid in full, calculated on the amount of the balance outstanding.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>89.</Label><Text>Section 124 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Interest to be compounded</MarginalNote><Label>124.</Label><Text>Interest computed at a prescribed rate or at a specified rate shall be compounded daily and, if interest computed in respect of an amount under a provision of this Act is unpaid on the day it would, but for this section, have ceased to be computed under that provision, interest at the specified rate, computed and compounded daily on the unpaid interest from that day to the day it is paid, shall be paid in the same manner as the provision requires the principal amount to be paid.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>90.</Label><Text>Subsection 127(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest on SIMA duty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who, under a provision of this Part other than section 115, is granted a drawback or refund of an amount in respect of duty levied under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> shall be granted, in addition to the drawback or refund, interest on it at the prescribed rate for the period beginning on the ninety-first day after the day an application for the drawback or refund is made in accordance with this Part and ending on the day the drawback or refund is granted.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-15</MarginalNote><TitleText>Special Import Measures Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>91.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>release</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>release</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>dédouanement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>release</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of goods, to authorize the removal of the goods from a customs office, sufferance warehouse, bonded warehouse or duty free shop for use in Canada, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of goods to which paragraph 32(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> applies, to receive the goods at the place of business of the importer, owner or consignee;</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (9):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> applies, with any modifications that the circumstances require, in respect of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the payment, collection or refund of any duty levied or returned under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the payment, collection, refund or waiver of interest on duty payable or returned under this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the time within which duties payable under this Act, or security posted under this Act, are deemed to be paid or posted.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 47, s. 149(1), par. 185(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(E); 1999, c. 17, par. 183(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>92.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Imposition of provisional duty</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where the Commissioner makes a preliminary determination of dumping or subsidizing in an investigation under this Act and considers that the imposition of provisional duty is necessary to prevent injury, retardation or threat of injury, the importer in Canada of dumped or subsidized goods that are of the same description as any goods to which the preliminary determination applies and that are released during the period commencing on the day the preliminary determination is made and ending on the earlier of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which the Commissioner causes the investigation to be terminated pursuant to subsection 41(1) with respect to goods of that description, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which the Tribunal makes an order or finding with respect to goods of that description,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>shall, within the time prescribed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of duties, at the option of the importer,</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay or cause to be paid on the imported goods provisional duty in an amount not greater than the estimated margin of dumping of, or the estimated amount of subsidy on, the imported goods, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>post or cause to be posted security for provisional duty in the prescribed form and in an amount or to a value not greater than the estimated margin of dumping of, or the estimated amount of subsidy on, the imported goods.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1988, c. 65, s. 26(1); 1994, c. 47, par. 185(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)(E); 1999, c. 12, ss. 3(1), (2), c. 17, paras. 183(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>), 184(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 8(1.1) and (1.2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Imposition of provisional duties on referral back to Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>If an order or finding of the Tribunal under subsection 43(1), 76.02(4) respecting a review under subsection 76.02(1), or 91(3), other than an order or finding described in any of sections 3 to 6, is referred back to the Tribunal under subsection 77.015(3) or (4) or 77.019(5), or under subsection 77.15(3) or (4) or 77.19(4), the importer of dumped or subsidized goods that are of the same description as any goods to which the order or finding applies and that are released during the period beginning on the day on which the preliminary determination is made under subsection 38(1) and ending on the day on which the Tribunal makes an order or finding, on the referral back, with respect to goods of that description, shall, within the time prescribed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of duties, at the option of the importer,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay or cause to be paid on the imported goods provisional duty in an amount not greater than the estimated margin of dumping of, or the estimated amount of subsidy on, the imported goods; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>post or cause to be posted security for provisional duty in the prescribed form and in an amount or to a value not greater than the estimated margin of dumping of, or the estimated amount of subsidy on, the imported goods.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Imposition of provisional duties on referral back from Federal Court of Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>If an order or finding of the Tribunal under subsection 43(1), 76.02(4) respecting a review under subsection 76.02(1), or 91(3), other than an order or finding described in any of sections 3 to 6, is referred back to the Tribunal by the Federal Court of Appeal, the importer of dumped or subsidized goods that are of the same description as any goods to which the order or finding applies and that are released during the period beginning on the day on which the preliminary determination is made under subsection 38(1) and ending on the day on which the Tribunal makes an order or finding, on the referral back, with respect to goods of that description, shall, within the time prescribed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of duties, at the option of the importer,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>pay or cause to be paid on the imported goods provisional duty in an amount not greater than the estimated margin of dumping of, or the estimated amount of subsidy on, the imported goods; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>post or cause to be posted security for provisional duty in the prescribed form and in an amount or to a value not greater than the estimated margin of dumping of, or the estimated amount of subsidy on, the imported goods.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.), s. 198(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 8(3) and (4) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, par. 183(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 8(6) of the Act after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>shall, within the time prescribed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of duties, at the option of the importer,</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 12, par. 52(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(E), c. 17, par. 183(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 8(6) of the Act after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>post or cause to be posted security for provisional duty in the prescribed form and in an amount or to a value not greater than the estimated margin of dumping of, or the estimated amount of subsidy on, the imported goods.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.), s. 199(2); 1994, c. 47, s. 150; 1999, c. 17, par. 183(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>93.</Label><Text>Section 11 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Duty payable by importer in Canada</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>The importer in Canada of any goods imported into Canada in respect of which duty, other than provisional duty, is payable shall, notwithstanding any security posted pursuant to section 8 or 13.2, pay or cause to be paid all such duties on the goods.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.), s. 200; 1988, c. 65, s. 30</MarginalNote><Label>94.</Label><Text>Section 13.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 47, s. 151; 1999, c. 17, par. 183(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>95.</Label><Text>Subsection 13.2(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Posting of security</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An importer of goods that are of the same description as any goods to which a review under subsection (3) applies and that are released during the period beginning on the day the review is initiated and ending on the day on which the Commissioner completes the review shall, within the time prescribed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> for the payment of duties, post, or cause to be posted, security in the prescribed manner and form and in an amount, or of a value, equal to the margin of dumping of, or amount of subsidy on, the goods.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 47, s. 177</MarginalNote><Label>96.</Label><Text>Paragraph 60(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the whole or a part of any duty, or duty and interest paid (other than interest that was paid because duties were not paid when required by subsection 32(5) or section 33 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>), in excess of the duties owing in respect of the goods shall be returned to the importer forthwith,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>97.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 60:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to be given</MarginalNote><Label>60.1</Label><Text>If a determination or a re-determination has been made under section 55, subsection 56(1) or section 57 or 59, notice of the determination or re-determination shall be given without delay to the importer in Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.), s. 207; 1994, c. 47, s. 178</MarginalNote><Label>98.</Label><Text>Section 62.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>99.</Label><Text>Sections 91 to 98 apply in relation to goods of a NAFTA country as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. T-2</MarginalNote><TitleText>Tax Court of Canada Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 45, s. 55</MarginalNote><Label>100.</Label><Text>Subsection 2.2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>amount in dispute</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, the <DefinedTermEn>amount in dispute</DefinedTermEn> in an appeal means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal under Part V.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the total of all amounts assessed by the Minister of National Revenue under section 97.44 of that Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal under Part IX of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount of tax, net tax and rebate, within the meaning of that Part, that is in issue in the appeal,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any interest or penalty under that Part that is in issue in the appeal, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any amount of tax, net tax or rebate, within the meaning of that Part, that is likely to be affected by the appeal in any other appeal, assessment or proposed assessment of the person who has brought the appeal.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 23, s. 188</MarginalNote><Label>101.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 12(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Court has exclusive original jurisdiction to hear and determine references and appeals to the Court on matters arising under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cultural Property Export and Import Act</XRefExternal>, Part V.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, Part IX of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Petroleum and Gas Revenue Tax Act</XRefExternal>, where references or appeals to the Court are provided for in those Acts.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 45, s. 57(2); 1998, c. 19, s. 290</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 12(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Further jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Court has exclusive original jurisdiction to hear and determine questions referred to it under section 173 or 174 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, section 97.58 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> or section 310 or 311 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extensions of time</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Court has exclusive original jurisdiction to hear and determine applications for extensions of time under section 97.52 or 97.53 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, section 166.2 or 167 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, subsection 103(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, section 304 or 305 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, subsection 28(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or section 33.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cultural Property Export and Import Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 45, s. 58</MarginalNote><Label>102.</Label><Text>Subsection 18.18(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Calculation of time limits</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of calculating a time limit for the purposes of section 18.3003 or 18.3005, the following periods shall be excluded:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the period beginning on December 21 in any year and ending on January 7 of the next year; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the period during which proceedings are stayed in accordance with subsection 106(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, in the case of an appeal under Part V.1 of that Act, or subsection 327(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, in the case of an appeal under Part IX of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 19, s. 295(2)</MarginalNote><Label>103.</Label><Text>Subsection 18.29(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extensions of time</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The provisions referred to in subsection (1) also apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, in respect of applications for extensions of time under section 97.51 or 97.52 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, section 166.2 or 167 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, section 304 or 305 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, subsection 103(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, subsection 28(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or section 33.2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cultural Property Export and Import Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 19, s. 296(1)</MarginalNote><Label>104.</Label><Text>Section 18.3001 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Application — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> and <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>18.3001</Label><Text>Subject to section 18.3002, if a person has so elected in the notice of appeal for an appeal under Part V.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> or Part IX of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> or at such later time as is provided in the rules of Court, this section and sections 18.3003 to 18.302 apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 45, s. 61</MarginalNote><Label>105.</Label><Text>Subsection 18.3002(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Costs</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Court shall, on making an order under subsection (1), order that all reasonable and proper costs of the person who has brought the appeal be borne by Her Majesty in right of Canada where</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal under Part V.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the amount in dispute is equal to or less than $10,000; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal under Part IX of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the amount in dispute is equal to or less than $7,000 and the aggregate of supplies for the prior fiscal year of that person is equal to or less than $1,000,000.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 27, s. 222</MarginalNote><Label>106.</Label><Text>Subsection 18.3003(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Time limit for reply to notice of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>18.3003</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the Minister of National Revenue shall file a reply to a notice of appeal referred to in section 18.3001 within sixty days after the day the Registry of the Court transmits to that Minister the notice of appeal, unless the person who has brought the appeal consents, before or after the sixty day period has elapsed, to the filing of that reply after the expiration of those sixty days or the Court allows the Minister, on application made before or after the expiration of those sixty days, to file the reply after that period.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 45, s. 61</MarginalNote><Label>107.</Label><Text>Subsection 18.3007(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Costs</MarginalNote><Label>18.3007</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Court may, if the circumstances so warrant, make no order as to costs or order that the person who brought an appeal be awarded costs, notwithstanding that under the rules of Court costs would be adjudged to Her Majesty in right of Canada, or make an order that that person be awarded costs, notwithstanding that under the rules of Court no order as to costs would be made if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an order has been made under subsection 18.3002(1) in respect of the appeal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the appeal is not an appeal referred to in subsection 18.3002(3); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>under Part V.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the amount in dispute in the appeal is equal to or less than $50,000, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>under Part IX of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the amount in dispute in the appeal is equal to or less than $50,000 and the aggregate of supplies for the prior fiscal year of the person who brought the appeal is equal to or less than $6,000,000.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 45, s. 61</MarginalNote><Label>108.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 18.3008(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal under Part V.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the amount in dispute was equal to or less than $10,000; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal under Part IX of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the amount in dispute was equal to or less than $7,000 and the aggregate of supplies for the prior fiscal year of that person was equal to or less than $1,000,000.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 19, s. 298</MarginalNote><Label>109.</Label><Text>Subsection 18.3009(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Costs — appeal under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> or <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>18.3009</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an appeal referred to in section 18.3001 is allowed, the Court shall reimburse to the person who brought the appeal the filing fee paid under paragraph 18.15(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) by that person and may award costs, in accordance with the rules of Court, to that person if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal under Part V.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the amount in dispute in the appeal was equal to or less than $10,000 and was reduced by more than one half by the judgement of the Court; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an appeal under Part IX of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount of tax, net tax, rebate, interest or penalty in issue in the appeal was reduced by more than one half by the judgement of the Court,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the amount in dispute was equal to or less than $7,000, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the aggregate of supplies for the prior fiscal year of that person was equal to or less than $1,000,000.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 45, s. 62</MarginalNote><Label>110.</Label><Text>Subsection 18.31(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of question</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If it is agreed under section 97.58 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> or under section 310 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> that a question should be determined by the Court, sections 17.1, 17.2 and 17.4 to 17.8, apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, in respect of the determination of the question.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-11</MarginalNote><Label>111.</Label><Text>If Bill C-11, introduced in the first session of the thirty-seventh Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> (the “other Act”), receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of subsection 107(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 61 of this Act, and the coming into force of section 1 of the other Act, paragraph 107(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official of the Department of Citizenship and Immigration solely for the purpose of administering or enforcing the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, if the information relates to the movement of people into and out of Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>112.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, and the provisions of any Act as enacted by this Act, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>