<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-5</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to enact the Free Trade and Labour Mobility in Canada Act and the Building Canada Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">One Canadian Economy Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>One Canadian Economy Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>2</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2025</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-06-04">91231</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">An Act to enact the Free Trade and Labour Mobility in Canada Act and the Building Canada Act</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Free Trade and Labour Mobility in Canada Act</XRefExternal>, which establishes a statutory framework to remove federal barriers to the interprovincial trade of goods and services and to improve labour mobility within Canada. In the case of goods and services, that Act provides that a good or service that meets provincial or territorial requirements is considered to meet comparable federal requirements that pertain to the interprovincial movement of the good or provision of the service. In the case of workers, it provides for the recognition of provincial and territorial authorizations to practise occupations and for the issuance of comparable federal authorizations to holders of such provincial and territorial authorizations. It also provides the Governor in Council with the power to make regulations respecting federal barriers to the interprovincial movement of goods and provision of services and to the movement of labour within Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 2 enacts the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Building Canada Act</XRefExternal>, which, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>authorizes the Governor in Council to add the name of a project and a brief description of it to a schedule to that Act if the Governor in Council is of the opinion, having regard to certain factors, that the project is in the national interest;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provides that determinations and findings that have to be made and opinions that have to be formed under certain Acts of Parliament and regulations for an authorization to be granted in respect of a project that is named in Schedule 1 to that Act are deemed to have been made or formed, as the case may be, in favour of permitting the project to be carried out in whole or in part;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>requires the minister who is designated under that Act to issue to the proponent of a project, if certain conditions are met, a document that sets out conditions that apply in respect of the project and that is deemed to be the authorizations, required under certain Acts of Parliament and regulations, that are specified in the document; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>requires that minister, each year, to cause an independent review to be conducted of the status of each national interest project.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">One Canadian Economy Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Free Trade and Labour Mobility in Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Enactment of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Free Trade and Labour Mobility in Canada Act</XRefExternal> is enacted as follows:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="yes"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act to promote free trade and labour mobility in Canada</LongTitle><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada intends to remove federal exceptions under the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="agreement">Canadian Free Trade Agreement</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada wishes to continue to work with provinces and territories towards establishing a national system of mutual recognition in which a good, service or worker that meets the requirements of one Canadian jurisdiction would be recognized as meeting the requirements of all;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas Parliament is committed to strengthening the Canadian economy by</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>improving labour mobility within Canada, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>making it easier for businesses and Canadians to buy Canadian goods and services through the removal of federal barriers to the interprovincial movement of goods and provision of services, while continuing to protect the health, safety and security of Canadians, their social and economic well-being and the environment;</Text></Provision></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Free Trade and Labour Mobility in Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal regulatory body</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in relation to a good or service,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a body that is empowered under an Act of Parliament to regulate the good or service, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a body designated by the regulations that regulates the good or service; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to an occupation,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a body that is empowered under an Act of Parliament to issue authorizations to practise the occupation, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a body designated by the regulations that issues authorizations to practise the occupation. (<DefinedTermFr>organisme de réglementation fédéral</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal requirement</DefinedTermEn> means a requirement established under an Act of Parliament or by a federal regulatory body. (<DefinedTermFr>exigence fédérale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada designated under section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial or territorial regulatory body</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in relation to a good or service,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a body that is empowered under an Act of the legislature of a province or territory to regulate the good or service, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a body designated by the regulations that regulates the good or service; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to an occupation,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a body that is empowered under an Act of the legislature of a province or territory to issue authorizations to practise the occupation, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a body designated by the regulations that issues authorizations to practise the occupation. (<DefinedTermFr>organisme de réglementation</DefinedTermFr> <DefinedTermFr>provincial ou territorial</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>provincial or territorial requirement</DefinedTermEn> means a requirement established under an Act of the legislature of a province or territory or by a provincial or territorial regulatory body. (<DefinedTermFr>exigence provinciale ou territoriale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Act and regulations prevail</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act and the regulations made under it prevail over the provisions of any other Act of Parliament and any regulations made under any other Act of Parliament to the extent of any conflict between them.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to promote free trade and labour mobility by removing federal barriers to the interprovincial movement of goods and provision of services and to the movement of labour within Canada while continuing to protect the health, safety and security of Canadians, their social and economic well-being and the environment.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>His Majesty</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Binding on His Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>This Act is binding on His Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation of Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, designate a member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Removal of Barriers</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Goods and Services</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal> apply in respect of a federal requirement only if the federal requirement pertains to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a good or service that is also subject to a provincial or territorial requirement; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the interprovincial movement of the good or provision of the service.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Goods</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, a good produced, used or distributed in accordance with a provincial or territorial requirement is considered to meet any comparable federal requirement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Comparable requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), a provincial or territorial requirement is considered to be comparable to a federal requirement only if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the requirements are in respect of the same aspect or element of the good;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the requirements are intended to achieve a similar objective; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any conditions set out in the regulations are met.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The federal regulatory body responsible for the administration and enforcement of a federal requirement may decide, in accordance with subsection (2), whether a provincial or territorial requirement is comparable to the federal requirement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Services</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, a service provided in accordance with a provincial or territorial requirement is considered to meet any comparable federal requirement so long as the provincial or territorial requirement continues to apply to the service provider.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Comparable requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), a provincial or territorial requirement is considered to be comparable to a federal requirement only if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the requirements are in respect of the same aspect or element of the service;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the requirements are intended to achieve a similar objective; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any conditions set out in the regulations are met.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The federal regulatory body responsible for the administration and enforcement of a federal requirement may decide, in accordance with subsection (2), whether a provincial or territorial requirement is comparable to the federal requirement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Labour Mobility</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Recognition</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, a federal regulatory body must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>recognize an authorization to practise an occupation issued by a provincial or territorial regulatory body as comparable to an authorization that the federal regulatory body may issue to practise that occupation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on application by the holder of such a provincial or territorial authorization, issue them an authorization to practise that occupation.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations respecting federal barriers to the interprovincial movement of goods and provision of services and to the movement of labour within Canada, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>providing for exceptions to subsection <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) or <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>(1) or section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>imposing obligations, prohibitions, conditions and restrictions for the purposes of any of sections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting, for the purposes of subsections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(2) and <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal>(2), the meaning of the expressions “same aspect or element” and “achieve a similar objective” or any term used in those expressions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>respecting the meaning of the term “authorization” for the purposes of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>respecting any transitional matters arising from the coming into force of this Act or of any amendments to it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>respecting anything that by this Act is to be provided for by the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before recommending a regulation to the Governor in Council under paragraph (1)(a) in relation to a federal requirement or authorization, the Minister must consult the federal regulatory body responsible for the administration and enforcement of the federal requirement or for the issuance of the authorization.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Limitation of Liability</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Acts done in good faith</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, no civil action lies against His Majesty, a servant or agent of the Crown or a federal regulatory body in respect of anything done or omitted to be done, or purported to be done or omitted to be done, in good faith in the course of applying section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> or any regulations made for the purposes of any of those sections, including anything in relation to whether provincial or territorial requirements are comparable to federal requirements and the recognition and issuance of authorizations to practise an occupation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsection (1) does not apply in respect of applications for judicial review or to proceedings under Chapter Ten of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="agreement">Canadian Free Trade Agreement</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must complete a review of this Act and its operation and cause a report on the review to be laid before each House of Parliament.</Text></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Free Trade and Labour Mobility in Canada Act</XRefExternal> comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Building Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Enactment of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Building Canada Act</XRefExternal>, whose text is as follows and whose Schedules 1 and 2 are set out in the schedule to this Act, is enacted:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="yes"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act respecting national interest projects</LongTitle><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes that it is in the interests of Canada’s economy, sovereignty and security, including its energy security, to urgently advance projects throughout Canada, including in the North, that are in the national interest, including projects that</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>foster the development of economic and trade corridors,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>connect different parts of the country and get goods to market,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>strengthen Canada’s ability to trade,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Text>create good-paying, unionized jobs, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>enhance the development of Canada’s natural resources as well as its energy production and infrastructure;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to working in partnership with provincial, territorial and Indigenous governments and Indigenous peoples;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to respecting the rights of Indigenous peoples recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> and the rights set out in the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to upholding rigorous standards with respect to environmental protection;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas Parliament affirms the need for projects that are in the national interest to be advanced through an accelerated process that enhances regulatory certainty and investor confidence;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Building Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>authorization</DefinedTermEn> means, in respect of a national interest project, an approval or other decision, or a permit, licence, regulation or other document or instrument, that is required, by a provision of an enactment or, if a portion of an enactment is listed in column 2 of Part 1 or Part 2 of Schedule 2, by that portion of the enactment, to permit the project to be carried out, in whole or in part. (<DefinedTermFr>autorisation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>enactment</DefinedTermEn> means an Act of Parliament listed in column 1 of Part 1 of Schedule 2 or a regulation listed in column 1 of Part 2 of that Schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>texte législatif</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous peoples</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by the definition <DefinitionRef>aboriginal peoples of Canada</DefinitionRef> in subsection 35(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>peuples autochtones</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada designated under section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>national interest project</DefinedTermEn> means a project named in Schedule 1. (<DefinedTermFr>projet d’intérêt national</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Parliamentary Review Committee</DefinedTermEn> means the committee referred to in subsection 62(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergencies Act</XRefExternal>. Its chair or joint chair, on the part of the House of Commons, shall be a member of that House who is not a member of the government party. (<DefinedTermFr>comité d’examen parlementaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation of Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, designate a member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to enhance Canada’s prosperity, national security, economic security, national defence and national autonomy by ensuring that projects that are in the national interest are advanced through an accelerated process that enhances regulatory certainty and investor confidence, while protecting the environment and respecting the rights of Indigenous peoples.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Interest Projects</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National interest</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, for the purposes of section 5, define <DefinitionRef>national interest</DefinitionRef>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Criteria</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In order to promote transparency and predictability, an order made under subsection (1) must set out specific criteria that must be met by the proponent of a project in order for the project to be found to be in the national interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an order is not made within 15 days after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must, within five sitting days of the end of that period, cause to be tabled in each House of Parliament a report that sets out the reasons for the delay and the expected timeline for the making of the order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Power of Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Governor in Council is of the opinion that a project is in the national interest, the Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, by order, amend Schedule 1 to add the name of the project and a detailed description of it, including the location where it is to be carried out.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication and consent of province or territory</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Before adding the name of a project to Schedule 1, the Governor in Council must cause a notice of 30 days, that includes the name and description of the project, to be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="canada-gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> and must consult with the government of the province or territory in which the project will be carried out, and obtain its written consent if the project falls within areas of exclusive provincial or territorial jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council is not authorized to make an order under subsection (1) while Parliament is prorogued or dissolved or after the fifth anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, by order, amend Schedule 1 to amend the name or the description of a national interest project.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deletion</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the Governor in Council is of the opinion that a project named in Schedule 1 is no longer in the national interest, the Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, by order, amend that Schedule to delete the name and the description of the project.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council is not authorized to make an order under subsection (4) in respect of a national interest project after a document is issued in respect of the project under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In deciding whether to make an order under subsection (1) or (4) in respect of a project, the Governor in Council may consider any factor that the Governor in Council considers relevant, including the extent to which the project can</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>strengthen Canada’s autonomy, resilience and security;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide economic or other benefits to Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>have a high likelihood of successful execution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>advance the interests of Indigenous peoples; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>contribute to clean growth and to meeting Canada’s objectives with respect to climate change.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions — conflict of interest</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>Before recommending that an order be made under subsection (1), the Minister must be satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the proponent of the project, or any director, officer or significant shareholder of the proponent, has not been found to have committed a violation under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Conflict of Interest Act</XRefExternal> and is not the subject of an ongoing proceeding in respect of a violation under that Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>every <DefinitionRef>reporting public office holder</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act, who could be in a conflict of interest in relation to the proponent of the project has recused themselves under that Act to avoid the conflict.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Before recommending that an order be made under any of subsections (1), (3) and (4), the Minister must consult with any other federal minister and any provincial or territorial government that the Minister considers appropriate and with Indigenous peoples whose rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> may be adversely affected by the carrying out of the project to which the order relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to an order made under subsection (1), (3) or (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="canada-gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (1), (3) or (4), and the reasons for it, must be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="canada-gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> as soon as feasible after it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in registry</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Within 30 days after an order is made under subsection (1), details of the project in respect of which the order is made must be published in the registry established under section 5.1.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Public registry</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must establish and maintain a public registry of national interest projects that is made accessible to the public through the Internet.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content of registry</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must include in the registry in respect of each project</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a detailed description of the project and the reasons why it is in the national interest;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the extent to which the project is expected to meet the outcomes set out in paragraphs 5(6)(a) to (d);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>detailed cost estimates that do not include private sector commercially sensitive financial information; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the estimated timelines for completion of the project.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deeming — favourable determinations, findings and opinions</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every determination and finding that has to be made and every opinion that has to be formed in order for an authorization to be granted in respect of a national interest project is deemed to be made or formed, as the case may be, in favour of permitting the project to be carried out in whole or in part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not exempt the proponent of a project from the requirement to take all measures that they are required to take, under an enactment, in respect of an authorization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An authorization is not to be granted solely on the basis of the deeming provision in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to issue document</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must issue to the proponent of a national interest project a document that is deemed to be each authorization that is specified in the document in respect of the project.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions to issuing document</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before a document is issued under subsection (1),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Minister must be satisfied that the proponent has taken all measures, including providing any information and paying any fees, that the proponent is required to take in respect of each authorization that is specified in the document;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Minister must consult the minister who is responsible for the enactment under which each authorization is required with respect to the conditions that should be set out in the document;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>the Minister must undertake a national security review for all state-owned or foreign investments from hostile countries in any national interest project;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Indigenous peoples whose rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> may be adversely affected by the carrying out of the project to which the document relates must be consulted; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the Minister must be satisfied that, with regard to any foreign investments in the project, all necessary measures have been taken to protect national security interests.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Participation of Indigenous peoples and report</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of consultations required under paragraph (2)(c), the Minister must ensure that a process is established that allows for the active and meaningful participation of the affected Indigenous peoples and that a report of the consultation process and results is made available to the public within 60 days after the day on which a document is issued under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>With respect to each authorization that is specified in it, the document is deemed to be the authorization issued under the enactment under which the authorization is required and to meet all of the requirements, under any enactment, that relate to the issuance of the authorization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, any powers that may be exercised and any duties and functions that may be performed in relation to an authorization that is specified in the document may be exercised or performed in relation to an authorization that is deemed to be issued in accordance with subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The document must set out the conditions that apply with respect to each authorization that is specified in it. The conditions set out in the document with respect to each authorization are deemed to be conditions imposed under the enactment under which the authorization is required.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subject matter of conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The conditions set out in the document with respect to each authorization must be conditions that could have been imposed under the enactment under which the authorization is required, taking into account subsection <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the document.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Document available to public</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The document, including any amendments to it, must be made available to the public in the manner determined by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Documents and information to be made public</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>All documents and information used to issue the document must also be made public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expiry</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>If the national interest project has not been substantially started within five years of the issuance of the document, the document expires.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Power to amend conditions</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may amend any condition that is set out in a document issued under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power to add authorizations and conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may amend a document issued under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) to specify additional authorizations and set out conditions in respect of each additional authorization, in accordance with section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Before amending a condition or document under subsection (1) or (2), the Minister must consult with</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the minister who is responsible for the enactment under which each authorization to which the amendment relates is required; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Indigenous peoples whose rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> may be adversely affected by the amendment.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister is not authorized to amend a condition under subsection (1) while Parliament is prorogued or dissolved or after the fifth anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Information available to public</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When the Minister establishes the conditions for issuing the document that is deemed to be each authorization that is specified in the document in respect of a national interest project under section 7, the Minister must make public</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>all the conditions that apply to the project;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the full contents of the studies and impact assessments conducted regarding the project;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>all the recommendations received from federal departments and agencies regarding the project;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in an accessible written document, the reasons some of the recommendations were not accepted; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a description of the normal regulatory process that would have been followed if the project had not been designated as a national interest project.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content — document under paragraph (1)(d)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The document referred to in paragraph (1)(d) must include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a comparative analysis of the conditions imposed and the recommendations received;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an assessment of the risks of disregarding the recommendations that were not accepted; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any alternative mitigation measures implemented.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>30 days to make information public</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must, not later than 30 days before the document referred to in section 7 is issued, make public the information set out in paragraphs (1)(a) to (e).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause to be tabled a report containing the information set out in paragraphs (1)(a) to (e) in each House of Parliament and, at the request of 10 or more members of that House, must appear, to explain the Minister’s decisions in establishing the conditions, before the committee of Parliament designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada–Newfoundland and Labrador Atlantic Accord Implementation and Offshore Renewable Energy Management Act</XRefExternal> — subsection 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before issuing a document under subsection 7(1) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada–Newfoundland and Labrador Atlantic Accord Implementation and Offshore Renewable Energy Management Act</XRefExternal> applies, the Minister must consult with the Canada–Newfoundland and Labrador Offshore Energy Regulator with respect to the conditions that should be set out in the document.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsections 8(1) and (2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before amending a condition or document under subsection 8(1) or (2) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada–Newfoundland and Labrador Atlantic Accord Implementation and Offshore Renewable Energy Management Act</XRefExternal> applies, the Minister must consult with the Canada–Newfoundland and Labrador Offshore Energy Regulator with respect to the amendment.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada–Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation and Offshore Renewable Energy Management Act</XRefExternal> — subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1)</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Before issuing a document under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada–Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation and Offshore Renewable Energy Management Act</XRefExternal> applies, the Minister must consult with the Canada–Nova Scotia Offshore Energy Regulator with respect to the conditions that should be set out in the document.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) and (2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before amending a condition or document under subsection <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada–Nova Scotia Offshore Petroleum Resources Accord Implementation and Offshore Renewable Energy Management Act</XRefExternal> applies, the Minister must consult with the Canada–Nova Scotia Offshore Energy Regulator with respect to the amendment.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Nuclear Safety and Control Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation — subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1)</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>Before issuing a document under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Nuclear Safety and Control Act</XRefExternal> applies, the Minister must consult with the Canadian Nuclear Safety Commission with respect to the conditions that should be set out in the document.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation — subsections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) and (2)</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>Before amending a condition or document under subsection <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Nuclear Safety and Control Act</XRefExternal> applies, the Minister must consult with the Canadian Nuclear Safety Commission with respect to the amendment.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limit — subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1)</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>The Minister is not authorized to issue a document under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Nuclear Safety and Control Act</XRefExternal> applies unless the Minister receives confirmation from the Canadian Nuclear Safety Commission that it is satisfied that issuing the document will not compromise the health or safety of persons, national security or the implementation of international obligations to which Canada has agreed.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limit — subsections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) and (2)</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>The Minister is not authorized to amend a condition or document under subsection <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Nuclear Safety and Control Act</XRefExternal> applies unless the Minister receives confirmation from the Canadian Nuclear Safety Commission that it is satisfied that the amendment will not compromise the health or safety of persons, national security or the implementation of international obligations to which Canada has agreed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation — subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1)</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>Before issuing a document under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal> applies, the Minister must consult with the Commission of the Canadian Energy Regulator with respect to the conditions that should be set out in the document.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation — subsections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) and (2)</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>Before amending a condition or document under subsection <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal> applies, the Minister must consult with the Commission of the Canadian Energy Regulator with respect to the amendment.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limit — subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1)</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>The Minister is not authorized to issue a document under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal> applies unless the Minister receives confirmation from the Commission of the Canadian Energy Regulator that it is satisfied that issuing the document will not compromise the safety or security of persons or <DefinitionRef>regulated facilities</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limit — subsections <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) and (2)</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>The Minister is not authorized to amend a condition or document under subsection <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal>(1) or (2) in respect of a project to which the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal> applies unless the Minister receives confirmation from the Commission of the Canadian Energy Regulator that it is satisfied that the amendment will not compromise the safety or security of persons or <DefinitionRef>regulated facilities</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Impact Assessment Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Non-application of certain provisions</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>If a national interest project is also a <DefinitionRef>designated project</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Impact Assessment Act</XRefExternal>, sections 9 to 17 and subsections 18(3) to (6) of that Act do not apply in respect of the project and, for the purposes of section 18 of that Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Impact Assessment Agency of Canada is deemed to have decided that an <DefinitionRef>impact assessment</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act, of the project is required; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the time limit set out in subsection 18(1) of that Act does not apply in respect of the project.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Office</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Role</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text>An office may be established to coordinate the exercise of powers and the performance of duties and functions under this Act and the enactments with respect to projects that are in the national interest and to serve as a source of information and point of contact for the proponents of those projects. If an office is established, the Minister is responsible for it.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Amendment to Schedule 2</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Add, amend or delete</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the Governor in Council may, by order, amend Schedule 2 to add, amend or delete the name of an Act of Parliament or a regulation or the reference to a portion of an Act of Parliament or a regulation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council is not authorized to amend Schedule 2 to add the name of any of the following Acts of Parliament or of any regulation made under any of those Acts, or a reference to a portion of any of those Acts or regulations:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Elections Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Conflict of Interest Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Influence Transparency and Accountability Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Investment Canada Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lobbying Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Use of French in Federally Regulated Private Businesses Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Auditor General Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Extractive Sector Transparency Measures Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Railway Safety Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trade Unions Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Explosives Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Hazardous Products Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council is not authorized to make an order under subsection (1) while Parliament is prorogued or dissolved or after the fifth anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations — enactment</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the minister responsible for an enactment, make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>exempting one or more national interest projects from the application of any provision of that enactment or any provision of regulations made under that enactment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>varying the application of any provision referred to in paragraph (a) in relation to one or more national interest projects.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council is not authorized to make regulations under subsection (1) while Parliament is prorogued or dissolved or after the fifth anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations — this Act</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations generally for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council is not authorized to make regulations under subsection (1) while Parliament is prorogued or dissolved or after the fifth anniversary of the day on which this section comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Annual Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review: national interest project</MarginalNote><Label>23.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 90 days after the end of each financial year, the Minister must cause an independent review to be conducted of the status of each national interest project that, in respect of each project, provides an assessment of the progress made on measurable outcomes, including in relation to timelines and budgets.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report on review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause a report of the review to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the review is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on an Internet site that is available to the public within 10 days after the day on which it has been tabled in both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review by Parliamentary Review Committee</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Parliamentary Review Committee is to review the Governor in Council’s and the Minister’s exercise of their powers and performance of their duties and functions under this Act and to report to each House of Parliament the results of its review at least once every 180 days while Parliament is neither prorogued nor dissolved.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review by Minister and report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister must complete a review of the provisions and operation of this Act and must cause a report on the review to be laid before the Parliamentary Review Committee and each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Common good of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The review is to be based on the common good of Canada, assured in part by the pursuit of the objectives set out in section 4 relating to shared jurisdiction, public safety, national and international security, the quality of the environment, public health, transparency, public participation and the protection of the rights of Indigenous peoples and linguistic communities.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 1</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> and subsections <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal>(1), (3) and (4))</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10"><table frame="topbot"><title>National Interest Projects</title><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="11.55*"/><colspec colname="2" colwidth="52.03*"/><colspec colname="3" colwidth="35.41*"/><thead><row rowsep="0" topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="2" valign="bottom"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom"></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0">Column 1</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0">Column 2</entry></row><row rowsep="1" topmarginspacing="2" valign="bottom"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Item</entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" valign="bottom">Name of Project</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" valign="bottom">Description of Project</entry></row></thead><tbody><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE 2</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal>)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10"><Caption position="over">PART 1</Caption><table frame="topbot"><title>Acts of Parliament</title><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="10.58*"/><colspec colname="2" colwidth="52.99*"/><colspec colname="3" colwidth="35.40*"/><thead><row rowsep="0" topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="2" valign="bottom"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom"></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0">Column 1</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0">Column 2</entry></row><row rowsep="1" topmarginspacing="2" valign="bottom"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Item</entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" valign="bottom">Act of Parliament</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" valign="bottom">Portion</entry></row></thead><tbody><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">2</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">International River Improvements Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">3</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">4</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Navigable Waters Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">5</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Dominion Water Power Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">6</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Migratory Birds Convention Act, 1994</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">7</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">section 98</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">8</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada Marine Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">9</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">Division 3 of Part 7</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">10</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Species at Risk Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">11</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">subsection 186(1)</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">paragraph 262(1)(c)</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">12</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Impact Assessment Act</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup><TableGroup pointsize="8" topmarginspacing="10"><Caption position="over">PART 2</Caption><table frame="topbot"><title>Regulations</title><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="1" colwidth="11.55*"/><colspec colname="2" colwidth="52.19*"/><colspec colname="3" colwidth="35.24*"/><thead><row rowsep="0" topdouble="yes" topmarginspacing="2" valign="bottom"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="bottom"></entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0">Column 1</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0">Column 2</entry></row><row rowsep="1" topmarginspacing="2" valign="bottom"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="1" valign="bottom">Item</entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" valign="bottom">Regulations</entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" valign="bottom">Portion</entry></row></thead><tbody><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">1</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Migratory Bird Sanctuary Regulations</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row rowsep="0" topmarginspacing="2"><entry colname="1" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top">2</entry><entry colname="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Dominion Water Power Regulations</XRefExternal></entry><entry colname="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0" valign="top"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">3</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Wildlife Area Regulations</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">4</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Marine Mammal Regulations</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">5</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Port Authorities Operations Regulations</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">sections 25 and 27</entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">6</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Metal and Diamond Mining Effluent Regulations</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row><row topmarginspacing="2"><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">7</entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Migratory Birds Regulations, 2022</XRefExternal></entry><entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></TableGroup></Schedule></Schedule></Bill>