<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-35</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50-51</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001-2002</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Foreign Missions and International Organizations Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Foreign Missions and International Organizations Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Foreign Missions and International Organizations</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2002</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>12</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2002</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2002-4-30">90163</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Missions and International Organizations Act</XRefExternal> to modernize the privileges and immunities regime. This will allow Canada to comply with its existing commitments under international treaties and to respond to recent developments in international law. The enactment also corrects the deficiency in the existing statutory definition of <DefinedTermEn>international organization</DefinedTermEn>. The enactment further provides that the Royal Canadian Mounted Police has the primary responsibility to ensure the security for the proper functioning of intergovernmental conferences. This clearer statutory authority supports security measures taken by Canadian police in fulfilling Canada’s obligations to protect persons who have privileges and immunities under the Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 41</MarginalNote><TitleText>FOREIGN MISSIONS AND INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>international organization</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Missions and International Organizations Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>international organization</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>organisation internationale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>international organization</DefinedTermEn> means an intergovernmental organization, whether or not established by treaty, of which two or more states are members, and includes an intergovernmental conference in which two or more states participate;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>accredited mission</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>mission accréditée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>accredited mission</DefinedTermEn> means a permanent mission of a foreign state that is accredited to an international organization headquartered in Canada;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Detention of goods</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister of Foreign Affairs may, by order, authorize the detention by officers under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> of goods imported by a diplomatic mission or consular post of a foreign state for any period during which, in the opinion of the Minister, the foreign state applies any of the provisions of the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations or the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations restrictively with the result that the privileges and immunities accorded to that state’s diplomatic mission and consular posts in Canada exceed those accorded to a Canadian diplomatic mission and Canadian consular posts in that foreign state.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5(1) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Privileges and immunities</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, provide that</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (1.2), accredited missions shall, to the extent specified in the order, have privileges and immunities comparable to the privileges and immunities accorded to diplomatic missions of foreign states in Canada under the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>representatives of a foreign state that is a member of or participates in an international organization shall, to the extent specified in the order, have the privileges and immunities set out in Article IV of the Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the United Nations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>representatives of a foreign state that is a member of an international organization headquartered in Canada, and members of their families forming part of their households, shall, to the extent specified in the order, have privileges and immunities comparable to the privileges and immunities accorded to diplomatic representatives, and members of their families forming part of their households, in Canada under the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>members of the administrative and technical staff, and members of their families forming part of their households, and the service staff of the mission of a foreign state that is a member of an international organization headquartered in Canada, other than persons who are Canadian citizens or permanent residents of Canada, shall, to the extent specified in the order, have privileges and immunities comparable to the privileges and immunities accorded to such persons under the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>que les hauts fonctionnaires d’une organisation internationale désignés par lui — ainsi que, dans le cas d’une organisation internationale ayant son siège au Canada, les membres de leur famille faisant partie de leur ménage — bénéficient, dans la mesure spécifiée, de privilèges et immunités comparables à ceux dont bénéficient respectivement les agents diplomatiques et, le cas échéant, les membres de leur famille faisant partie de leur ménage, en vertu de la Convention de Vienne sur les relations diplomatiques;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>such other classes of persons as may be designated by the Governor in Council who, in accordance with a treaty, convention or agreement set out in Schedule IV, are entitled to privileges and immunities, and members of their families forming part of their households, shall, to the extent specified in the order, have privileges and immunities comparable to the privileges and immunities accorded to diplomatic agents, and members of their families forming part of their households, under the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retroactive order</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>An order made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or subsection 6(2) that has the effect of granting to an international organization or to an office of a political subdivision of a foreign state, as the case may be, any duty or tax relief privileges may, in relation to those privileges, if it so provides, be made retroactive.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty and tax relief privileges — accredited missions</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>An order made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) may restrict or withdraw any duty or tax relief privileges in relation to a particular accredited mission for the purpose of according to that accredited mission treatment that is comparable to the treatment accorded by the foreign state in question to a Canadian permanent mission that is accredited to an international organization in that foreign state.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retroactive order</MarginalNote><Label>(1.3)</Label><Text>An order made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) that has the effect of granting to an accredited mission of the International Civil Aviation Organization any tax relief privileges in relation to Part IX of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> may, in relation to those privileges, if it so provides, be made retroactive and have effect with respect to any period beginning on January 1, 1991 at the earliest and ending on December 31, 2000 at the latest.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Immigration restrictions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency or conflict between an order made under subsection (1) and section 19 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration Act</XRefExternal>, the order prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 5, par. 25(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Privileges, immunities and benefits</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (4), the Minister of Foreign Affairs may, by order,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>grant to the office of a political subdivision of a foreign state, and to any person connected with that office, any of the privileges and immunities accorded under section 3 to consular posts, and to persons connected with those posts, other than duty and tax relief privileges;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>extend any of the privileges and immunities granted under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to that office, and to any person connected with it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>grant to that office, and to any person connected with it, any of the benefits set out in the regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>withdraw any of the privileges, immunities or benefits granted under this subsection or subsection (2); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>restore any privilege, immunity or benefit withdrawn under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty and tax relief privileges</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (4), on the joint recommendation of the Minister of Foreign Affairs and the Minister of Finance, the Governor in Council may, by order,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>grant to the office of a political subdivision of a foreign state, and to any person connected with that office, any of the duty and tax relief privileges accorded under section 3 to consular posts and to persons connected with those posts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>extend any of the duty and tax relief privileges provided for in the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations that have been granted to that office, and to any person connected with it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>grant to that office, and to any person connected with it, any duty or tax relief privilege not provided for in the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Condition</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Before the Minister makes an order under subsection (1) or the Governor in Council makes an order under subsection (2), the Minister or the Governor in Council, as the case may be, must be of the opinion that the office of the political subdivision of the foreign state performs, in Canada, duties that are substantially the same as the duties performed in Canada by a consular post as defined in Article 1 of the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Purpose of orders</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (1) or (2) must be for the purpose of according to the office of the political subdivision of the foreign state, and to any person connected with the office, treatment that is comparable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the treatment accorded to the office of a Canadian political subdivision in the foreign state, and to persons connected with that office; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if there is no office of a Canadian political subdivision in the foreign state, to the treatment that, in the opinion of the Minister or the Governor in Council, as the case may be, would, on the basis of assurances offered by that foreign state, be accorded to an office of a Canadian political subdivision in that foreign state, and to persons connected with that office.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Premises and archives</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister of Foreign Affairs may, by order, grant to the office of a political subdivision of a foreign state, and to the archives of that office, any of the immunities accorded to consular premises and consular archives by the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations for the purpose of according to that office treatment that is comparable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the treatment accorded to the office of a Canadian political subdivision in the foreign state; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if there is no office of a Canadian political subdivision in the foreign state, to the treatment that, in the opinion of the Minister, would, on the basis of assurances offered by that foreign state, be accorded to an office of a Canadian political subdivision in that foreign state.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 10:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Security of Intergovernmental Conferences</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Role of RCMP</MarginalNote><Label>10.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Royal Canadian Mounted Police has the primary responsibility to ensure the security for the proper functioning of any intergovernmental conference in which two or more states participate, that is attended by persons granted privileges and immunities under this Act and to which an order made or continued under this Act applies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of RCMP</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of carrying out its responsibility under subsection (1), the Royal Canadian Mounted Police may take appropriate measures, including controlling, limiting or prohibiting access to any area to the extent and in a manner that is reasonable in the circumstances.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The powers referred to in subsection (2) are set out for greater certainty and shall not be read as affecting the powers that peace officers possess at common law or by virtue of any other federal or provincial Act or regulation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Arrangements</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1), to facilitate consultation and cooperation between the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and provincial and municipal police forces, the Solicitor General may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, enter into arrangements with the government of a province concerning the responsibilities of members of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police and members of provincial and municipal police forces with respect to ensuring the security for the proper functioning of a conference referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 5, par. 25(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Section 11 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate of Minister of Foreign Affairs</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>A certificate purporting to be issued by or under the authority of the Minister of Foreign Affairs and containing any statement of fact relevant to any of the following questions shall be received in evidence in any action or proceeding as proof of the fact stated in the certificate without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the certificate:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether a diplomatic mission, a consular post or an office of a political subdivision of a foreign state has been established with the consent of the Government of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether an organization or conference is the subject of an order under section 5;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether a mission is accredited to an international organization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether any premises or archives are the premises or archives of an office of a political subdivision of a foreign state; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether any person, diplomatic mission, consular post, office of a political subdivision of a foreign state, international organization or accredited mission has privileges, immunities or benefits under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Importation of Alcohol</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Importation of alcohol</MarginalNote><Label>11.1</Label><Text>For greater certainty,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who, or a diplomatic mission, consular post, accredited mission or office of a political subdivision of a foreign state that, has privileges and immunities that are comparable to the privileges and immunities accorded under Article 36 of the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations or Article 50 of the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations may, despite any provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</XRefExternal>, exercise those privileges and benefit from those immunities in respect of alcohol imported for their personal consumption or official use, as the case may be; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an international organization that has privileges and immunities that are comparable to the privileges and immunities accorded under Section 7 of Article II of the Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the United Nations may, despite any provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</XRefExternal>, exercise those privileges and benefit from those immunities in respect of alcohol imported for its official use.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>The heading before section 12 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations and Orders</TitleText></Heading><?Pub Caret?></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment to Schedule IV</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purpose of paragraph 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">h.1</Emphasis>), the Governor in Council may, by order, add to or delete from Schedule IV a reference to a treaty, convention or agreement, or amend a reference in that Schedule.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding, after Schedule III, the schedule set out in the schedule to this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-11</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>If Bill C-11, introduced in the first session of the 37th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> (“the other Act”), receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>this Act, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the first of sections 33 to 43 of the other Act to come into force,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>subsection 5(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Foreign Missions and International Organizations Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Immigration restrictions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency or conflict between an order made under subsection (1) and any of sections 33 to 43 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, the order prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section></Body><Schedule><RunningHead>Foreign Missions and International Organizations — Schedule</RunningHead><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 9)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE IV</Label><OriginatingRef>(Paragraph 5(1)(h.1) and subsection 13(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>DESIGNATED TREATIES, CONVENTIONS AND AGREEMENTS</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Agreement with the Preparatory Commission for the Comprehensive Nuclear Test-Ban Treaty Organization</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Accord avec la Commission préparatoire pour l’Organisation du Traité d’interdiction complète des essais nucléaires</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Convention on the Prohibition of the Development, Production, Stockpiling and Use of Chemical Weapons, and on their Destruction</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Convention sur l’interdiction de la mise au point, de la fabrication, du stockage et de l’emploi des armes chimiques et sur leur destruction</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Provision></DocumentInternal></Schedule></Schedule></Bill>