<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>S-40</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50-51</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001-2002</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Payment Clearing and Settlement Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Payment Clearing and Settlement Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Payment Clearing and Settlement</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2002</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>4</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>14</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2002</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2002-6-4">90180</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payment Clearing and Settlement Act</XRefExternal> to protect the netting agreements of a securities and derivatives clearing house and to permit a securities and derivatives clearing house to realize the collateral of a member in the event of the bankruptcy or insolvency of the member.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payment Clearing and Settlement Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 13:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Securities and Derivatives Clearing Houses</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Securities and derivatives clearing houses</MarginalNote><Label>13.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Nothing in any law relating to bankruptcy or insolvency or in any order of a court made in respect of the administration of a reorganization, arrangement or receivership involving insolvency, including in any foreign law or order of a foreign court, has the effect of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>preventing a securities and derivatives clearing house from</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>if it is a party to a netting agreement, terminating the agreement and determining a net termination value or net settlement amount in accordance with the provisions of the agreement, with the party entitled to the value or amount becoming a creditor of the party owing the value or amount for that value or amount, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>acting in accordance with any of its rules that provide the basis on which payment and delivery obligations are calculated, netted and settled; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>interfering with the rights or remedies of a securities and derivatives clearing house in respect of any collateral that has been granted to it to secure the performance of obligations by a clearing member.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of this section, the Minister may designate an entity, other than one mentioned in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>securities and derivatives clearing house</DefinedTermEn> in subsection (3), as a securities and derivatives clearing house if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister is of the opinion that it is in the public interest to do so; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the entity provides clearing and settlement services to its clearing members in respect of transactions that involve securities or derivatives.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>clearing member</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>membre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>clearing member</DefinedTermEn> means a person who uses the services of a securities and derivatives clearing house.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>net termination value</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>reliquat net</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>net termination value</DefinedTermEn> means the net amount obtained after setting off or otherwise netting the obligations between a securities and derivatives clearing house and a clearing member in accordance with the netting agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>netting agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord de compensation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>netting agreement</DefinedTermEn> means an agreement between a securities and derivatives clearing house and a clearing member that is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an eligible financial contract within the meaning of section 22.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Winding-up and Restructuring Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an agreement that provides for the netting or setting off of present or future obligations to make payments or deliveries against present or future rights to receive payments or take deliveries.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>securities and derivatives clearing house</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>chambre spécialisée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>securities and derivatives clearing house</DefinedTermEn> means, in addition to an entity designated under subsection (2),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Canadian Derivatives Clearing Corporation, incorporated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>The Canadian Depository For Securities Limited, a corporation resulting from an amalgamation under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the WCE Clearing Corporation, incorporated under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">The Corporations Act</XRefExternal>, chapter C225 of the Re-enacted Statutes of Manitoba 1987.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>