<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-22</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50-51</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001-2002</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to provide for the recognition of the Canadian horse as the national horse of Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">National Horse of Canada Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Horse of Canada</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2002</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>30</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2002</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2002-4-30">36002</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment recognizes the Canadian horse as the national horse of Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>WHEREAS the Canadian horse was introduced into Canada in 1665, when the King of France sent horses from his own stables to the people of his North American colony;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS the Canadian horse increased in number during the ensuing century to become an invaluable ally to the settlers in their efforts to survive and prosper in their new home;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS all Canadians who have known the Canadian horse have made clear their high esteem for the qualities of great strength and endurance, resilience, intelligence and good temper that distinguish the breed;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS the Canadian horse was at one time in danger of being lost through interbreeding or as a casualty of war, but has survived these perils;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS, since 1885 and all during the present century, widespread and increasingly successful efforts have been made to re-establish and preserve the Canadian horse;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>AND WHEREAS the Government of Canada wishes to recognize the unique place of the Canadian horse in the history of Canada;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Horse of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>THE NATIONAL HORSE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>National horse</MarginalNote><?Pub Caret?><Label>2.</Label><Text>The horse known as the Canadian horse is hereby recognized and declared to be the national horse of Canada.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>