<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-37</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50-51</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001-2002</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to facilitate the implementation of those provisions of first nations’ claim settlements in the Provinces of Alberta and Saskatchewan that relate to the creation of reserves or the addition of land to existing reserves, and to make related amendments to the Manitoba Claim Settlements Implementation Act and the Saskatchewan Treaty Land Entitlement Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan) Implementation Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2002</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>3</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2002</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2002-3-21">90068</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment creates the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan) Implementation Act</XRefExternal>. This new Act establishes mechanisms to facilitate the implementation of those provisions of first nations’ claim settlements in Alberta and Saskatchewan that relate to the creation of reserves or the addition of lands to existing reserves. The new Act empowers the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development to set land apart as a reserve, and allows for the accommodation of third-party rights and interests in that land during the process of setting it apart as a reserve.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>The enactment makes related amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Manitoba Claim Settlements Implementation Act</XRefExternal> to make the relevant provisions of that Act consistent with the corresponding provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan) Implementation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Finally, the enactment makes related amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Saskatchewan Treaty Land Entitlement Act</XRefExternal></Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to ensure that section 9 of that Act and the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan) Implementation Act</XRefExternal> will not both apply to a given Saskatchewan treaty land entitlement settlement agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to give legislative confirmation to any NRTA Amendment Agreements between Canada and Saskatchewan (i.e. agreements to vary the Natural Resources Transfer Agreement) that are concluded on terms similar to those of the NRTA Amendment Agreement already confirmed by section 3 of that Act; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to effect minor technical changes to that Act.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>CLAIM SETTLEMENTS (ALBERTA AND SASKATCHEWAN) IMPLEMENTATION ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan) Implementation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>council of the first nation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>conseil de la première nation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>council of the first nation</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as the expression “council of the band” in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>first nation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>première nation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>first nation</DefinedTermEn> means a band within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>mines and minerals</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>mines et minéraux</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>mines and minerals</DefinedTermEn> means mines and minerals, whether precious or base, and includes oil and gas, and royalties derived from mines and minerals, but excludes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in Alberta, sand and gravel that is on the surface of the land, and royalties derived from that sand and gravel; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in Saskatchewan, all sand and gravel, and royalties derived from sand and gravel.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>reserve</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>réserve</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>reserve</DefinedTermEn> means a reserve within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application of Act</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>This Act applies in respect of any agreement, including amendments made to it from time to time in accordance with its provisions, to which a first nation in Alberta or Saskatchewan and Her Majesty in right of Canada are parties and by which lands are to be set apart as reserves, if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an agreement named in the schedule, the council of the first nation has adopted a resolution assenting to the application of this Act in relation to the agreement; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the agreement provides for the application of this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deposit of agreements</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Minister shall have a copy of each agreement to which this Act applies, and of any amendments made to it, deposited in the library of the Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development situated in the National Capital Region and in such regional offices of that Department and other places as the Minister considers advisable.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Setting lands apart</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in accordance with an agreement to which this Act applies, set apart as a reserve any lands the title to which is vested in Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Third parties</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Lands set apart as a reserve under this section are subject to any right or interest of a third party in the lands or in its mines and minerals if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the agreement contemplates the continuation of rights or interests of that kind, and any requirement of the agreement with respect to the continuation of the right or interest has been satisfied;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the right or interest has been granted to the third party under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Real Property and Federal Immovables Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the right or interest is granted to the third party in accordance with section 6 or 7.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of surrendered right or interest</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the council of a first nation has, by resolution, requested that the Minister set apart certain lands as a reserve under an agreement to which this Act applies, the first nation may, either</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>before the lands are transferred to Her Majesty in right of Canada by the first nation, by Her Majesty in right of Alberta, by Her Majesty in right of Saskatchewan or by a third party, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>before the lands are set apart as a reserve under section 5,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>designate conditionally or unconditionally, by way of a surrender to Her Majesty in right of Canada that is not absolute, any right or interest in the lands, including for the purpose of the replacement of an existing right or interest in those lands.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 39, 40 and 41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> apply in respect of a designation under subsection (1), any references to the Governor in Council being read as references to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power of the Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the acceptance by the Minister of a designation under subsection (1), the Minister may grant the designated right or interest to a third party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a designation under subsection (1) is accepted by the Minister, the designation and the granting of the right or interest by the Minister take effect at the time the lands are set apart as a reserve under section 5.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain acts deemed to have been done under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>As of the time when the Minister sets apart any lands as a reserve under section 5, any right or interest in the lands that was designated by way of a surrender under subsection (1), and any resulting grant that was made under subsection (3), are deemed to have been designated or made, as the case may be, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Issuance of permits by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the council of a first nation has, by resolution, requested that the Minister set apart certain lands as a reserve under an agreement to which this Act applies, the Minister may, either</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>before the lands are transferred to Her Majesty in right of Canada by the first nation, by Her Majesty in right of Alberta, by Her Majesty in right of Saskatchewan or by a third party, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>before the lands are set apart as a reserve under section 5,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>authorize, by permit in writing, any person for a period not exceeding one year or, with the consent of the council of the first nation, for any longer period, to occupy, use or reside on any of those lands or exercise any other right on them, including for the purpose of replacing an existing right or interest of that person in those lands.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Rights granted by permits issued under subsection (1) take effect at the time the lands are set apart as a reserve under section 5.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain acts deemed to have been done under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As of the time when the Minister sets apart any lands as a reserve under section 5, a permit issued under subsection (1) in relation to those lands, and any consent given under that subsection, are deemed to have been issued or given, as the case may be, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>RELATED AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 33</MarginalNote><TitleText>Manitoba Claim Settlements Implementation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 165</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>Paragraph 11(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Manitoba Claim Settlements Implementation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>le droit ou l’intérêt a été concédé au tiers au titre de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Section 12 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain acts deemed to have been done under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>As of the time when the Minister sets apart any lands as a reserve under section 11, any right or interest in the lands that was designated by way of a surrender under subsection (1), and any resulting grant that was made under subsection (3), are deemed to have been designated or made, as the case may be, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain acts deemed to have been done under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As of the time when the Minister sets apart any lands as a reserve under section 11, a permit issued under subsection (1) in relation to those lands, and any consent given under that subsection, are deemed to have been issued or given, as the case may be, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 11</MarginalNote><TitleText>Saskatchewan Treaty Land Entitlement Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>band</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Saskatchewan Treaty Land Entitlement Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an Indian band that is a party to an agreement to which this Act applies by virtue of subsection 11(2);</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 3(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confirmation of other agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, either before or after the coming into force of this subsection,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an agreement is entered into with an Indian band of Saskatchewan in settlement of a treaty land entitlement claim on the same or substantially the same basis as the Framework Agreement, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in connection with the agreement referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the Government of Canada and the Government of Saskatchewan enter into an agreement in the same or substantially the same form as the NRTA Amendment Agreement,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>the agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of Saskatchewan referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is hereby confirmed and shall take effect according to its terms.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>Section 9 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application of this section</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a band referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>band</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1), or the Nekaneet band, assents or agrees, under paragraph 3(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan) Implementation Act</XRefExternal>, to the application of that Act in relation to an agreement to which this Act applies, this section thereupon ceases to apply to that agreement in so far as the agreement affects the band so assenting or agreeing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application of this section</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an agreement is entered into with one or more Indian bands of Saskatchewan in settlement of a treaty land entitlement claim on the same or substantially the same basis as the Framework Agreement, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an Indian band referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) assents or agrees, under paragraph 3(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan) Implementation Act</XRefExternal>, to the application of that Act in relation to the agreement referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>this section does not apply, or thereupon ceases to apply, as the case may be, to the agreement referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) in so far as the agreement affects the Indian band so assenting or agreeing.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Text>Subsection 11(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of Act to other agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where an agreement is entered into with an Indian band of Saskatchewan in settlement of a treaty land entitlement claim on the same or substantially the same basis as the Framework Agreement, the Minister shall, having regard to subsection 9(4), cause a notice to be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> confirming the extent to which this Act applies to that agreement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></Body><Schedule><RunningHead>Claim Settlements (Alberta and Saskatchewan) — Schedule</RunningHead><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Paragraph 3(a))</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Agreement entered into by the White Bear Band, dated January 30 and 31, 1986</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Peigan Band of Indians, dated April 21, 1987</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Woodland Cree Indian Band No. 474, dated August 20, 1991</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Kawacatoose Band, dated November 5, 1991</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Sakimay Band, dated March 11, 1992</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Kahkewistahaw Band of Indians, dated March 13, 1992</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Keeseekoose, Muskowekwan, Ochapowace, Okanese, Piapot, Star Blanket, Yellowquill, Beardy’s &amp; Okemasis, Flying Dust, Little Pine, Moosomin, Mosquito Grizzly Bear’s Head, Muskeg Lake, One Arrow, Pelican Lake, Red Pheasant, Saulteaux, Sweetgrass, Thunderchild, Witchekan Lake, Canoe Lake and English River bands, dated September 22, 1992 and adhered to by the Onion Lake Band on October 26, 1992, by the Poundmaker Band on November 24, 1992 and by the Peter Ballantyne Band on February 25, 1993</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Nekaneet Band, dated September 23, 1992</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Janvier Indian Band No. 470, dated March 25, 1993</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Piapot Band, dated March 18, 1995Agreement entered into by the Alexis Indian Band No. 437, dated March 23, 1995</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Ochapowace Band, dated March 30, 1995</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Carry the Kettle, Cote, Cowessess, Day Star, Fishing Lake, Gordon, Kahkewistahaw, Kawacatoose, Keeseekoose, Key Band, Kinistin, Little Black Bear, Muscowpetung, Muskowekwan, Nekaneet, Oceanman, Ochapowace, Okanese, Pasqua, Peepeekisis, Pheasant Rump, Piapot, Sakimay, Star Blanket, White Bear and Yellowquill bands, dated September 14, 1995</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Cowessess Band, dated March 14, 1996</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Carry the Kettle First Nation, dated March 29, 1996</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Little Black Bear Band, dated May 17, 1996</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Kainaiwa Tribe (also known as the Blood Tribe), dated November 7, 1996</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Alexander Indian Band No. 438 (also known as the Alexander First Nation), dated March 24, 1998</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Loon River Cree Indian Band No. 476, dated February 5, 1999</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Smith’s Landing First Nation, dated March 31, 2000</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Kawacatoose Band, dated October 20, 2000</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Horse Lake First Nation, dated November 23, 2000</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Fishing Lake First Nation, dated January 5, 2001</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Agreement entered into by the Mistawasis First Nation, dated January 9, 2001</Text></Provision></DocumentInternal></Schedule></Bill>