<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>C-41</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>49-50-51</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2001-2002</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canadian Commercial Corporation Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Canadian Commercial Corporation Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canadian Commercial Corporation</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2002</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>4</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2002</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2002-3-21">90167</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Commercial Corporation Act</XRefExternal> by</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>separating the functions of chairperson of the Board and chief executive officer, and describing the roles and responsibilities of the Chairperson and President of the Corporation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorizing additional borrowing; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>permitting the Corporation to charge an amount that it considers appropriate for providing services.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-14</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> in the English version of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Commercial Corporation Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Board</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Board</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>conseil</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Board</DefinedTermEn> means the Chairperson, the President and the other directors of the Corporation;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (4th Supp.), s. 44 (Sch. II, item 7)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Corporation established</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>There is hereby established a corporation to be known as the Canadian Commercial Corporation consisting of a Chairperson, a President and not more than nine or less than five other directors.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment of Chairperson and President</MarginalNote><Label>3.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chairperson and the President shall be appointed by the Governor in Council to hold office during pleasure for any term that the Governor in Council considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration of Chairperson and President</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The remuneration of the Chairperson and the President, if they are not members of the public service of Canada, shall be fixed by the Governor in Council and paid by the Corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment of directors</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Each director of the Corporation, other than the Chairperson and the President, shall be appointed by the Minister, with the approval of the Governor in Council, to hold office during pleasure for any term not greater than three years that will ensure, as far as possible, the expiry in any one year of the terms of office of not more than one-half of the directors.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duties of Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>3.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chairperson shall preside at all meetings of the Board and shall perform any other duties that are assigned by the by-laws or by resolution of the Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence of Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Chairperson is absent from a meeting, the directors that are present at the meeting shall choose a director to preside at it. For that purpose, the director has all the powers and duties of the Chairperson.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties of President</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The President is the chief executive officer of the Corporation and has on behalf of the Board the direction and management of the business of the Corporation. The President shall perform any other duties that are assigned by the by-laws or by resolution of the Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity of President</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the President is absent or unable to act or the office of President is vacant, the Board may appoint a director or an officer of the Corporation to act as President and shall fix the remuneration and terms and conditions of the appointment. No person may be appointed for a term of more than 90 days without the approval of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Subsection 7(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 8(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Personnel</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>La Société peut employer les dirigeants et le personnel qu’elle estime nécessaires à l’exercice de ses activités et fixer leurs conditions d’emploi et leur rémunération.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 11(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Borrowing power</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Corporation may borrow moneys from the Consolidated Revenue Fund or any other source for any purpose for which the Corporation was established, but the total amount outstanding on all of those loans at any time shall not exceed $90 million or any greater amount that may be specified in an appropriation Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loans to the Corporation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance may lend moneys from the Consolidated Revenue Fund to the Corporation on any terms and conditions that the Minister of Finance may determine.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Charges</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Corporation may charge any amount that it considers appropriate for providing services to a person, department or agency, including an amount to cover the risk of any loss that the Corporation may incur as a result of a default or failure by that person, department or agency in respect of a transaction entered into with any of them.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>