<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE TOPS PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD TOPS//EN" "TOPS.dtd">
<TOPS xml:lang="en">
<Statute FlicsAlpha="2010, c. 23">
  <Title>Efficiency and adaptability of the Canadian economy by regulating certain activities that discourage reliance on electronic means of carrying out commercial activities, and to amend the Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission Act, the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act and the Telecommunications Act, An Act to promote the</Title>
  <ChapterNumber>2010, c. 23</ChapterNumber>
  <OtherLangTitle>(Efficacité et la capacité d’adaptation de l’économie canadienne par la réglementation de certaines pratiques qui découragent l’exercice des activités commerciales par voie électronique et modifiant la Loi sur le Conseil de la radiodiffusion et des télécommunications canadiennes, la Loi sur la concurrence, la Loi sur la protection des renseignements personnels et les documents électroniques et la Loi sur les télécommunications, Loi visant à promouvoir l’)</OtherLangTitle>
  <Minister>
    <Text>Introduced by the Minister of Industry</Text>
  </Minister>
  <Section>
    <Label>5</Label>
    <Text>2023, c. 8, s. 32</Text>
  </Section>
  <Section>
    <Label>6</Label>
    <Text>2010, c. 23, s. 68; 2023, c. 8, s. 33</Text>
  </Section>
  <Section>
    <Label>10</Label>
    <Text>2023, c. 8, s. 34</Text>
  </Section>
  <Section>
    <Label>20</Label>
    <Text>2024, c. 15, s. 270</Text>
  </Section>
  <Section>
    <Label>41.1</Label>
    <Text>to <Emphasis style="bold">41.7</Emphasis>, repealed, 2010, c. 23, s. 90</Text>
  </Section>
  <Transitional>
    <Text>Transitional, 2010, c. 23, ss. 66 and 67</Text>
  </Transitional>
  <CIF>
    <Text>CIF, 2010, c. 23 (assent: 15.12.2010),</Text>
    <List>
      <Item>
        <Text>— ss. 1 to 7, 9 to 46, 52 to 54, 56 to 67 and 69 to 82 in force 01.07.2014 <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2013- 127</Text>
      </Item>
      <Item>
        <Text>— s. 8 in force 15.01.2015 <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2013-127</Text>
      </Item>
      <Item>
        <Text>— ss. 12(1), (3) and (4), s. 12.1, s. 12.2(1) and (3), as enacted by s. 83, s. 84 and 85, s. 86(1) and s. 87 in force 01.04.2011, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2011-22</Text>
      </Item>
      <Item>
        <Text>— ss. 12(2) and 12.2(2), as enacted by s. 83, s. 86(2), s. 88 and s. 89(1) in force 01.04.2014, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2013-127</Text>
      </Item>
      <Item>
        <Text>— ss. 47 to 51 and 55 in force 01.07.2017 <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2013-127</Text>
      </Item>
      <Item>
        <Text>— <Emphasis style="italic">but see</Emphasis> SI/2017-31 amending SI/2013-127 by repealing par. (c) and delaying the coming-into-force date of ss. 47 to 51 and 55; repealing the coming into force of the Private Right of Action dispositions of <Emphasis style="italic">Canada’s Anti-Spam Law</Emphasis> — Not in force</Text>
      </Item>
      <Item>
        <Text>— ss. 68 and 90 come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> s. 91 — Not in force</Text>
      </Item>
    </List>
  </CIF>
  <CIF>
    <Text>CIF 2024, c. 15, s. 270 in force on the first anniversary of the day on which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fall Economic Statement Implementation Act, 2023</XRefExternal> receives royal assent <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> s. 272 (20.06.2025)</Text>
  </CIF>
</Statute>
</TOPS>
