<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-26</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>60-61</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2011-2012</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (citizen’s arrest and the defences of property and persons)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Citizen’s Arrest and Self-defence Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code (citizen’s arrest and the defences of property and persons)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>9</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2012</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2011-11-18">90593</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to enable a person who owns or has lawful possession of property, or persons authorized by them, to arrest within a reasonable time a person whom they find committing a criminal offence on or in relation to that property. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to simplify the provisions relating to the defences of property and persons.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizen’s Arrest and Self-defence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 1, s. 60 (Sch. I, s. 20)(F)</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Sections 34 to 42 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Defence — use or threat of force</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person is not guilty of an offence if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they believe on reasonable grounds that force is being used against them or another person or that a threat of force is being made against them or another person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the act that constitutes the offence is committed for the purpose of defending or protecting themselves or the other person from that use or threat of force; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the act committed is reasonable in the circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In determining whether the act committed is reasonable in the circumstances, the court shall consider the relevant circumstances of the person, the other parties and the act, including, but not limited to, the following factors:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the nature of the force or threat;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the extent to which the use of force was imminent and whether there were other means available to respond to the potential use of force;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person’s role in the incident;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether any party to the incident used or threatened to use a weapon;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the size, age, gender and physical capabilities of the parties to the incident;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the nature, duration and history of any relationship between the parties to the incident, including any prior use or threat of force and the nature of that force or threat;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any history of interaction or communication between the parties to the incident;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the nature and proportionality of the person’s response to the use or threat of force; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether the act committed was in response to a use or threat of force that the person knew was lawful.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No defence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply if the force is used or threatened by another person for the purpose of doing something that they are required or authorized by law to do in the administration or enforcement of the law, unless the person who commits the act that constitutes the offence believes on reasonable grounds that the other person is acting unlawfully.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Defence of Property</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Defence  —property</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person is not guilty of an offence if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they either believe on reasonable grounds that they are in peaceable possession of property or are acting under the authority of, or lawfully assisting, a person whom they believe on reasonable grounds is in peaceable possession of property;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they believe on reasonable grounds that another person</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is about to enter, is entering or has entered the property without being entitled by law to do so,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is about to take the property, is doing so or has just done so, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>is about to damage or destroy the property, or make it inoperative, or is doing so;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the act that constitutes the offence is committed for the purpose of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>preventing the other person from entering the property, or removing that person from the property, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>preventing the other person from taking, damaging or destroying the property or from making it inoperative, or retaking the property from that person; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the act committed is reasonable in the circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No defence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply if the person who believes on reasonable grounds that they are, or who is believed on reasonable grounds to be, in peaceable possession of the property does not have a claim of right to it and the other person is entitled to its possession by law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No defence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply if the other person is doing something that they are required or authorized by law to do in the administration or enforcement of the law, unless the person who commits the act that constitutes the offence believes on reasonable grounds that the other person is acting unlawfully.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 494(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Arrest by owner, etc., of property</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The owner or a person in lawful possession of property, or a person authorized by the owner or by a person in lawful possession of property, may arrest a person without a warrant if they find them committing a criminal offence on or in relation to that property and</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they make the arrest at that time; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they make the arrest within a reasonable time after the offence is committed and they believe on reasonable grounds that it is not feasible in the circumstances for a peace officer to make the arrest.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 494 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a person who is authorized to make an arrest under this section is a person who is authorized by law to do so for the purposes of section 25.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>