<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-19</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>60-61</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2011-2012</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and the Firearms Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code and Firearms</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>5</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>6</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2012</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2011-10-24">90625</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> to remove the requirement to register firearms that are neither prohibited nor restricted. It also provides for the destruction of existing records, held in the Canadian Firearms Registry and under the control of chief firearms officers, that relate to the registration of such firearms.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 91(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized possession of firearm</MarginalNote><Label>91.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), every person commits an offence who possesses a firearm without being the holder of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a licence under which the person may possess it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, a registration certificate for it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 91(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>obtains a licence under which the person may possess it and, in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, a registration certificate for it.</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 91(5) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 5</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 92(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Possession of firearm knowing its possession is unauthorized</MarginalNote><Label>92.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), every person commits an offence who possesses a firearm knowing that the person is not the holder of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a licence under which the person may possess it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, a registration certificate for it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 92(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>obtains a licence under which the person may possess it and, in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, a registration certificate for it.</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 92(5) and (6) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 7</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 94(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized possession in motor vehicle</MarginalNote><Label>94.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (4), every person commits an offence who is an occupant of a motor vehicle in which the person knows there is a firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, other than a replica firearm, or any prohibited ammunition, unless</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraphs 94(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) and (ii) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the person or any other occupant of the motor vehicle is the holder of</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>a licence under which the person or other occupant may possess the firearm, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, an authorization and a registration certificate for it,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the person had reasonable grounds to believe that any other occupant of the motor vehicle was the holder of</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>a licence under which that other occupant may possess the firearm, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, an authorization and a registration certificate for it, or</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 94(5) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 8(1)</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 95(1) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Possession of prohibited or restricted firearm with ammunition</MarginalNote><Label>95.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), every person commits an offence who, in any place, possesses a loaded prohibited firearm or restricted firearm, or an unloaded prohibited firearm or restricted firearm together with readily accessible ammunition that is capable of being discharged in the firearm, without being the holder of</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 106(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>after destroying any prohibited firearm, restricted firearm, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device or prohibited ammunition, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on becoming aware of the destruction of any prohibited firearm, restricted firearm, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device or prohibited ammunition that was in the person’s possession before its destruction,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>Subsection 108(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person is guilty of an offence under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) by reason only of possessing a prohibited firearm or restricted firearm the serial number on which has been altered, defaced or removed, if that serial number has been replaced and a registration certificate in respect of the firearm has been issued setting out a new serial number for the firearm.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>Subsections 117.03(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Seizure on failure to produce authorization</MarginalNote><Label>117.03</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 117.02, a peace officer who finds</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person in possession of a firearm who fails, on demand, to produce, for inspection by the peace officer, an authorization or a licence under which the person may lawfully possess the firearm and, in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, a registration certificate for it, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person in possession of a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition who fails, on demand, to produce, for inspection by the peace officer, an authorization or a licence under which the person may lawfully possess it,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>may seize the firearm, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device or prohibited ammunition unless its possession by the person in the circumstances in which it is found is authorized by any provision of this Part, or the person is under the direct and immediate supervision of another person who may lawfully possess it.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of seized thing on production of authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person from whom any thing is seized under subsection (1) claims the thing within 14 days after the seizure and produces for inspection by the peace officer by whom it was seized, or any other peace officer having custody of it,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a licence under which the person is lawfully entitled to possess it, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, an authorization and registration certificate for it,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>the thing shall without delay be returned to that person.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39</MarginalNote><TitleText>FIREARMS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 4(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>licences for firearms and authorizations and registration certificates for prohibited firearms or restricted firearms, under which persons may possess firearms in circumstances that would otherwise constitute an offence under subsection 91(1), 92(1), 93(1) or 95(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 13:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Registration certificate</MarginalNote><Label>12.1</Label><Text>A registration certificate may only be issued for a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 17</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Section 23 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization to transfer firearms neither prohibited nor restricted</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>A person may transfer a firearm that is neither a prohibited firearm nor a restricted firearm if, at the time of the transfer,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the transferee holds a licence authorizing the transferee to acquire and possess that kind of firearm; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the transferor has no reason to believe that the transferee is not authorized to acquire and possess that kind of firearm.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Voluntary request to Registrar</MarginalNote><Label>23.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A transferor referred to in section 23 may request that the Registrar inform the transferor as to whether the transferee, at the time of the transfer, holds and is still eligible to hold the licence referred to in paragraph 23(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), and if such a request is made, the Registrar or his or her delegate, or any other person that the federal Minister may designate, shall so inform the transferor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No record of request</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite sections 12 and 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and subsections 6(1) and (3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, neither the Registrar or his or her delegate nor a designated person shall retain any record of a request made under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization to transfer prohibited or restricted firearms</MarginalNote><Label>23.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person may transfer a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm if, at the time of the transfer,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the transferee holds a licence authorizing the transferee to acquire and possess that kind of firearm;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the transferor has no reason to believe that the transferee is not authorized to acquire and possess that kind of firearm;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the transferor informs the Registrar of the transfer;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the transferee is an individual, the transferor informs a chief firearms officer of the transfer and obtains the authorization of the chief firearms officer for the transfer;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a new registration certificate for the firearm is issued in accordance with this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the prescribed conditions are met.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, after being informed of a proposed transfer of a firearm, the Registrar decides to refuse to issue a registration certificate for the firearm, the Registrar shall inform a chief firearms officer of that decision.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 19</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>Subsection 26(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization to transfer prohibited or restricted firearms to Crown, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person may transfer a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm to Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province, to a police force or to a municipality if the person informs the Registrar of the transfer and complies with the prescribed conditions.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 20(1)</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>The portion of section 27 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Chief firearms officer</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>On being informed of a proposed transfer of a prohibited firearm or restricted firearm under section 23.2, a chief firearms officer shall</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 33(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, lends the registration certificate for it to the borrower; or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>Paragraph 34(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, the transferor lends the registration certificate for it to the borrower; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Text>Subsection 36(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Temporary licence and registration certificate</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A declaration that is confirmed under paragraph 35(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) has the same effect after the importation of the firearm as a licence authorizing the non-resident to possess only that firearm and, in the case of a restricted firearm, as a registration certificate for the firearm until</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the expiry of 60 days after the importation, in the case of a firearm that is neither a prohibited firearm nor a restricted firearm; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the earlier of the expiry of 60 days after the importation and the expiry of the authorization to transport, in the case of a restricted firearm.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 38(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>produces his or her licence and, in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, the registration certificate for the firearm and an authorization to transport the firearm; and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>Paragraph 44(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, holds the registration certificate for the firearm;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Text>Section 60 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Registration certificates and authorizations to export or import</MarginalNote><Label>60.</Label><Text>The Registrar is responsible for issuing registration certificates for prohibited firearms and restricted firearms and assigning firearms identification numbers to them and for issuing authorizations to export and authorizations to import.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>The portion of section 66 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Term of registration certificates</MarginalNote><Label>66.</Label><Text>A registration certificate for a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm expires when</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Paragraph 71(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may revoke a registration certificate for a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm for any good and sufficient reason; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Subsection 72(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposal of firearms — registration certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A notice given under subsection (1) in respect of a registration certificate for a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm must specify a reasonable period during which the applicant for or holder of the registration certificate may deliver to a peace officer or a firearms officer or a chief firearms officer or otherwise lawfully dispose of the firearm to which the registration certificate relates and during which sections 91, 92 and 94 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> do not apply to the applicant or holder.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 83(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>every licence, every registration certificate for a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm and every authorization that is issued or revoked by the Registrar;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>every application for a licence, a registration certificate for a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm or an authorization that is refused by the Registrar;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Section 88 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Reporting of loss, finding, theft and destruction</MarginalNote><Label>88.</Label><Text>A chief firearms officer to whom the loss, finding, theft or destruction of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm is reported shall have the Registrar informed without delay of the loss, finding, theft or destruction.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 90:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Right of access — subsection 23.1(1)</MarginalNote><Label>90.1</Label><Text>For the purpose of subsection 23.1(1), the person responding to a request made under that subsection has a right of access to records kept by a chief firearms officer under section 87.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>Section 105 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Demand to produce firearm</MarginalNote><Label>105.</Label><Text>An inspector who believes on reasonable grounds that a person possesses a firearm may, by demand made to that person, require that person, within a reasonable time after the demand is made, to produce the firearm in the manner specified by the inspector for the purpose of verifying the serial number or other identifying features of the firearm and of ensuring that, in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, the person is the holder of the registration certificate for it.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>Section 112 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28.</Label><Text>Sections 114 and 115 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Failure to deliver up revoked licence, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>114.</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who, being the holder of a licence, a registration certificate for a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm or an authorization that is revoked, does not deliver it up to a peace officer or firearms officer without delay after the revocation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>115.</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under section 113 or 114 is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Destruction of information — Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner of Firearms shall ensure the destruction as soon as feasible of all records in the Canadian Firearms Registry related to the registration of firearms that are neither prohibited firearms nor restricted firearms and all copies of those records under the Commissioner’s control.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Destruction of information — chief firearms officers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each chief firearms officer shall ensure the destruction as soon as feasible of all records under their control related to the registration of firearms that are neither prohibited firearms nor restricted firearms and all copies of those records under their control.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Sections 12 and 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal> and subsections 6(1) and (3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> do not apply with respect to the destruction of the records and copies referred to in subsections (1) and (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, “other Act” means <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (firearms) and the Firearms Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 8 of the Statutes of Canada, 2003.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 27 of the other Act and section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, paragraph 35.1(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the individual produces a licence authorizing him or her to acquire and possess that kind of firearm and, in the case of a restricted firearm, satisfies the customs officer that the individual holds a registration certificate for the firearm;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 28 of the other Act and section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, subsection 36(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Temporary licence and registration certificate</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A declaration that is confirmed under paragraph 35(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) has the same effect after the importation of the firearm as a licence authorizing the non-resident to possess only that firearm and, in the case of a restricted firearm, as a registration certificate for the firearm until</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the expiry of 60 days after the importation, in the case of a firearm that is neither a prohibited firearm nor a restricted firearm; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the earlier of the expiry of 60 days after the importation and the expiry of the authorization to transport, in the case of a restricted firearm.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 29 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label><XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>.</Label><Text>Paragraph 38(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>holds a licence to possess that kind of firearm and, in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, a registration certificate and an authorization to transport the firearm; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 29 of the other Act, then, on the day on which that section 29 comes into force, paragraph 38(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>holds a licence to possess that kind of firearm and, in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, a registration certificate and an authorization to transport the firearm; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If section 29 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> is deemed to have come into force before that section 29 and subsection (5) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 30 of the other Act and section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, paragraphs 40(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the individual produces a licence authorizing him or her to possess that kind of firearm;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, the individual holds an authorization to transport it and satisfies the customs officer that the individual holds a registration certificate for the firearm; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 31 of the other Act and section <XRefInternal><?Pub Caret?>17</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, section 41 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Temporary registration certificate</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Text>An authorization that is confirmed in accordance with paragraph 40(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) has the same effect as a registration certificate for a restricted firearm until a registration certificate is issued for it.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>