<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-310</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>60-61</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2011-2012</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (trafficking in persons)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (trafficking in persons)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code (trafficking in persons)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2012</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>28</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>15</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2012</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2011-09-26">411389</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to add the offence of trafficking in persons to the offences committed outside Canada for which Canadian citizens or permanent residents may be prosecuted in Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the Act to add factors that the Court may consider when determining whether an accused exploits another person.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4.1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence in relation to trafficking in persons</MarginalNote><Label>(4.11)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding anything in this Act or any other Act, every one who, outside Canada, commits an act or omission that if committed in Canada would be an offence against section 279.01, 279.011, 279.02 or 279.03 shall be deemed to commit that act or omission in Canada if the person who commits the act or omission is a Canadian citizen or a permanent resident within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 279.04 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exploitation</MarginalNote><Label>279.04</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 279.01 to 279.03, a person exploits another person if they cause them to provide, or offer to provide, labour or a service by engaging in conduct that, in all the circumstances, could reasonably be expected to cause the other person to believe that their safety or the safety of a person known to them would be threatened if they failed to provide, or offer to provide, the labour or service.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In determining whether an accused exploits another person under subsection (1), the Court may consider, among other factors, whether the accused</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>used or threatened to use force or another form of coercion;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>used deception; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>abused a position of trust, power or authority.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Organ or tissue removal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 279.01 to 279.03, a person exploits another person if they cause them, by means of deception or the use or threat of force or of any other form of coercion, to have an organ or tissue removed.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>