<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-237</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national framework for diabetes</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">National Framework for Diabetes Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Framework for Diabetes Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>19</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2021</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-02-13">431119</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national framework designed to support improved access for Canadians to diabetes prevention and treatment.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas one in four Canadians live with prediabetes or diabetes, a chronic disease that can result in life-threatening complications if not treated;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas Canada, the birthplace of insulin — a hormone that has played a key role in the control of diabetes —, seeks to be a leader in promoting diabetes awareness;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas diabetes awareness and education can help people identify early signs of diabetes and thus prevent or delay its onset;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas federal and provincial coordination and information sharing is required to prevent and treat diabetes as well as to prevent health inequities among people suffering with this disease;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>And whereas the Parliament of Canada recognizes the need to be proactive in the fight against diabetes, and the Government of Canada should develop and implement a national framework for diabetes;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Framework for Diabetes Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Framework for Diabetes</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Health must, in consultation with the representatives of the provincial governments responsible for health, Indigenous groups and with other relevant stakeholders, develop a national framework designed to support improved access to diabetes prevention and treatment to ensure better health outcomes for Canadians.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The national framework must include measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>explain what diabetes and prediabetes are;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>identify the training, education and guidance needs of health care and other professionals related to the prevention and treatment of diabetes, including clinical practice guidelines;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>promote research and improve data collection on diabetes prevention and treatment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>promote information and knowledge sharing in relation to diabetes prevention and treatment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>take into consideration any existing diabetes prevention and treatment frameworks, strategies and best practices, including those that focus on addressing health inequalities; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>ensure that the Canada Revenue Agency is administering the disability tax credit fairly and that the credit, in order to achieve its purposes, is designed to help as many persons with diabetes as possible.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conference</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must hold at least one conference with the persons referred to in subsection (1) for the purpose of developing the framework.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of framework</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Health must prepare a report setting out the national framework for diabetes and cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Health within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 3 is tabled in Parliament, the Minister of Health must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national framework for diabetes and on the current state of diabetes prevention and treatment. The report also sets out his or her conclusions and recommendations regarding the framework.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>