<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-220</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (bereavement leave)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (bereavement leave)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (bereavement leave)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>17</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2021</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-01-06">431060</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to extend, by five unpaid days, the period of bereavement leave to which an employee is entitled and to expand eligibility for the leave to include employees who, at the time a family member dies, are on compassionate care leave or leave related to critical illness in respect of the deceased person.</Text></Provision><?Pub Caret 0?></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subsection 210(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Employee entitled</MarginalNote><Label>210</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every employee is entitled to and shall be granted, in the event of the death of a member of their immediate family or a family member in respect of whom the employee is, at the time of the death, on leave under section 206.3 or 206.4, a leave of absence from employment of up to 10 days that may be taken during the period that begins on the day on which the death occurs and ends six weeks after the latest of the days on which any funeral, burial or memorial service of the deceased person occurs.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Three months after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the day that, in the third month after the month in which it receives royal assent, has the same calendar number as the day on which it receives royal assent or, if that third month has no day with that number, the last day of that third month.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>