<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-228</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a federal framework to reduce recidivism</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Reduction of Recidivism Framework Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Reduction of Recidivism Framework Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>18</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2021</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-02-06">431082</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment provides for the development and implementation of a federal framework to reduce recidivism.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the purpose of the correctional system is in part to contribute to the maintenance of a just, peaceful and safe society by assisting the rehabilitation of offenders and their reintegration into the community as law-abiding citizens through the provision of programs in penitentiaries and in the community;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas nearly one in four people who have been incarcerated reoffend within two years of their release;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas people who have been incarcerated should have the necessary resources and employment opportunities to be able to transition back into the community and avoid falling back into their old ways;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas victims are at the heart of the justice system and the best way to protect them is to reduce crime and recidivism;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas Parliament recognizes the need to reduce recidivism in order to provide safe and secure communities for all Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>And whereas cooperation and coordinated action between the federal and provincial governments that respect the legislative competence of each are required to develop a federal framework that, in the interest of reducing recidivism, ensures the needs of people who have been incarcerated are met and supports their rehabilitation;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Reduction of Recidivism Framework Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Federal Framework to Reduce Recidivism</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development and implementation</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness must, in consultation with representatives of the provinces, with a variety of Indigenous governing bodies and Indigenous organizations and with other relevant stakeholders such as non-governmental, non-profit, faith-based and private sector organizations, develop and implement a federal framework to reduce recidivism.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The framework must include measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>initiate pilot projects and develop standardized and evidence-based programs aimed at reducing recidivism;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>promote the reintegration of people who have been incarcerated back into the community through access to adequate and ongoing resources as well as employment opportunities in order to lessen the likelihood of their reoffending;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>support faith-based and communal initiatives that aim to rehabilitate people who have been incarcerated;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>review and implement international best practices related to the reduction of recidivism; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>evaluate and improve risk assessment instruments and procedures to address racial and cultural biases and ensure that all people who are incarcerated have access to appropriate programs that will help reduce recidivism.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of framework</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness must prepare a report setting out the federal framework to reduce recidivism and cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness within 10 days after the day on which the report is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three years after the day on which the report referred to in section 3 is tabled and every year after that, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the federal framework to reduce recidivism that sets out his or her conclusions and recommendations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled before each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>