<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-5</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>69-70</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2020-2021</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Bills of Exchange Act, the Interpretation Act and the Canada Labour Code (National Day for Truth and Reconciliation)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Bills of Exchange Act, the Interpretation Act and the Canada Labour Code (National Day for Truth and Reconciliation)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Bills of Exchange Act, the Interpretation Act and the Canada Labour Code (National Day for Truth and Reconciliation)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2021</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">N-4.5</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2021</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-9-28">90955</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends certain Acts to add a new holiday, namely, National Day for Truth and Reconciliation, which is observed on September 30.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose of this Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to respond to the Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Canada’s call to action number 80 by creating a holiday called the National Day for Truth and Reconciliation, which seeks to honour First Nations, Inuit and Métis Survivors and their families and communities and to ensure that public commemoration of their history and the legacy of residential schools remains a vital component of the reconciliation process.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. B-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Bills of Exchange Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subparagraph 42(a)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bills of Exchange Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>Sundays, New Year’s Day, Good Friday, Victoria Day, Canada Day, Labour Day, National Day for Truth and Reconciliation, which is observed on September 30, Remembrance Day and Christmas Day,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. I-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Interpretation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>holiday</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 35(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Interpretation Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>holiday</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following days, namely, Sunday; New Year’s Day; Good Friday; Easter Monday; Christmas Day; the birthday or the day fixed by proclamation for the celebration of the birthday of the reigning Sovereign; Victoria Day; Canada Day; the first Monday in September, designated Labour Day; National Day for Truth and Reconciliation, which is observed on September 30; Remembrance Day; any day appointed by proclamation to be observed as a day of general prayer or mourning or day of public rejoicing or thanksgiving; and any of the following additional days, namely,</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>general holiday</DefinedTermEn> in section 166 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>general holiday</DefinedTermEn> means New Year’s Day, Good Friday, Victoria Day, Canada Day, Labour Day, National Day for Truth and Reconciliation, which is observed on September 30, Thanksgiving Day, Remembrance Day, Christmas Day and Boxing Day and includes any day substituted for any such holiday under section 195; (<DefinedTermFr>jours fériés</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 193(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Alternative day for holiday falling on non-working Saturday or Sunday</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except as otherwise provided by this Division, when New Year’s Day, Canada Day, National Day for Truth and Reconciliation, Remembrance Day, Christmas Day or Boxing Day falls on a Sunday or Saturday that is a non-working day, the employee is entitled to and shall be granted a holiday with pay on the working day immediately preceding or following the general holiday.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Two months after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the day that, in the second month after the month in which it receives royal assent, has the same calendar number as the day on which it receives royal assent or, if that second month has no day with that number, the last day of that second month.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>