<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-34</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>56-57</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2007-2008</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to give effect to the Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2008</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><?Pub Caret1?><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>32</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2008</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2007-11-30">90445</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment gives effect to the Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement. It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> recognizes and affirms the existing aboriginal and treaty rights of the aboriginal peoples of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas the Tsawwassen First Nation is part of the Coast Salish, an aboriginal people of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas the reconciliation between the prior presence of aboriginal peoples and the assertion of sovereignty by the Crown is of significant social and economic importance to Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas Canadian courts have stated that this reconciliation is best achieved through negotiation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Whereas the Tsawwassen First Nation, the government of Canada and the government of British Columbia have negotiated the Agreement to achieve this reconciliation and to establish a new relationship among them;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>And whereas the Agreement requires that legislation be enacted by the Parliament of Canada in order for the Agreement to be ratified;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement, between the Tsawwassen First Nation, Her Majesty in right of Canada and Her Majesty in right of British Columbia, including any amendments made to it.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tax Treatment Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord sur le traitement fiscal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tax Treatment Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Tsawwassen Tax Treatment Agreement referred to in clause 22 of Chapter 20 of the Agreement, including any amendments made to it.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions in the Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Former Tsawwassen Reserve</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tsawwassen Corporation</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tsawwassen First Nation</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tsawwassen Government</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tsawwassen Lands</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tsawwassen Law</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tsawwassen Member</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Tsawwassen Public Institution</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Tsawwassen Territory</DefinedTermEn> have the same meanings as in Chapter 1 of the Agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Status of Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Agreement is a treaty and a land claims agreement within the meaning of sections 25 and 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>AGREEMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement given effect</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, any person or body has the powers, rights, privileges and benefits conferred on the person or body by the Agreement and shall perform the duties, and is subject to the liabilities, imposed on the person or body by the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Third parties</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Agreement is binding on, and may be relied on by, all persons and bodies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Inconsistency with Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agreement prevails over this Act and any other federal law to the extent of any inconsistency between them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conflict with Act</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This Act prevails over any other federal law to the extent of any conflict between them.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>APPROPRIATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>There shall be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund any sums that are required to meet the monetary obligations of Her Majesty in right of Canada under Chapters 4 and 18 of the Agreement.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>LANDS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Fee simple estate</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>On the effective date of the Agreement, the Tsawwassen First Nation owns the estate in fee simple, as set out in Chapter 4 of the Agreement, in</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Tsawwassen Lands referred to in clause 1 of Chapter 4 of the Agreement; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Other Tsawwassen Lands referred to in subclause 18.a of that chapter.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TAXATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tax Treatment Agreement given effect</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>The Tax Treatment Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law during the period that it is in effect.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a treaty</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>The Tax Treatment Agreement does not form part of the Agreement and is not a treaty or a land claims agreement within the meaning of sections 25 and 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>FISHERIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of Minister of Fisheries and Oceans</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>Despite section 7 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans may, on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada, enter into and implement the Tsawwassen First Nation Harvest Agreement referred to in clause 102 of Chapter 9 of the Agreement, including any amendments made to it.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a treaty</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>That Harvest Agreement does not form part of the Agreement and is not a treaty or a land claims agreement within the meaning of sections 25 and 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>APPLICATION OF OTHER ACTS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of Chapter 3 of the Agreement that deal with the continuing application of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>, and clauses 16 to 21 of Chapter 20 of the Agreement, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the Tsawwassen First Nation, Tsawwassen Members, the Tsawwassen Government or Tsawwassen Public Institutions as of the effective date of the Agreement, except for the purpose of determining whether an individual is an Indian.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal>, the Framework Agreement as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act and the Tsawwassen land code adopted under subsection 6(1) of that Act do not apply in respect of the Tsawwassen First Nation, Tsawwassen Members, Tsawwassen Lands, the Tsawwassen Government or Tsawwassen Public Institutions as of the effective date of the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any laws and bylaws of the Tsawwassen First Nation band that were in effect immediately before the effective date of the Agreement continue in effect on the Former Tsawwassen Reserve for 30 days beginning on that date.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>Tsawwassen Laws and other instruments made under the Agreement are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>APPLICATION OF LAWS OF BRITISH COLUMBIA</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>To the extent that a law of British Columbia does not apply of its own force to the Tsawwassen First Nation, Tsawwassen Members, Tsawwassen Lands, the Tsawwassen Government, Tsawwassen Public Institutions or Tsawwassen Corporations because of the exclusive legislative jurisdiction of Parliament set out in Class 24 of section 91 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>, that law applies to it or to them by virtue of this section, in accordance with the Agreement and subject to this Act and any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>GENERAL</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice of Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice shall be taken of the Agreement and the Tax Treatment Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agreement and the Tax Treatment Agreement shall be published by the Queen’s Printer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A copy of the Agreement or the Tax Treatment Agreement published by the Queen’s Printer is evidence of that agreement and of its contents, and a copy purporting to be published by the Queen’s Printer is deemed to be so published, unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice of Tsawwassen Laws</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice shall be taken of Tsawwassen Laws.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence of Tsawwassen laws</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A copy of a Tsawwassen Law purporting to be deposited in a public registry of laws referred to in subclause 16.a of Chapter 16 of the Agreement is evidence of that law and of its contents, unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make any orders and regulations that are necessary for the purpose of carrying out any of the provisions of the Agreement or of the Tax Treatment Agreement.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Chapters 21 and 24 of Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>Despite subsection 4(1), Chapters 21 and 24 of the Agreement are deemed to have effect as of December 8, 2006.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of issues arising</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an issue arises in any judicial or administrative proceeding in respect of the interpretation or validity of the Agreement, or the validity or applicability of this Act, the British Columbia <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal> or any Tsawwassen Law, then the issue shall not be decided until the party raising the issue has served notice on the Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of British Columbia and the Tsawwassen First Nation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The notice shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>describe the judicial or administrative proceeding;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specify what the issue arises in respect of;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>state the day on which the issue is to be argued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>give particulars necessary to show the point to be argued; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>be served at least 14 days before the day of argument, unless the court or tribunal authorizes a shorter period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Participation in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In any judicial or administrative proceeding to which subsection (1) applies, the Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of British Columbia and the Tsawwassen First Nation may appear and participate in the proceeding as parties with the same rights as any other party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Saving</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsections (2) and (3) do not require that an oral hearing be held if one is not otherwise required.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing interests — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal>, if an interest in land in the Former Tsawwassen Reserve was granted or approved under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> and exists on the effective date of the Agreement, the interest continues in effect in accordance with its terms and conditions unless a replacement interest is issued in accordance with Chapter 4 of the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer of rights and obligations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the effective date of the Agreement, the rights and obligations of Her Majesty in right of Canada as grantor in respect of such an interest are transferred to the Tsawwassen First Nation, which assumes those rights and obligations in accordance with the interest’s terms and conditions.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing interests — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>Despite section <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal>, if an interest in land in the Former Tsawwassen Reserve was granted or approved under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal> and exists on the effective date of the Agreement, the interest continues in effect in accordance with its terms and conditions unless a replacement interest is issued in accordance with Chapter 4 of the Agreement.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Her Majesty not liable</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, Her Majesty in right of Canada is not liable in respect of anything done or omitted to be done after the effective date of the Agreement by the Tsawwassen First Nation or any person or body authorized by it to act</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the exercise of the Tsawwassen First Nation’s rights and obligations referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal>(2) in respect of an interest in land referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal>(1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the exercise of powers, duties and functions in respect of such an interest that arise from Tsawwassen Laws.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Indemnification of Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tsawwassen First Nation shall indemnify Her Majesty in right of Canada for any loss suffered by Her Majesty in right of Canada as a result of an act or omission referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Indemnification of Tsawwassen First Nation</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>For as long as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal> is in force, Her Majesty in right of Canada shall, as of the effective date of the Agreement, indemnify the Tsawwassen First Nation in respect of lands in the Former Tsawwassen Reserve in the same manner and under the same conditions as would be the case if that Act continued to apply to those lands.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Documents in land registries</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>As of the effective date of the Agreement, registrations or records affecting Tsawwassen Lands that are registered or recorded in a land registry under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal> have no effect.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>Subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), by adding the word “or’’ at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tsawwassen Government, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 24</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>SOR/2003-178, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>Item 24 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Land Management Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-14</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 7, s. 22</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>Subsection 5(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Laws of certain First Nations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The powers and protections that a fishery officer or fishery guardian has under this or any other Act of Parliament, including the powers and protections of a peace officer under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, apply to a fishery officer or fishery guardian enforcing</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Nisga’a laws made under the Fisheries Chapter of the Nisga’a Final Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nisga’a Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Tsawwassen Laws, within the meaning of subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, made under chapter 9 of the Agreement, as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act, given effect by that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. M-13</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>taxing authority</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), by adding the word “or’’ at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tsawwassen Government, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, if it levies and collects a real property tax or a frontage or area tax in respect of Tsawwassen Lands, as defined in that subsection.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Text>Subsection 8(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), by adding the word “or’’ at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tsawwassen Government, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-30</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>If Bill C-30, introduced in the 2nd session of the 39th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the first day on which both that Act and section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, Part 1 of the schedule to that Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’accord définitif concernant la Première Nation de Tsawwassen</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-32</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (5) apply if Bill C-32, introduced in the 2nd session of the 39th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act, 2007</XRefExternal> (the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 29 of the other Act and section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, that section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of Minister of Fisheries and Oceans</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>The Minister of Fisheries and Oceans may, on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada, enter into and implement the Tsawwassen First Nation Harvest Agreement referred to in clause 102 of Chapter 9 of the Agreement, including any amendments made to it.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 74 of the other Act and section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> of this Act are in force, that section 74 is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Laws of certain First Nations</MarginalNote><Label>74.</Label><Text>The powers and protections that a fishery officer or fishery guardian has under this or any other Act of Parliament, including the powers and protections of a peace officer under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, apply to a fishery officer or fishery guardian enforcing</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Nisga’a laws made under the Fisheries Chapter of the Nisga’a Final Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nisga’a Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Tsawwassen Laws, within the meaning of subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tsawwassen First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, made under chapter 9 of the Agreement, as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act, given effect by that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the repeal of subsection 5(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> by section 247 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the repeal of subsection 5(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> by section 247 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal> is deemed to have come into force before that repeal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>This Act, other than sections <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>32</XRefInternal>, comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>