<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-30</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>56-57</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2007-2008</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish the Specific Claims Tribunal and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Specific Claims Tribunal</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2008</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>22</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2008</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2007-11-23">90439</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment establishes the Specific Claims Tribunal, the mandate of which is to decide issues of validity and compensation relating to specific claims of First Nations, after their submission to the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development. The enactment also makes consequential amendments to other Acts and repeals the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Resolution Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Recognizing that</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>it is in the interests of all Canadians that the specific claims of First Nations be addressed;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>resolving specific claims will promote reconciliation between First Nations and the Crown and the development and self-sufficiency of First Nations;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>there is a need to establish an independent tribunal that can resolve specific claims and is designed to respond to the distinctive task of adjudicating such claims in accordance with law and in a just and timely manner;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the right of First Nations to choose and have access to a specific claims tribunal will create conditions that are appropriate for resolving valid claims through negotiations;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the Assembly of First Nations and the Government of Canada have worked together on a legislative proposal from the Government of Canada culminating in the introduction of this Act;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>asset</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>élément d’actif</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>asset</DefinedTermEn> means tangible property.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>claimant</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>revendicateur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>claimant</DefinedTermEn> means a First Nation whose specific claim has been filed with the Tribunal.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>claim limit</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>indemnité maximale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>claim limit</DefinedTermEn> means the maximum amount under paragraph <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Crown</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Sa Majesté</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Crown</DefinedTermEn> means Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>First Nation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>première nation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>First Nation</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a band as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a group of persons that was, but is no longer, a band within the meaning of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and that has, under a land claims agreement, retained the right to bring a specific claim; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a group of persons that was a band within the meaning of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), that is no longer a band by virtue of an Act or agreement mentioned in the schedule and that has not released its right to bring a specific claim.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>land claims agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord sur des revendications territoriales</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>land claims agreement</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 35(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>party</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>partie</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>party</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a specific claim, means any claimant, the Crown or any province or First Nation added as a party under section <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>specific claim</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>revendication particulière</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>specific claim</DefinedTermEn> means a claim that is filed under section <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Tribunal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Specific Claims Tribunal established by subsection <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PURPOSE AND APPLICATION OF ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to establish the Specific Claims Tribunal, the mandate of which is to decide issues of validity and compensation relating to specific claims of First Nations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Inconsistency or conflict</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>In the event of any inconsistency or conflict between this Act and any other Act of Parliament, this Act prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>This Act affects the rights of a First Nation only if the First Nation chooses to file a specific claim with the Tribunal and only to the extent that this Act expressly provides.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SPECIFIC CLAIMS TRIBUNAL</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Establishment</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A tribunal to be known as the Specific Claims Tribunal is established.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Establishment of roster</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall establish a roster of 6 to 18 superior court judges to act as members of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chairperson and other members</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Chairperson and other members shall be appointed from the roster referred to in subsection (2) by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Membership</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall consist of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no more than six full-time members; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any number of part-time members, or combination of full-time and part-time members, so long as the combined time devoted to their functions and duties does not exceed the combined time that would be devoted by six full-time members.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Tenure</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Each member shall be appointed for a term not exceeding five years and holds office so long as he or she remains a superior court judge.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reappointment of members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each member, on the expiry of the first term of office, is eligible to be reappointed for one further term.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Role of Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chairperson has supervision over and direction of the work of the Tribunal, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the allocation of work among the members and the assignment of members to preside at hearings of the Tribunal; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the performance of the functions and duties of the Tribunal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On application by a party, the Chairperson may order that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specific claims be heard together or consecutively if they have issues of law or fact in common;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a specific claim is, together with any other specific claim, subject to one claim limit under subsection <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>(4); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specific claims be decided together if decisions with respect to the claims could be irreconcilable or if the claims are subject to one claim limit.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the office of Chairperson is vacant, or the Chairperson is absent or is for any reason unable to act, the powers of the Chairperson shall be exercised and the duties performed by the member who is the senior judge and is able and willing to act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Acting after termination of appointment</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), a judge who has ceased to be a member, for any reason other than removal, may, with the authorization of the Chairperson, perform and complete any functions or duties that they would otherwise have had if they had not ceased to be a member and that are in connection with any matter in which that judge became engaged while holding office as a member, and a judge so authorized is, for that purpose, deemed to be a member of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No judge who has ceased to be a member may, after the expiry of 120 days after ceasing to be a member, take part in the disposition of any matter under the authority granted by the Chairperson under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Administration of the Tribunal</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Registry</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There shall be a Registry of the Tribunal consisting of an office in the National Capital Region described in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Staff</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The registrar and any staff that is required for the proper conduct of the work of the Tribunal shall be appointed in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Role of the registrar</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The registrar is responsible for the management of the Tribunal’s administrative affairs and the duties of the staff of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Organization</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The staff of the Tribunal shall be organized and the offices shall be operated in any manner that may be provided by the rules referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Functions, Powers and Duties</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Functions</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Tribunal is responsible for holding hearings to decide the validity of specific claims and any compensation arising from those claims.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hearings</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A hearing before the Tribunal shall be held before a single member.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A decision of a member of the Tribunal is a decision of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rules of the Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A committee of no more than six Tribunal members, appointed by the Chairperson, may make general rules for carrying out the work of the Tribunal, the management of its internal affairs and the duties of its staff, as well as rules governing its practice and procedures, including rules governing</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the giving of notice;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the presentation of the positions of the parties with respect to issues before the Tribunal and of matters of fact or law on which the parties rely in support of their positions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the summoning of witnesses;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the production and service of documents;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applications;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>discovery proceedings;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the taking and preservation of evidence before the start of a hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>case management, including pre-hearing conferences and the use of mediation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the introduction of evidence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the imposition of time limits; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>costs.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Advisory committee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee referred to in subsection (1) may establish an advisory committee of interested parties to advise it in the development of the Tribunal’s rules of practice and procedure, including efficiencies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rules respecting costs</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Tribunal’s rules respecting costs shall accord with the rules of the Federal Court, with any modifications that the Tribunal considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of rules</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall make its rules available to the public and, if possible, publish them in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">First Nations Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of failure to publish</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Failure to publish the rules in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">First Nations Gazette</XRefExternal> does not affect the validity of the rules.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of the Tribunal</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Tribunal has, with respect to the attendance, swearing and examination of witnesses, the production and inspection of documents, the enforcement of its orders and other matters necessary or proper for the due exercise of its jurisdiction, all the powers, rights and privileges that are vested in a superior court of record and may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>determine any questions of law or fact in relation to any matter within its jurisdiction under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>receive and accept any evidence, including oral history, and other information, whether on oath or by affidavit or otherwise, that it sees fit, whether or not that evidence or information is or would be admissible in a court of law, unless it would be inadmissible in a court by reason of any privilege under the law of evidence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>take into consideration cultural diversity in developing and applying its rules of practice and procedure; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>award costs in accordance with its rules of practice and procedure.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Costs</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall deduct from any award of costs in favour of the claimant, any amount provided to the claimant by the Crown for the purpose of bringing the claim before the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Specific Claims</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Grounds of a specific claim</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to sections <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>, a First Nation may file with the Tribunal a claim based on any of the following grounds, for compensation for its losses arising from those grounds:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a failure to fulfil a legal obligation of the Crown to provide lands or other assets under a treaty or another agreement between the First Nation and the Crown;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a breach of a legal obligation of the Crown under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> or any other legislation — pertaining to Indians or lands reserved for Indians — of Canada or of a colony of Great Britain of which at least some portion now forms part of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a breach of a legal obligation arising from the Crown’s provision or non-provision of reserve lands, including unilateral undertakings that give rise to a fiduciary obligation at law, or its administration of reserve lands, Indian moneys or other assets of the First Nation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an illegal lease or disposition by the Crown of reserve lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a failure to provide adequate compensation for reserve lands taken or damaged by the Crown or any of its agencies under legal authority; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fraud by employees or agents of the Crown in connection with the acquisition, leasing or disposition of reserve lands.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extended meaning of <DefinedTermEn>Crown</DefinedTermEn> — obligations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of applying paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) in respect of any legal obligation that was to be performed in an area within Canada’s present boundaries before that area became part of Canada, a reference to the Crown includes the Sovereign of Great Britain and its colonies to the extent that the legal obligation or any liability relating to its breach or non-fulfilment became — or would, apart from any rule or doctrine that had the effect of limiting claims or prescribing rights against the Crown because of passage of time or delay, have become — the responsibility of the Crown in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extended meaning of <DefinedTermEn>Crown</DefinedTermEn> — illegal lease or disposition</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purpose of applying paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) in respect of an illegal lease or disposition of reserve land located in an area within Canada’s present boundaries before that area became part of Canada, a reference to the Crown includes the Sovereign of Great Britain and its colonies to the extent that liability for the illegal lease or disposition became — or would, apart from any rule or doctrine that had the effect of limiting claims or prescribing rights against the Crown because of passage of time or delay, have become — the responsibility of the Crown in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extended meaning of <DefinedTermEn>Crown</DefinedTermEn> — other</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purpose of applying paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) in respect of reserve lands located in an area within Canada’s present boundaries, a reference to the Crown includes the Sovereign of Great Britain and its colonies for the period before that area became part of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A First Nation may not file with the Tribunal a claim that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is based on events that occurred within the 15 years immediately preceding the date on which the claim was filed with the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is based on a land claims agreement entered into after December 31, 1973, or any related agreement or Act of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is based on an Act of Parliament or agreement that is mentioned in the schedule, or an Act of Parliament or agreement for the implementation of such an Act or agreement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>concerns the delivery or funding of programs or services related to policing, regulatory enforcement, corrections, education, health, child protection or social assistance, or of any similar programs or services;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is based on any agreement between the First Nation and the Crown that provides for another mechanism for the resolution of disputes arising from the agreement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is based on, or alleges, aboriginal rights or title; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is based on treaty rights related to activities of an ongoing and variable nature, such as harvesting rights.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) prevents a claim that is based on a treaty right to lands or to assets to be used for activities, such as ammunition to be used for hunting or plows to be used for cultivation, from being filed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When other proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A First Nation may not file a claim if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>there are proceedings before a court or tribunal other than the Tribunal that relate to the same land or other assets and could result in a decision irreconcilable with that of the claim, or that are based on the same or substantially the same facts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the First Nation and the Crown are parties to those proceedings; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the proceedings have not been adjourned.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restrictions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A First Nation may not file a claim if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is not claiming any compensation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is claiming any remedy other than monetary compensation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of its claim exceeds the claim limit.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Filing a specific claim</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A First Nation may file a claim with the Tribunal only if the claim has been previously filed with the Minister and</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister has notified the First Nation in writing of his or her decision not to negotiate the claim, in whole or in part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>three years have elapsed after the day on which the claim was filed with the Minister and the Minister has not notified the First Nation in writing of his or her decision on whether to negotiate the claim;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the course of negotiating the claim, the Minister consents in writing to the filing of the claim with the Tribunal; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>three years have elapsed after the day on which the Minister has notified the First Nation in writing of the Minister’s decision to negotiate the claim, in whole or in part, and the claim has not been resolved by a final settlement agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form and content of specific claim</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of subsection (1), the Minister shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establish a reasonable minimum standard to be followed in relation to the kind of information required for any claim to be filed with the Minister, as well as a reasonable form and manner for presenting the information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>publish the standard on the Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development’s Internet site; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>notify the First Nation in writing of the date on which the claim was filed with the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meeting minimum standard</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A claim is to be filed with the Minister only if the information in it meets the minimum standard referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and is presented in the form and manner established under that paragraph.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Hearings and Decisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application to strike</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Text>On application by a party to a specific claim, the Tribunal may, at any time, order that the claim be struck out in whole or in part, with or without leave to amend, on the ground that it</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is, on its face, not admissible under sections <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has not been filed by a First Nation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is frivolous, vexatious or premature; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may not be continued under section <XRefInternal>37</XRefInternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Hearing and decision</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>After providing notice to the parties, the Tribunal shall hold a hearing, at the time and place that it considers most appropriate, into the issue before it and make a decision on that issue.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>In deciding the issue of the validity of a specific claim, the Tribunal shall not consider any rule or doctrine that would have the effect of limiting claims or prescribing rights against the Crown because of the passage of time or delay.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Basis and limitations for decision on compensation</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Tribunal, in making a decision on the issue of compensation for a specific claim,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall award monetary compensation only;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall not, despite any other provision in this subsection, award total compensation in excess of $150 million;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall, subject to this Act, award compensation for losses in relation to the claim that it considers just, based on the principles of compensation applied by the courts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall not award any amount for</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>punitive or exemplary damages, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any harm or loss that is not pecuniary in nature, including loss of a cultural or spiritual nature;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall award compensation equal to the market value of a claimant’s reserve lands at the time they were taken brought forward to the current value of the loss, in accordance with legal principles applied by the courts, if the claimant establishes that those reserve lands were taken under legal authority, but that inadequate compensation was paid;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall award compensation equal to the value of the damage done to reserve lands brought forward to the current value of the loss, in accordance with legal principles applied by the courts, if the claimant establishes that certain of its reserve lands were damaged under legal authority, but that inadequate compensation was paid;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall award compensation equal to the current, unimproved market value of the lands that are the subject of the claim, if the claimant establishes that those lands were never lawfully surrendered, or otherwise taken under legal authority;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall award compensation equal to the value of the loss of use of a claimant’s lands brought forward to the current value of the loss, in accordance with legal principles applied by the courts, if the claimant establishes the loss of use of the lands referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall, if it finds that a third party caused or contributed to the acts or omissions referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal>(1) or the loss arising from those acts or omissions, award compensation against the Crown only to the extent that the Crown is at fault for the loss.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, in awarding the compensation referred to in subsection (1), the Tribunal may consider losses related to activities of an ongoing and variable nature, such as activities related to harvesting rights.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deduction of benefit</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall deduct from the amount of compensation calculated under subsection (1) the value of any benefit received by the claimant in relation to the subject-matter of the specific claim brought forward to its current value, in accordance with legal principles applied by the courts.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>One claim limit for related claims</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Two or more specific claims shall, for the purpose of paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), be treated as one claim if they</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>are made by the same claimant and are based on the same or substantially the same facts; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>are made by different claimants, are based on the same or substantially the same facts and relate to the same assets.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Equitable apportionment</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If claims are treated as one claim under paragraph (4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the Tribunal shall apportion equitably among the claimants the total compensation awarded.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compensation against province</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the Tribunal finds that a province that has been granted party status caused or contributed to the acts or omissions referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal>(1) or the loss arising from those acts or omissions, it may award compensation against the province to the extent that the province was at fault in causing or contributing to the loss.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Unlawful disposition</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If compensation is awarded under this Act for an unlawful disposition of all of the interests or rights of a claimant in or to land and the interests or rights have never been restored to the claimant, then all of the claimant’s interests in and rights to the land are released, without prejudice to any right of the claimant to bring any proceeding related to that unlawful disposition against a province that is not a party to the specific claim.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unlawful disposition of partial interest</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If compensation is awarded under this Act for the unlawful disposition of a partial interest or right of a claimant in or to reserve land, then the persons who, if the disposition had been lawful, would have had the partial interest or right in or to the land are deemed to have had that interest or right.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to others</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Tribunal’s decision of an issue in relation to a specific claim might, in its opinion, significantly affect the interests of a province, First Nation or person, the Tribunal shall so notify them. The parties may make submissions to the Tribunal as to whose interests might be affected.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of failure to notify</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Failure to provide notice does not invalidate any decision of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Tribunal has jurisdiction with respect to a province only if the province is granted party status.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Party status of a province — mandatory</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Crown alleges that a province that has been notified under subsection <XRefInternal>22</XRefInternal>(1) is wholly or partly at fault for the claimant’s losses, the Tribunal shall grant the province party status provided that the province certifies in writing that it has taken the steps necessary for it to be bound by decisions of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Party status of a province — discretionary</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Crown does not allege that a province that has been notified under subsection <XRefInternal>22</XRefInternal>(1) is wholly or partly at fault for the claimant’s losses, the Tribunal may, on application by the province, grant the province party status if the Tribunal considers it a necessary or proper party and provided that the province certifies in writing that it has taken the steps necessary for it to be bound by decisions of the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Party status of a First Nation</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>The Tribunal may, on application by a First Nation to whom notice under subsection <XRefInternal>22</XRefInternal>(1) is provided, grant the First Nation party status if the Tribunal considers it a necessary or proper party.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Intervention by persons affected</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A First Nation or person to whom notice under subsection <XRefInternal>22</XRefInternal>(1) is provided may, with leave of the Tribunal, intervene before it, to make representations relevant to the proceedings in respect of any matter that affects the First Nation or person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In exercising its discretion under subsection (1), the Tribunal shall consider all relevant factors, including the effect that granting intervenor status would have on the cost and length of the hearing.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conduct of hearings</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this Act, the Tribunal shall conduct its hearings in any manner that it considers fit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In deciding how to conduct a hearing, the Tribunal shall have regard to any submissions that a party has made regarding the manner in which the hearing is to be conducted and to the importance of achieving an expeditious resolution.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Public hearings</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), Tribunal hearings shall be public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidential hearings</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tribunal may, on application by a party, take any measures and make any order that it considers necessary to ensure the confidentiality of a hearing if it is satisfied that the reasons for confidentiality outweigh the societal interest that the hearing be public.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right to cross-examine</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>A party may cross-examine a witness</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>as of right, if the witness is called by a party adverse in interest; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with leave of the Tribunal, in any other case.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Defences of Crown</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>Subject to section <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal>, section 24 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Crown Liability and Proceedings Act</XRefExternal> applies in respect of a specific claim as if it were a proceeding.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Withdrawal</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A party may withdraw an issue from the Tribunal at any time before the Tribunal gives its decision on it and, in such a case, the Tribunal shall not render a decision on it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Costs</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tribunal may award costs on the withdrawal of an issue from the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not a bar</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Withdrawal of an issue does not bar any subsequent consideration of the issue by the Tribunal.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Evidence not admissible in other proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>Subject to subsection <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(1), evidence given by any person in the course of a Tribunal hearing, including anything said, any position taken or any admission made, is not admissible in any other proceeding.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Advance notice of decision on compensation</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall, not later than 14 days before it renders its decision on the issue of compensation, give notice to the parties and to the Chairperson that the decision will be rendered.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Written reasons and publication</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>The Tribunal shall give written reasons for its decisions and shall cause the reasons and the decisions to be published in the manner that it considers fit.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial review</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A decision of the Tribunal is subject to judicial review under section 28 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Final and conclusive</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1), the Tribunal’s decisions are final and conclusive between the parties in all proceedings in any court or tribunal arising out of the same or substantially the same facts and are not subject to review.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Release and indemnity</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>If the Tribunal decides that a specific claim is invalid or awards compensation for a specific claim,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>each respondent is released from any cause of action, claim or liability to the claimant and any of its members of any kind, direct or indirect, arising out of the same or substantially the same facts on which the claim is based; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the claimant shall indemnify each respondent against any amount that the respondent becomes liable to pay as a result of a claim, action or other proceeding for damages brought by the claimant or any of its members against any other person arising out of the same or substantially the same facts.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of award</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An award of compensation against the Crown may, at the discretion of the Crown, be paid by instalments, but the award must be fully paid within five years after the day on which the Tribunal makes its decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The unpaid balance of the award bears simple interest from the date of the award, at a rate equal to the Bank of Canada’s overnight rate on that day plus 2.5%, which shall be paid together with each instalment.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Abandoned specific claim</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Text>A specific claim is discontinued if the claimant</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>commences, before another tribunal or a court, a proceeding against the Crown that is based on the same or substantially the same facts as the claim, or that relates to the same land or other assets as the claim and could result in a decision irreconcilable with that of the claim, unless the claimant immediately has the proceeding adjourned; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>takes a new step in, or does not continue to adjourn, a proceeding mentioned in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or in subsection <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>(3).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Public documents</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), documents filed with the Tribunal are public documents.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Confidential documents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tribunal, on the application of a party, may take any measures that it considers necessary to ensure the confidentiality of a document if it is satisfied that the interest of a party or a person that the document not be disclosed outweighs the societal interest that it be public.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>GENERAL</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations adding to Part 2 of the schedule the name of any agreement related to aboriginal self-government.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Annual Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Chairperson shall submit an annual report on the work of the Tribunal in a fiscal year and its projected activities for the following fiscal year to the Minister within six months after the end of that fiscal year, including the financial statements of the Tribunal and any report on them of the Auditor General of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Resources</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The annual report may include a statement on whether the Tribunal had sufficient resources, including a sufficient number of members, to address its case load in the past fiscal year and whether it will have sufficient resources for the following fiscal year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall submit a copy of the report to each House of Parliament on any of the first 30 days on which that House is sitting after the report is submitted to the Minister.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one year after the fifth anniversary of the coming into force of this Act, the Minister shall undertake a review of the mandate and structure of the Tribunal, of its efficiency and effectiveness of operation and of any other matters related to this Act that the Minister considers appropriate. In carrying out the review, the Minister shall give First Nations an opportunity to make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within one year after a review is undertaken, the Minister shall cause to be prepared and sign a report that sets out a statement of any changes to this Act, including any changes to the Tribunal’s functions, powers or duties, that the Minister recommends and the representations which have been made by First Nations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling and referral of report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall submit to each House of Parliament a copy of the report on any of the first 90 days on which that House is sitting after the Minister signs the report, and each House shall refer the report to the appropriate committee of that House.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Existing claims</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a First Nation has submitted a claim based on any one or more of the grounds referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal>(1) to the Minister before the day on which this Act comes into force containing the kind of information that would meet the minimum standard established under subsection <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>(2), or if the claim is being negotiated on the day on which this Act comes into force, the claim is deemed to have been filed with the Minister in accordance with section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>, or the Minister is deemed to have decided to negotiate the claim and to have notified the First Nation in writing of that decision, as the case may be, on the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Examination by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within six months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister shall examine all claims — except those that the Minister has notified the First Nation in writing of the Minister’s decision not to negotiate, in whole or in part — that are based on any one or more of the grounds referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal>(1) submitted by First Nations to the Minister before the day on which this Act comes into force, and</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if a claim contains the kind of information that would meet the minimum stand- ard established under subsection <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>(2), the Minister shall notify the First Nation in writing that its claim is deemed to have been filed with the Minister in accordance with section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> on the day on which this Act comes into force;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if a claim does not contain that kind of information, the Minister shall request in writing that the First Nation provide the Minister with the missing information; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if a claim is being negotiated, in whole or in part, the Minister shall notify the First Nation in writing that for the purpose of section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> the date of the Minister’s decision to negotiate the claim is deemed to be the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Amended claim — deemed filing date</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a First Nation provides the Minister with the information requested under paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within six months after the date of the Minister’s request, its claim is deemed to have been filed with the Minister in accordance with section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> on the day on which this Act comes into force; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>later than six months after the date of the Minister’s request, its claim will be filed with the Minister in accordance with section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> on the date the requested information is received by the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Notice of filing date</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On receiving the information referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the Minister shall notify the First Nation in writing of the date on which its claim was filed with the Minister.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Previous decision not to negotiate</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, if, before the coming into force of this Act, a First Nation has been notified by the Minister of his or her decision not to negotiate a claim, the First Nation may not file that claim with the Tribunal on the basis of that decision but nothing prevents the First Nation from filing the claim with the Minister after the coming into force of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>44.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Specific Claims Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal des revendications particulières </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45.</Label><Text>Schedule II to the Act is amended by adding, in alphabetical order, a reference to</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Specific Claims Tribunal Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur le Tribunal des revendications particulières</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>and a corresponding reference to “subsections <XRefInternal>27</XRefInternal>(2) and <XRefInternal>38</XRefInternal>(2)”.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-7; 2002, c. 8, s. 14</MarginalNote><TitleText>Federal Courts Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>46.</Label><Text>Subsection 28(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>), by adding the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Specific Claims Tribunal established by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>Financial Administration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>47.</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding, in alphabetical order in column I, a reference to</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Registry of the Specific Claims Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Greffe du Tribunal des revendications particulières</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>and a corresponding reference in column II to the “Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development”.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48.</Label><Text>Schedule IV to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Specific Claims Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal des revendications particulières</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49.</Label><Text>Part III of Schedule VI to the Act is amended by adding, in alphabetical order in column I, a reference to</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Registry of the Specific Claims Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Greffe du Tribunal des revendications particulières</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>and a corresponding reference in column II to the “Registrar”.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>50.</Label><Text>The schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Specific Claims Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal des revendications particulières</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-36</MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Service Superannuation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>51.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Specific Claims Tribunal</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Tribunal des revendications particulières</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>REPEAL</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>52.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Resolution Act,</XRefExternal> chapter 23 of the Statutes of Canada, 2003, is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>53.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force 120 days after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2, paragraph <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>(1)(c) and section <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal>)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>ACTS RELATED TO SELF-GOVERNMENT</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les Cris et les Naskapis du Québec</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Kanesatake Interim Land Base Governance Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur le gouvernement du territoire provisoire de Kanesatake</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Mi’kmaq Education Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’éducation des Mi’kmaq</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Nisga’a Final Agreement Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’Accord définitif nisga’a</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la bande indienne sechelte</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les revendications territoriales et l’autonomie gouvernementale du peuple tlicho</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Westbank First Nation Self-Government Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la première nation de Westbank </BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’autonomie gouvernementale des premières nations du Yukon</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Provision></Group><Group><GroupHeading format-ref="group1-part"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>AGREEMENTS RELATED TO SELF-GOVERNMENT</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Carcross/Tagish First Nation Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la Première nation de Carcross/Tagish</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Champagne and Aishihik First Nations Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale des Premières Nations de Champagne et de Aishihik</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Kluane First Nation Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la Première nation de Kluane</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Kwanlin Dun First Nation Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la Première nation des Kwanlin Dun</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Little Salmon/Carmacks Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la première nation de Little Salmon/Carmacks</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Nacho Nyak Dun First Nation Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la première nation des Nacho Nyak Dun</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Selkirk First Nation Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la première nation de Selkirk</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Ta’an Kwach’an Council Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale du Conseil des Ta’an Kwach’an</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Teslin Tlingit Council Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale du conseil des Tlingits de Teslin</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Tr’ondek Hwech’in Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale des Tr’ondèk Hwëch’in</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Vuntut Gwitchin First Nation Self-Government Agreement</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Entente sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la première nation des Gwitchin Vuntut</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Provision></Group></DocumentInternal></Schedule></Bill>