<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-42</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>56-57</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2007-2008</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Museums Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act amending the Museums Act and making consequential amendments to other Acts</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Museums</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2008</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>13</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>9</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2008</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2008-1-28">90449</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Museums Act</XRefExternal> to establish a corporation called the Canadian Museum for Human Rights and to set out its purpose, capacity and powers. It also makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 3</MarginalNote><TitleText>MUSEUMS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>museum material</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Museums Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>museum material</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>matériel de musée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>museum material</DefinedTermEn> means objects and documentary material, regardless of medium or form, of a type normally kept by a museum for reference or exhibition purposes.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 15:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Establishment of the Canadian Museum for Human Rights</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>15.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is established a corporation to be called the Canadian Museum for Human Rights.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Affiliated museums</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Canadian Museum for Human Rights shall include any affiliated museums that the Board of the Canadian Museum for Human Rights may, by by-law, establish with the approval of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Purpose, Capacity and Powers of the Canadian Museum for Human Rights</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>15.2</Label><Text>The purpose of the Canadian Museum for Human Rights is to explore the subject of human rights, with special but not exclusive reference to Canada, in order to enhance the public’s understanding of human rights, to promote respect for others and to encourage reflection and dialogue.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Capacity and powers</MarginalNote><Label>15.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In furtherance of its purpose, the Canadian Museum for Human Rights has, subject to this Act, the capacity of a natural person and, elsewhere than in Quebec, the rights, powers and privileges of a natural person. In particular, but without limiting the generality of the foregoing, the Canadian Museum for Human Rights may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>collect museum material related to human rights;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>maintain its collection by preservation, conservation or restoration or the establishment of records or documentation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sell, exchange, give away, destroy or otherwise dispose of museum material in its collection and use any revenue obtained from that disposal to further its collection;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>lend or borrow museum material on long- or short-term loan;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>organize, sponsor, arrange for or participate in travelling exhibitions, in Canada or internationally, of museum material in its collection or from other sources;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>undertake or sponsor any research related to its purpose or to museology and communicate the results of that research;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide facilities to permit qualified individuals to use or study its collection;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>promote knowledge and disseminate information related to its purpose, throughout Canada and internationally, by any appropriate means of education and communication;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establish and foster links with other organizations that have a purpose similar to its own;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>share the expertise of its staff by undertaking or sponsoring training and apprenticeship programs that relate to its purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide or arrange for professional and technical services to any other organization that has a purpose similar to its own;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>acquire property by gift, bequest or otherwise and hold in trust or otherwise, expend, invest, administer and dispose of that property;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>develop, operate and maintain branches or exhibition centres;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>operate restaurants, lounges, parking facilities, shops and other facilities for the use of the public;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>lease or otherwise make available any of its facilities to other persons; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>charge for goods, services and admission and use the revenue so obtained for its own purposes.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Canadian Museum for Human Rights may not deal with property otherwise than in accordance with the terms, if any, on which it was acquired or is held.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 23(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Director</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1.1), there shall be a Director of each museum who shall be appointed, with the approval of the Governor in Council, by the museum’s Board to hold office during pleasure for a term of not more than five years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Director of the Canadian Museum for Human Rights</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall, by order, on the recommendation of the Minister, appoint the first Director of the Canadian Museum for Human Rights to hold office during pleasure for a term of not more than five years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reappointment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Director of each museum is eligible to be reappointed, with the approval of the Governor in Council, by the museum’s Board.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 23(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (5.1), the Director shall be paid by the museum any remuneration that the Board, with the approval of the Governor in Council, may determine.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration — first Director of the Canadian Museum for Human Rights</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>The first Director of the Canadian Museum for Human Rights shall be paid by that museum for the duration of his or her first term of office any remuneration that the Governor in Council may, by order, on the recommendation of the Minister, determine.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 25:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Pre-establishment contracts</MarginalNote><Label>24.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As of the date of its establishment under this Act, each museum shall be bound by any deed, contract or agreement entered into on its behalf by the Minister before its establishment and shall be entitled to the benefits of any such deed, contract or agreement and the Minister shall cease to be bound.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not retroactive</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to any museum already established by this Act on the day on which that subsection comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 11, s. 22</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>Paragraph 68(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>material placed in the Library and Archives of Canada, the National Gallery of Canada, the Canadian Museum of Civilization, the Canadian Museum of Nature, the National Museum of Science and Technology or the Canadian Museum for Human Rights by or on behalf of persons or organizations other than government institutions.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum for Human Rights</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien des droits de la personne</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>Financial Administration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule III to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum for Human Rights</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien des droits de la personne</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. M-13; 2000, c. 8, s. 2</MarginalNote><TitleText>Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision first-line-indent="0" language-align="no" list-item="no" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Text>Canadian Museum for Human Rights, with respect to real property or immovables that are owned by Her Majesty in right of Canada and whose administration and control are held by the Museum, whether title to the real property or immovables is vested in the name of Her Majesty or in the name of the Museum.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>Schedule III to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum for Human Rights</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien des droits de la personne</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 11, s. 39</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>Paragraph 69(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>material placed in the Library and Archives of Canada, the National Gallery of Canada, the Canadian Museum of Civilization, the Canadian Museum of Nature, the National Museum of Science and Technology or the Canadian Museum for Human Rights by or on behalf of persons or organizations other than government institutions.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum for Human Rights</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien des droits de la personne</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 30</MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Sector Compensation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>Schedule II to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum for Human Rights</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien des droits de la personne</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-36</MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Service Superannuation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canadian Museum for Human Rights</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Musée canadien des droits de la personne</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>