<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-23</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>56-57</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2007-2008</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Marine Act, the Canada Transportation Act, the Pilotage Act and other Acts in consequence</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Canada Marine Act, the Canada Transportation Act, the Pilotage Act and other Acts in consequence</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canada Marine, Canada Transportation and Pilotage</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2008</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>21</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2008</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2007-11-15">90432</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Marine Act</XRefExternal> to clarify and make technical changes to certain provisions. As well, the amendments</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>modify the Act’s purpose;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>modify a port authority’s access to federal funding;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>add provisions regarding the power of a port authority to borrow money;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide additional regulatory powers to the Governor in Council;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>add provisions regarding port amalgamation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>modify provisions regarding the appointment of directors of port authorities; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>add a penalty scheme and streamline certain other enforcement provisions.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>The amendments also include transitional provisions, corrections to other Acts and consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 10</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">CANADA MARINE ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermFr>droits</DefinedTermFr> and <DefinedTermFr>installations portuaires</DefinedTermFr> in subsection 2(1) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Marine Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>goods</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>port authority</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>goods</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>marchandises</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>goods</DefinedTermEn> includes personal property and movables, other than ships.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>port authority</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>administration portuaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>port authority</DefinedTermEn> means a port authority incorporated or continued under this Act.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>fees</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>port facility</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>fees</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>droit</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>fees</DefinedTermEn> includes harbour dues, berthage and wharfage, as well as duties, tolls, rates and other charges, but does not include payments made under a lease or licence agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>port facility</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>installation portuaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>port facility</DefinedTermEn> means a wharf, pier, breakwater, terminal, warehouse or other building or work that is located in, on or adjacent to navigable waters that is used in connection with navigation or shipping, land incidental to its use and any land adjacent to navigable waters that is used in connection with navigation or shipping.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>owner</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of goods, the agent, sender, consignee or bailee of the goods, as well as the carrier of the goods to, on, over or from any real property or immovables to which this Act applies.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the French version of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>droit</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>fees</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermFr>droit</DefinedTermFr> S’entend de toute forme de taxe, péage, contribution ou redevance, notamment pour l’accès, l’accostage et l’amarrage au port, à l’exclusion de toute somme versée au titre d’un bail ou d’un permis.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>installation portuaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>port facility</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermFr>installation portuaire</DefinedTermFr> Quai, jetée, brise-lames, terminal, entrepôt ou autre construction situés dans les eaux navigables ou à la surface ou à proximité de celles-ci — y compris les terrains liés à leur utilisation ou adjacents aux eaux navigables — et affectés à la navigation ou au transport par eau.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The heading before section 4 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading><TitleText>PURPOSE</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 4 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose of the Act</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>In recognition of the significance of marine transportation to Canada and its contribution to the Canadian economy, the purpose of this Act is to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>implement marine policies that provide Canada with the marine infrastructure that it needs and that offer effective support for the achievement of national, regional and local social and economic objectives and will promote and safeguard Canada’s competitiveness and trade objectives;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>promote the success of ports for the purpose of contributing to the competitiveness, growth and prosperity of the Canadian economy;</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>promote coordination and integration of marine activities with surface and air transportation systems.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 6(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment of schedule</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by regulation, amend the schedule.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 8(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Letters patent</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may issue letters patent — that take effect on the date stated in them — incorporating a port authority without share capital for the purpose of operating a particular port in Canada if the Minister is satisfied that the port</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 8(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of letters patent</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The letters patent shall set out the following:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 8(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(iii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>one individual appointed by the province in which the port is situated, and, in the case of the port wholly or partially located in Vancouver, another individual appointed by the Provinces of Alberta, Saskatchewan and Manitoba acting together, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 8(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the limits on the power of the port authority to borrow money on the credit of the port authority for port purposes or a code governing that power, as the case may be; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Section 9 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Supplementary letters patent</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, either on the Minister’s own initiative and after giving notice of the proposed changes to the board of directors, or when the board of directors has, by resolution, requested it, issue supplementary letters patent amending the letters patent of a port authority if the Minister is satisfied that the amendment is consistent with this Act, and the supplementary letters patent take effect on the date stated in them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notice must be given in writing and set out a time limit within which the board of directors may comment to the Minister regarding the proposed changes.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 10(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Continuance of harbour commissions</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister is satisfied that the criteria set out in subsection 8(1) are met, the Minister may issue in respect of one or more harbour commissions established under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Harbour Commissions Act</XRefExternal>, letters patent continuing the harbour commission as a port authority that set out the information required by subsection 8(2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of letters patent</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the day on which the letters patent are issued, the harbour commission becomes a port authority and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Harbour Commissions Act</XRefExternal> ceases to apply.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 10(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations preserved — harbour commissions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The rights and obligations of a port authority that was one or more harbour commissions immediately before letters patent were issued are as follows:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 10(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the personal property or movable, and any rights related to it, that the harbour commission manages, or the title to which it holds, on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada, whether or not in its own name, become the property and rights of the port authority;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 12(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the personal property or movable, and any rights related to it, that the local port corporation administers, or the title to which it holds, on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada, whether or not in its own name, become the property and rights of the port authority;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 12(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the personal property or movable, and any rights related to it, that relate to the port and that the Canada Ports Corporation administers, or the title to which it holds, on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada, whether or not in its own name, become the property and rights of the port authority;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 13:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amalgamation of Port Authorities</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Directors</MarginalNote><Label>13.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may remove any director of an amalgamating port authority during the period that begins on the day on which the Governor in Council requires the amalgamation and ends on the day before the day on which the amalgamation takes effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsection 14(2.3)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 14(2.3) does not apply to a director of an amalgamating port authority who holds office on the day on which the Governor in Council requires the amalgamation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fees continued</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A fee that is in force in respect of a port on the day on which an amalgamation takes effect continues in force for a period that ends on the earlier of the expiry of six months and the day on which it is replaced by a fee fixed under subsection 49(1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>Subsection 14(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directors appointed by provinces and municipalities</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may appoint a director under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) who has been nominated by the Minister if the position has been vacant for more than one year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tenure of office</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Directors are appointed to hold office for any term of not more than three years that will ensure as far as possible the expiry in any one year of the terms of office of not more than one half of the directors, the terms being renewable twice only.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum term of office</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>A director shall serve no more than nine consecutive years on the board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effective day of appointment</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>A director’s appointment takes effect on the day on which notice of the appointment is received by the port authority.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension of term</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2.1), if a successor has not been appointed at the expiry of a director’s term, the director continues to hold office until their term is renewed or their successor is appointed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directors appointed by municipalities and provinces</MarginalNote><Label>(2.4)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2.1) and despite subsection (2), the term of office of a director appointed under subsection (1.1) to fill a vacant position under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) expires on the day on which a director is nominated under that paragraph.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22, s. 113(E)</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a Senator or a member of the House of Commons;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an officer or employee of the federal public administration, a federal Crown corporation or a port authority;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>Paragraph 19(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is removed for cause by the authority that made the appointment, namely, the Governor in Council, the municipalities or the province or provinces, as the case may be; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 21:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Delegation</MarginalNote><Label>21.1</Label><Text>Subject to the letters patent, the board of directors may delegate the powers to manage the activities of the port authority to a committee of directors or to the officers of the port authority.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Text>Section 25 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>No appropriation</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Even if the port authority or subsidiary is an agent of Her Majesty in right of Canada as provided under section 7, no payment to a port authority or a wholly-owned subsidiary of a port authority may be made under an appropriation by Parliament to enable the port authority or subsidiary to discharge an obligation or liability unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the payment</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergencies Act</XRefExternal> or any other Act in respect of emergencies,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is a contribution in respect of the capital costs of an infrastructure project,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>is a contribution in respect of envi- ronmental sustainability, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>is a contribution in respect of security, or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the authority for the funding of Her Majesty’s obligations is an agreement that was in existence before March 1, 1999.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 25:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Contribution</MarginalNote><Label>25.1</Label><Text>The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council given on the recommendation of the Treasury Board and on any terms and conditions specified by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Treasury Board, make a contribution under subparagraph 25(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(iv).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Text>Subsection 27(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the information and documents to be provided by a port authority to the Minister at the Minister’s request; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the amalgamation of port authorities.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 28(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restrictions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A port authority shall not carry on any activity or exercise any power that it is restricted by its letters patent from carrying on or exercising, nor shall it carry on any activity or exercise any power in a manner contrary to its letters patent or this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 28(6) and (7) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compliance with code</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>If a port authority that is subject to a code governing its power to borrow enters into a contract, or executes any other document, for the borrowing of money, the document shall include an express statement that the borrowing complies with the code.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty of directors</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The directors of a port authority shall take all necessary measures to ensure</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the port authority and any wholly-owned subsidiary of the port authority comply with subsections (5) and, if appli- cable, (5.1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that any subcontract arising directly or indirectly from a contract to which subsection (5) applies expressly states that the port authority or subsidiary, as the case may be, enters into the contract on its own behalf and not as agent of Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Borrowing limitations may be imposed</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If a port authority or a wholly-owned subsidiary of a port authority fails to comply with subsection (5) or (5.1), or the directors of a port authority fail to comply with subsection (6) or section 30.1, the Minister of Finance, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, may impose any limitations that the Minister of Finance considers to be in the public interest on the power of the port authority or subsidiary to borrow money, including limitations on the time and terms and conditions of any borrowing.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 28(13) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Activités antérieures</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>La filiale à cent pour cent d’une administration portuaire peut continuer à exercer les pouvoirs et les activités qu’elle exerçait le 1<Sup>er</Sup> décembre 1995; les pouvoirs et les activités qu’elle cesse d’exercer après cette date ne peuvent être exercés de nouveau que si les lettres patentes le lui permettent.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 30:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Borrowing policy</MarginalNote><Label>30.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The directors of a port authority that is subject to a code governing its power to borrow shall certify to the Minister that the borrowing policy is in compliance with the code.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Changes to borrowing policy</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If there are any changes in respect of the borrowing policy, the directors of the port authority shall certify to the Minister that the policy remains in compliance with the code.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copy of policy</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The directors of the port authority shall provide a copy of the borrowing policy to the Minister if the Minister requests one.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 139(1)</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 31(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>No security interest in property</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), a port authority may not mortgage, hypothecate or otherwise create a security interest in any federal real property or federal immovable that it manages in any way other than to create a security interest in the revenues of that property.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 31(5) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Définition de <DefinedTermFr>sûreté</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Pour l’application des paragraphes (3) et (4), <DefinedTermFr>sûreté</DefinedTermFr> s’entend d’un droit grevant les biens gérés par une administration portuaire pour garantir l’exécution de ses obligations ou d’un intérêt sur ceux-ci aux mêmes fins.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 37(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The annual financial statements shall set out the total remuneration paid in money or in kind to each of the following persons in that year by the port authority or its wholly-owned subsidiary, including any fee, allowance or other benefit:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Section 39 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Business plan</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>A port authority shall, within three months after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the Minister, in respect of itself and each of its wholly-owned subsidiaries, a five-year business plan containing any information that the Minister may require, including any material changes in respect of information provided in the previous business plan.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 140(1)</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 44(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Pour l’application de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal>, le ministre a la responsabilité des immeubles fédéraux et des biens réels fédéraux qui se trouvent dans le port qu’une administration portuaire exploite en vertu de ses lettres patentes, à l’exception de ceux dont la responsabilité est confiée à un autre membre du Conseil privé de la Reine pour le Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 140(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 44(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Management</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by letters patent or supplementary letters patent, give to a port authority the management of any federal real property or federal immovable that is administered by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister under subsection (1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada, if the Minister has the consent of that other member.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Minister gives the management of any federal real property or federal immovable to a port authority, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Real Property and Federal Immovables Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to that property, other than sections 3, 5, 12 to 14 and 16 to the extent that those sections are not inconsistent with this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 141</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 45(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall undertake and defend any legal proceedings, subject to any instructions that may be provided by the Attorney General of Canada, with respect to that property; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 141</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 45(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Legal proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A civil, criminal or administrative action or proceeding shall be taken by or against a port authority and not by or against the Crown with respect to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any personal property or movable owned by that port authority;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any federal real property or federal immovable that it manages;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any real property or immovable that it holds; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any act or omission relating to any property referred to in paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 45 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3.1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Temporary use</MarginalNote><Label>(3.2)</Label><Text>A port authority may lease or license any federal real property or federal immovable it manages for temporary use under paragraph 28(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 45:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Acquisition of real property and immovables</MarginalNote><Label>45.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Her Majesty in right of Canada may acquire any real property or immovable for the purpose of operating a port at the request of the port authority and the port authority may pay the price of the property in question.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of management</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the management of the real property or immovable acquired under subsection (1) is removed from the port authority, Her Majesty does not become liable to the port authority for any portion of the price paid by it.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 141</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 46(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Disposition d’immeubles fédéraux et de biens réels fédéraux</MarginalNote><Label>46.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sous réserve du paragraphe 45(3), une administration portuaire ne peut disposer des immeubles fédéraux et des biens réels fédéraux dont la gestion lui est confiée; elle peut toutefois :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 141</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 46(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>without the issuance of supplementary letters patent, grant a road allowance, an easement, a real servitude, a right of way or a licence for utilities, services or access; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 141</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 46(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>exchange that property for other real property or immovables of comparable value, if supplementary letters patent that describe the other property as federal real property or federal immovables have been issued, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 141</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 46(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>disposer des accessoires fixés à demeure sur des immeubles fédéraux et des biens réels fédéraux.</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 141</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 46(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other real property and immovables</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A port authority may dispose of any real property or immovable that it holds, other than federal real property or federal immovables, if supplementary letters patent have been issued, and, without the issuance of supplementary letters patent, it may grant a road allowance, an easement, a real servitude, a right of way or a licence for utilities, services or access.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Acquisition, lease or license of real property and immovables</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The port authority may acquire, lease as lessee or license as licensee real property or immovables other than federal real property or federal immovables, if supplementary letters patent have been issued.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Temporary use</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>A port authority may lease or license any real property or immovable it holds, other than federal real property or federal immovables, for temporary use under paragraph 28(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>Section 47 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Navigable Waters Protection Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Navigable Waters Protection Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a work, within the meaning of that Act, that has been exempted by a regulation made under section 62.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>Subsection 51(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Le préavis est publié dans un journal à grand tirage du lieu où est situé le port, envoyé par courrier ou par voie électronique aux organisations dont les membres, de l’avis de l’administration portuaire, seront touchés par les droits — nouveaux ou révisés — ainsi qu’à tout utilisateur ou toute personne lui ayant manifesté, au moins dix jours auparavant, le désir de recevoir les préavis exigés par la présente partie; il est aussi inscrit en un endroit accessible sur le réseau communément appelé Internet.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28.</Label><Text>Subsection 52(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Plaintes</MarginalNote><Label>52.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Tout intéressé peut déposer auprès de l’Office une plainte portant qu’un droit fixé aux termes du paragraphe 49(1) opère une discrimination injustifiée; l’Office examine la plainte sans délai et communique ses conclusions à l’administration portuaire qui est liée par celles-ci.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Text>Section 53 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Fees by contract</MarginalNote><Label>53.</Label><Text>A port authority may enter into an agreement, that the parties may agree to keep confidential, fixing an amount to be paid to the port authority in respect of the persons and things set out in paragraphs 49(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) that is different from the fees fixed under those paragraphs.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 56(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>surveiller la circulation des navires qui se trouvent dans les eaux du port ou s’apprêtent à y entrer;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 56(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>créer des zones de contrôle de la circulation pour l’application des alinéas <Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) à <Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 58(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Traffic control</MarginalNote><Label>58.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of promoting safe and efficient navigation or environmental protection, a port authority may designate a person or a member of a class of persons, each of whom shall be furnished with a certificate of designation, to exercise the following powers with respect to ships about to enter or within the port or an area of the port:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 58(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct the master, the person in charge of the deck watch or any other person in charge of a ship or the pilot to provide information in respect of the ship specified by the designated person;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 58(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>un problème de pollution ou un risque sérieux de pollution dans la zone de contrôle de la circulation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 58(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>la présence d’obstacles à la navigation dans la zone de contrôle de la circulation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>la proximité d’un navire apparemment en difficulté ou qui présente un risque de pollution ou un danger pour les personnes et les biens;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraph 58(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>dans les cas où il est tenu d’obtenir une autorisation de mouvement, d’entrer dans un port ou dans une zone de contrôle de la circulation de ce port, d’en sortir ou de s’y déplacer sans avoir obtenu une telle autorisation sous le régime du présent article;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 59(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>soit ne se conforme pas aux pratiques et procédures établies en vertu de l’alinéa 56(1)<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) ou n’a pas à bord l’équipement permettant l’utilisation des fréquences déterminées par l’administration portuaire en vertu de cet alinéa;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 59(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence available in certain cases</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>It is a defence to a charge under subsection (1) that the master, the person in charge of the deck watch or other person in charge of the ship or the pilot</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 59(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Preuve d’une infraction par un navire</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Lorsqu’un navire est poursuivi pour infraction au présent article, il suffit pour établir l’infraction de prouver que l’acte ou l’omission qui la constitue est le fait du capitaine ou d’une autre personne à bord du navire, que celle-ci soit identifiée ou non.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33.</Label><Text>Section 61 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 61(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Marine transportation security</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to any regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Transportation Security Act</XRefExternal>, a port authority shall take appropriate measures for the maintenance of marine transportation security.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 62(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>l’enlèvement ou la disposition, notamment par destruction, de navires ou de toutes parties s’en étant détachées, de bâtiments, d’ouvrages ou d’autres choses qui gênent la navigation dans le port, et le recouvrement des coûts afférents;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 62(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the information or documents that must be provided by the owner or the person in charge of a ship to the port authority;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 143</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 62(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the obligations of a port authority in respect of federal real property and federal immovables under the management of the port authority.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35.</Label><Text>Paragraph 65(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate as a public port any navigable waters within the jurisdiction of Parliament and any land covered by the navigable waters, if the land is under the administration of the Minister, including any related foreshore;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 144</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>Section 66 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>66.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Pour l’application de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal>, le ministre a la responsabilité des immeubles fédéraux et des biens réels fédéraux qui font partie des ports publics ou des installations portuaires publiques.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Autres ports et installations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le ministre n’a pas la responsabilité des immeubles fédéraux et des biens réels fédéraux qui sont placés sous la responsabilité d’un autre membre du Conseil privé de la Reine pour le Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pouvoir du ministre</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Il est entendu que l’abrogation de la désignation de port public ou d’installation portuaire publique est sans effet sur la responsabilité du ministre, en vertu de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal>, à l’égard des immeubles fédéraux et des biens réels fédéraux qui faisaient partie du port ou de l’installation et qui appartiennent à Sa Majesté.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37.</Label><Text>Subsection 69(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Harbour masters and wharfingers</MarginalNote><Label>69.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may appoint as a harbour master or wharfinger for all or part of a public port or public port facility any person who, in the Minister’s opinion, is qualified and assign responsibilities to that person, including the responsibility to collect fees and interest on fees.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 145</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>Subsection 71(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Baux et permis</MarginalNote><Label>71.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Par dérogation à la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal>, le ministre peut louer les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux qui font ou faisaient partie d’un port public ou d’installations portuaires publiques ou accorder des permis à leur égard qui, comme les baux, doivent être approuvés par le gouverneur en conseil, si leur durée est supérieure à vingt ans.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 146(1)</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 72(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Pouvoir de disposition</MarginalNote><Label>72.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le ministre peut conclure des ententes en vue :</Text><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>de la disposition, par vente ou tout autre mode de cession, de la totalité ou d’une partie des immeubles fédéraux et des biens réels fédéraux qui faisaient partie d’un port public ou d’installations portuaires publiques;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 146(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 72(5) and (6) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition et transfert</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Les dispositions et les transferts peuvent être effectués sous le régime du présent article ou en conformité avec la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application du droit provincial</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>La disposition ou le transfert des immeubles fédéraux et des biens réels fédéraux visés au présent article est fait par un acte qui, en vertu des lois de la province où ils sont situés, peut servir à opérer la disposition ou le transfert d’immeubles ou de biens réels entre sujets de droit privé.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 72(7) and (8) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister responsible</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Subject to any regulations made under section 74, the Minister continues to have the management of public ports and public port facilities that the Minister has not disposed of or transferred.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40.</Label><Text>Section 73 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Navigable Waters Protection Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>73.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Navigable Waters Protection Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a work, within the meaning of that Act, that has been exempted by a regulation made under section 74.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 74(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Règlements</MarginalNote><Label>74.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le gouverneur en conseil peut prendre des règlements en vue de la gestion, du contrôle, du développement et de l’utilisation des ports publics et des installations portuaires publiques, notamment dans les domaines suivants :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 74(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>l’enlèvement ou la disposition, notamment par destruction, de navires ou de toutes parties s’en étant détachées, de bâtiments, d’ouvrages ou d’autres choses qui gênent la navigation dans ces ports, et le recouvrement des coûts afférents;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 74(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the information or documents that must be provided by the owner or the person in charge of a ship to the Minister;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42.</Label><Text>Paragraph 82(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the personal property or movable, and any rights related to it, that the Authority administers, or the title to which it holds, on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada, whether or not in its own name, other than those set out specifically or by class in the agreement and notice, become the property and rights of the person.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 148</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Text>Section 90 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>90.</Label><Text>Pour l’application de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les immeubles fédéraux et les biens réels fédéraux</XRefExternal>, le ministre ou tout autre membre du Conseil privé de la Reine pour le Canada est responsable de tous les immeubles fédéraux et biens réels fédéraux qui lui sont transférés en vertu des paragraphes 80(1) ou (2).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 149</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Text>Subsection 91(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procédures</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Toute poursuite civile, pénale ou administrative relative à un immeuble ou un bien réel dont la gestion a été confiée à une personne qui a conclu une entente en vertu du paragraphe 80(5) ou à tout autre bien qu’elle détient — ou à tout acte ou omission qui y survient — doit être engagée soit par cette personne, soit contre celle-ci à l’exclusion de la Couronne.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45.</Label><Text>Subsection 94(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Plaintes</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Tout intéressé peut déposer auprès de l’Office une plainte portant qu’un droit visé au paragraphe (1) opère une discrimination injustifiée; l’Office examine la plainte sans délai et communique ses conclusions au ministre ou à la personne qui a fixé le droit, selon le cas, le ministre et cette personne étant liés par celles-ci.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 4, s. 150(F)</MarginalNote><Label>46.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 98(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Pouvoir réglementaire</MarginalNote><Label>98.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le gouverneur en conseil peut prendre des règlements en vue de la gestion, du contrôle, du développement et de l’utilisation de la voie maritime, des immeubles ou biens réels ou des entreprises liés à celle-ci, notamment en ce qui touche :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 98(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>l’enlèvement ou la disposition, notamment par destruction, de navires ou de toutes parties s’en étant détachées, de bâtiments, d’ouvrages ou d’autres choses qui gênent la navigation dans la voie maritime, et le recouvrement des coûts afférents;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 98(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the information or documents that must be provided by the owner or the person in charge of a ship to the Minister or to any person who has entered into an agreement under subsection 80(5);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47.</Label><Text>Section 101 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Navigable Waters Protection Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>101.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Navigable Waters Protection Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a work, within the meaning of that Act, that has been exempted by a regulation made under section 98.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48.</Label><Text>Subsection 107(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Navires</MarginalNote><Label>107.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Les droits et les intérêts fixés sous le régime de la présente loi à l’égard des navires ou des marchandises doivent être acquittés par le propriétaire ou le responsable du navire ou le propriétaire des marchandises sans préjudice des recours ouverts en droit contre d’autres personnes.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49.</Label><Text>Paragraph 115(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the ship or the owner or person in charge of the ship or goods has, in respect of the ship or goods, contravened any provision of this Act or the regulations;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 116(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>security in the amount of $100,000 has been given to, and has been determined satisfactory by, the port authority, the Minister or the person who has entered into an agreement under subsection 80(5), as the case may be;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the ship has not been charged with an offence under this Act within 30 days after the making of the detention order;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 116(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>le navire a été accusé d’une infraction à la présente loi dans le délai mentionné à l’alinéa <Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) et :</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 116(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>security satisfactory to the Minister of not more than $5,000 is given to Her Majesty in right of Canada, or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 117(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the security referred to in paragraph 116(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) has not been given.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 117(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the security referred to in paragraph 116(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) has not been given.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 117(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the security referred to in paragraph 116(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) has not been given.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52.</Label><Text>Section 121 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Vente de marchandises périssables</MarginalNote><Label>121.</Label><Text>S’il estime que des marchandises saisies et retenues conformément à la présente loi ou qui ont été abandonnées risquent de se détériorer, l’agent de l’autorité peut en disposer, notamment par vente, selon les modalités et aux prix justifiés par les circonstances. Le produit de la disposition est affecté au paiement des frais qu’elle a occasionnés, ainsi qu’à l’acquittement des sommes dues à l’égard du navire ou des marchandises.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 26, s. 279</MarginalNote><Label>53.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 122(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Privilèges — navires</MarginalNote><Label>122.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>L’administration portuaire, le ministre ou la personne qui a conclu une entente en vertu du paragraphe 80(5) est toujours titulaire d’un privilège sur le navire et sur le produit de toute disposition qui en est faite, pour sa créance; ce privilège a priorité sur tous autres droits et créances, quelle qu’en soit la nature, à la seule exception des créances salariales des membres de l’équipage, visées par la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi de 2001 sur la marine marchande du Canada</XRefExternal>, dans les cas suivants :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>54.</Label><Text>Subsections 127(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Offence and fine</MarginalNote><Label>127.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person or ship that contravenes a provision of this Act, except section 107, or of the regulations made under paragraph 27(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), or of the regulations made under this Act for which no penalty is otherwise provided is guilty of an offence and liable to a fine of not more than $5,000 in the case of an individual, and of not more than $50,000 in the case of a corporation or ship.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of offence by ship</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>If a ship is prosecuted for an offence under a provision of this Act, except section 107, or of the regulations, it is sufficient proof that the ship has committed the offence to establish that the act or omission that constitutes the offence was committed by the master of the ship or any person on board the ship, whether or not the person on board has been identified.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>By-laws</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>No person is guilty of an offence under this Act for a contravention of a by-law made under section 30.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person or ship shall be found guilty of an offence under this Act if the person or ship establishes that the person or ship exercised due diligence to prevent its commission.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>55.</Label><Text>Subsection 128(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Separate offence</MarginalNote><Label>128.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When an offence under this Act is committed by a person or ship on more than one day or is continued by a person or ship for more than one day, it is deemed to be a separate offence for each day on which it is committed or continued.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>56.</Label><Text>Subsection 129(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Order to comply</MarginalNote><Label>129.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person or ship is guilty of an offence under Part 1 or the regulations made under paragraph 27(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), a court in which proceedings in respect of the offence are taken may, in addition to any punishment it may impose, order the person or ship to comply with those provisions for the contravention of which the person or ship is convicted.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>57.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 129:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Administrative Monetary Penalties</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Appeal Tribunal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>129.01</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 129.06, 129.08 and 129.1 to 129.13, <DefinedTermEn>Appeal Tribunal</DefinedTermEn> means the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada established by subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Violations</MarginalNote><Label>129.02</Label><Text>Every person or ship that contravenes a provision or instruction designated under paragraph 129.03(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) commits a violation and is liable to an administrative monetary penalty not exceeding the maximum established by regulation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>129.03</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating any of the following as a provision or instruction whose contravention may be proceeded with as a violation, namely,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>any provision of this Act, other than paragraphs 59(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and 126(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>any provision of the regulations, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any instruction that may be given under the regulations;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing the maximum administrative monetary penalty for a particular violation, which may not exceed $5,000 in the case of an individual and $25,000 in the case of a corporation or ship;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing criteria to be taken into account in determining the penalty;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating provisions or instructions the contravention of which, if continued on more than one day, constitutes a separate violation in respect of each day during which the violation is continued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the service of the notice that is required to be served under subsection 129.05(1), including the manner and proof of service and the circumstances under which the notice is deemed to be served; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>generally, for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this section and sections 129.04 to 129.17.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Criteria for penalty</MarginalNote><Label>129.04</Label><Text>The administrative monetary penalty imposed is, in each case, to be determined taking into account</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the purpose of the penalty, which is to promote compliance with this Act and not to punish;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the seriousness of the violation, including the frequency and duration of the conduct;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the history of the person or ship that has been served with the notice of violation with respect to any prior violation or conviction under this Act within the five-year period immediately before the violation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other criteria established under paragraph 129.03(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of violation</MarginalNote><Label>129.05</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an enforcement officer believes on reasonable grounds that a person or ship has committed a violation, the officer may issue, and shall cause to be served on the person or ship, a notice of violation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may establish the form and content of notices of violation, but each notice of violation shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>name the person or ship believed to have committed the violation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>identify the violation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>set out the administrative monetary penalty that the person or ship is liable to pay;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>set out the particulars concerning the time for and manner of paying the penalty and the time for and manner of requesting a review; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>inform the person or ship that, if they do not pay the penalty or request a review in accordance with the particulars set out in the notice, they will be deemed to have committed the violation and the penalty set out in the notice will be imposed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Option</MarginalNote><Label>129.06</Label><Text>A person or ship that has been served with a notice of violation shall either pay the penalty set out in the notice or file with the Appeal Tribunal a written request for a review of the facts of the alleged violation or of the amount of the penalty.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payment of penalty</MarginalNote><Label>129.07</Label><Text>If the person or ship pays the penalty in accordance with the particulars set out in the notice of violation, the person or ship is deemed to have committed the violation and proceedings in respect of the violation are ended.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>129.08</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A request for a review shall be filed with the Appeal Tribunal at the address set out in the notice of violation on or before the date specified in the notice or within any further time that the Appeal Tribunal, on application, may allow.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time and place for review</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On receipt of the request, the Appeal Tribunal shall appoint a time and place for the review and shall so notify, in writing, the Minister and the person or ship that filed the request.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The member of the Appeal Tribunal who is assigned to conduct the review shall provide the Minister and the person or ship that filed the request with an opportunity that is consistent with procedural fairness and natural justice to present evidence and make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden of proof</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The burden of establishing that a person or ship has committed the violation identified in the notice is on the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person or ship not compelled to testify</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person or ship that is alleged to have committed a violation is not required, and may not be compelled, to give any evidence or testimony in the matter.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Failure to pay penalty or request review</MarginalNote><Label>129.09</Label><Text>A person or ship that neither pays the penalty nor files a request for a review in accordance with the particulars set out in the notice of violation is deemed to have committed the violation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Determination by Appeal Tribunal member</MarginalNote><Label>129.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the conclusion of a review under section 129.08, the member of the Appeal Tribunal who conducts the review shall without delay inform the person or ship and the Minister of the member’s determination on the review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No violation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the member determines that the person or ship has not committed the alleged violation, then, subject to section 129.11, no further proceedings may be taken against the person or ship in respect of the alleged violation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Violation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the member determines that the person or ship has committed the alleged violation, then the member shall also inform the person or ship and the Minister of the administrative monetary penalty determined by the member to be payable in respect of the violation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>129.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister or a person or ship affected by a determination made under section 129.1 may, within 30 days after the determination, appeal it to the Appeal Tribunal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loss of right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A party that does not appear at a review hearing is not entitled to appeal a determination, unless they establish that there was sufficient reason to justify their absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The appeal panel of the Appeal Tribunal that is assigned to hear the appeal may dispose of the appeal by dismissing it or allowing it and, in allowing the appeal, the panel may substitute its decision for the determination appealed against.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Obligation to inform</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the appeal panel finds that a person or ship has committed the alleged violation, the panel shall without delay inform the person or ship of the finding and of the administrative monetary penalty determined by the panel to be payable in respect of the violation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Debts due to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>129.12</Label><Text>The following amounts constitute debts due to Her Majesty in right of Canada that may be recovered in a court of competent jurisdiction:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless a review of the facts of the alleged violation or the amount of the penalty is requested in accordance with the particulars set out in the notice of violation, the amount of a penalty set out in the notice, beginning on the day on which the notice was served;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of a penalty determined by a member of the Appeal Tribunal under section 129.1 or decided by the appeal panel of the Appeal Tribunal under section 129.11, beginning on the day on which the respective determination or decision was made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of any reasonable expenses incurred in attempting to recover an amount referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>129.13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All or part of a debt referred to in section 129.12 in respect of which there is a default of payment may be certified by the Appeal Tribunal at the request of the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Judgments</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On production in any superior court, a certificate made under subsection (1) is to be registered in that court and, when registered, has the same force and effect, and all proceedings may be taken on it, as if it were a judgment obtained in that court for a debt of the amount specified in it and all reasonable costs and charges attendant in its registration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Directors and officers of corporations</MarginalNote><Label>129.14</Label><Text>If a corporation commits a violation, every person who at the time of the commission of the violation was a director or officer of the corporation is a party to and liable for the violation unless the act or omission constituting the violation took place without the person’s knowledge or consent or the person exercised due diligence to prevent the commission of the violation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Vicarious liability — acts of employees, agents and mandataries</MarginalNote><Label>129.15</Label><Text>A person or ship is liable for a violation that is committed by their employee acting within the scope of their employment or their agent or mandatary acting within the scope of their authority, whether or not the employee, agent or mandatary who actually committed the violation is identified or proceeded against, unless the person or ship establishes that the violation was committed without the person’s or ship’s knowledge or consent.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Violations not offences</MarginalNote><Label>129.16</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a violation is not an offence. Accordingly, section 126 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> does not apply in respect of a violation.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Due diligence available</MarginalNote><Label>129.17</Label><Text>Due diligence is a defence in a proceeding in respect of a violation.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>How act or omission may be proceeded with</MarginalNote><Label>129.18</Label><Text>If an act or an omission can be proceeded with either as a violation or as an offence, proceeding in one manner precludes proceeding in the other.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Time limit</MarginalNote><Label>129.19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No proceedings in respect of a violation or a prosecution for an offence may be commenced later than one year after the subject-matter of the proceedings became known to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certification by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A document appearing to have been issued by the Minister, certifying the day on which the subject-matter of any proceedings became known to the Minister, is admissible in evidence without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed the document and is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof that the Minister became aware of the subject-matter on that day.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>58.</Label><Text>The portion of section 133 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Successor rights</MarginalNote><Label>133.</Label><Text>Where, under section 10, letters patent are issued to a harbour commission continuing it as a port authority, sections 44 to 46 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> apply as if</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>59.</Label><Text>Item 16 of Part 1 of the schedule to the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>16.</Label><Text>Trois-Rivières Port Authority</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>60.</Label><Text>The heading of Part 2 of the schedule to the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Heading><TitleText>ADMINISTRATIONS PORTUAIRES QUI NE SONT PAS DES ADMINISTRATIONS PORTUAIRES INITIALES</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 10</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">CANADA TRANSPORTATION ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2007, c. 19, s. 5</MarginalNote><Label>61.</Label><Text>Subsection 18(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Residence of members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The members appointed under subsection 7(2) shall reside in the National Capital Region described in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal> or within any distance of it that the Governor in Council determines.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-14</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">PILOTAGE ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 26, par. 318(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>62.</Label><Text>Paragraph 48(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pilotage Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>à une disposition de la présente partie autre que l’article 15.3;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continued effect</MarginalNote><Label>63.</Label><Text>Paragraph 25(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Marine Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the coming into force of section <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal> of this Act, continues to apply in respect of a grant under an agreement in existence at the time of the coming into force of that section.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 40</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Transportation Security Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 73</MarginalNote><Label>64.</Label><Text>Section 11.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Transportation Security Act</XRefExternal> and the heading before it are repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 29</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2007, c. 1, s. 59</MarginalNote><Label>65.</Label><Text>Subsection 2(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction in respect of other Acts</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Tribunal also has jurisdiction in respect of reviews and appeals in connection with administrative monetary penalties provided for under sections 177 to 181 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal>, sections 43 to 55 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Bridges and Tunnels Act</XRefExternal> and sections 129.01 to 129.19 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Marine Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>66.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, other than section <XRefInternal>64</XRefInternal>, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>