<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-292</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>39</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>56-57</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2007-2008</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to implement the Kelowna Accord</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Kelowna Accord Implementation Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Kelowna Accord</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2008</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>23</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2008</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2006-05-11">391318</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>This enactment requires the Government of Canada to fulfil its obligations under the Kelowna Accord.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>WHEREAS Parliament recognizes that narrowing and ultimately eliminating the troubling gaps between aboriginal and non-aboriginal Canadians that exist in the areas of education, skills development, health care, housing, access to clean water and employment, as provided for in the Kelowna Accord, are essential to improving the socio-economic conditions of aboriginal people in Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>AND WHEREAS the Government of Canada entered into the Kelowna Accord with the governments of Canada’s provinces and territories and with Canada’s aboriginal leadership, and it is incumbent upon the Government of Canada to honour its word and its commitments;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><?Pub Caret?><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Kelowna Accord Implementation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Implementation of Kelowna Accord</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The Government of Canada shall immediately take all measures necessary to implement the terms of the accord, known as the “Kelowna Accord”, that was concluded on November 25, 2005 at Kelowna, British Columbia, by the Prime Minister of Canada, the first ministers of each of the provinces and territories of Canada and the leaders of the Assembly of First Nations, the Inuit Tapiriit Kanatami, the Metis National Council, the Native Womens’ Association of Canada and the Congress of Aboriginal Peoples.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>At the end of the fiscal year beginning on April 1, 2007, and at the end of each of the next four fiscal years, the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development shall prepare a report reviewing the progress made by the Government of Canada in fulfilling its obligations under the Kelowna Accord during that fiscal year, and shall cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament within sixty days after the end of the fiscal year or, if that House is not then sitting, on any of the first fifteen days next thereafter that the House is sitting.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>