<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-36</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Export and Import of Rough Diamonds Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Export and Import of Rough Diamonds Act, An Act to amend the</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Export and Import of Rough Diamonds</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>51</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2005-5-17">90330</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import of Rough Diamonds Act</XRefExternal> for the purpose of enabling Canada to meet new international obligations under the Kimberley Process Certification Scheme by conferring on the Minister of Natural Resources the power to prescribe the classes of diamonds to be excluded from the definition <DefinedTermEn>rough diamond</DefinedTermEn>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>It also provides for the publication of statistics respecting Canadian Certificates issued by the Minister and Kimberley Process Certificates accompanying imports into Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><?Pub Caret?><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 25</MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>rough diamond</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import of Rough Diamonds Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>rough diamond</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>diamant brut</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>rough diamond</DefinedTermEn> means a diamond that is unsorted, unworked or simply sawn, cleaved or bruted, and that falls under subheading 7102.10, 7102.21 or 7102.31 in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff,</XRefExternal> but does not include diamonds that are of a class prescribed by regulation.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Statistics</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Minister may collect, compile and use statistics respecting Canadian Certificates and Kimberley Process Certificates accompanying imports into Canada for analysis, study or exchange with other participants. The Minister may also publish those statistics in any form and manner that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Section 8 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 8(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rough diamonds to be parcelled separately</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who exports rough diamonds must ensure that, on export, the rough diamonds in the container are not parcelled with diamonds excluded from the definition <DefinedTermEn>rough diamond</DefinedTermEn> or with anything else.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Section 14 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 14(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rough diamonds to be parcelled separately</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who imports rough diamonds must ensure that, on import, the rough diamonds in the container are not parcelled with diamonds excluded from the definition <DefinedTermEn>rough diamond</DefinedTermEn> or with anything else.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Subsection 15(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Return of imported rough diamonds</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If imported rough diamonds arrive in Canada accompanied by a Kimberley Process Certificate that meets the requirements of subsection 14(1) but are in a container that has been opened, the Minister may order the person who imported the rough diamonds to return them to the participant who issued the certificate.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Paragraph 35(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the classes of diamonds to be excluded from the definition <DefinedTermEn>rough diamond</DefinedTermEn> in section 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the manner of submitting an application under subsection 9(1) or section 11 and specifying the information that must be included in it and the documents that must accompany it;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>