<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-2</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (protection of children and other vulnerable persons) and the Canada Evidence Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (protection of children and other vulnerable persons) and the Canada Evidence Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code (protection of children and other vulnerable persons)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>7</MM><DD>20</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>32</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2004-10-7">90281</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>amend the child pornography provisions with respect to the type of written and audio material that constitutes child pornography, and with respect to the child pornography offences, defences and penalties;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>add a new category to the offence of sexual exploitation of young persons and make additional amendments to further protect children from sexual exploitation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>increase the maximum penalty for child sexual offences, for failing to provide the necessaries of life and for abandoning a child;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make child abuse an aggravating factor for the purpose of sentencing and direct the courts to give primary consideration to the objectives of denunciation and deterrence in sentencing for offences involving abuse of a child;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>amend and clarify the applicable test and criteria that need to be met for the use of testimonial aids, for excluding the public, for imposing a publication ban, for using video-recorded evidence or for appointing counsel for self-represented accused to conduct a cross-examination of certain witnesses; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>create an offence of voyeurism and the distribution of voyeuristic material.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no"><Text>This enactment also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> to abolish the requirement for a competency hearing for children under 14 years of age.</Text></Provision></Summary><?Pub Caret?><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>WHEREAS the Parliament of Canada has grave concerns regarding the vulnerability of children to all forms of exploitation, including child pornography, sexual exploitation, abuse and neglect;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS Canada, by ratifying the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child, has undertaken to protect children from all forms of sexual exploitation and sexual abuse, and has obligations as a signatory to the Optional Protocol to the Convention on the Rights of the Child on the sale of children, child prostitution and child pornography;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS the Parliament of Canada wishes to encourage the participation of witnesses in the criminal justice system through the use of protective measures that seek to facilitate the participation of children and other vulnerable witnesses while ensuring that the rights of accused persons are respected;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>AND WHEREAS the continuing advancements in the development of new technologies, while having social and economic benefits, facilitate sexual exploitation and breaches of privacy;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent=""><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Subsection 127(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Disobeying order of court</MarginalNote><Label>127.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every one who, without lawful excuse, disobeys a lawful order made by a court of justice or by a person or body of persons authorized by any Act to make or give the order, other than an order for the payment of money, is, unless a punishment or other mode of proceeding is expressly provided by law, guilty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 150.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is not in a position of trust or authority towards the complainant, is not a person with whom the complainant is in a relationship of dependency and is not in a relationship with the complainant that is exploitative of the complainant.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 150.1(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption for accused aged twelve or thirteen</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person aged twelve or thirteen years shall be tried for an offence under section 151 or 152 or subsection 173(2) unless the person is in a position of trust or authority towards the complainant, is a person with whom the complainant is in a relationship of dependency or is in a relationship with the complainant that is exploitative of the complainant.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>Sections 151 and 152 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Sexual interference</MarginalNote><Label>151.</Label><Text>Every person who, for a sexual purpose, touches, directly or indirectly, with a part of the body or with an object, any part of the body of a person under the age of fourteen years</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of forty-five days; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of fourteen days.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Invitation to sexual touching</MarginalNote><Label>152.</Label><Text>Every person who, for a sexual purpose, invites, counsels or incites a person under the age of fourteen years to touch, directly or indirectly, with a part of the body or with an object, the body of any person, including the body of the person who so invites, counsels or incites and the body of the person under the age of fourteen years,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of forty-five days; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of fourteen days.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 153(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Sexual exploitation</MarginalNote><Label>153.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who is in a position of trust or authority towards a young person, who is a person with whom the young person is in a relationship of dependency or who is in a relationship with a young person that is exploitative of the young person, and who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for a sexual purpose, touches, directly or indirectly, with a part of the body or with an object, any part of the body of the young person; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for a sexual purpose, invites, counsels or incites a young person to touch, directly or indirectly, with a part of the body or with an object, the body of any person, including the body of the person who so invites, counsels or incites and the body of the young person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 153 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of forty-five days; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of fourteen days.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inference of sexual exploitation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>A judge may infer that a person is in a relationship with a young person that is exploitative of the young person from the nature and circumstances of the relationship, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the age of the young person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the age difference between the person and the young person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the evolution of the relationship; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the degree of control or influence by the person over the young person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 13, s. 4(1)</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 161(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Order of prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>161.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When an offender is convicted, or is discharged on the conditions prescribed in a probation order under section 730, of an offence referred to in subsection (1.1) in respect of a person who is under the age of fourteen years, the court that sentences the offender or directs that the accused be discharged, as the case may be, in addition to any other punishment that may be imposed for that offence or any other condition prescribed in the order of discharge, shall consider making and may make, subject to the conditions or exemptions that the court directs, an order prohibiting the offender from</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 161 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The offences for the purpose of subsection (1) are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under section 151, 152, 155 or 159, subsection 160(2) or (3), section 163.1, 170, 171 or 172.1, subsection 173(2) or section 271, 272, 273 or 281;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under section 144 (rape), 145 (attempt to commit rape), 149 (indecent assault on female), 156 (indecent assault on male) or 245 (common assault) or subsection 246(1) (assault with intent) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as it read immediately before January 4, 1983; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 146(1) (sexual intercourse with a female under 14) or section 153 (sexual intercourse with step-daughter), 155 (buggery or bestiality), 157 (gross indecency), 166 (parent or guardian procuring defilement) or 167 (householder permitting defilement) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as it read immediately before January 1, 1988.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 161:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Voyeurism</MarginalNote><Label>162.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every one commits an offence who, surreptitiously, observes — including by mechanical or electronic means — or makes a visual recording of a person who is in circumstances that give rise to a reasonable expectation of privacy, if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person is in a place in which a person can reasonably be expected to be nude, to expose his or her genital organs or anal region or her breasts, or to be engaged in explicit sexual activity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person is nude, is exposing his or her genital organs or anal region or her breasts, or is engaged in explicit sexual activity, and the observation or recording is done for the purpose of observing or recording a person in such a state or engaged in such an activity; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the observation or recording is done for a sexual purpose.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>visual recording</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, “visual recording” includes a photographic, film or video recording made by any means.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) do not apply to a peace officer who, under the authority of a warrant issued under section 487.01, is carrying out any activity referred to in those paragraphs.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Printing, publication, etc., of voyeuristic recordings</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every one commits an offence who, knowing that a recording was obtained by the commission of an offence under subsection (1), prints, copies, publishes, distributes, circulates, sells, advertises or makes available the recording, or has the recording in his or her possession for the purpose of printing, copying, publishing, distributing, circulating, selling or advertising it or making it available.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every one who commits an offence under subsection (1) or (4)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>No person shall be convicted of an offence under this section if the acts that are alleged to constitute the offence serve the public good and do not extend beyond what serves the public good.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Question of law, motives</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (6),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>it is a question of law whether an act serves the public good and whether there is evidence that the act alleged goes beyond what serves the public good, but it is a question of fact whether the act does or does not extend beyond what serves the public good; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the motives of an accused are irrelevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 163.1(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and by replacing paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any written material, visual representation or audio recording that advocates or counsels sexual activity with a person under the age of eighteen years that would be an offence under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any written material whose dominant characteristic is the description, for a sexual purpose, of sexual activity with a person under the age of eighteen years that would be an offence under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any audio recording that has as its dominant characteristic the description, presentation or representation, for a sexual purpose, of sexual activity with a person under the age of eighteen years that would be an offence under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 163.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of ninety days.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 2; 2002, c. 13, s. 5(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 163.1(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distribution, etc. of child pornography</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who transmits, makes available, distributes, sells, advertises, imports, exports or possesses for the purpose of transmission, making available, distribution, sale, advertising or exportation any child pornography is guilty of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding ten years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of one year; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of ninety days.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 163.1(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of forty-five days; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of fourteen days.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 13, s. 5(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 163.1(4.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of forty-five days; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of fourteen days.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Section 163.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4.2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aggravating factor</MarginalNote><Label>(4.3)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under this section, the court that imposes the sentence shall consider as an aggravating factor the fact that the person committed the offence with intent to make a profit.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 13, s. 5(4)</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsections 163.1(6) and (7) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>No person shall be convicted of an offence under this section if the act that is alleged to constitute the offence</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has a legitimate purpose related to the administration of justice or to science, medicine, education or art; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>does not pose an undue risk of harm to persons under the age of eighteen years.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Question of law</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, for the purposes of this section, it is a question of law whether any written material, visual representation or audio recording advocates or counsels sexual activity with a person under the age of eighteen years that would be an offence under this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 3(1); 1997, c. 18, s. 5</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 164(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Mandat de saisie</MarginalNote><Label>164.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le juge peut décerner, sous son seing, un mandat autorisant la saisie des exemplaires d’une publication ou des copies d’une représentation, d’un écrit ou d’un enregistrement s’il est convaincu, par une dénonciation sous serment, qu’il existe des motifs raisonnables de croire :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 3(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and by replacing paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any representation, written material or recording, copies of which are kept in premises within the jurisdiction of the court, is child pornography within the meaning of section 163.1, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any recording, copies of which are kept for sale or distribution in premises within the jurisdiction of the court, is a voyeuristic recording,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 3(2); 2002, c. 13, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 164(3) to (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Owner and maker may appear</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The owner and the maker of the matter seized under subsection (1), and alleged to be obscene, a crime comic, child pornography or a voyeuristic recording, may appear and be represented in the proceedings in order to oppose the making of an order for the forfeiture of the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order of forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the publication, representation, written material or recording referred to in subsection (1) is obscene, a crime comic, child pornography or a voyeuristic recording, it may make an order declaring the matter forfeited to Her Majesty in right of the province in which the proceedings take place, for disposal as the Attorney General may direct.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposal of matter</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is not satisfied that the publication, representation, written material or recording referred to in subsection (1) is obscene, a crime comic, child pornography or a voyeuristic recording, it shall order that the matter be restored to the person from whom it was seized without delay after the time for final appeal has expired.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 46, s. 3(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consent</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If an order is made under this section by a judge in a province with respect to one or more copies of a publication, a representation, written material or a recording, no proceedings shall be instituted or continued in that province under section 162, 163 or 163.1 with respect to those or other copies of the same publication, representation, written material or recording without the consent of the Attorney General.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 164(8) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>voyeuristic recording</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>enregistrement voyeuriste</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>voyeuristic recording</DefinedTermEn> means a visual recording within the meaning of subsection 162(2) that is made as described in subsection 162(1).</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 13, s. 7</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 164.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Warrant of seizure</MarginalNote><Label>164.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a judge is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is material — namely child pornography within the meaning of section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording within the meaning of subsection 164(8) or data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography or a voyeuristic recording available — that is stored on and made available through a computer system within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that is within the jurisdiction of the court, the judge may order the custodian of the computer system to</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 13, s. 7</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 164.1(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied, on a balance of probabilities, that the material is child pornog­raphy within the meaning of section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording within the meaning of subsection 164(8) or data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography or the voyeuristic recording available, it may order the custodian of the computer system to delete the material.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 13, s. 7</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 164.1(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of material</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the court is not satisfied that the material is child pornography within the meaning of section 163.1, a voyeuristic recording within the meaning of subsection 164(8) or data within the meaning of subsection 342.1(2) that makes child pornography or the voyeuristic recording available, the court shall order that the electronic copy be returned to the custodian and terminate the order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 5</MarginalNote><Label>9.1</Label><Text>Sections 170 and 171 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Parent or guardian procuring sexual activity</MarginalNote><Label>170.</Label><Text>Every parent or guardian of a person under the age of eighteen years who procures the person for the purpose of engaging in any sexual activity prohibited by this Act with a person other than the parent or guardian is guilty of an indictable offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of six months if the person procured is under the age of fourteen years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of forty-five days if the person procured is fourteen years of age or more but under the age of eighteen years.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Householder permitting sexual activity</MarginalNote><Label>171.</Label><Text>Every owner, occupier or manager of premises, or any other person who has control of premises or assists in the management or control of premises, who knowingly permits a person under the age of eighteen years to resort to or to be in or on the premises for the purpose of engaging in any sexual activity prohibited by this Act is guilty of an indictable offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of six months if the person in question is under the age of fourteen years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of forty-five days if the person is fourteen years of age or more but under the age of eighteen years.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition “offence” in section 183 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xxvii):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xxvii.1)</Label><Text>section 162 (voyeurism),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 9</MarginalNote><Label>10.1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 212(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Living on the avails of prostitution of person under eighteen</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>), every person who lives wholly or in part on the avails of prostitution of another person who is under the age of eighteen years is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding fourteen years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of two years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 5, s. 8</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 212(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence — prostitution of person under eighteen</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who, in any place, obtains for consideration, or communicates with anyone for the purpose of obtaining for consideration, the sexual services of a person who is under the age of eighteen years is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of six months.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>Subsection 215(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every one who commits an offence under subsection (2)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Text>Section 218 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Abandoning child</MarginalNote><Label>218.</Label><Text>Every one who unlawfully abandons or exposes a child who is under the age of ten years, so that its life is or is likely to be endangered or its health is or is likely to be permanently injured,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding five years; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding eighteen months.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 38, s. 2</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Subsection 276.3(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Publication prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>276.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall publish in any document, or broadcast or transmit in any way, any of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the contents of an application made under section 276.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any evidence taken, the information given and the representations made at an application under section 276.1 or at a hearing under section 276.2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the decision of a judge or justice under subsection 276.1(4), unless the judge or justice, after taking into account the complain­ant’s right of privacy and the interests of justice, orders that the decision may be published, broadcast or transmitted; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the determination made and the reasons provided under section 276.2, unless</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that determination is that evidence is admissible, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the judge or justice, after taking into account the complainant’s right of privacy and the interests of justice, orders that the determination and reasons may be published, broadcast or transmitted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 30, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 278.9(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Publication prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>278.9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall publish in any document, or broadcast or transmit in any way, any of the following:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 203, c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 14(2), c. 23 (4th Supp.), s. 1; 1993, c. 45, s. 7(1); 1997, c. 16, s. 6(4); 1999, c. 25, s. 2; 2001, c. 32, ss. 29(1), (2), (4) and (5), c. 41, ss. 34 and 133(13) and (14); 2002, c. 13, s. 20</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>Section 486 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exclusion of public in certain cases</MarginalNote><Label>486.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any proceedings against an accused shall be held in open court, but the presiding judge or justice may order the exclusion of all or any members of the public from the court room for all or part of the proceedings if the judge or justice is of the opinion that such an order is in the interest of public morals, the maintenance of order or the proper administration of justice or is necessary to prevent injury to international relations or national defence or national security.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protection of witnesses under 18 and justice system participants</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), the “proper administration of justice” includes ensuring that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the interests of witnesses under the age of eighteen years are safeguarded in all proceedings; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>justice system participants who are involved in the proceedings are protected.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons to be stated</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an accused is charged with an offence under section 151, 152, 153, 153.1, 155 or 159, subsection 160(2) or (3) or section 163.1, 171, 172, 172.1, 173, 212, 271, 272 or 273 and the prosecutor or the accused applies for an order under subsection (1), the judge or justice shall, if no such order is made, state, by reference to the circumstances of the case, the reason for not making an order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Support person — witnesses under 18 or who have a disability</MarginalNote><Label>486.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In any proceedings against an accused, the judge or justice shall, on application of the prosecutor, of a witness who is under the age of eighteen years or of a witness who has a mental or physical disability, order that a support person of the witness’ choice be permitted to be present and to be close to the witness while the witness testifies, unless the judge or justice is of the opinion that the order would interfere with the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other witnesses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In any proceedings against an accused, the judge or justice may, on application of the prosecutor or a witness, order that a support person of the witness’ choice be permitted to be present and to be close to the witness while the witness testifies if the judge or justice is of the opinion that the order is necessary to obtain a full and candid account from the witness of the acts complained of.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>An application referred to in subsection (1) or (2) may be made, during the proceedings, to the presiding judge or justice or, before the proceedings begin, to the judge or justice who will preside at the proceedings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In making a determination under subsection (2), the judge or justice shall take into account the age of the witness, whether the witness has a mental or physical disability, the nature of the offence, the nature of any relationship between the witness and the accused, and any other circumstance that the judge or justice considers relevant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Witness not to be a support person</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The judge or justice shall not permit a witness to be a support person unless the judge or justice is of the opinion that doing so is necessary for the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No communication while testifying</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The judge or justice may order that the support person and the witness not communicate with each other while the witness testifies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No adverse inference</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>No adverse inference may be drawn from the fact that an order is, or is not, made under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Testimony outside court room — witnesses under 18 or who have a disability</MarginalNote><Label>486.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 650, in any proceedings against an accused, the judge or justice shall, on application of the prosecutor, of a witness who is under the age of eighteen years or of a witness who is able to communicate evidence but may have difficulty doing so by reason of a mental or physical disability, order that the witness testify outside the court room or behind a screen or other device that would allow the witness not to see the accused, unless the judge or justice is of the opinion that the order would interfere with the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other witnesses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite section 650, in any proceedings against an accused, the judge or justice may, on application of the prosecutor or a witness, order that the witness testify outside the court room or behind a screen or other device that would allow the witness not to see the accused if the judge or justice is of the opinion that the order is necessary to obtain a full and candid account from the witness of the acts complained of.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>An application referred to in subsection (1) or (2) may be made, during the proceedings, to the presiding judge or justice or, before the proceedings begin, to the judge or justice who will preside at the proceedings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In making a determination under subsection (2), the judge or justice shall take into account the factors referred to in subsection 486.1(3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Specific offences</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite section 650, if an accused is charged with an offence referred to in subsection (5), the presiding judge or justice may order that any witness testify</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>outside the court room if the judge or justice is of the opinion that the order is necessary to protect the safety of the witness; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>outside the court room or behind a screen or other device that would allow the witness not to see the accused if the judge or justice is of the opinion that the order is necessary to obtain a full and candid account from the witness of the acts complained of.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The offences for the purposes of subsection (4) are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under section 423.1, 467.11, 467.12 or 467.13, or a serious offence committed for the benefit of, at the direction of, or in association with, a criminal organization;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a terrorism offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 16(1) or (2), 17(1), 19(1), 20(1) or 22(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 21(1) or section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> that is committed in relation to an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Same procedure for determination</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the judge or justice is of the opinion that it is necessary for a witness to testify in order to determine whether an order under subsection (2) or (4) should be made in respect of that witness, the judge or justice shall order that the witness testify in accordance with that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions of exclusion</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>A witness shall not testify outside the court room under subsection (1), (2), (4) or (6) unless arrangements are made for the accused, the judge or justice and the jury to watch the testimony of the witness by means of closed-circuit television or otherwise and the accused is permitted to communicate with counsel while watching the testimony.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No adverse inference</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>No adverse inference may be drawn from the fact that an order is, or is not, made under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Accused not to cross-examine witness under 18</MarginalNote><Label>486.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In any proceedings against an accused, on application of the prosecutor or a witness who is under the age of eighteen years, the accused shall not personally cross-examine the witness, unless the judge or justice is of the opinion that the proper administration of justice requires the accused to personally conduct the cross-examination. The judge or justice shall appoint counsel to conduct the cross-examination if the accused does not personally conduct the cross-examination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other witnesses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In any proceedings against an accused, on application of the prosecutor or a witness, the accused shall not personally cross-examine the witness if the judge or justice is of the opinion that, in order to obtain a full and candid account from the witness of the acts complained of, the accused should not personally cross-examine the witness. The judge or justice shall appoint counsel to conduct the cross-examination if the accused does not personally conduct the cross-examination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In making a determination under subsection (2), the judge or justice shall take into account the factors referred to in subsection 486.1(3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Victim of criminal harassment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In any proceedings in respect of an offence under section 264, on application of the prosecutor or the victim of the offence, the accused shall not personally cross-examine the victim unless the judge or justice is of the opinion that the proper administration of justice requires the accused to personally conduct the cross-examination. The judge or justice shall appoint counsel to conduct the cross-examination if the accused does not personally conduct the cross-examination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>An application referred to in subsection (1), (2) or (4) may be made, during the proceedings, to the presiding judge or justice or, before the proceedings begin, to the judge or justice who will preside at the proceedings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No adverse inference</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No adverse inference may be drawn from the fact that counsel is, or is not, appointed under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Order restricting publication — sexual offences</MarginalNote><Label>486.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the presiding judge or justice may make an order directing that any information that could identify the complainant or a witness shall not be published in any document or broadcast or transmitted in any way, in proceedings in respect of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any of the following offences:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an offence under section 151, 152, 153, 153.1, 155, 159, 160, 162, 163.1, 170, 171, 172, 172.1, 173, 210, 211, 212, 213, 271, 272, 273, 346 or 347,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an offence under section 144 (rape), 145 (attempt to commit rape), 149 (indecent assault on female), 156 (indecent assault on male) or 245 (common assault) or subsection 246(1) (assault with intent) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as it read immediately before January 4, 1983, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>an offence under subsection 146(1) (sexual intercourse with a female under 14) or (2) (sexual intercourse with a female between 14 and 16) or section 151 (seduction of a female between 16 and 18), 153 (sexual intercourse with step-daughter), 155 (buggery or bestiality), 157 (gross indecency), 166 (parent or guardian procuring defilement) or 167 (householder permitting defilement) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as it read immediately before January 1, 1988; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>two or more offences being dealt with in the same proceeding, at least one of which is an offence referred to in any of subparagraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) to (iii).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mandatory order on application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In proceedings in respect of the offences referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the presiding judge or justice shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at the first reasonable opportunity, inform any witness under the age of eighteen years and the complainant of the right to make an application for the order; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on application made by the complainant, the prosecutor or any such witness, make the order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Child pornography</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In proceedings in respect of an offence under section 163.1, a judge or justice shall make an order directing that any information that could identify a witness who is under the age of eighteen years, or any person who is the subject of a representation, written material or a recording that constitutes child pornography within the meaning of that section, shall not be published in any document or broadcast or transmitted in any way.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order made under this section does not apply in respect of the disclosure of information in the course of the administration of justice when it is not the purpose of the disclosure to make the information known in the community.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Order restricting publication — victims and witnesses</MarginalNote><Label>486.5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Unless an order is made under section 486.4, on application of the prosecutor, a victim or a witness, a judge or justice may make an order directing that any information that could identify the victim or witness shall not be published in any document or broadcast or transmitted in any way if the judge or justice is satisfied that the order is necessary for the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Justice system participants</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On application of a justice system participant who is involved in proceedings in respect of an offence referred to in subsection 486.2(5) or of the prosecutor in those proceedings, a judge or justice may make an order directing that any information that could identify the justice system participant shall not be published in any document or broadcast or transmitted in any way if the judge or justice is satisfied that the order is necessary for the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An order made under this section does not apply in respect of the disclosure of information in the course of the administration of justice if it is not the purpose of the disclosure to make the information known in the community.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application and notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An applicant for an order shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>apply in writing to the presiding judge or justice or, if the judge or justice has not been determined, to a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction in the judicial district where the proceedings will take place; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide notice of the application to the prosecutor, the accused and any other person affected by the order that the judge or justice specifies.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Grounds</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An applicant for an order shall set out the grounds on which the applicant relies to establish that the order is necessary for the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hearing may be held</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The judge or justice may hold a hearing to determine whether an order should be made, and the hearing may be in private.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>In determining whether to make an order, the judge or justice shall consider</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the right to a fair and public hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether there is a real and substantial risk that the victim, witness or justice system participant would suffer significant harm if their identity were disclosed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether the victim, witness or justice system participant needs the order for their security or to protect them from intimidation or retaliation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>society’s interest in encouraging the reporting of offences and the participation of victims, witnesses and justice system participants in the criminal justice process;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whether effective alternatives are available to protect the identity of the victim, witness or justice system participant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the salutary and deleterious effects of the proposed order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the impact of the proposed order on the freedom of expression of those affected by it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other factor that the judge or justice considers relevant.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>An order may be subject to any conditions that the judge or justice thinks fit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Unless the judge or justice refuses to make an order, no person shall publish in any document or broadcast or transmit in any way</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the contents of an application;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any evidence taken, information given or submissions made at a hearing under subsection (6); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other information that could identify the person to whom the application relates as a victim, witness or justice system participant in the proceedings.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>486.6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with an order made under subsection 486.4(1), (2) or (3) or 486.5(1) or (2) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, an order referred to in subsection (1) applies to prohibit, in relation to proceedings taken against any person who fails to comply with the order, the publication in any document or the broadcasting or transmission in any way of information that could identify a victim, witness or justice system participant whose identity is protected by the order.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 69</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 487.2(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction on publication</MarginalNote><Label>487.2</Label><Text>If a search warrant is issued under section 487 or 487.1 or a search is made under such a warrant, every one who publishes in any document, or broadcasts or transmits in any way, any information with respect to</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 69</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 487.2(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 517(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Order directing matters not to be published for specified period</MarginalNote><Label>517.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the prosecutor or the accused intends to show cause under section 515, he or she shall so state to the justice and the justice may, and shall on application by the accused, before or at any time during the course of the proceedings under that section, make an order directing that the evidence taken, the information given or the representations made and the reasons, if any, given or to be given by the justice shall not be published in any document, or broadcast or transmitted in any way before such time as</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 517(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 97</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 539(1) of the Act after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>make an order directing that the evidence taken at the inquiry shall not be published in any document or broadcast or transmitted in any way before such time as, in respect of each of the accused,</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>he or she is discharged, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if he or she is ordered to stand trial, the trial is ended.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 539(4) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 542(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction of publication of reports of preliminary inquiry</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every one who publishes in any document, or broadcasts or transmits in any way, a report that any admission or confession was tendered in evidence at a preliminary inquiry or a report of the nature of such admission or confession so tendered in evidence unless</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 542(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 32, s. 82(4)</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>Subsection 631(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Ban on publication</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>On application by the prosecutor or on its own motion, the court or judge before which a jury trial is to be held may, if an order under subsection (3.1) has been made, make an order directing that the identity of a juror or any information that could disclose their identity shall not be published in any document or broadcast or transmitted in any way if the court or judge is satisfied that such an order is necessary for the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 648(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Restriction on publication</MarginalNote><Label>648.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>After permission to separate is given to members of a jury under subsection 647(1), no information regarding any portion of the trial at which the jury is not present shall be published in any document or broadcast or transmitted in any way before the jury retires to consider its verdict.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 648(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 43, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 672.51(11) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition on publication</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>No person shall publish in any document or broadcast or transmit in any way</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 16; 1997, c. 16, s. 7; 1998, c. 9, s. 8</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>The heading before section 715.1 and sections 715.1 and 715.2 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Video-recorded Evidence</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Evidence of victim or witness under 18</MarginalNote><Label>715.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In any proceeding against an accused in which a victim or other witness was under the age of eighteen years at the time the offence is alleged to have been committed, a video recording made within a reasonable time after the alleged offence, in which the victim or witness describes the acts complained of, is admissible in evidence if the victim or witness, while testifying, adopts the contents of the video recording, unless the presiding judge or justice is of the opinion that admission of the video recording in evidence would interfere with the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order prohibiting use</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The presiding judge or justice may prohibit any other use of a video recording referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Evidence of victim or witness who has a disability</MarginalNote><Label>715.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In any proceeding against an accused in which a victim or other witness is able to communicate evidence but may have difficulty doing so by reason of a mental or physical disability, a video recording made within a reasonable time after the alleged offence, in which the victim or witness describes the acts complained of, is admissible in evidence if the victim or witness, while testifying, adopts the contents of the video recording, unless the presiding judge or justice is of the opinion that admission of the video recording in evidence would interfere with the proper administration of justice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order prohibiting use</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The presiding judge or justice may prohibit any other use of a video recording referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 718:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives — offences against children</MarginalNote><Label>718.01</Label><Text>When a court imposes a sentence for an offence that involved the abuse of a person under the age of eighteen years, it shall give primary consideration to the objectives of denunciation and deterrence of such conduct.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 22, s. 6; 2000, c. 12, par. 95(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 718.2(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>evidence that the offender, in committing the offence, abused the offender’s spouse or common-law partner,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii.1)</Label><Text>evidence that the offender, in committing the offence, abused a person under the age of eighteen years,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-5</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA EVIDENCE ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 19 (3rd Supp.), s. 18</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 16(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Witness whose capacity is in question</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a proposed witness is a person of fourteen years of age or older whose mental capacity is challenged, the court shall, before permitting the person to give evidence, conduct an inquiry to determine</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 16:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Person under fourteen years of age</MarginalNote><Label>16.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person under fourteen years of age is presumed to have the capacity to testify.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No oath or solemn affirmation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A proposed witness under fourteen years of age shall not take an oath or make a solemn affirmation despite a provision of any Act that requires an oath or a solemn affirmation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence shall be received</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The evidence of a proposed witness under fourteen years of age shall be received if they are able to understand and respond to questions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Burden as to capacity of witness</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A party who challenges the capacity of a proposed witness under fourteen years of age has the burden of satisfying the court that there is an issue as to the capacity of the proposed witness to understand and respond to questions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court inquiry</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied that there is an issue as to the capacity of a proposed witness under fourteen years of age to understand and respond to questions, it shall, before permitting them to give evidence, conduct an inquiry to determine whether they are able to understand and respond to questions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Promise to tell truth</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The court shall, before permitting a proposed witness under fourteen years of age to give evidence, require them to promise to tell the truth.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Understanding of promise</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>No proposed witness under fourteen years of age shall be asked any questions regarding their understanding of the nature of the promise to tell the truth for the purpose of determining whether their evidence shall be received by the court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, if the evidence of a witness under fourteen years of age is received by the court, it shall have the same effect as if it were taken under oath.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>REVIEW AND REPORT TO PARLIAMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>27.1</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Five years after this section comes into force, a committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that is designated or established for the purpose shall undertake a comprehensive review of this Act and its operation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee shall submit a report on the review to Parliament, including a statement of any changes that it recommends, within six months after it undertakes the review or within any further time authorized by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>If section 10 of this Act comes into force before the coming into force of any provision of the definition “offence” in section 183 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 108 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Safety Act, 2002</XRefExternal> (the “other Act”), then, on the coming into force of that section 10, paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition “offence” in section 183 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 108 of the other Act, is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xxvii):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xxvii.1)</Label><Text>section 162 (voyeurism),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, other than section 28, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>