<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-8</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Financial Administration Act, the Canada School of Public Service Act and the Official Languages Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">An Act to amend the Financial Administration Act, the Canada School of Public Service Act and the Official Languages Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Financial Administration, Canada School of Public Service and Official Languages</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>15</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2004-10-4">90275</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> to establish the office of the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada and to provide that the President of the Treasury Board is responsible for the coordination of the activities of the Secretary of the Treasury Board, the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada and the Comptroller General of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada School of Public Service Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> to refer to the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><?Pub Caret?><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may appoint an officer called the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada to hold office during pleasure, which officer ranks as and has the powers of a deputy head of a department.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation to President of Agency</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>The Treasury Board may, subject to any terms and conditions that it considers appropriate, delegate to the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any of the powers or functions in relation to human resources management, official languages, employment equity, and values and ethics that it is authorized to exercise under any Act of Parliament or by any order made by the Governor in Council; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any of the powers or functions in relation to employment that it is authorized to exercise under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>President of the Treasury Board to coordinate activities</MarginalNote><Label>(3.2)</Label><Text>The President of the Treasury Board is responsible for the coordination of the activities of the Secretary of the Treasury Board, the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada and the Comptroller General of Canada and may, subject to any terms and conditions that the President of the Treasury Board considers appropriate, delegate that responsibility to the Secretary of the Treasury Board or to any person under the President of the Treasury Board’s jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 16; 2003, c. 22, s. 22</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA SCHOOL OF PUBLIC SERVICE ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22, s. 28</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Subsection 10(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada School of Public Service Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><Language xml:lang="la">Ex officio</Language> governors</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Secretary of the Treasury Board, the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada and the President of the School are <Language xml:lang="la">ex officio</Language> governors.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 31 (4th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>OFFICIAL LANGUAGES ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Section 47 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Audit reports to be made available to Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Text>The President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada shall provide the Commissioner with any audit reports that are prepared pursuant to paragraph 46(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>If section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal> comes into force before the day on which section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force, then, on the later of the day on which this Act receives Royal Assent and the day on which that section 5 comes into force, section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> of this Act is repealed and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended as follows:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 6 is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may appoint an officer called the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada to hold office during pleasure, which officer ranks as and has the powers of a deputy head of a department.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 6 is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation to President of Agency</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>The Treasury Board may, subject to any terms and conditions that it considers appropriate, delegate to the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any of the powers or functions in relation to human resources management, official languages, employment equity, and values and ethics that it is authorized to exercise under any Act of Parliament or by any order made by the Governor in Council; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any of the powers or functions in relation to employment that it is authorized to exercise under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>President of the Treasury Board to coordinate activities</MarginalNote><Label>(4.2)</Label><Text>The President of the Treasury Board is responsible and accountable for the coordination of the activities of the Secretary of the Treasury Board, the President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada and the Comptroller General of Canada and may, subject to any terms and conditions that the President of the Treasury Board considers appropriate, delegate that responsibility to the Secretary of the Treasury Board or to any person under the President of the Treasury Board’s jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 6(5) and (6) are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsections (4) and (4.1) do not apply in respect of the Treasury Board’s power to delegate under those subsections or to its power to make regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sub-delegation</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Any person to whom powers or functions are delegated under subsection (4) or (4.1) may, subject to and in accordance with the delegation, sub-delegate any of those powers or functions to any person under their jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>If section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal> comes into force after the day on which section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force, then, on the day on which that section 5 comes into force, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended in the manner and to the extent set out in paragraphs 4(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The person occupying the position of President of the Public Service Human Resources Management Agency of Canada on the day on which section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> comes into force or the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> operates according to its terms, as the case may be, is deemed, as of that day, to be appointed to that position under subsection 6(2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> and continues to occupy it until another person is appointed to that position under that subsection.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, other than sections <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>