<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-18</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Telefilm Canada Act and another Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Telefilm Canada Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Telefilm Canada</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>14</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment provides Telefilm Canada with a mandate to act in audio-visual industries including film, television and new media. It also provides the Corporation with the authority to act in the sound recording industry under agreements made with the Department of Canadian Heritage. The enactment also grants Telefilm Canada, for the purpose of carrying out its mandate, the powers of a natural person. Everything done by the Corporation before the coming into force of this enactment is deemed to be valid to the same extent as it would have been were it done after this enactment comes into force.</Text></Provision></Summary><?Pub Caret?><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-16; 2002, c. 17, s. 6</MarginalNote><TitleText>TELEFILM CANADA ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Canadian feature film</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Canadian feature film production</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>film activity</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>film-maker</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>film production</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>film technician</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Telefilm Canada Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Eligibility for membership</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>No person who has, directly or indirectly and individually or as a shareholder, partner or otherwise, any pecuniary interest in the audio-visual industry is eligible to be appointed or to hold office as a member of the Corporation.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The heading before section 10 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading><TitleText>MANDATE AND POWERS</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 25, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Section 10 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Mandate</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The mandate of the Corporation is to foster and promote the development of the audio-visual industry in Canada and to act in connection with agreements entered into under subsection (8).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>General capacity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of carrying out its mandate, the Corporation has the capacity, rights, powers and privileges of a natural person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Specific powers</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of subsection (2), the Corporation may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>invest in individual Canadian audio-visual productions in return for a share in the proceeds from those productions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make loans to producers of individual Canadian audio-visual productions and charge interest on those loans;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make awards for outstanding accomplishments in Canadian audio-visual productions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make grants to audio-visual industry professionals resident in Canada to assist them in improving their craft; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>advise and assist Canadian audio-visual producers in the distribution of their works and in the administrative functions of audio-visual production.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Borrowing</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Corporation shall not borrow money within the meaning of Part X of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> otherwise than from the Crown.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loan guarantees</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (4), the Corporation may, in accordance with terms and conditions approved by the Treasury Board and the Minister of Finance, guarantee loans for audio-visual productions and their distribution.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Canadian content, ownership, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, a “Canadian audio-visual production” is an audio-visual production in respect of which the Corporation has determined</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the completed production will, in the judgment of the Corporation, have a significant Canadian creative, artistic and technical content, and that arrangements have been made to ensure that the copyright in the completed production will be owned by an individual resident in Canada, by a corporation incorporated under the laws of Canada or a province or by any combination of owners described in this paragraph; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that provision has been made for the production under a co-production agreement entered into between Canada and another country.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Corporation not a partner</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Corporation shall not be regarded as a partner in any production in which it may invest, and its liability shall be limited to the amount of its investment in the production.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contribution agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The Corporation may enter into agreements with the Department of Canadian Her­itage for the provision of services or programs relating to the audio-visual or sound recording industries.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation and cooperation</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The Corporation shall, to the greatest possible extent consistent with the performance of its duties under this Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>carry out its mandate in the broader context of the policies of the Government of Canada with respect to culture; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>consult and cooperate with any departments, boards and agencies of the Government of Canada and the governments of the provinces that have a mandate related to the mandate of the Corporation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 25, s. 2(1)</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 19(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amounts to be charged to Account</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All amounts required for the purposes of paragraphs 10(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and subsection 10(5) shall be paid</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 25, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 19(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>proceeds from any production in which the Corporation has invested under paragraph 10(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the principal amount of or interest on any loan made by the Corporation under paragraph 10(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fees charged by the Corporation in respect of loan guarantees provided under subsection 10(5).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Paragraph 20(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the purposes of paragraphs 10(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Section 21 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 21(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 90 to 93, subsection 94(2) and sections 95, 99, 100 and 102 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> apply, with any necessary modifications, to the Corporation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENT TO FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 11, s. 6(1), c. 34, par. 16(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)(E); 2002, c. 17, par. 14(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>Subsection 85(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Exempted Crown corporations</MarginalNote><Label>85.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Divisions I to IV do not apply to the Bank of Canada, the Canada Council for the Arts, the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board, the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, the International Development Research Centre or the National Arts Centre Corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption for Telefilm Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection 21(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Telefilm Canada Act</XRefExternal>, Divisions I to IV do not apply to Telefilm Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Validation</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>Everything done by Telefilm Canada before the coming into force of this Act is valid to the same extent as it would have been were it done after that coming into force.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>