<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-14</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to give effect to a land claims and self-government agreement among the Tlicho, the Government of the Northwest Territories and the Government of Canada, to make related amendments to the Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>2</MM><DD>15</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><?Pub Caret1?><AnnualStatuteNumber>1</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment gives effect to the Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Agreement and the Tlicho Tax Treatment Agreement. It includes related amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal> and consequential amendments to a number of other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>WHEREAS the Tlicho is an aboriginal people of Canada that has used and occupied lands in and adjacent to the Northwest Territories from time immemorial;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS the Tlicho, as represented by the Dogrib Treaty 11 Council, the Government of the Northwest Territories and the Government of Canada negotiated a land claims and self-government agreement in order to define and provide certainty in respect of rights of the Tlicho relating to lands, resources and self-government;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS the Tlicho, by a vote held on June 26 and 27, 2003, approved the agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS the Tlicho, as represented by the Dogrib Treaty 11 Council, the Government of the Northwest Territories and the Government of Canada signed the agreement on August 25, 2003;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>WHEREAS on October 10, 2003 the Commissioner in Council of the Northwest Territories made an ordinance entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Agreement Act</XRefExternal> approving the agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>AND WHEREAS the agreement provides that the agreement will be a land claims agreement within the meaning of section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> and that approval by Parliament is a condition precedent to the validity of the agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Preamble></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Accord</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Land Claims and Self-Government Agreement among the Tlicho, the Government of the Northwest Territories and the Government of Canada, signed on August 25, 2003, including any amendments made to it from time to time.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tax Treatment Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord sur le traitement fiscal</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tax Treatment Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Tlicho Tax Treatment Agreement among the Government of Canada, the Government of the Northwest Territories and the Tlicho First Nation, signed on behalf of the Government of Canada on February 6, 2003, on behalf of the Government of the Northwest Territories on February 27, 2003 and on behalf of the Tlicho First Nation on March 3, 2003, including any amendments made to it from time to time.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho Government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>gouvernement tlicho</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho Government</DefinedTermEn> means the government of the Tlicho First Nation established in accord­ance with chapter 7 of the Agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho law</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>loi tlicho</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho law</DefinedTermEn> means a law enacted by the Tlicho Government.</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>AGREEMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement given effect</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, any person or body may exercise the powers, rights, privileges and benefits conferred on the person or body by the Agreement and shall perform the duties, and is subject to the liabilities, imposed on the person or body by the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement binding</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Agreement is binding on, and may be relied on by, all persons and bodies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Publication of Agreement and amendments</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development shall cause a copy of the Agreement and of any amendments made to it to be deposited in</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Library of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the library of the Legislative Assembly of the Northwest Territories;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the main office of the Tlicho Government;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the library of the Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development that is situated in the National Capital Region;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the office of the Registrar of Land Titles for the Northwest Territories;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the regional office of the Department of Indian Affairs and Northern Development that is situated in the Northwest Territories; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other places that that Minister considers necessary.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OTHER LAWS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Conflict between the Agreement or this Act and other legislation</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency or conflict between the Agreement or this Act, or any regulations made under this Act, and the provisions of any other Act of Parliament, any ordinance of the Northwest Territories, any regulations made under any of those other Acts or ordinances, or any Tlicho law, then the Agreement or this Act, or regulations made under this Act, as the case may be, prevail to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conflict between the Agreement and this Act</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency or conflict between the Agreement and the provisions of this Act or any regulations made under this Act, the Agreement prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>APPROPRIATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>There shall be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund any sums that are required to meet the monetary obligations of Canada under chapters 9, 18 and 24 to 26 of the Agreement.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TAXATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tax Treatment Agreement given effect</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Tax Treatment Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law during the period that it is in effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not a treaty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tax Treatment Agreement does not form part of the Agreement and is not a treaty or a land claims agreement within the meaning of section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>WEKEEZHII RENEWABLE RESOURCES BOARD</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Legal capacity</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>For the purposes of carrying out its objectives, the Wekeezhii Renewable Resources Board established by chapter 12 of the Agreement has the capacity, rights, powers and privileges of a natural person.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>GENERAL</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice of Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice shall be taken of the Agreement and the Tax Treatment Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agreement and the Tax Treatment Agreement shall be published by the Queen’s Printer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A copy of the Agreement or the Tax Treatment Agreement published by the Queen’s Printer is evidence of that Agreement, and a copy purporting to be published by the Queen’s Printer is deemed to be so published, unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice of Tlicho laws</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice shall be taken of Tlicho laws.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence of Tlicho laws</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A copy of a Tlicho law purporting to be deposited in the public registry of Tlicho laws referred to in chapter 7 of the Agreement is evidence of that law and of its contents, unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, Tlicho laws are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make any orders and regulations that are necessary for the purpose of carrying out the Agreement or the Tax Treatment Agreement.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Eligibility Committee</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Despite having been established before the effective date of the Agreement, the Eligibility Committee referred to in chapter 3 of the Agreement is deemed to have been validly established under the Agreement and to have had, since it was established, the jurisdiction, powers and authority provided by the Agreement.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of issues arising</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in any judicial or administrative proceeding, an issue arises in respect of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the interpretation, validity or applicability of the Agreement, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the validity or applicability of this Act, the ordinance of the Northwest Territories entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Agreement Act</XRefExternal> or any Tlicho law,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>the issue shall not be decided until the party raising the issue has served notice on the Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of the Northwest Territories and the Tlicho Government.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content of notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The notice must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>describe the judicial or administrative proceeding in which the issue arises;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>state whether the issue arises in respect of the matters referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or both;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>state the day on which the issue is to be argued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>give particulars necessary to show the point to be argued; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>be served at least 14 days before the day of argument, unless the court or tribunal authorizes a shorter period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Participation in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In any judicial or administrative proceeding to which subsection (1) applies, the Attorney General of Canada, the Attorney General of the Northwest Territories and the Tlicho Government may appear and participate in the proceeding as parties with the same rights as any other party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Saving</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsections (2) and (3) do not require that an oral hearing be held if one is not otherwise required.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 25</MarginalNote><TitleText>AMENDMENTS TO THE MACKENZIE VALLEY RESOURCE MANAGEMENT ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>first nation</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>land claim agreement</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>local government</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>settlement area</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>settlement lands</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>first nation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>première nation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>first nation</DefinedTermEn> means the Gwich’in First Nation, the Sahtu First Nation or bodies representing other Dene or Metis of the North Slave, South Slave or Deh Cho region of the Mackenzie Valley, but does not include the Tlicho First Nation or the Tlicho Government.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>land claim agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord de revendication</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>land claim agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Gwich’in Agreement, the Sahtu Agreement or the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>local government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>administration locale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>local government</DefinedTermEn> means any local government established under the laws of the Northwest Territories, including a city, town, village, hamlet, charter community, settlement or government of a Tlicho community, whether incorporated or not, and includes the territorial government acting in the place of a local government pursuant to those laws.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>settlement area</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>région désignée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>settlement area</DefinedTermEn> means the area described in appendix A to the Gwich’in Agreement or in appendix A to the Sahtu Agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>settlement lands</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>terres désignées</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>settlement lands</DefinedTermEn> means lands referred to as settlement lands in the Gwich’in Agreement or the Sahtu Agreement.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Monfwi Gogha De Niitlee</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Monfwi gogha de niitlee</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Monfwi Gogha De Niitlee</DefinedTermEn> means the area described in part 1 of the appendix to chapter 1 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>territorial law</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>règle de droit territoriale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>territorial law</DefinedTermEn> means an ordinance of the Northwest Territories and any regulations made under such an ordinance.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho Agreement</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>accord tlicho</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Land Claims and Self-Government Agreement among the Tlicho, the Government of the Northwest Territories and the Government of Canada, signed on August 25, 2003 and approved, given effect and declared valid by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, as that Agreement is amended from time to time in accordance with its provisions.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho citizen</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>citoyen tlicho</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho citizen</DefinedTermEn> means a person whose name is on the Register as defined in chapter 1 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho community</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>collectivité tlicho</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho community</DefinedTermEn> means a community for which a community government is established in accordance with chapter 8 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho First Nation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>première nation tlicho</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho First Nation</DefinedTermEn> means the aboriginal people of Canada to whom section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> applies, consisting of all Tlicho citizens.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho Government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>gouvernement tlicho</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho Government</DefinedTermEn> means the government of the Tlicho First Nation established in accord­ance with chapter 7 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho lands</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>terres tlichos</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho lands</DefinedTermEn> means Tlicho lands as defined in chapter 1 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho law</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>loi tlicho</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Tlicho law</DefinedTermEn> means a law enacted by the Tlicho Government.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Wekeezhii</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Wekeezhii</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Wekeezhii</DefinedTermEn> means the area described in part 2 of the appendix to chapter 1 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Text>Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation by Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Tlicho Government may, in conformity with the Tlicho Agreement, delegate any of its functions under this Act to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a body or office established by a Tlicho law;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any department, agency or office of the federal or the territorial government;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a board or other public body established by or under an Act of Parliament or by a territorial law; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a local government.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 5:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement between Tlicho Government and another aboriginal people</MarginalNote><Label>5.1</Label><Text>The rights of the Tlicho First Nation, Tlicho citizens and the Tlicho Government under this Act are subject to the provisions of any agreement entered into between the Tlicho Government and an aboriginal people, other than the Tlicho First Nation, under 2.7.3 of chapter 2 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>Subsection 8(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The federal Minister shall consult the first nations and the Tlicho Government with respect to the amendment of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 11(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment of members by federal Minister</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The members of a board — other than the chairperson, any members appointed pursuant to a determination under section 15 and any members appointed by the Tlicho Government under subsection 57.1(2) or in accordance with an agreement referred to in that subsection — shall be appointed by the federal Minister in accordance with Parts 2 to 5.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 11(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Alternate members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except in the case of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board, the federal Minister may appoint</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>Subsections 12(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except in the case of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board, the chairperson of a board shall be appointed by the federal Minister from persons nominated by a majority of the members.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment by federal Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except in the case of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board, if a majority of the members does not nominate a person acceptable to the federal Minister within a reasonable time, the Minister may appoint any person as chairperson of the board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Wekeezhii Land and Water Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The chairperson of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board shall be appointed jointly by the federal Minister and the Tlicho Government on the nomination of the members of the Board other than the chairperson.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Subsection 14(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal by federal Minister after consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A member who has been appointed by the federal Minister may not be removed from office except after consultation by the federal Minister with the board and, where applicable, with the territorial Minister, the first nation or the Tlicho Government that nominated the member.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal by Tlicho Government after consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A member of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board who has been appointed by the Tlicho Government may not be removed from office except after consultation by the Tlicho Government with the Board and the federal Minister.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Section 15 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Implementation of right of representation of other aboriginal peoples</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>Despite any provision of this Act respecting members of a board, if an aboriginal people has a right under a land claim agreement to representation on that board in relation to a decision of the board that might affect an area used by that aboriginal people that is outside the board’s area of jurisdiction, the board shall, in accordance with that land claim agreement, determine how to implement that right.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>Subsection 16(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Status or entitlements under agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A member of a board is not placed in a material conflict of interest merely because of any status or entitlement conferred on the member under the Gwich’in Agreement, the Sahtu Agreement, the Tlicho Agreement or any other agreement between a first nation and Her Majesty in right of Canada for the settlement of a claim to lands.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Subsection 17(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Members of a board, other than any members appointed pursuant to a determination under section 15, shall be paid such fees or other remuneration as the federal Minister may fix.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Text>Section 22 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Government information</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>Subject to any other federal or territorial law and to any Tlicho law, a board may obtain from any department or agency of the federal or territorial government or the Tlicho Government any information in the possession of the department or agency or the Tlicho Government that the board requires for the performance of its functions.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>Section 24 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Hearings</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>In addition to hearings that a board is authorized or required to hold under this Act, a board may conduct any hearings that it considers to be desirable for the purpose of carrying out any of its functions.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Coordination</MarginalNote><Label>24.1</Label><Text>A board shall coordinate its activities, including hearings, with the activities of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>other boards;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>departments and agencies of the federal government that have responsibility for the administration, management and control of parks to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> applies or lands acquired pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>committees established under any of the land claim agreements for the management of parks to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> applies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>committees, or similar bodies, established for the management of protected areas as defined in any of the land claim agreements;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>renewable resources boards established under any of the land claim agreements; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>land use planning bodies established for Wekeezhii or any part of Wekeezhii.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 31(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 3, 5 and 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> do not apply in respect of rules under section 30, a land use plan or amendment thereto under Part 2, rules under subsection 49(2), guidelines or policies under section 65, policy directions under subsection 83(1) or (2), directions under section 106, policy directions under section 109 or 109.1 or guidelines under section 120.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 31 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, permits issued by a board under Part 3 or 4 either before or after the coming into force of this subsection are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 8, par. 182(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">x</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>Section 32 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Jurisdiction of Courts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Concurrent jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding the exclusive jurisdiction referred to in section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>, the Attorney General of Canada or anyone directly affected by the matter in respect of which relief is sought may make an application to the Supreme Court of the Northwest Territories for any relief against a board by way of an injunction or declaration or by way of an order in the nature of <Emphasis style="italic">certiorari</Emphasis>, <Emphasis style="italic">mandamus</Emphasis>, <Emphasis style="italic">quo warranto</Emphasis> or prohibition.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exclusive original jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1) and section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>, the Supreme Court of the Northwest Territories has exclusive original jurisdiction to hear and determine any action or proceeding, whether or not by way of an application of a type referred to in subsection (1), concerning the jurisdiction of the Mackenzie Valley Land and Water Board or the Mackenzie Valley Environmental Impact Review Board.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>board</DefinedTermEn> in section 51 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>board</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>office</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>board</DefinedTermEn> means the Gwich’in Land and Water Board, the Sahtu Land and Water Board or the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board established by sections 54, 56 and 57.1, respectively.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 51 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>management area</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>zone de gestion</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>management area</DefinedTermEn> means an area in respect of which a board has been established, namely,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of the Gwich’in Land and Water Board, the area described in appendix A to the Gwich’in Agreement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of the Sahtu Land and Water Board, the area described in appendix A to the Sahtu Agreement; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board, Wekeezhii.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 32, s. 53</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 52(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>National parks and historic sites</MarginalNote><Label>52.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Part, except sections 78, 79, 79.2 and 79.3, does not apply in respect of the use of land or waters or the deposit of waste within a park to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> applies or within lands acquired pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), an authority responsible for authorizing uses of land or waters or deposits of waste in a portion of a management area excluded by that subsection from the application of this Part shall consult the board established for that management area before authorizing any such use or deposit.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 52(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with authority</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A board shall consult a responsible authority referred to in subsection (2) before issuing a licence, permit or authorization for a use of land or waters or deposit of waste that may have an effect in the portion of the management area in which the authority is responsible.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 57:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Wekeezhii Land and Water Board</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Board established</MarginalNote><Label>57.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There is hereby established, in respect of Wekeezhii, a board to be known as the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Membership</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Board shall consist of five members including, apart from the chairperson, two members who, subject to any agreement between the Tlicho Government and an aboriginal people of Canada to whom section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> applies, other than the Tlicho First Nation, are appointed by the Tlicho Government and one member who is appointed on the nomination of the territorial Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The federal Minister and the Tlicho Government shall consult each other before making their appointments.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Quorum</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A quorum of the Board consists of three members, or any larger number that is determined by the Board, including one of the members appointed by the Tlicho Government or in accordance with any agreement referred to in subsection (2) and one of the members appointed by the federal Minister, other than the chairperson.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Main office</MarginalNote><Label>57.2</Label><Text>The main office of the Board shall be located in Wekeezhii.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Text>Section 58 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives — Gwich’in and Sahtu Land and Water Boards</MarginalNote><Label>58.</Label><Text>The Gwich’in Land and Water Board and the Sahtu Land and Water Board shall regulate the use of land and waters and the deposit of waste so as to provide for the conservation, development and utilization of land and water resources in a manner that will provide the optimum benefit for residents of their respective management areas and of the Mackenzie Valley and for all Canadians.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives — Wekeezhii Land and Water Board</MarginalNote><Label>58.1</Label><Text>The Wekeezhii Land and Water Board shall regulate the use of land and waters and the deposit of waste so as to provide for the conservation, development and utilization of land and water resources in a manner that will provide the optimum benefit generally for all Canadians and in particular for residents of its management area.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33.</Label><Text>Subsection 59(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction — land</MarginalNote><Label>59.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A board has jurisdiction in respect of all uses of land in its management area for which a permit is required under this Part and may, in accordance with the regulations, issue, amend, renew, suspend and cancel permits and authorizations for the use of land, and approve the assignment of permits.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 60(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction — water and waste</MarginalNote><Label>60.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A board has jurisdiction in respect of all uses of waters and deposits of waste in its management area for which a licence is required under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> and may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>issue, amend, renew and cancel licences and approve the assignment of licences, in accordance with that Act, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>exercise any other power of the Northwest Territories Water Board under that Act,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>and, for those purposes, references in that Act to that Board shall be read as references to the board.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 15, par. 48(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 60(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect outside management area</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In respect of a use of waters or deposit of waste in a management area that has an effect in a region of the Northwest Territories or Nunavut outside the management area, subsections 14(4) and (5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> apply in relation to the protection of the rights of licensees and other persons referred to in those subsections who are in such a region.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 60(4) and (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> do not apply in respect of a management area, namely, sections 10 to 13, subsection 14(6), sections 20 and 22, paragraphs 23(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), section 24, section 26 except in relation to type A licences under that Act, sections 27 and 28 and subsection 37(2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (1), section 31 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> does not apply in respect of first nation lands or Tlicho lands.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35.</Label><Text>Section 61 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Considerations</MarginalNote><Label>60.1</Label><Text>In exercising its powers, a board shall consider</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the importance of conservation to the well-being and way of life of the aboriginal peoples of Canada to whom section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> applies and who use an area of the Mackenzie Valley; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any traditional knowledge and scientific information that is made available to it.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conformity with land use plan — Gwich’in and Sahtu Boards</MarginalNote><Label>61.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Gwich’in Land and Water Board and the Sahtu Land and Water Board may not issue, amend or renew a licence, permit or authorization except in accordance with an applicable land use plan under Part 2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conformity with land use plan — Wekeezhii Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Wekeezhii Land and Water Board may not issue, amend or renew a licence, permit or authorization except in accordance with any land use plan, established under a federal, territorial or Tlicho law, that is applicable to any part of its management area.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conformity with Tlicho laws — Wekeezhii Board</MarginalNote><Label>61.1</Label><Text>The Wekeezhii Land and Water Board may not exercise its discretionary powers relating to the use of Tlicho lands except in accordance with any Tlicho laws enacted under 7.4.2 of chapter 7 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36.</Label><Text>Subsection 63(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of applications</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A board shall notify affected communities and first nations of an application made to the board for a licence, permit or authorization and allow a reasonable period of time for them to make representations to the board with respect to the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Wekeezhii Land and Water Board shall notify the Tlicho Government of an application made to the Board for a licence, permit or authorization and allow a reasonable period of time for it to make representations to the Board with respect to the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Wekeezhii Land and Water Board shall consult the Tlicho Government before issuing, amending or renewing any licence, permit or authorization for a use of Tlicho lands or waters on those lands or a deposit of waste on those lands or in those waters.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 64(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Heritage resources</MarginalNote><Label>64.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A board shall seek and consider the advice of any affected first nation and, in the case of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board, the Tlicho Government and any appropriate department or agency of the federal or territorial government respecting the presence of heritage resources that might be affected by a use of land or waters or a deposit of waste proposed in an application for a licence or permit.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 64(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Wildlife resources</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A board shall seek and consider the advice of the renewable resources board established by the land claim agreement applicable in its management area respecting the presence of wildlife and wildlife habitat that might be affected by a use of land or waters or a deposit of waste proposed in an application for a licence or permit.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38.</Label><Text>Section 68 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39.</Label><Text>Section 73 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 73(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Wildlife harvesting and traditional use — Tlicho citizens</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite sections 8 and 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> — and subject to any applicable Tlicho laws and, in relation to waters that are on settlement lands, any limitations under the applicable land claim agreement that are of the same type as those that apply in relation to waters on Tlicho lands — Tlicho citizens have the right to use water in the part of Monfwi Gogha De Niitlee that is in the Northwest Territories without a licence, for purposes of wildlife harvesting under 10.1.1 of chapter 10 of the Tlicho Agreement, for purposes of transportation related to such wildlife harvesting and for heritage, cultural or spiritual purposes of the Tlicho First Nation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40.</Label><Text>The portion of section 76 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Issuance, amendment or renewal of licences, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>76.</Label><Text>The Gwich’in Land and Water Board or the Sahtu Land and Water Board may issue, amend or renew a licence, permit or authorization where the use of land or waters or the deposit of waste proposed by the applicant would, in the opinion of the board, interfere with a first nation’s rights under section 75, if the board is satisfied that</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41.</Label><Text>Section 77 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Compensation — Gwich’in and Sahtu First Nations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Conditions for licence</MarginalNote><Label>77.</Label><Text>The Gwich’in Land and Water Board or the Sahtu Land and Water Board may not issue, amend or renew a licence pursuant to section 76 unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant and the first nation enter into an agreement to compensate the first nation for any loss or damage resulting from any substantial alteration to the quality, quantity or rate of flow of waters when on or flowing through its first nation lands, or waters adjacent to its first nation lands; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant or the first nation applies to the board for a determination pursuant to subsection 79(1).</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 15, par. 48(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>); 2000, c. 32, s. 54</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Text>Subsection 78(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Application to water authority</MarginalNote><Label>78.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Gwich’in Land and Water Board or the Sahtu Land and Water Board determines that a use of waters or a deposit of waste that is proposed, in an application made to a water authority, to be carried out in</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an area of the Northwest Territories or Nunavut outside the board’s management area, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a park to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> applies, or lands acquired pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal>, in the board’s management area</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>would be likely to substantially alter the quality, quantity or rate of flow of waters when on or flowing through first nation lands of the Gwich’in or Sahtu First Nation or waters adjacent to those first nation lands, the board shall notify the water authority in writing of its determination.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 79(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Referral of compensation to Board</MarginalNote><Label>79.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a compensation agreement referred to in section 77 or 78 is not entered into within the period allowed by the rules of the Gwich’in Land and Water Board or the Sahtu Land and Water Board, as the case may be, the applicant or the first nation may apply to the board for a determination of compensation.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 79(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the first nation’s use of waters when on or flowing through its first nation lands or waters adjacent to its first nation lands, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 79:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Compensation — Tlicho First Nation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Conditions for licence</MarginalNote><Label>79.1</Label><Text>The Wekeezhii Land and Water Board may not issue, amend or renew a licence for the use of waters or the deposit of waste if, in its opinion, that use or deposit is likely to substantially alter the quality, quantity or rate of flow of waters when on or flowing through Tlicho lands or waters adjacent to Tlicho lands unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Board is satisfied that there is no alternative that could reasonably satisfy the requirements of the applicant and that there are no reasonable measures by which the applicant could avoid the alteration; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant has entered into an agreement with the Tlicho Government to compensate the Tlicho First Nation for any loss or damage that may be caused by the alteration, or the applicant or the Tlicho Government has applied to the Board under subsection 79.3(1) for a determination of compensation for that loss or damage.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application to water authority</MarginalNote><Label>79.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board determines that a use of waters or a deposit of waste that is proposed, in an application made to a water authority, to be carried out in</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Nunavut or an area of the Northwest Territories outside Wekeezhii, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a park to which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> applies, or lands acquired pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal>, in Wekeezhii</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>would be likely to substantially alter the quality, quantity or rate of flow of waters when on or flowing through Tlicho lands or waters adjacent to Tlicho lands, the Board shall notify the water authority in writing of its determination.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Access to information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A water authority shall provide the Board with any information in its possession that the Board requires in order to make a determination under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act, a water authority that is notified by the Board under subsection (1) may not authorize the proposed use of waters or deposit of waste unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant and the Tlicho Government have entered into an agreement to compensate the Tlicho First Nation for any loss or damage that may be caused by the alteration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the applicant or the Tlicho Government applies to the Board under subsection 79.3(1) for a determination.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Referral of compensation to Wekeezhii Board</MarginalNote><Label>79.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a compensation agreement referred to in paragraph 79.1(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or 79.2(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), as the case may be, is not entered into, the applicant or the Tlicho Government may, after having participated in mediation under chapter 6 of the Tlicho Agreement, apply to the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board for a determination of compensation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of compensation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On an application under subsection (1), the Board shall determine the compensation payable in respect of the proposed use of waters or deposit of waste, taking into consideration</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the effect of the proposed use or deposit on</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the use by Tlicho citizens of waters when on or flowing through Tlicho lands, or waters adjacent to Tlicho lands,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Tlicho lands, taking into account any cultural or special value of those lands to the Tlicho First Nation, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>wildlife harvesting carried on by Tlicho citizens;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the nuisance or inconvenience, including noise, caused by the proposed use or deposit to Tlicho citizens on Tlicho lands; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other factor that the Board considers relevant in the circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Form of compensation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The compensation may be in the form of a lump sum payment or periodic payments or non-monetary compensation, including replacement of, or substitution for, damaged or lost property or relocation of Tlicho citizens or their property, or any combination of those forms of compensation.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 80(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation de fournir les matériaux — premières nations des Gwich’in et du Sahtu</MarginalNote><Label>80.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Les premières nations des Gwich’in ou du Sahtu sont tenues, sur demande, de fournir aux ministères et organismes des gouvernements fédéral et territorial ou à toute personne les matériaux de construction — sable, gravier, argile et autres — se trouvant sur leurs terres, et d’y donner accès, dans les cas où il n’existe aucune autre source d’approvisionnement accessible, sans difficulté excessive, dans la région avoisinante.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 80(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reference to Board</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On application by the person or department or agency requesting the supply or access, the Gwich’in Land and Water Board or the Sahtu Land and Water Board, as the case may be, shall</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 80:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to supply — Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>80.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Tlicho Government shall supply, and permit access to, sand, gravel, clay and like construction materials situated on Tlicho lands to any person that requests it, including any department or agency of the federal or territorial government or any local government of a Tlicho community.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply if the materials are to be used on lands other than Tlicho lands, unless no alternate source of supply is reasonably available in an area closer to the lands where the materials are to be used.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compensation — Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Tlicho Government is entitled to be paid for the value of materials supplied under subsection (1) and for the exercise of a right of access to the materials under that subsection, unless the materials are to be used for a public purpose on Tlicho lands or in a Tlicho community or for a public road contiguous to Tlicho lands or to a Tlicho community.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reference to Wekeezhii Land and Water Board</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On application by any person, department, agency or government requesting the supply of, or access to, materials under subsection (1) and after the applicant has participated in mediation under chapter 6 of the Tlicho Agreement, the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>determine, for the purpose of subsection (2), whether an alternate source of supply is reasonably available in an area closer to the lands where the materials are to be used;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>determine, for the purpose of subsection (3), whether the materials are to be used for a public purpose on Tlicho lands or in a Tlicho community or for a public road contiguous to Tlicho lands or a Tlicho community;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>resolve any dispute concerning terms or conditions of supply or access, excluding the amount to be paid under subsection (3); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>resolve any dispute concerning conflicting uses of materials referred to in subsection (1) by the applicant and by the Tlicho Government or Tlicho citizens.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reference to Board by Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In the case of a dispute referred to in paragraph (4)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), an application for its resolution may also be made to the Board by the Tlicho Government after it has participated in mediation under chapter 6 of the Tlicho Agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47.</Label><Text>Sections 82 and 83 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation with first nations and Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>82.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The federal Minister shall consult the Gwich’in and Sahtu First Nations and the Tlicho Government with respect to the amendment of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> or regulations made under that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with boards</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The federal Minister shall consult the boards with respect to the amendment of this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> or the making or amendment of any instrument pursuant to this Act or that Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Policy Directions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Minister’s policy directions to board</MarginalNote><Label>83.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The federal Minister may, after consultation with a board, give written policy directions binding on the board with respect to the exercise of any of its functions under this Part. The federal Minister shall also consult the Tlicho Government before giving such written policy directions to the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Policy directions by the Tlicho Government to the Wekeezhii Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tlicho Government may, after consultation with the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board and the federal Minister, give written policy directions with respect to the exercise of any of its functions under this Part in relation to the use of Tlicho lands. Policy directions shall be binding on the Board to the extent that compliance with them does not require the Board to exceed its approved budget.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Except as provided by subsection (4), policy directions do not apply in respect of any application that, at the time the directions are given, is pending before a board or has been approved by a board and is awaiting approval under section 81.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Policy directions apply in respect of an application referred to in subsection (3) if their non-application could result in the inconsistency of a licence, permit or authorization with another Act or with a regulation or order made under another Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conflict between policy directions</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If there is a conflict between policy directions given by the federal Minister under subsection (1) and policy directions given by the Tlicho Government under subsection (2), the policy directions given under subsection (2) prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conflict between legislation and policy directions</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If there is a conflict between policy directions given by the federal Minister or the Tlicho Government under this section and the provisions of any Act of Parliament, any regulations made under an Act of Parliament or any territorial law, those provisions prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48.</Label><Text>Section 85 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>An inspector shall, if it is reasonable to do so, give the Tlicho Government prior notice of entry by the inspector on Tlicho lands.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49.</Label><Text>Section 89 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Tlicho Government by water inspector</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>An inspector designated under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> shall, if it is reasonable to do so, give the Tlicho Government prior notice of entry on Tlicho lands.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50.</Label><Text>The portion of section 90 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations respecting the use of land</MarginalNote><Label>90.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, following consultation by the federal Minister with first nations and the Tlicho Government, make regulations respecting the protection, control and use of lands in the Mackenzie Valley and, in particular, may make regulations</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 90:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Prohibition — Tlicho lands</MarginalNote><Label>90.1</Label><Text>Even if the regulations do not require a permit or authorization under Part 3 or 4 for a particular use of land, no person shall use Tlicho lands without such a permit or authorization if one is required by a Tlicho law for uses of that type.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exemption for use of land in Tlicho communities</MarginalNote><Label>90.2</Label><Text>Despite the regulations, a permit or authorization under Part 3 or 4 for a particular use of land in a Tlicho community is not required if the local government of that community has enacted a bylaw providing that one is not required for uses of that type.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52.</Label><Text>Paragraph 91(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the determination of matters in dispute under section 80 or 80.1.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>53.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 92(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Principal offences</MarginalNote><Label>92.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes section 90.1, any provision of the regulations, any condition of a permit or an order of an inspector under subsection 86(1) or (2) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding $15,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or to both.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 92(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reparation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In addition to the penalty provided by subsection (1), a court that convicts a person of using land without a permit may, taking into account the nature of the offence and the circumstances of its commission, order the person to take any measures that it considers reasonable in order to repair or limit any damage resulting from the act or omission that constituted the offence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>54.</Label><Text>Section 95 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Fees</MarginalNote><Label>95.</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection 14(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal>, the Gwich’in and Sahtu First Nations and the Tlicho Government are not required to pay any fee in respect of the use of waters or the deposit of waste for non-commercial purposes on their first nation lands or Tlicho lands, as the case may be.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>55.</Label><Text>Subsections 96(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms defined in Part 3</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this Part, the expressions <DefinedTermEn>first nation lands</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>land</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>management area</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>waters</DefinedTermEn> have the same meaning as in Part 3.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of <DefinedTermEn>permit</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Part, references to a permit in section 90, in the regulations made pursuant to that section and in sections 90.1, 90.2 and 92 include a permit as defined in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>56.</Label><Text>Subsections 99(2) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regional panels — Gwich’in and Sahtu Boards</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the coming into force of this Part, a board established by section 54 or 56 continues as a regional panel of the Board under the same name and in respect of the same management area as that of the board. Its members become members of the Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regional panel — Wekeezhii Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Six months after the coming into force of section 57.1, the board established by that section continues as a regional panel of the Board under the same name and in respect of the same management area as that of the board. Its members become members of the Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Applicable provisions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The provisions of Part 1 respecting the appointment, tenure and removal from office of members of a board and respecting the chairperson of a board, and the provisions of Part 3 respecting the appointment of members of a board, the quorum of a board and its main office, continue to apply to a regional panel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Composition</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In addition to the members of the regional panels referred to in subsections (2) and (2.1) and a chairperson, the Board shall, subject to subsection 108(7), consist of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>two members appointed following consultation by the federal Minister with the first nations and the Tlicho Government;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>one member appointed on the nomination of the territorial Minister; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>one other member.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>57.</Label><Text>The heading before section 102 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Heading><TitleText>Mission et compétence de l’Office</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>58.</Label><Text>Section 102 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Objectives — Board</MarginalNote><Label>101.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The objectives of the Board are to provide for the conservation, development and utilization of land and water resources in a manner that will provide the optimum benefit generally for all Canadians and in particular for residents of the Mackenzie Valley.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Objectives — Gwich’in and Sahtu regional panels</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The objectives of a regional panel referred to in subsection 99(2) are to provide for the conservation, development and utilization of land and water resources in a manner that will provide the optimum benefit for residents of its management area and of the Mackenzie Valley and for all Canadians.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Objectives — Wekeezhii regional panel</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The objectives of the regional panel referred to in subsection 99(2.1) are to provide for the conservation, development and utilization of land and water resources in a manner that will provide the optimum benefit generally for all Canadians and in particular for residents of its management area.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction — Board</MarginalNote><Label>102.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board has jurisdiction in respect of all uses of land or waters or deposits of waste in the Mackenzie Valley for which a permit is required under Part 3 or a licence is required under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal>, and for that purpose the Board has the powers and duties of a board established under Part 3, other than powers under sections 78, 79 and 79.2 to 80.1, as if a reference in that Part to a management area were a reference to the Mackenzie Valley, except that, with regard to subsection 61(2), the reference to management area continues to be a reference to Wekeezhii.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction — regional panels</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A regional panel of the Board shall exercise</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the powers and duties referred to in subsection (1) in respect of a use of land or waters or a deposit of waste that is to take place, and that is likely to have an impact, wholly within the management area of the regional panel; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the powers conferred by sections 78, 79 and 79.2 to 80.1 on the board established under Part 3 for that management area.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>59.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 103(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Applications to Board</MarginalNote><Label>103.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application shall be made to the Board where the application relates to a use of land or waters or a deposit of waste</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that is to take place, or is likely to have an impact, in more than one management area, or in a management area and an area outside any management area; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that is to take place wholly outside any management area.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 103(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Applications to regional panel</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An application relating to a use of land or waters or a deposit of waste described in subsection 102(2), including an application relating to a licence or permit for such a use or deposit issued pursuant to Part 3 before the coming into force of this Part, shall be made to the regional panel of the Board for the management area referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>60.</Label><Text>Section 104 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Power of chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>104.</Label><Text>Applications referred to in subsection 103(1) shall be disposed of by three or more members of the Board designated by the chairperson for that purpose, including at least one of the members appointed to a regional panel — on the nomination of a first nation or by the Tlicho Government — or appointed to the Board following consultation with first nations and the Tlicho Government and at least one of the members of the Board not so appointed.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>61.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 106:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Requirement to make recommendations</MarginalNote><Label>106.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board shall, at the request of the federal Minister, make recommendations to the federal Minister with respect to the amendment of this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> or the making or amendment of any instrument under this Act or that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Discretion to make recommendations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Board may make recommendations to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister responsible for any Act of Parliament regarding the use of land or waters or the deposit of waste, with respect to the amendment of that Act or the making or amendment of any instrument under that Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the territorial Minister with respect to the amendment of territorial laws regarding the use of land or waters or the deposit of waste;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a local government with respect to the amendment of bylaws enacted by that government regarding the use of land or waters or the deposit of waste; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government with respect to the amendment of Tlicho laws regarding the use of Tlicho lands or waters on those lands or a deposit of waste on those lands or in those waters.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>62.</Label><Text>Subsections 108(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of additional panels</MarginalNote><Label>108.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the federal Minister, establish up to two regional panels of the Board in addition to those referred to in subsections 99(2) and (2.1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The area of the Mackenzie Valley in which such a regional panel has jurisdiction shall be specified by the Governor in Council, following consultation with affected first nations, which area must be wholly outside any management area. Subsections 102(2) and 103(2) to (5) apply in relation to that area with such modifications as are required.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>63.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 109:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Powers of Tlicho Government</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Policy directions by the Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>109.1</Label><Text>The Tlicho Government may exercise the same powers and shall perform the same duties in relation to the Board and the regional panel of the Board referred to in subsection 99(2.1) as those that the Tlicho Government has under section 83 in relation to the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Precedence Relating to Policy Directions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Conflict between policy directions</MarginalNote><Label>109.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If there is a conflict between policy directions given by the federal Minister under section 109 and policy directions given by the Tlicho Government under section 109.1, the policy directions under section 109.1 prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conflict between legislation and policy directions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If there is a conflict between policy directions given by the federal Minister under section 109 or by the Tlicho Government under section 109.1 and the provisions of any Act of Parliament, any regulations made under an Act of Parliament or any territorial law, those provisions prevail to the extent of the conflict.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>64.</Label><Text>The heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Interpretation</Emphasis>” before section 111 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading><TitleText>Interpretation and Application</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>65.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 111 of the Act before the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated regulatory agency</DefinedTermEn> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>111.</Label><Text>(1) The following definitions apply in this Part.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 32, s. 55</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>development</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 111(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>development</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>projet de développement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>development</DefinedTermEn> means any undertaking, or any part or extension of an undertaking, that is carried out on land or water and includes an acquisition of lands pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal> and measures carried out by a department or agency of government leading to the establishment of a park subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> or the establishment of a park under a territorial law.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 111 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This Part applies in respect of developments to be carried out wholly or partly within the Mackenzie Valley and, except for section 142, does not apply in respect of developments wholly outside the Mackenzie Valley.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>66.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 112(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Nominations by first nations and the Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>One half of the members of the Review Board other than the chairperson shall be persons appointed on the nomination of first nations and the Tlicho Government, including at least one nominated by the Gwich’in First Nation, one nominated by the Sahtu First Nation and one nominated by the Tlicho Government.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 112(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Government members</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Of the members of the Review Board other than the chairperson and those appointed in accordance with subsection (2), at most one half shall be nominated by the territorial Minister.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 112(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Quorum</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A quorum of the Review Board consists of five members, including two of the members appointed in accordance with subsection (2) and two of the members not so appointed other than the chairperson.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>67.</Label><Text>Section 115 of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), by adding the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the importance of conservation to the well-being and way of life of the aboriginal peoples of Canada to whom section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal> applies and who use an area of the Mackenzie Valley.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>68.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 115:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Considerations</MarginalNote><Label>115.1</Label><Text>In exercising its powers, the Review Board shall consider any traditional knowledge and scientific information that is made available to it.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>69.</Label><Text>Paragraph 116(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>proposals that are the subject of agreements referred to in paragraph 141(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), to the extent provided by such agreements.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>70.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 117(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>where the development is likely to have a significant adverse impact on the environment, the need for mitigative or remedial measures; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 117 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Joint panels</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) and (3) apply in respect of an examination of a proposal for a development by a review panel, or a joint panel, established jointly by the Review Board and any other person or body.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>71.</Label><Text>Section 118 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Implementation of proposals</MarginalNote><Label>118.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No licence, permit or other authorization required for the carrying out of a development may be issued under any federal, territorial or Tlicho law unless the requirements of this Part have been complied with in relation to the development.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Implementation of proposals</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the Gwich’in or Sahtu First Nation, the Tlicho Government, a local government or a department or agency of the federal or territorial government proposes to carry out a development that does not require a licence, permit or other authorization under any federal, territorial or Tlicho law, it shall comply with the requirements of this Part before taking any irrevocable action in relation to the development.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>72.</Label><Text>The portion of section 120 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Guidelines</MarginalNote><Label>120.</Label><Text>Following consultation with first nations, the Tlicho Government and the federal and territorial Ministers and subject to any regulations made under paragraph 143(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the Review Board may establish guidelines respecting the process established by this Part, including guidelines</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>73.</Label><Text>Section 121 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Written reasons</MarginalNote><Label>121.</Label><Text>The Review Board, a review panel thereof, a review panel, or a joint panel, established jointly by the Review Board and any other person or body, the federal Minister, a responsible minister, a designated regulatory agency, a regulatory authority, a department or agency of the federal or territorial government, a local government, the Gwich’in or Sahtu First Nation or the Tlicho Government shall issue and make available to the public written reasons for any decision or recommendation made under the process established by this Part.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>74.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 123:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>123.1</Label><Text>In conducting a review or examination of the impact on the environment of a development, a review panel of the Review Board or a review panel, or a joint panel, established jointly by the Review Board and any other person or body,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall carry out any consultations that are required by any of the land claim agreements; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may carry out other consultations with any persons who use an area where the development might have an impact on the environment.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conflict of interest</MarginalNote><Label>123.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person shall not be appointed, or continue, as a member of a review panel of the Review Board or of a review panel, or a joint panel, established jointly by the Review Board and any other person or body, if doing so would place the member in a material conflict of interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Status or entitlements under agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person is not in a material conflict of interest merely because of any status or entitlement conferred on the person under the Gwich’in Agreement, the Sahtu Agreement, the Tlicho Agreement or any other agreement between a first nation and Her Majesty in right of Canada for the settlement of a claim to lands.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Nominations</MarginalNote><Label>123.3</Label><Text>In appointing a review panel of the Review Board or a review panel, or a joint panel, established jointly by the Review Board and any other person or body, the Review Board and those other persons or bodies shall comply with the requirements of land claim agreements respecting nominations for appointment.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>75.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 124(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proposal not requiring application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a development that does not require a licence, permit or other authorization under any federal or territorial law is proposed to be carried out by a department or agency of the federal or territorial government or by the Gwich’in or Sahtu First Nation or the Tlicho Government, the body proposing to carry out that development shall, after notifying the Review Board in writing of the proposal for the development, conduct a preliminary screening of the proposal, unless</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 124(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Preliminary screening by Gwich’in, Sahtu or Tlicho</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Gwich’in First Nation, the Sahtu First Nation or the Tlicho Government, as the case may be, may conduct a preliminary screening of a proposal for a development to determine whether to refer the proposal for an environmental assessment in accordance with paragraph 126(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cooperation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where more than one body conducts a preliminary screening in respect of a development, any of them may consult the others, adopt another’s report or participate in a joint preliminary screening and, where one of them is a board established under Part 3 or 4, the others are not required to conduct a preliminary screening.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>76.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 126(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Gwich’in or Sahtu First Nation, in the case of a development to be carried out in its settlement area or a development that might have an impact on the environment in that settlement area;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, in the case of a development to be carried out wholly or partly in the part of Monfwi Gogha De Niitlee that is in the Northwest Territories or a development that might have an impact on the environment in that part; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a local government, in the case of a development to be carried out within its boundaries or a development that might have an impact on the environment within its boundaries.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 126(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsections (2) and (3) apply even if a preliminary screening has not been commenced or, if commenced, has not been completed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>77.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 127:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>127.1</Label><Text>Before completing an environmental assessment of a proposal for a development that is to be carried out wholly or partly on first nation lands as defined in section 51 or on Tlicho lands, the Review Board shall consult the first nation on whose lands the development is to be carried out or, if the development is to be carried out on Tlicho lands, the Tlicho Government.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>78.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 128(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to ministers, agencies and Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Review Board shall make a report of an environmental assessment to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the federal Minister, who shall distribute it to every responsible minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any designated regulatory agency from which a licence, permit or other authorization is required for the carrying out of the development; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the development is to be carried out wholly or partly on Tlicho lands, the Tlicho Government.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 128(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copie</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>L’Office adresse une copie du rapport au promoteur du projet de développement, à l’organe en ayant effectué l’examen préalable et, en cas de renvoi effectué en vertu du paragraphe 126(2), au ministère, à l’organisme, à la première nation, au gouvernement tlicho ou à l’administration locale concernée.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>79.</Label><Text>Section 129 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Delay</MarginalNote><Label>129.</Label><Text>Where the Review Board makes a determination under paragraph 128(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a regulatory authority, a designated regulatory agency or the Tlicho Government shall not issue a licence, permit or other authorization for the development, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>where no licence, permit or authorization is required under any federal, territorial or Tlicho law for the development, the person or body that proposes to carry it out shall not proceed,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>before the expiration of ten days after receiving the report of the Review Board.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>80.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 130 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Before making an order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or a referral under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), the federal Minister and the responsible ministers shall consult the Tlicho Government if the development is to be carried out wholly or partly on Tlicho lands.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 130(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The federal Minister and responsible ministers shall carry out a decision made under this section to the extent of their respective authorities. A first nation, local government, regulatory authority or department or agency of the federal or territorial government affected by a decision made under this section shall act in conformity with the decision to the extent of their respective authorities.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>81.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 131:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Decision by Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>131.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a development is to be carried out wholly or partly on Tlicho lands, the Tlicho Government shall, after considering a report of the Review Board containing a recommendation made under subparagraph 128(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>adopt the recommendation or refer it back to the Review Board for further consideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>after consulting the Review Board, adopt the recommendation with modifications or reject it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Tlicho Government shall carry out, to the extent of its authority, any recommendation that it adopts.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Tlicho Government considers any new information that was not before the Review Board, or any matter of public concern that was not referred to in the Review Board’s reasons, the new information or matter shall be identified in the decision made under this section and in any consultation under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conservation</MarginalNote><Label>131.2</Label><Text>In making a decision under paragraph 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or subsection 131(1) or 131.1(1), the federal Minister and the responsible ministers, a designated regulatory agency or the Tlicho Government, as the case may be, shall consider the importance of the conservation of the lands, waters and wildlife of the Mackenzie Valley on which the development might have an impact.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>82.</Label><Text>Subsections 132(2) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expert members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A review panel may, in addition to members of the Review Board, include as members of the panel persons having particular expertise related to the development.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Board members to participate in appointments</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The members of the Review Board who participate in the appointment of a review panel must include in equal numbers</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>members who were appointed on the nomination of a first nation or the Tlicho Government; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>members not so appointed, other than the chairperson.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>83.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 133:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Coordination</MarginalNote><Label>133.1</Label><Text>The Review Board shall to the extent possible coordinate any environmental impact review conducted by a review panel of a proposal for a development that, as determined by the Review Board, is to be carried out partly outside the Mackenzie Valley with any examination of the environmental impact of that development conducted by another authority responsible for the examination of environmental effects of the part of the development to be carried out outside the Mackenzie Valley.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>84.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 134(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the preparation by the Review Board of terms of reference for the review panel, after consultation with the responsible ministers, with any first nation affected by the proposal and, if the Board has determined that the development is likely to have a significant adverse impact on the environment, or to be a cause of significant public concern, in Monfwi Gogha De Niitlee, with the Tlicho Government;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 134(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Submission to ministers, agencies and Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The report of a review panel shall be submitted to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the federal Minister, who shall distribute it to every responsible minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any designated regulatory agency from which a licence, permit or other authorization is required for the carrying out of the development; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, if the development is to be carried out wholly or partly on Tlicho lands.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>85.</Label><Text>Subsection 136(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The federal Minister and responsible ministers shall carry out a decision made under section 135 to the extent of their respective authorities. A first nation, local government, regulatory authority or department or agency of the federal or territorial government affected by a decision under that section shall act in conformity with the decision to the extent of their respective authorities.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>86.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 137:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Decision by Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>137.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a development is to be carried out wholly or partly on Tlicho lands, the Tlicho Government shall, after considering the report of a review panel,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>adopt the recommendation of the review panel or refer it back to the panel for further consideration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>after consulting the review panel, adopt the recommendation with modifications or reject it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Tlicho Government considers any new information that was not before the review panel, or any matter of public concern that was not referred to in the review panel’s reasons, the new information or matter shall be identified in the decision made under this section and in any consultation under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Tlicho Government shall carry out, to the extent of its authority, any recommendation that it adopts.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Conservation</MarginalNote><Label>137.2</Label><Text>In making a decision under subsection 135(1), 137(1) or 137.1(1), the federal Minister and the responsible ministers, a designated regulatory agency or the Tlicho Government, as the case may be, shall consider the importance of the conservation of the lands, waters and wildlife of the Mackenzie Valley on which the development might have an impact.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>137.3</Label><Text>Before making a decision under subsection 135(1), 137(1) or 137.1(1) in respect of a proposal for a development that, as determined by the Review Board, is to be carried out partly outside the Mackenzie Valley, the person or body making the decision shall take into consideration any report in respect of the proposal that is submitted by a review panel established under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> and shall consult every responsible authority to whom the report is submitted under that Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>87.</Label><Text>Sections 138 and 139 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Report by review panel — national interest referral</MarginalNote><Label>138.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A review panel established under subsection 40(2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> in respect of a proposal for a development that was referred pursuant to paragraph 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of this Act shall, in addition to satisfying the requirements of paragraph 41(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of that Act, submit the report of its recommendations to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the federal Minister, who shall distribute it to every responsible minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any designated regulatory agency from which a licence, permit or other authorization is required for the carrying out of the development; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, if the development is to be carried out wholly or partly on Tlicho lands.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An examination by a review panel referred to in subsection (1) stands in lieu of an environmental impact review and paragraphs 134(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and sections 135 to 137.2 apply, with such modifications as may be required, in respect of the examination, except that a recommendation of a panel may not be referred back to the panel for further consideration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement — national interest referral</MarginalNote><Label>138.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a proposal for a development that, as determined by the Review Board, is to be carried out partly outside the Mackenzie Valley and either is to be carried out partly in Wekeezhii or might have an impact on the environment in Wekeezhii is referred to the Minister of the Environment under paragraph 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), then the Review Board shall enter into an agreement with the Minister of the Environment for the purpose of jointly establishing a review panel and prescribing the manner of its examination of the impact on the environment of the development in accordance with subsection 40(2.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mediation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Review Board and the Minister of the Environment have not entered into an agreement under subsection (1) within the period fixed by any regulations, they shall participate in mediation in accordance with those regulations for the purpose of reaching an agreement under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Arbitration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Review Board and the Minister of the Environment have not entered into an agreement under subsection (1) by the end of any mediation required under subsection (2), they may, within the period fixed by any regulations, by mutual agreement refer any unresolved matter to arbitration in accordance with those regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where no agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (1) to (3), if, within the period fixed by the regulations, an agreement has not been entered into under this section, a panel of the Review Board shall conduct an environmental impact review of the development, but the review shall be limited to the part of the development to be carried out in the Mackenzie Valley.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement — designated regulatory agency</MarginalNote><Label>139.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where an environmental impact review of a proposal for a development that, as determined by the Review Board, is to be carried out wholly in the Mackenzie Valley, other than a development that has been referred to the Minister of the Environment under paragraph 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), is ordered under this Part, and a licence, permit or other authorization must be issued by a designated regulatory agency in order for the proposed development to be carried out, the Review Board and the agency may enter into an agreement for the examination of the impact of the development on the environment by a joint panel established for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to ministers, agencies and Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A joint panel so established shall make a report of its examination to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the federal Minister, who shall distribute it to every responsible minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any designated regulatory agency from which a licence, permit or other authorization is required for the carrying out of the development; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, if the development is to be carried out wholly or partly on Tlicho lands.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An examination by a joint panel established under this section stands in lieu of an environmental impact review and paragraphs 134(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and sections 135 to 137.2 apply, with such modifications as may be required, in respect of the examination, except that a recommendation of a panel may not be referred back to the panel for further consideration.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>88.</Label><Text>Subsections 140(2) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement — other authority</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the Review Board has determined that a development referred to in subsection (1), other than a development that has been referred to the Minister of the Environment under paragraph 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), is likely to have a significant adverse impact on the environment in a region outside the Mackenzie Valley, the Review Board may, with the approval of the federal Minister, enter into an agreement with the authority responsible for the examination of environmental effects in that region to provide for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the coordination of the respective examinations of the environmental impact of the development; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the examination of the environmental impact of the development by a joint panel established for that purpose.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to ministers, agencies and Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A joint panel established under subsection (2) shall make a report of its recommendations to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the federal Minister, who shall distribute it to every responsible minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any designated regulatory agency from which a licence, permit or other authorization is required for the carrying out of the development; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, if the development is to be carried out wholly or partly on Tlicho lands.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An examination by a joint panel established under subsection (2) stands in lieu of an environmental impact review of the proposal and paragraphs 134(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and sections 135 to 137.2 apply, with such modifications as may be required, in respect of the examination, except that a recommendation of a panel may not be referred back to the panel for further consideration.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>89.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 141(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement — cases other than Wekeezhii</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an environmental impact review is ordered under subparagraph 128(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i), paragraph 128(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), subparagraph 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii) or paragraph 131(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) in respect of a proposal for a development referred to in subsection (1), other than a development referred to in subsection (3), the Review Board may, with the approval of the federal Minister,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 15, par. 48(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>); 2002, c. 7, s. 206(2)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 141(3) to (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement — Wekeezhii</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an environmental impact review is ordered under subparagraph 128(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i), paragraph 128(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), subparagraph 130(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii) or paragraph 131(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) in respect of a proposal for a development that, as determined by the Review Board, is to be carried out partly outside the Mackenzie Valley and either is to be carried out partly in Wekeezhii or might have an impact on the environment in Wekeezhii, the Review Board shall enter into an agreement for the purpose of jointly establishing a review panel and prescribing the manner of its examination of the impact on the environment of the development</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with an authority responsible for the examination of environmental effects of the part of the development that is to be carried out outside the Mackenzie Valley; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with the Minister of the Environment if that Minister is authorized under section 40 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> to enter into such an agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where no agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (3), if, within the period fixed by the regulations, an agreement has not been entered into under that subsection, a panel of the Review Board shall conduct an environmental impact review of the development, but the review shall be limited to the part of the development to be carried out in the Mackenzie Valley.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A review panel or joint panel established by an agreement referred to in subsection (2) or (3) shall make a report of its examination to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the federal Minister, who shall distribute it to every responsible minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any designated regulatory agency from which a licence, permit or other authorization is required for the carrying out of the development;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a joint panel referred to in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the minister of the federal, provincial or territorial government having jurisdiction in relation to examinations conducted by the authority referred to in that paragraph; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, if the development is to be carried out partly on Tlicho lands.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provisions applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An examination by a review panel or joint panel referred to in subsection (2) or (3) stands in lieu of an environmental impact review of the proposal referred to in that subsection and paragraphs 134(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) and sections 135 to 137.2 apply, with such modifications as may be required, in respect of the examination, except that a recommendation of a panel may not be referred back to the panel for further consideration.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>90.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 143(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>143.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, following consultation by the federal Minister with the territorial Minister, first nations and the Tlicho Government, make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Part and, in particular, regulations</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 143(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fixing a period for the purposes of subsection 138.1(2) and respecting mediation referred to in that subsection;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fixing the period within which a matter may be referred to arbitration under subsection 138.1(3) and respecting arbitration under that subsection; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>fixing a period for the purposes of subsections 138.1(4) and 141(4).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 143(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with Review Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations may only be made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>), or amended under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), following consultation by the federal Minister with the Review Board.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>91.</Label><Text>Subsection 144(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Schedule</MarginalNote><Label>144.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by regulations made following consultation by the federal Minister with the territorial Minister, the Review Board, the first nations and the Tlicho Government, amend the schedule by adding, or by deleting, the name of any agency, other than a land and water board established by Part 3 or 4, that exercises regulatory powers pursuant to territorial or federal laws and that is not subject to specific control or direction by a minister of the federal or territorial government or the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>92.</Label><Text>Section 147 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation with first nations and Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>147.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A responsible authority that is a minister of the Crown in right of Canada shall carry out the functions referred to in section 146 in consultation with the first nations and the Tlicho Government.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Role of first nations and Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a responsible authority is other than a minister of the Crown in right of Canada, the Gwich’in and Sahtu First Nations and the Tlicho Government are entitled to participate in the functions referred to in section 146 in the manner provided by the regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>93.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 148(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms of reference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The federal Minister shall, after consulting the Gwich’in First Nation, the Sahtu First Nation, the Tlicho Government and the territorial government, fix the terms of reference of an environmental audit, including the key components of the environment to be examined.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 148(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Participation by first nations and Tlicho Government</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Gwich’in and Sahtu First Nations and the Tlicho Government are entitled to participate in an environmental audit in the manner provided by the regulations.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>94.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 150 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>150.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, after consultation by the federal Minister with affected first nations, the Tlicho Government and the territorial Minister, make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Part and, in particular, regulations</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 150(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the manner of participation of the Gwich’in and Sahtu First Nations and the Tlicho Government in the functions of a responsible authority that is not a minister of the Crown or in an environmental audit.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Wekeezhii Land and Water Board</MarginalNote><Label>95.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Wekeezhii Land and Water Board established by section 57.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>31</XRefInternal> of this Act, may not exercise its powers or perform its duties under sections 58.1 and 59, subsections 60(1) and (2), sections 79.1 to 79.3, 80.1 and 88 and subsection 89(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal> until six months after the coming into force of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Mackenzie Valley Land and Water Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 102(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>, the Mackenzie Valley Land and Water Board shall exercise the powers and perform the duties of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board under sections 58.1, 79.1 to 79.3, 80.1 and 88 and subsection 89(2) of that Act during the period of six months after the coming into force of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Exclusive original jurisdiction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 32(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal> and section 18 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>, the Supreme Court of the Northwest Territories has exclusive original jurisdiction to hear and determine any action or proceeding, whether or not by way of an application of a type referred to in subsection 32(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>, concerning the jurisdiction of the Wekeezhii Land and Water Board during the period of six months after the coming into force of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Validity of ordinances of the Northwest Territories</MarginalNote><Label>96.</Label><Text>The following ordinances of the Northwest Territories are deemed for all purposes to have been validly made if they were made before the coming into force of this Act and would have been validly made if they had been made after that coming into force, and everything done under any of those ordinances before that coming into force has the effect that it would otherwise have if the ordinance had been validly made after that coming into force:</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the ordinance of the Northwest Territories entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Agreement Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an ordinance that establishes community governments as required by chapter 8 of the Agreement; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an ordinance that establishes a community services agency as required by the first intergovernmental services agreement referred to in 7.10 of chapter 7 of the Agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 7, s. 21(2)</MarginalNote><Label>97.</Label><Text>Subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>aboriginal government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The expression <DefinedTermEn>aboriginal government</DefinedTermEn> in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Nisga’a Government, as defined in the Nisga’a Final Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nisga’a Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act.</XRefExternal></Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. L-6</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Lands Surveys Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>98.</Label><Text>Paragraph 24(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Lands Surveys Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of subparagraph (iv), by replacing the word “and” at the end of subparagraph (v) with the word “or” and by adding the following after subparagraph (v):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>Tlicho lands, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 37</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>99.</Label><Text>Section 40 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2.1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where no agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (2.1), if, in respect of a proposal referred to in subsection 138.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>, no agreement is entered into under that subsection within the period fixed by the regulations referred to in subsection 138.1(4) of that Act, an assessment by a review panel of the proposal shall be conducted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Coordination</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall to the extent possible ensure that any assessment of the proposal required by subsection (2.2) is coordinated with any environmental impact review of the proposal under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2.4)</Label><Text>Before taking a course of action under subsection 37(1) in respect of a proposal referred to in subsection (2.3), the responsible authority shall take into consideration any report in respect of the proposal that is issued under subsection 134(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal> and shall consult the persons and bodies to whom the report is submitted or distributed under subsection 134(3) of that Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 44 (4th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Lobbyists Registration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>100.</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lobbyists Registration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d.2</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.3</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>members or employees of the Tlicho Government, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, or persons on the staff of those members;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. N-27</MarginalNote><TitleText>Northwest Territories Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>101.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 16:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Roads identified in Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>16.1</Label><Text>Ordinances made by the Commissioner in Council under paragraph 16(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>) apply to roads identified in the Agreement, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, as if they were on public lands if the Agreement provides that those ordinances apply to those roads.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>102.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 17:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement implementation Acts</MarginalNote><Label>17.1</Label><Text>Despite section 17, the Commissioner in Council may, in exercising the powers of the Commissioner in Council under section 16 for the purpose of implementing the Agreement, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, make ordinances that are in relation to the matters coming within class 24 of section 91 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 39</MarginalNote><TitleText>Northwest Territories Waters Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>103.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Northwest Territories Waters Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 9:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>TLICHO COMMUNITIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Exemption</MarginalNote><Label>9.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 8 and 9 do not apply in respect of a use of waters or a deposit of waste in a Tlicho community, if the local government of that community has enacted a bylaw providing that a licence is not required for that type of use or deposit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Same meaning</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The expressions <DefinedTermEn>Tlicho community</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>local government</DefinedTermEn> in subsection (1) have the same meaning as in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>104.</Label><Text>Section 14 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, licences issued by the Board under this Act either before or after the coming into force of this subsection are not statutory instruments within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. M-13; 2000, c. 8, s. 2</MarginalNote><TitleText>Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>105.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>taxing authority</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), by adding the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, if it levies and collects a real property tax or a frontage or area tax in respect of Tlicho lands, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mackenzie Valley Resource Management Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 7, s. 26(2)</MarginalNote><Label>106.</Label><Text>Subsection 8(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>aboriginal government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The expression <DefinedTermEn>aboriginal government</DefinedTermEn> in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Nisga’a Government, as defined in the Nisga’a Final Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nisga’a Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>107.</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Westbank First Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal> and section <XRefInternal>97</XRefInternal> of this Act, subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>aboriginal government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The expression <DefinedTermEn>aboriginal government</DefinedTermEn> in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Nisga’a Government, as defined in the Nisga’a Final Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nisga’a Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the council, as defined in the Westbank First Nation Self-Government Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Westbank First Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 44 (4th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Lobbyists Registration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>108.</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 17 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Westbank First Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal> and section <XRefInternal>100</XRefInternal> of this Act, paragraph 4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d.3</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lobbyists Registration Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.3</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>members of the council, as defined in the Westbank First Nation Self-Government Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Westbank First Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, or persons on the staff of the council or of a member of the council;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.4</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>members or employees of the Tlicho Government, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, or persons on the staff of those members;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>109.</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of subsection 18(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Westbank First Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal> and section <XRefInternal>106</XRefInternal> of this Act, subsection 8(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>aboriginal government</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The expression <DefinedTermEn>aboriginal government</DefinedTermEn> in paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Nisga’a Government, as defined in the Nisga’a Final Agreement given effect by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nisga’a Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the council of the Westbank First Nation; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Tlicho Government, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tlicho Land Claims and Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Other Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 10</MarginalNote><Label>110.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If subsection 3(1) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Lobbyists Registration Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 10 of the Statutes of Canada, 2003 (the “other Act”), comes into force before the coming into force of section <XRefInternal>100</XRefInternal> of this Act, then, on the later of the coming into force of that subsection 3(1) and the day on which this Act receives royal assent, section <XRefInternal>100</XRefInternal> of this Act and the heading before it are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection 3(1) of the other Act comes into force on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>100</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force and section <XRefInternal>108</XRefInternal> of this Act has not had its effect, then, on the coming into force of that subsection 3(1), paragraph 4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d.3</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lobbyists Registration Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If subsection 3(1) of the other Act comes into force on or after the day on which section <XRefInternal>100</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force and section <XRefInternal>108</XRefInternal> of this Act has had its effect, then, on the coming into force of that subsection 3(1), paragraphs 4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d.3</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d.4</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lobbyists Registration Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>111.</Label><Text>This Act, other than sections <XRefInternal>107</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>110</XRefInternal>, comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>