<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-39</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act and to enact An Act respecting the provision of funding for diagnostic and medical equipment</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements and Funding for Diagnostic and Medical Equipment</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements and Funding for Diagnostic and Medical Equipment</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2005-2-7">90313</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The purpose of this enactment is to give effect to the 2004 10-Year Plan to Strengthen Health Care by increasing the Canada Health Transfer in the fiscal years in the period beginning on April 1, 2004 and ending on March 31, 2014 and establishing a Wait Times Reduction Transfer, payable first to a trust for the benefit of the provinces, and then directly to provinces as of the fiscal year 2009-10. This enactment also provides funding to provinces for diagnostic and medical equipment.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-8; 1995, c. 17, s. 45(1)</MarginalNote><TitleText>FEDERAL-PROVINCIAL FISCAL ARRANGEMENTS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 15, s. 8</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>The headings before section 24 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading><Label>PART V.1</Label><TitleText>CANADA HEALTH TRANSFER, CANADA SOCIAL TRANSFER, HEALTH REFORM TRANSFER AND WAIT TIMES REDUCTION TRANSFER</TitleText></Heading><Heading><TitleText>Canada Health Transfer</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 15, s. 8</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The portion of section 24 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Purposes</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>Subject to this Part and for the purpose of giving effect to the 2003 First Ministers’ Accord on Health Care Renewal and the 2004 10-Year Plan to Strengthen Health Care, a Canada Health Transfer in the amounts referred to in subsection 24.1(1) is to be provided to the provinces for the purposes of</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 15, s. 8</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 24.1(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a cash contribution equal to</Text></Paragraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>$12.65 billion for the fiscal year beginning on April 1, 2004,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>$1 billion for the fiscal year beginning on April 1, 2004,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>$19 billion for the fiscal year beginning on April 1, 2005, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the product obtained by multiplying the cash contribution for the immediately preceding year by 1.06, rounded to the nearest thousand, for each fiscal year in the period beginning on April 1, 2006 and ending on March 31, 2014; and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 24.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The cash contribution referred to in subparagraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) is not subject to subparagraphs 4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) to (iii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Canada Health Transfer and Canada Social Transfer Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 15, s. 8</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 24.6(2) of the Act is amended by adding the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and by repealing paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>).</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 24.6:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Wait Times Reduction Transfer</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purposes</MarginalNote><Label>24.61</Label><Text>Subject to this Part, a Wait Times Reduction Transfer is established under section 24.62 to provide funding for the purposes of assisting the provinces to reduce wait times according to their respective priorities, including training and hiring more health professionals, clearing backlogs, building capacity for regional centres of excellence, expanding appropriate ambulatory and community care programs and expanding tools to manage wait times, as outlined in the 2004 10-Year Plan to Strengthen Health Care.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer</MarginalNote><Label>24.62</Label><Text>The Wait Times Reduction Transfer shall consist of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the cash contribution referred to in subsection 24.63(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the cash contributions referred to in subsection 24.64(1).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payment to trust</MarginalNote><Label>24.63</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may pay $4.25 billion to a trust established to provide the provinces with funding for the purposes referred to in section 24.61.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provincial share</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The amount that may be provided to a province by the trust is to be determined in accordance with the terms of the trust indenture establishing the trust.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding section 24.8, the amount payable under subsection (1) may be paid by the Minister to the trust out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund at the times and in the manner that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Cash contributions to provinces</MarginalNote><Label>24.64</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes referred to in section 24.61, the Minister may make cash contributions to the provinces equal to $250 million for each fiscal year in the period beginning on April 1, 2009 and ending on March 31, 2014.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provincial share</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The amount that may be paid to a province for each of the fiscal years mentioned in subsection (1) is the amount determined by multiplying the amount set out for that fiscal year by the quotient obtained by dividing</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the population of the province for the fiscal year</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>by</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the total of the population of all provinces for the fiscal year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 25.8:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Parliamentary Review</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>25.9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Parliament having authorized the appropriation of money for the Canada Health Transfer and the Wait Times Reduction Transfer for the purpose of giving effect to the 2004 10-Year Plan to Strengthen Health Care, a review of the progress in implementing that Plan shall be undertaken by such committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament as may be designated or established, using the reports referred to in the Plan. The committee shall undertake the review on or before March 31, 2008 and three years thereafter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee shall, within three months after beginning the review or within such further time as the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, may authorize, submit a report on the result of that review to that House or both Houses.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Communiqués</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Communiqués</MarginalNote><Label>25.91</Label><Text>For greater certainty and for the purposes of this Part (V.1), the 2004 10-Year Plan to Strengthen Health Care includes the communiqués released in respect of the First Ministers’ Meeting on the Future of Health Care that was held from September 13 to 15, 2004.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>AN ACT RESPECTING THE PROVISION OF FUNDING FOR DIAGNOSTIC AND MEDICAL EQUIPMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text><XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the provision of funding for diagnostic and medical equipment</XRefExternal> is enacted as follows:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act respecting the provision of funding for diagnostic and medical equipment</LongTitle><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Payment — equipment and services</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of giving effect to the 2004 10-Year Plan to Strengthen Health Care, the Minister of Finance may, for the fiscal year beginning on April 1, 2004, make direct payments, in an aggregate of $500 million, to the provinces for the purposes of acquiring diagnostic and medical equipment and related specialized staff training in order to improve access to and reduce wait times for publicly funded diagnostic and treatment services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Provincial share</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The amount payable to a province for the fiscal year shall be determined by multiplying the amount referred to in subsection (1) by the quotient obtained by dividing</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the population of the province for the fiscal year</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>by</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the total population of all provinces for the fiscal year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of population</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, the population of a province for the fiscal year shall be determined by the Chief Statistician of Canada on the basis of Statistics Canada’s official estimate of the population of that province on June 1, 2004.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any amount payable under this Act may be paid by the Minister out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund at the times and in the manner that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Communiqués</MarginalNote><Label><Emphasis style="bold">2.</Emphasis></Label><Text>For greater certainty and for the purposes of this Act, the 2004 10-Year Plan to Strengthen Health Care includes the communiqués released in respect of the First Ministers’ Meeting on the Future of Health Care that was held from September 13 to 15, 2004.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>