<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-18</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Statistics Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Statistics</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Statistics</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>31</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2004-10-29">90215</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment removes a legal ambiguity in relation to access to census records made between 1910 and 2005. It allows unrestricted access to those records, beginning 92 years after the census was taken. Starting in 2006, the consent of Canadians is required in order for their census information to be released 92 years after the census is taken. The enactment provides for a parliamentary review of the administration of that requirement.</Text></Provision></Summary><?Pub Caret?><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-19</MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 18:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Census taken between 1910 and 2005</MarginalNote><Label>18.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The information contained in the returns of each census of population taken between 1910 and 2005 is no longer subject to sections 17 and 18 ninety-two years after the census is taken.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Census in 2006 or later</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The information contained in the returns of each census of population taken in 2006 or later is no longer subject to sections 17 and 18 ninety-two years after the census is taken, but only if the person to whom the information relates consents, at the time of the census, to the release of the information ninety-two years later.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Library and Archives of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>When sections 17 and 18 cease to apply to information referred to in subsection (1) or (2), the information shall be placed under the care and control of the Library and Archives of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Review by parliamentary committee</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No later than two years before the taking of the third census of population under section 19 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal> after the coming into force of this Act, the administration and operation of subsection 18.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 1, shall be reviewed by any committee of the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee shall submit a report to the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, in relation to the review that includes a statement of any changes to the administration of subsection 18.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 1, that the committee recommends.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>