<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-26</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish the Canada Border Services Agency</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Canada Border Services Agency Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canada Border Services Agency</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>11</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>38</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2004-11-22">90294</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment establishes the Canada Border Services Agency, which was first created by order in council on December 12, 2003. The Agency brings together the border services of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency, the Canadian Food Inspection Agency and the Department of Citizenship and Immigration. The enactment sets out the responsibilities, mandate, powers, duties and functions of the Minister responsible for the Agency and its President. It continues the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency under the name of the Canada Revenue Agency and contains transitional provisions as well as consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Border Services Agency established under subsection <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Solicitor General of Canada.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>président</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> means the President of the Agency appointed under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>program legislation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>législation frontalière</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>program legislation</DefinedTermEn> means any other Act of Parliament or any instrument made under it, or any part of such an Act or instrument,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the Governor in Council or Parliament authorizes the Minister, the Agency, the President or an employee of the Agency to administer and enforce, including the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the Governor in Council or Parliament authorizes the Minister, the Agency, the President or an employee of the Agency to enforce, including the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Agricultural Products Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Feeds Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fertilizers Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fish Inspection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Health of Animals Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Meat Inspection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Plant Protection Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seeds Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under which the Minister or another minister authorizes the Agency, the President or an employee of the Agency to administer a program or carry out an activity; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under which duties or taxes collected and paid pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> are imposed.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ESTABLISHMENT AND MANDATE OF THE AGENCY</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Agency established</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Canada Border Services Agency is established as a body corporate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agent of Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agency is for all purposes an agent of Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Head office</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The head office of the Agency is to be in the National Capital Region described in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Mandate of Agency</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agency is responsible for providing integrated border services that support national security and public safety priorities and facilitate the free flow of persons and goods, including animals and plants, that meet all requirements under the program legislation, by</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>supporting the administration or enforcement, or both, as the case may be, of the program legislation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>implementing agreements between the Government of Canada or the Agency and a foreign state or a public body performing a function of government in a foreign state to carry out an activity, provide a service or administer a tax or program;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>implementing agreements between the Government of Canada or the Agency and the government of a province or other public body performing a function of the Government in Canada to carry out an activity, provide a service or administer a tax or program;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>implementing agreements or arrangements between the Agency and departments or agencies of the Government of Canada to carry out an activity, provide a service or administer a program; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>providing cooperation and support, including advice and information, to other departments and agencies of the Government of Canada to assist them in developing, evaluating and implementing policies and decisions in relation to program legislation for which they have responsibility.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Support</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agency may provide support, through the provision of services, to departments and agencies for which the Minister is responsible, in accordance with agreements or arrangements entered into with those departments and agencies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>MINISTER</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Minister responsible</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister is responsible for the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may delegate to any person any power, duty or function conferred on the Minister under this Act or under the program legislation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not apply if an Act of Parliament other than this Act authorizes the Minister to delegate the power, duty or function to any person or authorizes any person to exercise or perform it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not apply in respect of a power to make regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PRESIDENT AND EXECUTIVE VICE-PRESIDENT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall appoint a President of the Agency to hold office during pleasure for a term of not more than five years, which term may be renewed for one or more further terms.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Executive Vice-president</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may appoint an Executive Vice-president of the Agency to hold office during pleasure for a term of not more than five years, which term may be renewed for one or more further terms.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Role of President</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President, under the direction of the Minister, has the control and management of the Agency and all matters connected with it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rank of deputy head</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President has the rank and all the powers of a deputy head of a department.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Executive Vice-president’s powers</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Executive Vice-president shall exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions that the President may assign and shall act as President if that office is vacant or if the President is absent or incapacitated.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Delegation by President</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President may delegate to any person any power, duty or function that the President is authorized to exercise or perform under this Act or any other enactment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation of officers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President may designate any person, or person within a class of persons,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>as an officer as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to exercise any powers or perform any duties and functions of an officer under that Act that the President may specify; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>as an inspector or a veterinary inspector or other officer for the enforcement of any Act or instrument made under it, or any part of an Act or instrument, that the Governor in Council or Parliament authorizes the Minister, the Agency, the President or an employee of the Agency to enforce, including the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Agricultural Products Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Feeds Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fertilizers Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fish Inspection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Health of Animals Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Meat Inspection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Plant Protection Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seeds Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation power</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The President may exercise any power that the Minister has to designate officers under subsection 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President and the Executive Vice-president shall be paid the remuneration that is fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President and the Executive Vice-president are entitled to be paid reasonable travel and living expenses incurred by them in the course of performing their duties while absent from their ordinary place of work.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed employment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The President and the Executive Vice-president are deemed to be employed in the Public Service for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> and to be employed in the public service of Canada for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>HUMAN RESOURCES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Officers and employees</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Officers and employees necessary for the proper conduct of the work of the Agency shall be appointed in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>POWERS OF THE AGENCY</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Exercise of powers conferred on Minister</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to any direction given by the Minister, the Agency may exercise the powers, and shall perform the duties and functions, that relate to the program legislation and that are conferred on, or delegated, assigned or transferred to, the Minister under any Act or regulation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Officers and employees</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer or employee of the Agency may exercise any power or perform any duty or function referred to in subsection (1) if the officer or employee is appointed to serve in the Agency in a capacity appropriate to the exercise of the power or the performance of the duty or function, and, in so doing, shall comply with any general or special direction given by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any power, duty or function of the Minister under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a power to make regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> </MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A direction given by the Minister under subsection (1) or (2) is not a statutory instrument for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to section 38 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal>, the Agency may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister and the Minister of Foreign Affairs and International Trade, enter into an agreement with a foreign state or an international organization, for the purposes of carrying out the mandate of the Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Arrangements and agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agency may, for the purposes of carrying out its mandate,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enter into an arrangement with a foreign state or an international organization; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enter into an agreement or arrangement with the government of a province, a department or agency of the Government of Canada or any person or organization.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements to administer a tax</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agency may enter into or amend an agreement with a provincial or territorial government to administer a tax or other fiscal measure if the agreement is in accordance with guidelines relating to agreements of that kind established jointly by the Minister and the Minister of Finance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> </MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Parts III and III.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> do not apply to an agreement entered into or amended under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>EXPENDITURES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appropriation Acts</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>An appropriation Act may provide that the balance of money appropriated by Parliament for the use of the Agency that remains unexpended at the end of the fiscal year, after the adjustments referred to in section 37 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> are made, lapses at the end of the following fiscal year.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ANNUAL REPORT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>15.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall, as soon as possible after the end of each fiscal year but no later than the end of the calendar year in which that fiscal year ends, cause to be laid before each House of Parliament a report of the operations and performance of the Agency for that fiscal year. </Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reports required by Treasury Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The obligation imposed by subsection (1) may be satisfied by the tabling of any reports of the operations and performance of the Agency required by the Treasury Board that contain the information required by that subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Definitions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in sections 17 to 19 and 21 to 28.</Text><Definition type="transitional"><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>former agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ancienne agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>former agency</DefinedTermEn> means the portion of the public service of Canada known as the Canada Border Services Agency.</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>new agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>nouvelle agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>new agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Border Services Agency established under subsection <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(1).</Text></Definition><Definition type="transitional"><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>order P.C. 2003-2064</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>décret C.P. 2003-2064</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>order P.C. 2003-2064</DefinedTermEn> means Order in Council P.C. 2003-2064 of December 12, 2003, registered as SI/2003-216.</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Former Agency</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>President and Executive Vice-president</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The persons occupying the positions of President and Executive Vice-president of the former agency on the day on which this section comes into force become the President and Executive Vice-president of the new agency on that day and are deemed to have been appointed under section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Positions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act is to be construed as affecting the status of an employee who, immediately before the coming into force of this section, occupied a position in the former agency, except that the employee shall, on the coming into force of this section, occupy his or her position in the new agency under the direction of the President.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definition of “employee”</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In subsection (2), <DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer of appropriations</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any amount appropriated, for the fiscal year in which this section comes into force, by an appropriation Act based on the Estimates for that year for defraying the charges and expenses of the public service of Canada for the former agency that, on the day on which this section comes into force, is unexpended is deemed, on that day, to be an amount appropriated for defraying the charges and expenses of the public service of Canada for the new agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer of powers, duties and functions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Wherever under any Act, order, rule or regulation, or any contract, lease, licence or other document, any power, duty or function is vested in or exercisable by the President of the former agency or an employee of the former agency, the power, duty or function is vested in and shall be exercised by the President of the new agency or an employee of the new agency unless the Governor in Council by order designates a deputy minister or an officer of the public service of Canada to exercise that power or perform that duty or function.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any action, suit or other legal or administrative proceeding to which the former agency or its President is a party that is pending on the coming into force of this section may be continued by or against the new agency or its President in a similar manner and to the same extent as it would have been continued by or against the former agency or its President.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Decisions made by the President of the former agency are deemed to be decisions made by the President of the new agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Validity of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>All orders, rules, regulations, decisions, determinations and re-determinations, directions, licences, authorizations, certificates, consents, approvals, declarations, designations, permits, registrations, rates or other documents that are in force on the coming into force of this section and that are made or issued by the President of the former agency or any person under his or her authority continue in force as if they were made or issued by the President of the new agency or a person under his or her authority, as the case may be, until they expire or are repealed, replaced, rescinded or altered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of evidentiary presumption</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Every affidavit sworn, or document purporting to be certified, by an employee of the former agency before the day on which this section comes into force has the same probative value as if it were sworn or certified by an employee of the new agency after that day.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A reference to the former agency in any of the following is deemed to be a reference to the new agency:</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any order of the Governor in Council made under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition “head” in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any direction of the Governor in Council made under subsection 24(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Auditor General Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any order of the Governor in Council made under paragraph 29(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any order of the Governor in Council made under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition “head” in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any order of the Governor in Council made under the definition “department” in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deputy head</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The designation of a person as deputy head of the former agency in any of the following is deemed to be a designation of the President of the new agency as deputy head of that agency:</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any order of the Governor in Council made under paragraph 29(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Security Intelligence Service Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any order of the Governor in Council made under the definition “deputy head” in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Canada Customs and Revenue Agency</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Positions</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed as affecting the status of an employee who, immediately before the coming into force of this section, occupied a position in the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency, except that the employee shall occupy that position in the Canada Revenue Agency.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of rights and property</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), all rights and property of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency continue as the rights and property of the Canada Revenue Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer to new agency</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All rights and property of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency that are in respect of those portions of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064 are transferred to the new agency.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of obligations and liabilities</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), all obligations and liabilities of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency continue as obligations and liabilities of the Canada Revenue Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer to new agency</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All obligations and liabilities of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency that were incurred in respect of those portions of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064 are transferred to the new agency.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Real property, immovables and licences</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The administration of any real property or immovable, and the administrative responsibility for any licence in respect of any real property or immovable, that was under the administration or administrative responsibility of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency immediately before the coming into force of this section and that was used for or in support of those portions of the Canada Customs and Reve­nue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064 are transferred to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>List</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As soon as practicable after the coming into force of this section, the Minister of National Revenue shall publish in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> a list of the real property and immovables the administration of which was transferred under subsection (1) in such a way that each is sufficiently identified.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Title</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the title of any real property or immovable was held in the name of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency immediately before the coming into force of this section and that real property or immovable was used for or in support of those portions of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064, the title to that real property or immovable is deemed to be held in the name of Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Other real property, immovables and licences — Canada Revenue Agency</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The administration of any real property or immovable, and the administrative responsibility for any licence in respect of any real property or immovable, that is not referred to in subsection (1) and that was under the administration or administrative responsibility of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency immediately before the coming into force of this section continues under the administration or administrative responsibility, as the case may be, of the Canada Revenue Agency.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of legal proceedings: Canada Revenue Agency</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), any action, suit or other legal or administrative proceeding to which the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency is a party that is pending on the coming into force of this section may be continued by or against the Canada Revenue Agency in the same manner and to the same extent as it could have been continued by or against the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of legal proceedings: new agency</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any action, suit or other legal or administrative proceeding to which the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency is a party that is pending on the coming into force of this section may be continued by or against the new agency in the same manner and to the same extent as it could have been continued by or against the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency in respect of those portions of the Canada Customs and Reve­nue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Validity of documents: Canada Revenue Agency</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), all orders, rules, regulations, decisions, determinations and re-determinations, directions, licences, authorizations, certificates, consents, approvals, declarations, designations, permits, registrations, rates or other documents that are in force on the coming into force of this section and that were made or issued by the Minister of National Revenue or by the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue or any person under their authority continue in force as if they were made or issued by the Minister of National Revenue or the Commissioner of Revenue or any person under their authority, as the case may be, until they expire or are repealed, replaced, rescinded or altered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Validity of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>All orders, rules, regulations, decisions, determinations and re-determinations, directions, licences, authorizations, certificates, consents, approvals, declarations, designations, permits, registrations, rates or other documents that are in force on the coming into force of this section and that were made or issued by the Minister of National Revenue or by the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue or any person under their authority that are in respect of those portions of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064 continue in force as if they were made or issued by the Minister, the President of the new agency or a person under their authority, as the case may be, until they expire or are repealed, replaced, rescinded or altered.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of evidentiary presumption: Canada Revenue Agency</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), every affidavit sworn, or document purporting to be certified, by an employee of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency before the day on which this section comes into force has the same probative value as if it were sworn or certified by an employee of the Canada Revenue Agency after that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continuation of evidentiary presumption: Canada Border Services Agency</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every affidavit sworn, or document purporting to be certified, by an employee of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency before the day on which this section comes into force that was sworn or was purported to be certified in respect of those portions of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064 has the same probative value as if it were sworn or certified by an employee of the new agency after that day.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), every reference to the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Deputy Commissioner of Customs and Revenue or any person under their authority in a document issued in the name of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue or the Deputy Commissioner of Customs and Revenue is to be read, unless the context otherwise requires, as a reference to the Canada Revenue Agency, the Commissioner of Revenue, the Deputy Commissioner of Revenue or a person under their authority, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every reference to the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Deputy Commissioner of Customs and Revenue or any person under their authority in a document issued in the name of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue or the Deputy Commissioner of Customs and Revenue is to be read in respect of those documents that relate to those portions of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064, unless the context otherwise requires, as a reference to the new agency, the President of the new agency, the Executive Vice-president of the new agency or a person under their authority, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>References in documents and other provisions: Canada Revenue Agency</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), any expression referring to the Deputy Minister of National Revenue, the Department of National Revenue, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue or the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency in any document, any instrument made under an Act of Parliament or any provision of an Act of Parliament not amended by this Act is to be read, unless the context otherwise requires, as a reference to the Commissioner of Revenue or the Canada Revenue Agency, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>References in documents and other provisions: Canada Border Services Agency</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any expression referring to the Deputy Minister of National Revenue, the Department of National Revenue, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue or the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency in any document, any instrument made under an Act of Parliament or any provision of an Act of Parliament not amended by this Act and the document, instrument or provision is in respect of those portions of the Canada Customs and Revenue Agency the control and supervision of which were transferred to the former agency by order P.C. 2003-2064 is to be read, unless the context otherwise requires, as a reference to the President of the new agency or the new agency, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Royal Canadian Mint Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mint Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>The Minister of National Revenue is the Minister for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mint Act</XRefExternal> until another member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada is designated under section 2.1 of that Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 40</MarginalNote><TitleText>Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Text>The definition “Minister” in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister of Agriculture and Agri-Food; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with respect to a notice of violation issued in relation to the contravention of program legislation referred to in subsection 11(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Food Inspection Agency Act</XRefExternal>, the Solicitor General of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 9, s. 5</MarginalNote><TitleText>Air Travellers Security Charge Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>31.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Air Travellers Security Charge Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Revenue Agency continued by subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner of Revenue appointed under section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Text>Subsection 83(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Every document purporting to have been executed under or in the course of the administration or enforcement of this Act over the name in writing of the Minister, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner or an officer authorized to exercise the powers or perform the duties of the Minister under this Act is deemed to be a document signed, made and issued by the Minister, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner or the officer, unless it has been called into question by the Minister or a person acting for the Minister or for Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 20 (4th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Agricultural Products Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 39</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>Subsection 19(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Agricultural Products Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may designate inspectors under paragraph 9(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> for the purposes of enforcing this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Inspectors shall be given certificates in a form established by the President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, attesting to their designation and, on entering any place under this Act, an inspector shall show the certificate to the person in charge of the place on request.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Customs and Revenue Agency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>34.</Label><Text>The long title of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Customs and Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>An Act to continue the Canada Revenue Agency and to amend and repeal other Acts as a consequence</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35.</Label><Text>Section 1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 22, s. 322</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermFr>législation fiscale et douanière</DefinedTermFr> in section 2 of the French version of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Revenue Agency continued by subsection 4(1).</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 22, s. 322</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>program legislation</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the Governor in Council or Parliament authorizes the Minister, the Agency, the Commissioner or an employee of the Agency to administer or enforce, including the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Air Travellers Security Charge Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the French version of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>législation fiscale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>program legislation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermFr>législation fiscale</DefinedTermFr> Tout ou partie d’une autre loi fédérale ou de ses textes d’application :</Text><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>dont le ministre, l’Agence, le commissaire ou un employé de l’Agence est autorisé par le Parlement ou le gouverneur en conseil à assurer ou contrôler l’application, notamment la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur le droit pour la sécurité des passagers du transport aérien</XRefExternal>, la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur les douanes</XRefExternal>, la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur l’accise</XRefExternal>, la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi de 2001 sur l’accise</XRefExternal>, la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur la taxe d’accise</XRefExternal> et la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi de l’impôt sur le revenu</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>en vertu desquels le ministre ou un autre ministre autorise l’Agence, le commissaire ou un employé de l’Agence à appliquer un programme ou à exercer une activité.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37.</Label><Text>The heading before section 4 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading><TitleText>CONTINUATION AND MANDATE OF THE AGENCY</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38.</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Continuation</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Canada Customs and Revenue Agency is continued as a body corporate under the name of the Canada Revenue Agency.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39.</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>de fournir l’appui nécessaire à l’application et au contrôle d’application de la législation fiscale;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 6(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 6(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the collection of debts due to Her Majesty under Part V.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 22, s. 323</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of officers</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The Minister may designate any person, or person within a class of persons, as an officer as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> or section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal> to exercise any powers or perform any duties and functions of an officer under those Acts that the Minister may specify.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42.</Label><Text>Section 9 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Instructions sur l’exercice des attributions</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>Le ministre peut donner des instructions au commissaire ou à toute autre personne sur l’exercice de celles de ses attributions qui leur sont confiées soit au titre des paragraphes 8(1) ou (4), soit sous le régime de la législation fiscale.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 16, s. 4(F)</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Text>Subsection 26(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment and tenure of Deputy Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A Deputy Commissioner of Revenue may be appointed by the Governor in Council to hold office during pleasure for a term of not more than five years, which term may be renewed for one or more further terms of not more than five years each.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44.</Label><Text>Section 33 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Fonctions consultatives</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>Il peut conseiller le ministre sur les questions liées à l’application et au contrôle d’application, en général, de la législation fiscale.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 34(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>à l’exercice des attributions soit qui leur sont conférées ou déléguées sous le régime de la législation fiscale ou d’une loi provinciale, soit qu’ils sont autorisés à exercer au nom du ministre sous le régime de la présente loi;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>à l’application ou au contrôle d’application de la législation fiscale.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46.</Label><Text>Section 35 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Confidentialité de certains renseignements</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>La présente loi n’a pas pour effet d’autoriser la divulgation au conseil de renseignements qui, même indirectement, révèlent l’identité de la personne, de l’organisation ou de l’entreprise commerciale à laquelle ils ont trait et qui ont été soit obtenus sous le régime de la législation fiscale ou d’une loi provinciale, soit préparés à partir de renseignements ainsi obtenus.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>47.</Label><Text>Subsection 37(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization by Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner may authorize any person, subject to any terms and conditions that the Commissioner may specify, to exercise or perform on behalf of the Commissioner any power, duty or function of the Commissioner under this Act or any other Act.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48.</Label><Text>Subsection 39(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation de renseigner les organismes fédéraux</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sous réserve des dispositions de la législation fiscale et de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur la protection des renseignements personnels</XRefExternal> relatives à la confidentialité, le commissaire est tenu de fournir, aux ministères et organismes fédéraux pour le compte desquels l’Agence applique un programme ou exerce une activité, l’information nécessaire à l’évaluation du programme ou de l’activité et à l’élaboration des orientations correspondantes.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49.</Label><Text>Subsection 40(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation de renseigner les gouvernements provinciaux</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sous réserve des dispositions de la législation fiscale et de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur la protection des renseignements personnels</XRefExternal> relatives à la confidentialité, le commissaire est tenu de fournir aux gouvernements provinciaux pour le compte desquels l’Agence applique un programme, administre une taxe ou un impôt ou exerce une activité, l’information nécessaire à l’évaluation du programme, de la taxe, de l’impôt ou de l’activité et à l’élaboration des orientations correspondantes.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50.</Label><Text>Subsection 60(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Ne constituent pas des recettes d’exploitation les taxes, impôts, droits, pénalités et intérêts perçus sous le régime de la législation fiscale ou d’une loi provinciale, ni les sommes perçues pour le compte d’un ministère, gouvernement ou organisme public.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51.</Label><Text>Subsection 63(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements to administer a tax</MarginalNote><Label>63.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agency may enter into or amend an agreement with a provincial, territorial or aboriginal government to administer a tax or other fiscal measure if the agreement is in accordance with guidelines relating to agreements of that kind established jointly by the Minister and the Minister of Finance.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52.</Label><Text>Section 186 of the Act and the heading before it are repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian Food Inspection Agency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>53.</Label><Text>Section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Food Inspection Agency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Role of Canada Border Services Agency</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Canada Border Services Agency is responsible for the enforcement of the program legislation referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition “program legislation” in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> as that program legislation relates to the delivery of passenger and initial import inspection services performed at airports and other Canadian border points other than import service centres.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 47 (4th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canadian International Trade Tribunal Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>54.</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian International Trade Tribunal Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>président</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> means the President of the Canada Border Services Agency appointed under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>55.</Label><Text>Every reference to the “Commissioner of Customs and Revenue” or the “Commissioner” in the following provisions of the Act is replaced by a reference to the “President”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 26(4) and (5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 28(1) and (2); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 49(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>56.</Label><Text>Subsections 2(1), 26(4) and (5) and 28(1) and (2) and paragraph 49(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian International Trade Tribunal Act</XRefExternal>, as amended by sections <XRefInternal>54</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>55</XRefInternal> of this Act, apply to goods of a NAFTA country, as defined in subsection 2(2) of that Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 31</MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Citizenship and Immigration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>57.</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Citizenship and Immigration Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The powers, duties and functions of the Minister extend to and include all matters over which Parliament has jurisdiction relating to citizenship and immigration and that are not by law assigned to any other department, board or agency of the Government of Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 22, s. 324</MarginalNote><Label>58.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>peace officer</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an officer within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, or a person having the powers of such an officer, when performing any duty in the administration of any of those Acts,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an officer authorized under subsection 138(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 2(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>justice system participant</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is amended by replacing subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ix) with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>an employee of the Canada Revenue Agency who is involved in the investigation of an offence under an Act of Parliament,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ix.1)</Label><Text>an employee of the Canada Border Services Agency who is involved in the investigation of an offence under an Act of Parliament,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-51</MarginalNote><TitleText>Cultural Property Export and Import Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 121</MarginalNote><Label>59.</Label><Text>Section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cultural Property Export and Import Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of permit officers</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Minister, with the approval of the Solicitor General of Canada, may designate any persons or classes of persons employed by the Canada Border Services Agency as permit officers to receive applications for export permits and to issue export permits under this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Customs Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 123(2)</MarginalNote><Label>60.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 1(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Border Services Agency;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means, except in Part V.1, the Solicitor General of Canada;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>président</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> means the President of the Canada Border Services Agency appointed under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 1(4)(F)</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions of President</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any power, duty or function of the President under this Act may be exercised or performed by any person, or by any officer within a class of officers, authorized by the President to do so and, if so exercised or performed, is deemed to have been exercised or performed by the President.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister may authorize a person employed by the Canada Revenue Agency, or a class of those persons, to exercise powers or perform duties of the Minister, including any judicial or quasi-judicial powers or duties of the Minister, under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation by Minister of National Revenue</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister of National Revenue may authorize a person employed by the Canada Revenue Agency or the Agency, or a class of those persons, to exercise powers or perform duties of that Minister, including any judicial or quasi-judicial powers or duties of that Minister, under this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>61.</Label><Text>Subsection 3.3(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Waiver of penalty or interest</MarginalNote><Label>3.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except with respect to the collection of any debt due to Her Majesty under Part V.1, the Minister or any officer designated by the President for the purposes of this section may at any time waive or cancel all or any portion of any penalty or interest otherwise payable by a person under this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 2(1)</MarginalNote><Label>62.</Label><Text>Subsection 3.4(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Additional security</MarginalNote><Label>3.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where security has been given to the Minister by a person under a provision of this Act and the Minister or any officer (in this section referred to as a “designated officer”) designated by the President for the purposes of this section determines that the security that has been given is no longer adequate, the Minister or a designated officer may, by notice served personally or by registered or certified mail, require additional security to be given by or on behalf of the person within such reasonable time as may be stipulated in the notice.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 5(1)</MarginalNote><Label>63.</Label><Text>Subsection 32(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorization to account</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Minister or an officer designated by the President for the purposes of this subsection may authorize any person not resident in Canada to account for goods under this section, in such circumstances and under such conditions as may be prescribed, in lieu of the importer or owner of those goods.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>64.</Label><Text>Section 33.2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Notice requiring accounting</MarginalNote><Label>33.2</Label><Text>The Minister or any officer designated by the President for the purposes of this section may, by notice served personally or by registered or certified mail, require any person to account, within such reasonable time as may be stipulated in the notice, in the manner described in paragraph 32(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), for any goods as may be designated in the notice.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>65.</Label><Text>Section 33.5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Notice requiring payment</MarginalNote><Label>33.5</Label><Text>The Minister or any officer designated by the President for the purposes of this section may, by notice served personally or by registered or certified mail, require any person to pay any amount owing as duties, within such reasonable time as may be stipulated in the notice, on any goods as may be designated in the notice.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 7(1)</MarginalNote><Label>66.</Label><Text>Subsection 33.7(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Extension of time</MarginalNote><Label>33.7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister or any officer designated by the President for the purposes of this section may at any time extend in writing the time prescribed by the regulations made under this Part for the accounting of goods or the payment of any amount owing as duties.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 44, s. 83</MarginalNote><Label>67.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 35.02(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice requiring marking or compliance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister or any officer designated by the President for the purposes of this section may, by notice served personally or by registered mail, require any person</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 32</MarginalNote><Label>68.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 42(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inspections</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer, or an officer within a class of officers, designated by the President for the purposes of this section, may at all reasonable times, for any purpose related to the administration or enforcement of this Act,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 33</MarginalNote><Label>69.</Label><Text>Section 42.01 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Methods of verification</MarginalNote><Label>42.01</Label><Text>An officer, or an officer within a class of officers, designated by the President for the purposes of this section may conduct a verification of origin (other than a verification of origin referred to in section 42.1), verification of tariff classification or verification of value for duty in respect of imported goods in the manner that is prescribed and may for that purpose at all reasonable times enter any prescribed premises.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 14, s. 38</MarginalNote><Label>70.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 42.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Methods of verification</MarginalNote><Label>42.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any officer, or any officer within a class of officers, designated by the President for the purposes of this section, or any person, or any person within a class of persons, designated by the President to act on behalf of such an officer, may, subject to the prescribed conditions,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 36</MarginalNote><Label>71.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 43.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Advance rulings</MarginalNote><Label>43.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any officer, or any officer within a class of officers, designated by the President for the purposes of this section shall, before goods are imported, on application by any member of a prescribed class that is made within the prescribed time, in the prescribed manner and in the prescribed form containing the prescribed information, give an advance ruling with respect to</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 39(1)</MarginalNote><Label>72.</Label><Text>Subsection 57.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Marking determination</MarginalNote><Label>57.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any officer, or any officer within a class of officers, designated by the President for the purposes of this section may, at or before the time goods imported from a NAFTA country are accounted for under subsection 32(1), (3) or (5), in the prescribed manner and subject to the prescribed conditions, make a determination as to whether the goods have been marked in the manner referred to in section 35.01.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36, s. 166</MarginalNote><Label>73.</Label><Text>Subsection 58(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Determination by officer</MarginalNote><Label>58.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any officer, or any officer within a class of officers, designated by the President for the purposes of this section, may determine the origin, tariff classification and value for duty of imported goods at or before the time they are accounted for under subsection 32(1), (3) or (5).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 41(1)</MarginalNote><Label>74.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 59(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Re-determina- tion or further re-determination</MarginalNote><Label>59.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An officer, or any officer within a class of officers, designated by the President for the purposes of this section may</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>75.</Label><Text>Section 97.21 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner of Revenue appointed under section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of National Revenue.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>76.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 97.21:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Ancillary Powers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Ancillary powers</MarginalNote><Label>97.211</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, for the purposes of administering or enforcing this Part, exercise any of the following powers that are necessary for the collection of debts due to Her Majesty under this Part:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the powers provided for in paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition “prescribed” in subsection 2(1) as well as those provided for in subsections 3.3(1) and (2), 43(1) and 115(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other powers that are conferred under any provision of this Act that is specified by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Minister and the Solicitor General of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made for the purpose of subsection (1) must be published in Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> as soon as practicable after it is made.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 58(1)</MarginalNote><Label>77.</Label><Text>Subsection 97.22(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amounts demanded</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any amount of money demanded under paragraph 133(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (1.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and any interest payable under subsection 133(7), from and after the time notice is served under subsection 131(2), is a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada from the person who requested the decision and the person shall pay the amount so demanded or, if the person appeals the decision of the Solicitor General of Canada under section 135, give security satisfactory to that Minister.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 58(1)</MarginalNote><Label>78.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 97.34(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal to Federal Court</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person has appealed a decision of the Solicitor General of Canada to the Federal Court under section 97.23 or 135, the Minister must not take any action described in subsection (1) to collect the amount in controversy before the date of the decision of the Court or the day on which the person discontinues the appeal.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 58(1); 2002, c. 8, s. 193</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 97.34(4) and (5) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a person has made a request under section 60 or 129 or has appealed under section 67 or 68 and the person agrees in writing with the Solicitor General of Canada to delay proceedings on the request or appeal, as the case may be, until judgment has been given in another action before the Federal Court, the Canadian International Trade Tribunal or the Supreme Court of Canada, in which action the issue is the same or substantially the same as that raised in the request or appeal of the person, the Minister may take any of the actions described in subsection (1) for the purpose of collecting the amount payable, or a part of the amount payable, determined in a manner consistent with the decision or judgment in the other action at any time after the Solicitor General of Canada notifies the person in writing that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the decision of the Canadian International Trade Tribunal or Federal Court in that action has been mailed to the Solicitor General of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>judgment has been pronounced by the Federal Court of Appeal in that action; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>judgment has been delivered by the Supreme Court of Canada in that action.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of taking security</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister must not, for the purpose of collecting an amount payable, or a part of an amount payable, under this Act, take any of the actions described in subsection (1) if a person has given security to the Solicitor General of Canada when requesting or appealing from a decision of that Minister or the President.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 58(1)</MarginalNote><Label>79.</Label><Text>Subsection 97.5(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>How application made</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The application must be made by delivering or mailing the application and a copy of the notice of objection to the Chief of Appeals in a Tax Services Office or Taxation Centre of the Canada Revenue Agency.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 61</MarginalNote><Label>80.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>customs information</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 107(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>relates to one or more persons and is obtained by or on behalf of</Text></Paragraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Minister for the purposes of this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Minister of National Revenue for the purposes of the collection of debts due to Her Majesty under Part V.1;</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 61, c. 41, s. 121</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 107(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorized use of customs information by official</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An official may use customs information</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the purposes of administering or enforcing this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Imports Measures Act</XRefExternal> or Part 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> or for any purpose set out in subsection (4), (5) or (7);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the purposes of exercising the powers or performing the duties and functions of the Solicitor General of Canada under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, including establishing a person’s identity or determining their inadmissibility; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for the purposes of any Act or instrument made under it, or any part of such an Act or instrument, that the Governor in Council or Parliament authorizes the Minister, the Agency, the President or an employee of the Agency to enforce, including the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Agricultural Prod­ucts Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Feeds Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fertilizers Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fish Inspection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Health of Animals Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Meat Inspection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Plant Protection Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seeds Act.</XRefExternal></Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 61, c. 41, s. 121</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 107(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may reasonably be regarded as necessary solely for a purpose relating to the administration or enforcement of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> or Part 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> by an official of the Agency;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may reasonably be regarded as necessary solely for a purpose relating to the enforcement of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Agricultural Products Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Feeds Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fertilizers Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fish Inspection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Health of Animals Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Meat Inspection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Plant Protection Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seeds Act</XRefExternal> by an official of the Agency;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may reasonably be regarded as necessary solely for a purpose relating to the administration or enforcement of Part V.1 by an official or a class of officials of the Canada Revenue Agency designated by the Minister of National Revenue;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may reasonably be regarded as necessary solely for a purpose relating to the administration or enforcement of this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export and Import Permits Act</XRefExternal> by a member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 107(5) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official of the Canada Revenue Agency solely for a purpose relating to the administration or enforcement of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 107(5) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency for the purpose of administering or enforcing any Act referred to in section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Food Inspection Agency Act</XRefExternal> if the information relates to the import, export or in-transit movement of goods into or out of Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 61</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 107(12) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appeal from order to disclose customs information</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>An order or direction that is made in the course of or in connection with any legal proceeding and that requires an official to give or produce evidence relating to customs information may, by notice served on all interested parties, be immediately appealed by the Minister or the Minister of National Revenue, as the case may be, or by the person against whom the order or direction is made</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 68</MarginalNote><Label>81.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 127.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Corrective measures</MarginalNote><Label>127.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister, or any officer des­ignated by the President for the purposes of this section, may cancel a seizure made under section 110, cancel or reduce a penalty assessed under section 109.3 or an amount demanded under section 124 or refund an amount received under any of sections 117 to 119 within thirty days after the seizure, assessment or demand, if</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 80</MarginalNote><Label>82.</Label><Text>Section 149.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Proof of no appeal</MarginalNote><Label>149.1</Label><Text>An affidavit of an officer, sworn before a commissioner or other person authorized to take affidavits, setting out that the officer has charge of the appropriate records and has knowledge of the practice of the Agency or the Canada Revenue Agency, as the case may be, and that an examination of the records shows that a notice of assessment under Part V.1 was mailed or otherwise sent to a person under this Act and that, after careful examination and search of the records, the officer has been unable to find that a notice of objection or of appeal from the assessment was received within the time allowed for the notice, is evidence of the statements contained in the affidavit.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 7, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>83.</Label><Text>Subsection 163.4(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Designation by President</MarginalNote><Label>163.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President may designate any officer for the purposes of this Part and shall provide the officer with a certificate of designation.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>84.</Label><Text>Every reference to the <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in the following provisions of the Act is replaced by a reference to the <DefinedTermEn>Solicitor General of Canada</DefinedTermEn>:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 97.22(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 97.23; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 97.27.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>85.</Label><Text>Every reference to <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner’s</DefinedTermEn> in the following provisions of the Act is replaced by a reference to <DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>President’s</DefinedTermEn>, respectively:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the heading before section 60;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 60(3) to (5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 60.1(1) and (3) to (5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 60.2(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 61(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 67(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 67.1(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 68(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 69(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 70(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 97.34(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 114(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 128;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 130(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 137; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 141(1).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-53</MarginalNote><TitleText>Customs and Excise Offshore Application Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 129(1)</MarginalNote><Label>86.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs and Excise Offshore Application Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Information and documentation</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may require from any person, within any reasonable time that the President stipulates, the production of any book, record, writing or other document or any information that the President considers necessary for ascertaining whether any of sections 5 to 10 apply in any particular case.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 129(2)(E)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 4(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with a requirement of the President under subsection (1) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 36</MarginalNote><TitleText>Customs Tariff</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 130</MarginalNote><Label>87.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 68(3) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application to goods in transit</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may relieve goods from payment of a surtax imposed by an order under subsection (1) if the President is of the opinion that</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>88.</Label><Text>Paragraph 108(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in respect of goods of tariff item No. 9993.00.00, when the goods are destroyed in the manner that the Solicitor General of Canada directs or the destruction is certified by a customs officer or another person designated by the President of the Canada Border Services Agency;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>89.</Label><Text>Every reference to the “<Language xml:lang="fr">ministre du Revenu national</Language>” in the following provisions of the French version of the Act is replaced by a reference to the “<Language xml:lang="fr">solliciteur général du Canada</Language>”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 102(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 111(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 113(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 119.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 23</MarginalNote><TitleText>Employment Insurance Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 133</MarginalNote><Label>90.</Label><Text>Subsection 102(13) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>Every document appearing to be an order, direction, demand, notice, certificate, requirement, decision, assessment, discharge of mortgage, release of hypothec or other document executed under, or in the course of the administration or enforcement of, this Part over the name in writing of the Minister, the Deputy Minister of National Revenue, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner of Revenue or an officer authorized to exercise the powers or perform the duties of the Minister under this Part, is deemed to be a document signed, made and issued by the Minister, the Deputy Minister, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner of Revenue or the officer unless it has been called into question by the Minister or by a person acting for the Minister or for Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-14</MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.), s. 213(2) (Sch. II, item 5(F)); 1999, c. 17, s. 139(5)</MarginalNote><Label>91.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>collector</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>collector</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>receveur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>collector</DefinedTermEn> means every officer of excise who is appointed to collect the duties imposed by this Act in any defined district or excise division;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner of Revenue appointed under section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 22</MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Act, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>92.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>officer</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Revenue Agency continued by subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner of Revenue appointed under section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>officer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>préposé</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>officer</DefinedTermEn> means, except in sections 167, 226 and 296,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who is appointed or employed in the administration or enforcement of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a member of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or a member of a police force designated under subsection 10(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with respect to imported goods that have not been released under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, an officer as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>93.</Label><Text>Section 9 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Solicitor General of Canada may authorize a designated officer or agent, or a class of officers or agents, to exercise powers and perform duties of that Minister under section 68.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>94.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 68(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Availability and sampling of imported DA and SDA</MarginalNote><Label>68.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any person who imports a product that is reported under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> as being denatured alcohol or specially denatured alcohol shall make the product available for sampling and the product is required to be sampled by the Solicitor General of Canada before it is released under that Act.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 68(3) and (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister may waive</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Solicitor General of Canada may at any time waive the requirement to sample an imported product under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fees</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Solicitor General of Canada may fix fees to be paid by the importer of the product but those fees must not exceed an amount determined by that Minister to be the costs to Her Majesty in respect of the sampling and testing.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>95.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 188(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation on refunding overpayments</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An overpayment of duty payable for a fiscal month of a person and interest on the overpayment shall not be applied under paragraph (4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or refunded under paragraph (4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) unless the person has, before the day on which notice of the assessment is sent to the person, filed all returns or other records that the person was required to file with</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister under this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Solicitor General of Canada under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 188(7)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the person has, before the day on which notice of the assessment is sent to him or her, filed all returns or other records that the person was required to file</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>with the Minister under this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>with the Solicitor General of Canada under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act.</XRefExternal></Text></Clause></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>96.</Label><Text>Subsection 189(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A refund shall not be paid until the person has filed with the Minister or the Solicitor General of Canada, all returns or other records that are required to be filed under this Act, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>97.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>confidential information</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 211(1) of the Act is amended by striking out the word “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and by replacing paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) with the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>obtained by or on behalf of the Solicitor General of Canada for the purposes of section 68; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prepared from information referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>98.</Label><Text>Subsection 301(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Every document purporting to have been executed under or in the course of the administration or enforcement of this Act over the name in writing of the Minister, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner or an officer authorized to exercise the powers or perform the duties of the Minister under this Act is deemed to be a document signed, made and issued by the Minister, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner or the officer, unless it has been called into question by the Minister or a person acting for the Minister or for Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents: Canada Border Services Agency</MarginalNote><Label>(8.1)</Label><Text>Every document purporting to have been executed under or in the course of the administration or enforcement of this Act over the name in writing of the Solicitor General of Canada, the President of the Canada Border Services Agency or an officer authorized to exercise the powers or perform the duties of that Minister under this Act is deemed to be a document signed, made and issued by that Minister, the President or the officer, unless it has been called into question by that Minister or a person acting for that Minister or for Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-15</MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 145(3)</MarginalNote><Label>99.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Revenue Agency continued by subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner of Revenue appointed under section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>100.</Label><Text>Subsection 59(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Delegation of powers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may authorize a designated officer or agent, or officer or agent of a designated class of officers or agents, to exercise powers or perform duties of the Minister, including judicial or quasi-judicial powers or duties, under this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 7 (2nd Supp.), s. 34(1); 1995, c. 41, s. 114; 2002, c. 22, s. 381(2)</MarginalNote><Label>101.</Label><Text>Subsections 70(2) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Specific sum</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, under regulations of the Governor in Council, pay a specific sum in lieu of a drawback under subsection (1) in any case where a specific sum in lieu of a drawback of duties is granted under section 117 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Drawback on imported goods</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>On application, the Solicitor General of Canada may, under section 113 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, grant a drawback of the tax imposed under Part III and paid on or in respect of goods imported into Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application for drawback</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An application for a drawback under subsection (1) shall be made in the prescribed form and contain the prescribed information and shall be filed with the Minister within such time and in such manner as the Governor in Council may, by regulation, prescribe.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No drawback shall be granted under subsection (1) unless the person applying for the drawback provides such evidence in support of the application as the Minister may require.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 7 (2nd Supp.), s. 50(1); 1999, c. 17, par. 156(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>102.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 105(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>An affidavit of an officer of the Canada Border Services Agency, sworn before a commissioner or other person authorized to take affidavits, setting out</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the officer has charge of the appropriate records, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that a document annexed to the affidavit is a document or a true copy of a document, or a print-out of an electronic document, made by or on behalf of the Solicitor General of Canada or a person exercising the powers of that Minister or by or on behalf of a person,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>is evidence of the nature and contents of the document.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of no objection</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An affidavit of an officer of the Agency or the Canada Border Services Agency, sworn before a commissioner or other person authorized to take affidavits, setting out</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the officer has charge of the appropriate records,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that the officer has knowledge of the practice of the Agency or the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that an examination of the records shows that a notice of determination or a notice of assessment was sent to a person on a named day pursuant to this Act, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that after careful examination of the records the officer was unable to find that a notice of objection to the determination or assessment was received within the time limited for it,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>is evidence of the statements contained in the affidavit.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 7(2nd Supp.), s. 50(1); 1999, c. 17, par. 156(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 105(9) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Presumption</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Where evidence is offered under this section by an affidavit from which it appears that the person making the affidavit is an officer of the Agency or the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, it is not necessary to prove his or her signature or that the person is such an officer, nor is it necessary to prove the signature or official character of the person before whom the affidavit was sworn.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 17, s. 235</MarginalNote><Label>103.</Label><Text>Subsection 106.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Presumption</MarginalNote><Label>106.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every document purporting to be an order, direction, notice, certificate, requirement, decision, determination, assessment, discharge of mortgage or acquittance of a hypothecary claim or other document and purporting to have been executed under, or in the course of the administration or enforcement of, this Act or the regulations over the name in writing of the Minister, the Deputy Minister of National Revenue, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner or an officer authorized by the Minister to exercise his or her powers or perform his or her duties or functions under this Act is deemed to be a document signed, made and issued by the Minister, Deputy Minister, Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner or the officer, unless called into question by the Minister or by some person acting for the Minister or Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Presumption</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Every document purporting to be an order, a direction, a notice, a certificate, a requirement, a decision, a determination, an assessment, a discharge of mortgage or an acquittance of a hypothecary claim or other document and purporting to have been executed under, or in the course of the administration or enforcement of, this Act or the regulations over the name in writing of the Solicitor General of Canada, the President of the Canada Border Services Agency or an officer authorized by that Minister to exercise his or her powers or perform his or her duties or functions under this Act is deemed to be a document signed, made and issued by that Minister, the President or the officer, unless called into question by that Minister or by some person acting for that Minister or Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 152(2)</MarginalNote><Label>104.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 123(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Canada Revenue Agency continued by subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner of Revenue appointed under section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 27, s. 81(1)</MarginalNote><Label>105.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 215.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Solicitor General of Canada has, under any of sections 73, 74 and 76 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, granted an abatement or refund of all or part of the duties paid on the goods,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 27, s. 81(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 215.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the goods had been subject to duties under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the Solicitor General of Canada would, because of any of the circumstances described in paragraph 73(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or 74(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or subsection 76(1) of that Act, have granted, under section 73, 74 or 76 of that Act, an abatement or refund of all or part of the duties paid on the goods,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 10, s. 41.1(1); 1999, c. 17, par. 155(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>106.</Label><Text>Subsection 216(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of Part IX and <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal> </MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The provisions of this Part and of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Tax Court of Canada Act</XRefExternal> that apply to an appeal taken under section 302 apply, with such modifications as the circumstances require, to an appeal taken under subsection 67(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> from a decision of the President of the Canada Border Services Agency made under section 60 or 61 of that Act in a determination of the tax status of goods as if the decision of the President were a confirmation of an assessment or a reassessment made by the Minister under subsection 301(3) or (4) as a consequence of a notice of objection filed under subsection 301(1.1) by the person to whom the President is required to give notice under section 60 or 61 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, as the case may be, of the decision.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 45, s. 12(1); 1999, c. 17, s. 154, par. 156(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>107.</Label><Text>Subsections 335(6) to (8) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>An affidavit of an officer of the Canada Border Services Agency, sworn before a commissioner or other person authorized to take affidavits, setting out that the officer has charge of the appropriate records and that a document annexed to the affidavit is a document or a true copy of a document, or a printout of an electronic document, made by or on behalf of the Solicitor General of Canada or a person exercising the powers of that Minister or by or on behalf of a person, is evidence of the nature and contents of the document.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of no appeal</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An affidavit of an officer of the Agency or the Canada Border Services Agency, sworn before a commissioner or other person authorized to take affidavits, setting out that the officer has charge of the appropriate records and has knowledge of the practice of the Agency or the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, and that an examination of the records shows that a notice of assessment was mailed or otherwise sent to a person on a particular day under this Part and that, after careful examination and search of the records, the officer has been unable to find that a notice of objection or of appeal from the assessment, as the case may be, was received within the time allowed, is evidence of the statements contained in the affidavit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Presumption</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Where evidence is offered under this section by an affidavit from which it appears that the person making the affidavit is an officer of the Agency or the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, it is not necessary to prove the signature of the person or that the person is such an officer, nor is it necessary to prove the signature or official character of the person before whom the affidavit was sworn.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Every document purporting to have been executed under or in the course of the administration or enforcement of this Part over the name in writing of the Minister, the Deputy Minister of National Revenue, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner or an officer authorized to exercise the powers or perform the duties of the Minister under this Part, shall be deemed to be a document signed, made and issued by the Minister, the Deputy Minister, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner or the officer, unless it has been called in question by the Minister or a person acting for the Minister or for Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(8.1)</Label><Text>Every document purporting to have been executed under or in the course of the administration or enforcement of this Part over the name in writing of the Solicitor General of Canada or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, or an officer authorized to exercise the powers or perform the duties of that Minister under this Part, shall be deemed to be a document signed, made and issued by that Minister, the President or the officer, unless it has been called in question by that Minister or a person acting for that Minister or for Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 41(1)</MarginalNote><Label>108.</Label><Text>Section 1 of Part X of Schedule VI to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><Label>1.</Label><Text>A supply made by Canada Post Corporation of a service under an agreement made with the Solicitor General of Canada under subsection 147.1(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 10, s. 254</MarginalNote><Label>109.</Label><Text>Section 4 of Part I of Schedule X to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><Label>4.</Label><Text>Arms, military stores and munitions of war brought into a participating province by the Government of Canada in replacement of or in anticipation or actual exchange for similar goods loaned to or exchanged or to be exchanged with the governments of a foreign country designated by the Governor in Council under heading No. 98.10 of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, under such regulations as the Solicitor General of Canada may make for purposes of heading No. 98.11 of that Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 10, s. 254</MarginalNote><Label>110.</Label><Text>Section 6 of Part I of Schedule X to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><Label>6.</Label><Text>Property, (other than advertising matter, tobacco or an alcoholic beverage) that is a casual donation sent by a person in a non-participating province to a person in a participating province, or brought into a particular participating province by a person who is not resident in the participating provinces as a gift to a person in that participating province, where the fair market value of the property does not exceed $60, under such regulations as the Solicitor General of Canada may make for purposes of heading No. 98.16 of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 4 (2nd Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 31, s. 9(F)</MarginalNote><Label>111.</Label><Text>Section 15 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Information banks that may be searched</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>The information banks that may be searched under this Part are the information banks designated by the regulations from among the information banks controlled by the Department of Human Resources Development, the Canada Revenue Agency and the Canada Employment Insurance Commission.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-9</MarginalNote><TitleText>Feeds Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 46</MarginalNote><Label>112.</Label><Text>Subsection 6(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Feeds Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may designate inspectors under paragraph 9(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> for the purposes of enforcing this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Inspectors shall be given certificates in a form established by the President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, attesting to their designation and, on entering any place under subsection 7(1), an inspector shall, if so required, produce the certificate to the person in charge of that place.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-10</MarginalNote><TitleText>Fertilizers Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 49</MarginalNote><Label>113.</Label><Text>Subsection 6(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fertilizers Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may designate inspectors under paragraph 9(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> for the purposes of enforcing this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Inspectors shall be given certificates in a form established by the President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, attesting to their designation and, on entering any place under subsection 7(1), an inspector shall, if so required, produce the certificate to the person in charge of that place.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>Financial Administration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>SOR/2003-431</MarginalNote><Label>114.</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out, in column I, the reference to</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>and the corresponding reference in column II to the Appropriate Minister for that Agency.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>115.</Label><Text>Schedule II to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-12</MarginalNote><TitleText>Fish Inspection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 60</MarginalNote><Label>116.</Label><Text>Subsection 17(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fish Inspection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may designate inspectors under paragraph 9(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> for the purposes of enforcing this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Inspectors shall be given certificates in a form established by the President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, attesting to their designation and, on entering any place under subsection 4(1), an inspector shall, if so required, produce the certificate to the person in charge of that place.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 21</MarginalNote><TitleText>Health of Animals Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 68</MarginalNote><Label>117.</Label><Text>Subsection 32(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Health of Animals Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may designate inspectors under paragraph 9(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> for the purposes of enforcing this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Inspectors, officers and veterinary inspectors shall be given certificates in a form established by the President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, attesting to their designation and, on entering any place under this Act, an inspector, officer or veterinary inspector shall show the certificate to the person in charge of the place if the person requests proof of the designation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 27</MarginalNote><TitleText>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>118.</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Minister of Citizenship and Immigration </MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration is responsible for the administration of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Solicitor General of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> is responsible for the administration of this Act as it relates to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>examinations at ports of entry;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the enforcement of this Act, including arrest, detention and removal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the establishment of policies respecting the enforcement of this Act and inadmissibility on grounds of security, organized criminality or violating human or international rights; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>determinations under any of subsections 34(2), 35(2) and 37(2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Specification</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (1) and (2), the Governor in Council may specify</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>which Minister referred to in subsections (1) and (2) shall be the Minister for the purposes of any provision of this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that both Ministers may be the Minister for the purposes of any provision of this Act and the circumstances under which each Minister shall be the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any order made under subsection (3) must be published in Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 72</MarginalNote><Label>119.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 150.1(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the collection, retention, use, disclosure and disposal of information for the purposes of this Act or for the purposes of program legislation as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the disclosure of information for the purposes of national security, the defence of Canada or the conduct of international affairs, including the implementation of an agreement or arrangement entered into under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Citizenship and Immigration Act</XRefExternal> or section 13 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2004, c. 15, s. 72</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 150.1(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under subsection (1) may include conditions under which the collection, retention, use, disposal and disclosure may be made.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>120.</Label><Text>Subsection 244(13) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of documents</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>Every document purporting to have been executed under, or in the course of the administration or enforcement of, this Act over the name in writing of the Minister, the Deputy Minister of National Revenue, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner of Revenue or an officer authorized to exercise a power or perform a duty of the Minister under this Act is deemed to have been signed, made and issued by the Minister, the Deputy Minister, the Commissioner of Customs and Revenue, the Commissioner of Revenue or the officer unless it has been called in question by the Minister or by a person acting for the Minister or Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 25 (1st Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Meat Inspection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 72</MarginalNote><Label>121.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Meat Inspection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>inspecteur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn> means a person designated as an inspector pursuant to subsection 12(1) or (1.1);</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 73</MarginalNote><Label>122.</Label><Text>Subsection 12(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may designate inspectors under paragraph 9(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> for the purposes of enforcing this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Inspectors shall be given certificates in a form established by the President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, attesting to their designation and, on entering any place or vehicle referred to in subsection 13(1), an inspector shall, if so required, produce the certificate to the person in charge of that place or vehicle.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 22</MarginalNote><TitleText>Plant Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 82</MarginalNote><Label>123.</Label><Text>Subsection 21(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Plant Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may designate inspectors under paragraph 9(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> for the purposes of enforcing this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Inspectors shall be given certificates in a form established by the President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, attesting to their designation and, on entering any place under this Act, an inspector shall show the certificate to the person in charge of the place if the person requests proof of the inspector’s designation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 17; 2001, c. 41, s. 48</MarginalNote><TitleText>Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>124.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means, in relation to sections 25 to 39, the Solicitor General of Canada and, in relation to any other provision of this Act, the member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada who is designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of that provision.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following definition in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>président</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> means the President of the Canada Border Services Agency appointed under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>125.</Label><Text>Paragraph 38(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>information set out in reports made under subsection 12(1) in respect of currency or monetary instruments imported into Canada from that state will be provided to a department, institution or agency of that state that has powers and duties similar to those of the Canada Border Services Agency in respect of the reporting of currency or monetary instruments; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>126.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 55(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Canada Revenue Agency, if the Centre also determines that the information is relevant to an offence of evading or attempting to evade paying taxes or duties imposed under an Act of Parliament administered by the Minister of National Revenue;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Canada Border Services Agency, if the Centre also determines that the information is relevant to an offence of evading or attempting to evade paying taxes or duties imposed under an Act of Parliament administered by the Agency; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 123(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 55(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Canada Border Services Agency, if the Centre also determines that the information would promote the objective set out in paragraph 3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and is relevant to determining whether a person is a person described in sections 34 to 42 of that Act or to an offence under any of sections 117 to 119, 126 or 127 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 55 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) does not apply in respect of an offence relating to taxes or duties imposed under a prescribed Act or a prescribed portion of an Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>127.</Label><Text>Every reference to <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner’s</DefinedTermEn> in the following provisions of the Act is replaced by a reference to <DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>President’s</DefinedTermEn>, respectively:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 20;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 26(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 31;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 32(3) and (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 35(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 39(2).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-36</MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Service Superannuation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>128.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. R-9</MarginalNote><TitleText>Royal Canadian Mint Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>129.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Royal Canadian Mint Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>130.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 2:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>DESIGNATION OF MINISTER</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Power of Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>2.1</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may designate a member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada to be the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-8</MarginalNote><TitleText>Seeds Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 6, s. 88</MarginalNote><Label>131.</Label><Text>Subsection 5(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seeds Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The President of the Canada Border Services Agency may designate inspectors under paragraph 9(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal> for the purposes of enforcing this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate to be produced</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Inspectors shall be given certificates in a form established by the President of the Canadian Food Inspection Agency or the President of the Canada Border Services Agency, as the case may be, attesting to their designation and, on entering any place under subsection 6(1), an inspector shall show the certificate to the person in charge of the place if the person requests proof of the inspector’s designation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-15</MarginalNote><TitleText>Special Import Measures Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 180(2)</MarginalNote><Label>132.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Solicitor General of Canada;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>président</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> means the President of the Canada Border Services Agency appointed under subsection <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Border Services Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17, s. 182</MarginalNote><Label>133.</Label><Text>Section 94 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Ruling binding</MarginalNote><Label>94.</Label><Text>A ruling given by the Tribunal on the question of who is the importer in Canada of any goods imported or to be imported into Canada is binding on the President, and on every person employed by the Canada Border Services Agency in the administration or enforcement of this Act, with respect to the particular goods in relation to which the ruling is given, unless the Tribunal is fraudulently misled or, in the case only of goods to be imported into Canada, material facts that are not available to the President at the time the Tribunal gives its ruling come to the President’s attention after it is given.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>134.</Label><Text>Every reference to <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner’s</DefinedTermEn> in the following provisions of the Act is replaced by a reference to <DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>President’s</DefinedTermEn>, respectively:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(iii) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>properly documented</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>undertaking</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>undertakings</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 2(7.3), (7.4) and (9);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 4(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 5(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs 6(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 7(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 8(1) to (2), (5) and (6);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 9.2(1) before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 9.21(1) before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of section 9.3 before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 10;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 12(2) and (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 13.2(1), (3) and (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 15(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs 16(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 16(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 17 to 20;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">s</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 25(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">t</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 29(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">u</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 30.2(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">v</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 30.3(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">w</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 30.4(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">x</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 31(1) and (6) to (8);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">y</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 31.1(1) to (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 32 to 39;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 41 to 41.2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 43(2) before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.3</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of section 46 after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.4</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 47(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.5</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 49 and 50;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.6</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 51 to 52;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.7</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 53;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.8</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 53.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.9</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 55(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.10</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the heading before section 56;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.11</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 57;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.12</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 58(1.1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.13</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 59(1) to (3.1) and (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.14</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 60(2) before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.15</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 61(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.16</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 62(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.17</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 76.01(1) and (6);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.18</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 76.02(1) and (5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.19</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 76.03(3) and (6) to (11);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.20</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 76.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.21</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>appropriate authority</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 77.01(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.22</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">f.1</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>definitive decision</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 77.01(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.23</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>appropriate authority</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 77.1(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.24</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">f.1</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>definitive decision</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 77.1(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.25</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 78(1) after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.26</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 78(3) to (5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.27</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 81(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.28</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 83 and 83.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.29</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 84(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.30</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 84(3) before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.31</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 84(3.1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.32</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 85 to 89;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.33</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs 91(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.34</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 91(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.35</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 95 and 96;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.36</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 96.1(1) to (3) and (6);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.37</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 96.11(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.38</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 96.2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.39</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs 96.4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">z.40</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraphs 97(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">k.3</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">k.4</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>135.</Label><Text>Every reference to <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in the following provisions of the English version of the Act is replaced by a reference to <DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn>:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 77.011(4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subparagraph 77.012(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 77.013(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 77.11(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subparagraph 77.12(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 77.13(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the heading before section 78;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 78(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 78(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 79(1) and (2); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 84(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>136.</Label><Text>Every reference to <DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr> in the following provisions of the French version of the Act is replaced by a reference to <DefinedTermFr>président</DefinedTermFr>:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 13.2(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 56(1.01);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 56(1.1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 77.021(2); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 77.21(2).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>137.</Label><Text>The provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted or amended by sections <XRefInternal>132</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>136</XRefInternal> and paragraph 145(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) of this Act, apply to goods of a NAFTA country, as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Terminology Changes</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>138.</Label><Text>Every reference to the “Canada Customs and Revenue Agency” in the following provisions is replaced by a reference to the “Canada Revenue Agency”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Auditor General Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 25(12),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 26.1(1) before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 27.2(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsection 41(6),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsection 103(3),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>paragraph 104.03(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>subsection 104.03(3);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 72(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Petroleum Resources Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 462.48(14) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 33(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cultural Property Export and Import Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 69(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 88(12),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 90(1) before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsection 93(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsection 102(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>subsections 102(5) to (11),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>subsection 102(18),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>section 122, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>paragraph 131(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>holiday</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>information bank director</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders</XRefExternal> and <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Farm Income Protection Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 41(2), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Schedule II;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 165(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 166.1(3),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 231.4(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsection 231.5(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>paragraph 237.1(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>subsection 244(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>subsections 244(5) to (11), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>subsection 244(19);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Schedule III to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 33.03(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Old Age Security Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>managerial or confidential position</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>Part II of Schedule I; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>139.</Label><Text>Every reference to the “Canada Customs and Revenue Agency” in the following provisions is replaced by a reference to the “Canada Border Services Agency”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 4.81(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Copyright Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 42.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph 38(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>140.</Label><Text>Every reference to the “Commissioner of Customs and Revenue” in the following provisions is replaced by a reference to the “Commissioner of Revenue”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Customs and Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in section 2, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 25;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 462.48(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 97(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 63 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Energy Administration Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 166.2(3),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsections 170(1) and (2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 220(1), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsections 232(5) to (7); and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Petroleum and Gas Revenue Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 19(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsections 22(2) and (3), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 29(1).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>141.</Label><Text>Every reference to the “Commissioner of Customs and Revenue” in the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> is replaced by a reference to the “President of the Canada Border Services Agency”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 134(1) and (2); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>142.</Label><Text>Every reference to the “Minister of National Revenue” in the following provisions is replaced by a reference to the “Solicitor General of Canada”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 4.81(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 4.81(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 40(1.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Post Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Coasting Trade Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 2(3),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 4(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 5, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsections 6(1) and (3);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition “Minister” in section 44.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Copyright Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 9,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 16(2.1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 18(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsection 19(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>section 88,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>paragraph 89(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>subsection 89(4),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>subsections 90(1) and (2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>section 91,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(x)</Label><Text>section 93,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>subsection 95(4),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xii)</Label><Text>the portion of section 99 before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xiii)</Label><Text>section 100,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xiv)</Label><Text>paragraph 101(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xv)</Label><Text>paragraph 102(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xvi)</Label><Text>subsection 105(2),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xvii)</Label><Text>subsections 106(1) and (3) to (5),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xviii)</Label><Text>the portion of section 108 before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xix)</Label><Text>subparagraph 108(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)(ii),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xx)</Label><Text>paragraph 109(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxi)</Label><Text>section 112,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxii)</Label><Text>paragraph 113(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxiii)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 113(4) before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxiv)</Label><Text>subsection 115(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxv)</Label><Text>section 117,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxvi)</Label><Text>paragraph 118(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxvii)</Label><Text>paragraph 118(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxviii)</Label><Text>section 125,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxix)</Label><Text>subsection 126(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxx)</Label><Text>sections 129 and 130,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxxi)</Label><Text>section 133,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxxii)</Label><Text>subsections 134(1) and (2), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(xxxiii)</Label><Text>the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 52 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 16(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Industry Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 472, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 596(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 25 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statistics Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition “Minister” in section 52 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Trade Marks Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 24 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Visiting Forces Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>143.</Label><Text>The reference to the “Minister of National Revenue” in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition “prescribed” in subsection 2(1) of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal> is replaced by a reference to the “Solicitor General of Canada”.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>144.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the definition <DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Labour Relations Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal>, comes into force before section 1 of this Act comes into force, then, on the day on which section 1 of this Act comes into force, subparagraph 138(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)(i) of this Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the definition <DefinedTermEn>managerial or confidential position</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Labour Relations Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal>, comes into force before section 1 of this Act comes into force, then, on the day on which section 1 of this Act comes into force, subparagraph 138(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)(ii) of this Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal> comes into force before section 1 of this Act comes into force, then, on the day on which section 1 of this Act comes into force, subparagraph 138(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)(iii) of this Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal> and the coming into force of section 1 of this Act,</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the reference in Schedule V to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> to the “Canada Customs and Revenue Agency” is replaced by a reference to the “Canada Revenue Agency”; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Schedule IV to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Canada Border Services Agency</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Agence des services frontaliers du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If section 1 of this Act comes into force before subsection 49(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal>, then, on the day on which section 1 of this Act comes into force, that subsection is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Legal officers</MarginalNote><Label>49.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the new Act, including any application under section 58 of the new Act, an employee who, on or after the day on which the definition “managerial or confidential position” in subsection 2(1) of that Act comes into force, is employed as a legal officer in the Department of Justice or the Canada Revenue Agency is deemed not to be included in any unit determined, in accordance with the former Act, to constitute a unit of employees appropriate for collective bargaining.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If section 1 of this Act comes into force before section 95 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal>, then, on the day on which section 1 of this Act comes into force, that section and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="3" type="amending"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>95.</Label><Text>Paragraph 16(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is employed on a full-time basis in the federal public administration or the public service of a province or territory.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 224 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal> and the coming into force of section 1 of this Act, subsection 10(3) of the English version of this Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed employment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The President and the Executive Vice-president are deemed to be employed in the public service for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> and to be employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 224 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal> and the coming into force of section 1 of this Act, a reference to the “public service of Canada” in the following provisions of the English version of this Act is replaced by a reference to “federal public administration”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>former agency</DefinedTermEn> in section <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>(1) and (2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If section 1 of this Act comes into force before section 224 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal>, then, on the day on which section 1 of this Act comes into force, paragraph 224(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) of that Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 21 and 66 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>If section 1 of this Act comes into force before section 229 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal>, then, on the day on which section 1 of this Act comes into force, that section and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="3" type="amending"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>229.</Label><Text>Subsection 55(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Mobility to departments</MarginalNote><Label>55.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of deployments or appointments made, or advertised internal appointment processes, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, employees of the Agency must be treated as if they were employees within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal> and had the rights of recourse provided by that Act.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-6</MarginalNote><Label>145.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill C-6, introduced in the 1st Session of the 38th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness Act</XRefExternal> (in this section, the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 1 of this Act and section 1 of the other Act, every reference to the “Solicitor General of Canada” in the following provisions is replaced by a reference to the “Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness”:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 30 of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cultural Property Import and Export Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>59</XRefInternal> of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>60</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 97.211(1), as enacted by section <XRefInternal>76</XRefInternal> of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 97.22(3), as enacted by section 77 of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>subsection 97.34(2), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>78</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsections 97.34(4) and (5), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>78</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>paragraph 107(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>80</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>subsection 97.22(2) and sections 97.23 and 97.27, as amended by section 84 of this Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 108(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), as enacted by section <XRefInternal>88</XRefInternal> of this Act, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the provisions referred to in section 89 of this Act, as amended by that section;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 9(3), as enacted by section 93 of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 68(1), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>94</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsections 68(3) and (4), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>94</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>paragraph 188(6)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), as enacted by subsection 95(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subparagraph 188(7)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>95</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>subsection 189(4), as enacted by section <XRefInternal>96</XRefInternal> of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>confidential information</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 211(1), as enacted by section 97 of this Act, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>subsection 301(8.1), as enacted by section <XRefInternal>98</XRefInternal> of this Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal>,</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 70(2.1) as enacted by section <XRefInternal>101</XRefInternal> of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 105(5.1), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>102</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 106.1(1.1), as enacted by section <XRefInternal>103</XRefInternal> of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>paragraph 215.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>105</XRefInternal>(1) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>paragraph 215.1(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>105</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>subsections 335(5.1) and (8.1), as enacted by section <XRefInternal>107</XRefInternal> of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>section 1 of Part X of Schedule VI, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>108</XRefInternal> of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>section 4 of Part I of Schedule X, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>109</XRefInternal> of this Act, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>section 6 of Part I of Schedule X, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>110</XRefInternal> of this Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>124</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Import Measures Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsection <XRefInternal>132</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the provisions referred to in section 142 of this Act, as amended by that section.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 1 of this Act and section 1 of the other Act, the reference to the “Solicitor General of Canada” in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition “prescribed” in subsection 2(1) of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>, as amended by section 143 of this Act, is replaced by a reference to the “Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 1 of this Act and section 1 of the other Act, every reference to the “<Language xml:lang="fr">solliciteur général du Canada</Language>” in the French version of the provisions referred to in section 89 is replaced by a reference to “ministre de la Sécurité publique et de la Protection civile”.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If it comes into force after section 114 of this Act, paragraph 34(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>) of the other Act is repealed on its coming into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-22</MarginalNote><Label>146.</Label><Text>If Bill C-22, introduced in the 1st Session of the 38th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Social Development Act</XRefExternal> (in this section, the “other Act”), receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of section 1 of this Act and section 2 of the other Act, section 15 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Information banks that may be searched</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>The information banks that may be searched under this Part are the information banks designated by the regulations from among the information banks controlled by the Department of Social Development, the Canada Revenue Agency and the Canada Employment Insurance Commission.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>147.</Label><Text>This Act, except for sections <XRefInternal>144</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>146</XRefInternal>, comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>