<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-3</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>38</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>53-54</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004-2005</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Shipping Act, the Canada Shipping Act, 2001, the Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act and the Oceans Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Shipping, Marine Conservation Areas and Oceans</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Shipping, Marine Conservation Areas and Oceans</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2005</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>29</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2005</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2004-10-6">90276</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment transfers powers, duties and functions from the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans to the Minister of Transport.</Text></Provision></Summary><?Pub Caret?><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-9</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA SHIPPING ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 31, s. 95</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Department</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Department</DefinedTermEn> </MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministère</DefinedTermFr> </MarginalNote><Text> <DefinedTermEn>Department</DefinedTermEn> means, except in Part VII, the Department of Transport;</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> </MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr> </MarginalNote><Text> <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means, except in Part VII, the Minister of Transport;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 16, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The heading before section 7 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Heading><TitleText>Responsabilité du ministre</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 16, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Role of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>Except as otherwise provided in this Act, the Minister is responsible for the administration of this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 385(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of rescue coordinators</MarginalNote><Label>385.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Fisheries and Oceans may designate persons, to be known as rescue coordinators, to organize search and rescue operations in Canadian waters and on the high seas off the coasts of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c.31, s. 96</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>Section 422 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Superintendence</MarginalNote><Label>422.</Label><Text>The Minister has, throughout Canada, the general superintendence of all matters relating to salvage, wrecks and receivers of wrecks and, subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Transportation Accident Investigation and Safety Board Act</XRefExternal>, shipping casualties.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before section 517:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>516.1</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Part.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Department</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministère</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Department</DefinedTermEn> means the Department of Fisheries and Oceans.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans.</Text></Definition></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Sections 518 and 519 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment of keepers, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>518.</Label><Text>The Minister may appoint in the manner authorized by law any keepers, superintendents and other officers that are necessary for the purposes of this Part.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>519.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting aids to navigation in Canadian waters; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the fines for any contravention of any regulation made under this section, and those fines may not be more than $200.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>519.1</Label><Text>The Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister, may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the government of Sable Island and of St. Paul Island, the duties of the resident keepers on those islands, the administration of relief to shipwrecked persons and their removal, the preservation and removal of shipwrecked property, the prevention of persons not authorized by the Minister from taking up residence on those islands and the general management of those islands; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the fines for any contravention of any regulation made under this section, and those fines may not be more than $200.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 6 (3rd Supp.), s. 78</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>The portion of section 562.15 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Clearance of ships to enter Canadian waters, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>562.15</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 6 (3rd Supp.), s. 78</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>The portion of section 562.16 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Vessel Traffic Services Zones</MarginalNote><Label>562.16</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, for the purpose of promoting safe and efficient navigation or environmental protection in Canadian waters or in any shipping safety control zone prescribed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Arctic Waters Pollution Prevention Act</XRefExternal>, make regulations</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 36, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> in section 654 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 36, s. 3</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>response organization</DefinedTermEn> in section 654 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>response organization</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>organisme d’intervention</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>response organization</DefinedTermEn> means any person or body in Canada in respect of which a certificate of designation is issued by the Minister under subsection 660.4(1);</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 36, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Section 660.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 36, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 660.10(1) to (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Advisory councils</MarginalNote><Label>660.10</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall establish one advisory council in respect of each geographic area: Pacific, Great Lakes and St. Lawrence River and Great Lakes Basin, Atlantic and Arctic.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other advisory councils</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may establish other advisory councils if he or she considers them necessary.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Members</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Each advisory council is composed of no more than seven members who reside in the geographic area in respect of which the advisory council is established, who are appointed to the advisory council by the Minister and who, in the opinion of the Minister, represent the various interests likely to be involved in matters referred to in sections 660.2 to 660.9.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 36, s. 6; 1996, c. 31, s. 102</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 660.10(6) and (7) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Members of each advisory council shall be paid, in connection with their work for the advisory council, the remuneration that may be fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Travel, living and other expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>Members of each advisory council are entitled to be reimbursed, in accordance with Treasury Board directives, the travel, living and other expenses incurred in connection with their work for the advisory council while absent, in the case of full-time members, from their ordinary place of work or, in the case of part-time members, from their ordinary place of residence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recommendations and response</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Each advisory council shall advise and may make recommendations to the Minister, and may report to any standing committee of either House of Parliament that normally considers matters relating to transportation or the environment, and shall receive a response to the report within 30 days or, if that House is not sitting, within 14 days after it resumes sitting.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 36, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Paragraph 660.11(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>review the operation of sections 660.2 to 660.10 and, in particular, the capability of the response organizations to meet the arrangements that ships and operators of oil handling facilities are required to have, as set out in paragraphs 660.2(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 36, s. 16</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>Subsection 678(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Minister may take necessary measures</MarginalNote><Label>678.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans believes on reasonable grounds that a ship has discharged, is discharging or is likely to discharge a pollutant, he or she may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>take any measures that he or she considers necessary to repair, remedy, minimize or prevent pollution damage from the ship, including the removal or destruction of the ship and its contents, and may sell or otherwise dispose of the ship and its contents;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>monitor the measures taken by any person to repair, remedy, minimize or prevent pollution damage from the ship; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if he or she considers it necessary to do so, direct any person to take measures to repair, remedy, minimize or prevent pollution damage from the ship, or prohibit any person from taking those measures.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 26</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA SHIPPING ACT, 2001</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Shipping Act, 2001</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, make regulations prescribing anything that may be prescribed under section 2.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 35(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting record keeping, information management and reporting for the purposes of this Part or Part 2 (Registration, Listing and Recording), 3 (Personnel), 4 (Safety), 6 (Incidents, Accidents and Casualties), 7 (Wreck), 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans) to the extent that the Minister of Transport is responsible for that Part, 9 (Pollution Prevention — Department of Transport), 10 (Pleasure Craft) or 11 (Enforcement — Department of Transport) or the regulations made under subsection 136(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the form and manner of giving notice under this Part or Part 2 (Registration, Listing and Recording), 3 (Personnel), 4 (Safety), 7 (Wreck), 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans) to the extent that the Minister of Transport is responsible for that Part, 9 (Pollution Prevention — Department of Transport), 10 (Pleasure Craft) or 11 (Enforcement — Department of Transport) or the regulations made under subsection 136(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the setting and payment of fees for services provided in the administration of this Part or Part 2 (Registration, Listing and Recording), 3 (Personnel), 4 (Safety), 6 (Incidents, Accidents and Casualties), 7 (Wreck) other than section 163, 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans) to the extent that the Minister of Transport is responsible for that Part, 9 (Pollution Prevention — Department of Transport), 10 (Pleasure Craft) or 11 (Enforcement — Department of Transport) or the regulations made under any of those Parts or under subsection 136(1).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 35(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations — Minister of Fisheries and Oceans</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans, make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>implementing, in whole or in part, an international convention, protocol or resolution that is listed in Schedule 2, as amended from time to time, including regulations</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>implementing it in respect of persons or vessels to which it does not apply,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>establishing stricter standards than it sets out, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>establishing additional or complementary standards to those it sets out if the Governor in Council is satisfied that the additional or complementary standards meet the objectives of the convention, protocol or resolution;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting record keeping, information management and reporting for the purposes of Part 5 (Navigation Services) or 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans), to the extent that the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans is responsible for those Parts;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the form and manner of giving notice under Part 5 (Navigation Services) or 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans), to the extent that the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans is responsible for those Parts; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the setting and payment of fees for services provided in the administration of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>Part 5 (Navigation Services) or 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans), to the extent that the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans is responsible for those Parts, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>regulations made under subsection 136(2).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>The portion of section 116 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>When boarding a vessel prohibited</MarginalNote><Label>116.</Label><Text>Subject to sections 135 (stopping and boarding a vessel), 175.1 (powers of pollution response officers — general), 196 and 198 (pleasure craft inspections), 200 (stopping and boarding a vessel) and 211 (inspections) and to any other Act of Parliament, no person shall go or attempt to go on board a vessel or to leave or attempt to leave one</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>Section 136 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations — Minister of Transport</MarginalNote><Label>136.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister of Transport, make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establishing VTS Zones within Canadian waters or in a shipping safety control zone prescribed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Arctic Waters Pollution Prevention Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the information to be provided and the procedures and practices to be followed by vessels that are about to enter, leave or proceed within a VTS Zone;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the conditions under which a clearance under section 126 is to be granted;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>defining the expression “about to enter” for the purpose of this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting aids to navigation in Canadian waters;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>regulating or prohibiting the navigation, anchoring, mooring or berthing of vessels for the purposes of promoting the safe and efficient navigation of vessels and protecting the public interest and the environment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the safety of persons on Canadian waters for the purposes of sporting, recreational or public events or activities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specifying classes of persons, or appointing persons, to ensure compliance with regulations made under any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and specifying their powers and duties; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing anything that may be prescribed under this Part.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations — Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the administration and control of Sable Island;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specifying classes of persons, or appointing persons, to ensure compliance with regulations made under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and specifying their powers and duties; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting maritime search and rescue.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 153 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>The headings before section 165 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading><Label>PART 8</Label><TitleText>POLLUTION PREVENTION AND RESPONSE — DEPARTMENT OF TRANSPORT AND DEPARTMENT OF FISHERIES AND OCEANS</TitleText></Heading><Heading><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 165 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 167(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>have on board a declaration, in the form specified by the Minister, that</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>The heading before section 174 and sections 174 and 175 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Pollution Prevention Officers and Pollution Response Officers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of pollution prevention officers</MarginalNote><Label>174.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may designate any persons or classes of persons as pollution prevention officers in respect of oil handling facilities and response organizations and may limit in any manner that he or she considers appropriate the powers that the officers may exercise under this Part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate of designation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must furnish every pollution prevention officer with a certificate of designation and, if the officer’s powers are limited under subsection (1), the certificate must specify the powers that the officer may exercise.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Pollution prevention officers are not personally liable for anything they do or omit to do in good faith under this Part.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of pollution response officer</MarginalNote><Label>174.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Fisheries and Oceans may designate any persons or classes of persons as pollution response officers in respect of discharges or threats of discharges and may limit in any manner that he or she considers appropriate the powers that the officers may exercise under this Part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate of designation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Fisheries and Oceans must furnish every pollution response officer with a certificate of designation and, if the officer’s powers are limited under subsection (1), the certificate must specify the powers that the officer may exercise.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Pollution response officers are not personally liable for anything they do or omit to do in good faith under this Part.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of pollution prevention officers</MarginalNote><Label>175.</Label><Text>A pollution prevention officer may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct the operator of an oil handling facility to provide him or her with any document that the operator is required to have on site under this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct a response organization to provide him or her with any document that the organization is required to have under this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>inspect an oil handling facility to determine whether its equipment and resources meet the requirements of this Part; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>inspect a response organization’s facilities to determine whether the organization’s equipment and resources meet the requirements of this Part.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of pollution response officers — general</MarginalNote><Label>175.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A pollution response officer may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct a vessel, if it is about to enter or is within waters in respect of which this Part applies, to provide him or her with any information that he or she considers appropriate for the administration of this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct any vessel that is within or about to enter waters in respect of which this Part applies and that he or she believes on reasonable grounds to be carrying a pollutant to proceed through those waters by the route, and at a speed not in excess of the speed, that he or she may specify;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct a vessel that is required to have a shipboard oil pollution emergency plan under the regulations to provide information concerning it and its implementation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct the operator of an oil handling facility to provide any document that the operator is required to have on site under this Part; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct a response organization to provide any document that the organization is required to have under this Part.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers — discharge of pollutant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the pollution response officer believes on reasonable grounds that a vessel might discharge, or might have discharged, a pollutant, he or she may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct a vessel that is within or about to enter waters in respect of which this Part applies to proceed through those waters by the route, and at a speed not in excess of the speed, that he or she may specify;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>go on board and take samples of any substance that he or she believes to be the pollutant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the vessel is within or about to enter waters in respect of which this Part applies, direct the vessel to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>proceed to the place within waters in respect of which this Part applies that he or she may specify, by the route and in the manner that he or she may specify, and to moor, anchor or remain there for any reasonable period that he or she may specify,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>proceed out of waters in respect of which this Part applies, by the route and in the manner that he or she may specify, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>remain outside waters in respect of which this Part applies; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if he or she is informed that a substantial quantity of a pollutant has entered or been discharged in waters in respect of which this Part applies, or if on reasonable grounds he or she is satisfied that a grave and imminent danger of a substantial discharge of a pollutant in those waters exists, declare an emergency zone, the size of which is reasonable with regard to the seriousness of the situation, and</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>direct any vessel within that emergency zone to report its position to him or her,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>direct any vessel not to enter or not to leave the emergency zone, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>direct any vessel within the emergency zone in respect of routes, speed limits and pilotage and equipment requirements.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposition of samples</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An officer who takes a sample under paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) may dispose of it in any manner that he or she considers appropriate or may submit it for analysis or examination to a person designated by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate or report</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person who has made an analysis or examination may issue a certificate or report that sets out the results of the analysis or examination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (6) and (7), the certificate or report is admissible in evidence in any proceeding related to an offence under this Part and, in the absence of any evidence to the contrary, is proof of the statements contained in the certificate or report without proof of the signature or the official character of the person appearing to have signed it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Attendance of person</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The party against whom the certificate or report is produced may, with leave of the court, require for the purposes of cross-examination the attendance of the person who issued it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The certificate or report may be admitted in evidence only if the party who intends to produce it has given to the party against whom it is intended to be produced reasonable notice of that intention, together with a copy of the certificate or report.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 176(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Assistance to officer</MarginalNote><Label>176.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of exercising his or her powers under this Part, a pollution prevention officer or a pollution response officer may</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 176(3) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to issue warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application, a justice, within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, may issue a warrant authorizing a pollution prevention officer or a pollution response officer to enter living quarters, subject to any conditions that may be specified in the warrant, if the justice is satisfied by information on oath that entry to the living quarters</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 177(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Detention</MarginalNote><Label>177.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a pollution response officer believes on reasonable grounds that an offence under this Part has been committed by or in respect of a vessel, he or she may make a detention order in respect of the vessel.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 177(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if an indictment has been preferred in respect of the offence, indicate the amount and form of security that, pending the outcome of any proceedings related to the indictment, must be deposited with the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans for the detention order to be rescinded.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 177(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rescission of orders</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A pollution response officer must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>rescind a detention order made under this section if he or she is satisfied that the measures indicated in the notice referred to in subsection (4) have been taken and, if applicable, security in the amount and form indicated in the notice referred to in that subsection has been deposited with the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>notify, in the form and manner specified by the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans, the master and the persons referred to in subsection (2) of the rescission.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 177(10) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of security</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>The Minister of Fisheries and Oceans, after proceedings in respect of which security was deposited are concluded,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>Section 179 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Direction to move a detained vessel</MarginalNote><Label>179.</Label><Text>The Minister of Fisheries and Oceans may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on application made by the authorized representative or, if there is no authorized representative, the owner of a detained vessel, in the form and manner specified by the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans, permit the master to move it in accordance with the directions of the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on application made by the owner of a dock or wharf, or by the person in charge of a harbour, at which a detained vessel is situated, in the form and manner specified by the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans, direct the person who is, or appears to be, in charge of the vessel to move the vessel in accordance with the directions of the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if a person to whom a direction is given under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) does not comply with it and the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans is satisfied that the applicant for the direction has sufficient insurance in place to cover any incident that may arise from the moving of the vessel, authorize the applicant to move the vessel in accordance with the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans’ directions and at the expense of the authorized representative or, if there is no authorized representative, the owner.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>Subsection 180(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Minister may take necessary measures</MarginalNote><Label>180.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans believes on reasonable grounds that a vessel or an oil handling facility has discharged, is discharging or is likely to discharge a pollutant, he or she may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>take the measures that he or she considers necessary to repair, remedy, minimize or prevent pollution damage from the vessel or oil handling facility, including, in the case of a vessel, the removal or destruction of the vessel and its contents, and may sell or otherwise dispose of the vessel and its contents;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>monitor the measures taken by any person to repair, remedy, minimize or prevent pollution damage from the vessel or oil handling facility; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if he or she considers it necessary to do so, direct any person or vessel to take measures referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or to refrain from doing so.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28.</Label><Text>Paragraph 183(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a direction given under paragraph 175.1(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) (direction resulting from a discharge or possible discharge of a pollutant);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29.</Label><Text>The portion of the definition <DefinedTermEn>pollutant</DefinedTermEn> in section 185 of the Act after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><ContinuedDefinition><Text>It includes oil and any substance or class of substances that is prescribed for the purpose of Part 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans) to be a pollutant.</Text></ContinuedDefinition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Text>Section 189 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>direct a vessel that is required to have a shipboard oil pollution emergency plan under the regulations to provide him or her with any information concerning it and its implementation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 194 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Transport.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>relevant provision</DefinedTermEn> in section 210 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>relevant provision</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>disposition visée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>relevant provision</DefinedTermEn> means a provision of this Act or the regulations that the Minister is responsible for administering, other than</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 40(1) with respect to a provision of regulations made under paragraph 35(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) in relation to any of Parts 7 (Wreck), 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans) and 10 (Pleasure Craft); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a provision of any of Parts 5 (Navigation Services), 7 (Wreck), 8 (Pollution Prevention and Response — Department of Transport and Department of Fisheries and Oceans) and 10 (Pleasure Craft) or a provision of any regulation made under any of those Parts, except a provision of the regulations made under paragraph 136(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) in so far as it applies in respect of Canadian vessels or foreign vessels.</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33.</Label><Text>Subsection 252(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Proof of offence</MarginalNote><Label>252.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In a prosecution of a vessel for an offence under this Act, it is sufficient proof that the vessel has committed the offence to establish that the act or omission that constitutes the offence was committed by the master or any person on board, other than a person carrying out an inspection under this Act, a pollution prevention officer or a pollution response officer, whether or not the person on board has been identified.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 18</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA NATIONAL MARINE CONSERVATION AREAS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>34.</Label><Text>Subsection 9(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister of Fisheries and Oceans</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Provisions of a management plan or an interim management plan respecting fishing, aquaculture and fisheries management are subject to an agreement between the Minister and the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister of Transport and Minister of Fisheries and Oceans</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Provisions of a management plan or an interim management plan respecting marine navigation and marine safety are subject to an agreement between the Minister, the Minister of Transport and the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35.</Label><Text>Subsections 16(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fisheries and aquaculture</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations under this section respecting fisheries management and conservation or restricting or prohibiting fishing or aquaculture may be made only on the recommendation of the Minister and the Minister of Fisheries and Oceans.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Marine matters</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Regulations under this section restricting or prohibiting marine navigation or activities related to marine safety may be made only on the recommendation of the Minister and the Minister of Transport.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 31</MarginalNote><TitleText>OCEANS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>36.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 41(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Oceans Act</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>marine pollution response; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, and the provisions of any Act as enacted by this Act, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>