<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>C-33</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>57-58</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2009</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the War Veterans Allowance Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the War Veterans Allowance Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>War Veterans Allowance</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2009</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>20</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2009</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2009-6-1">90508</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">War Veterans Allowance Act</XRefExternal> in order to extend the application of that Act to certain allied veterans and extends certain benefits provided for by regulations to those veterans and their dependants.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. W-3</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">WAR VETERANS ALLOWANCE ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">War Veterans Allowance Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Korean War</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>guerre de Corée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Korean War</DefinedTermEn> means the military operations undertaken by the United Nations to restore peace in the Republic of Korea during the period from June 25, 1950 to July 27, 1953, inclusive.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Surviving spouse of allied veteran</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, the definition <DefinedTermEn>survivor</DefinedTermEn> in subsection (1) includes a person who has resided in Canada for a total period of at least 10 years and who was the spouse or common-law partner of an individual at the time of the individual’s death and the individual</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>died after October 13, 2008;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was, at the time of death, a resident in Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>was, at the time of death, an individual described in subsection 37(4.1) or (4.2), even if they had not resided in Canada for a total period of at least 10 years, but only if the total of the time they resided in Canada prior to their death and the time that has elapsed since their death is at least 10 years.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Survivor — limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the definition <DefinedTermEn>survivor</DefinedTermEn> in subsection (1), a spouse or common-law partner is the survivor of an allied veteran referred to in paragraph 37(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>) or subsection 37(4.1) or (4.2) only if that allied veteran died after October 13, 2008.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — allied veterans</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>Subsections (4) and (5) do not apply to an allied veteran referred to in paragraph 37(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>) or subsection 37(4.1) or (4.2) or to the survivor or orphan of that veteran.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Section 9 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Enemy forces</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>No allowance shall be paid to any person who served in enemy forces during either World War II or the Korean War.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 37(4) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any of the forces that took part in the Korean War</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 37(4) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>served in a theatre of operations during the Korean War,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 37 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Allied veteran — World War II</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>An allied veteran is also any former member of any of His Majesty’s forces, or of any of the forces, other than resistance groups, of any of His Majesty’s allies in World War II, who served during that war, who resided in Canada for a total period of at least 10 years beginning on or after August 15, 1945, who has been honourably discharged or has been permitted honourably to resign or retire from one of those forces and who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>served in a theatre of actual war during that war;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is in receipt of a pension for an injury or disease incurred or aggravated during service in any such force during that war or is declared to have been eligible for, or awarded, such a pension subsequent to their death; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has accepted a commuted pension.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Allied veteran — Korean War</MarginalNote><Label>(4.2)</Label><Text>An allied veteran is also any former member of any of the forces that took part in the Korean War and who served during that war, who resided in Canada for a total period of at least 10 years beginning on or after July 27, 1953, who has been honourably discharged or has been permitted honourably to resign or retire from one of those forces and who served in a theatre of operations during that war.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>October 14, 2008</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The allowance payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">War Veterans Allowance Act</XRefExternal> may be paid to any person or in respect of any person who would have been eligible to receive that allowance if sections <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> had come into force on October 14, 2008. In order for the allowance to be paid, an application must be made to the Minister of Veterans Affairs no later than December 31, 2010.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Veterans Health Care Regulations</XRefExternal> and <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Veterans Burial Regulations, 2005</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The benefits under the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Veterans Health Care Regulations</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Veterans Burial Regulations, 2005</XRefExternal> are extended to allied veterans or in respect of allied veterans described in paragraph 37(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>) or subsection 37(4.1) or (4.2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">War Veterans Allowance Act</XRefExternal>, enacted by section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>, for the period beginning on October 14, 2008 and ending on December 31, 2009. Any application for the benefits must be made to the Minister of Veterans Affairs no later than December 31, 2010.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Assistance Fund (W.V.A. and C.W.A.) Regulations</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The financial assistance payable under the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Assistance Fund (W.V.A. and C.W.A.) Regulations</XRefExternal> may be paid to any person or in respect of any person who would have been eligible to receive that financial assistance if sections <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> had come into force on October 14, 2008. In order for the financial assistance to be paid, an application must be made to the Minister of Veterans Affairs no later than December 31, 2010.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>January 1, 2010</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on January 1, 2010.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>