<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>S-2</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>57-58</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2009</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Customs Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Customs Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Customs</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2009</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>11</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>10</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2009</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2009-1-15">90453</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> to clarify certain provisions and to make technical amendments to others. It also imposes additional requirements in customs controlled areas, amends provisions respecting the determination of value for duty, and modifies the advance commercial reporting requirements. Finally, it provides that regulations may incorporate material by reference.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>CUSTOMS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 19, s. 262(1)</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>Subsection 2(4) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Délégation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Le ministre peut autoriser un agent ou une catégorie d’agents à exercer les pouvoirs et fonctions, y compris les pouvoirs et fonctions judiciaires ou quasi judiciaires, qui lui sont conférés en vertu de la présente loi.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.3(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>has been authorized by the Minister; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 11.3 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 11.3(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment, etc., of authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may amend, suspend, renew, cancel or reinstate an authorization.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 11.4(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Presentation and reporting — when leaving customs controlled area</MarginalNote><Label>11.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), every person who is leaving a customs controlled area shall, if requested to do so by an officer,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>report in the prescribed manner any goods that he or she has acquired through any means while in the customs controlled area;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>present those goods and remove any covering from them, unload any conveyance or open any part of it, or open or unpack any package or container that an officer wishes to examine; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11.4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>répondre véridiquement aux questions que lui pose un agent dans l’exercice des fonctions que lui confère la présente loi ou une autre loi fédérale.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 11.4(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Presentation and reporting — within customs controlled area</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Every person who is in a customs controlled area shall, if requested to do so by an officer,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>present himself or herself in the prescribed manner to an officer and identify himself or herself; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>answer truthfully any questions asked by an officer in the performance of his or her duties under this or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application of subsections (1) and (1.1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (1.1) do not apply to persons who are required to present themselves under section 11 or report goods under section 12.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 11.5(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the persons or classes of persons who may be granted access under paragraph 11.3(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the manner in which a person must present himself or herself under paragraphs 11.4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (1.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and report goods under paragraph 11.4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 28, s. 3(1)</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>Paragraph 12(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of goods, other than goods referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or goods imported as mail, on board a conveyance arriving in Canada, by prescribed persons; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Advance information</MarginalNote><Label>12.1</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring persons to give, before a conveyance’s arrival in Canada, information about the conveyance and the persons and the goods on board the conveyance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the information that must be given;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the persons or classes of persons who must give the information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the circumstances in which the information must be given; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the time within which and the manner in which the information must be given.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Paragraph 48(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when any part of the proceeds of any subsequent resale, disposal or use of the goods by the purchaser is to accrue, directly or indirectly, to the vendor, the price paid or payable for the goods includes the value of that part of the proceeds or the price is adjusted in accordance with paragraph (5)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>); and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 49(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Fixation de la valeur en douane fondée sur la valeur transactionnelle de marchandises identiques</MarginalNote><Label>49.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sous réserve des paragraphes (2) à (5), la valeur en douane des marchandises, dans les cas où elle n’est pas déterminée par application de l’article 48, est, si elle est déterminable, la valeur transactionnelle de marchandises identiques vendues pour exportation au Canada et exportées au même moment ou à peu près au même moment que les marchandises à apprécier, pourvu que cette valeur transactionnelle soit la valeur en douane des marchandises identiques vendues :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 49(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at the same or substantially the same trade level as the goods being appraised; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 49(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>en une quantité égale ou sensiblement égale à celle des marchandises à apprécier.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 49(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at the same or substantially the same trade level as the goods being appraised but in different quantities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at a trade level different from that of the goods being appraised but in the same or substantially the same quantities; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at a trade level different from that of the goods being appraised and in different quantities.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraph 49(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the transaction value is in respect of identical goods sold under the conditions described in any of paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), differences in the trade levels of the identical goods and the goods being appraised or the quantities in which the identical goods were sold and the goods being appraised were imported or both, as the case may be.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 50(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Valeur en douane fondée sur la valeur transactionnelle de marchandises semblables</MarginalNote><Label>50.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sous réserve des paragraphes (2) et 49(2) à (5), la valeur en douane des marchandises, dans les cas où elle n’est pas déterminée par application de l’article 48 ou 49, est, si elle est déterminable, la valeur transactionnelle de marchandises semblables vendues pour exportation au Canada et exportées au même moment ou à peu près au même moment que les marchandises à apprécier, pourvu que cette valeur transactionnelle soit la valeur en douane des marchandises semblables vendues :</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 50(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at the same or substantially the same trade level as the goods being appraised; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 50(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>en une quantité égale ou sensiblement égale à celle des marchandises à apprécier.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 60</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>Subsections 99.2(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Search of persons</MarginalNote><Label>99.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An officer may search any person who is in or is leaving a customs controlled area, other than a prescribed person or a member of a prescribed class of persons who may be searched under subsection (2), if the officer suspects on reasonable grounds that the person has secreted on or about their person anything in respect of which this Act or the regulations have been or might be contravened, anything that would afford evidence with respect to a contravention of this Act or the regulations or any goods the importation or exportation of which is prohibited, controlled or regulated under this or any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Search of prescribed persons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer may, in accordance with the regulations, search any prescribed person or member of a prescribed class of persons who is in or is leaving a customs controlled area.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 60</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Section 99.3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Non-intrusive examination of goods</MarginalNote><Label>99.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An officer may, in accordance with the regulations and without individualized suspicion, conduct a non-intrusive examination of goods in the custody or possession of a person who is in or is leaving a customs controlled area.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other examination of goods</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An officer may examine any goods in the custody or possession of a person who is in or is leaving a customs controlled area and open or cause to be opened any baggage, package or container and take samples of the goods in reasonable amounts, if the officer suspects on reasonable grounds that this Act or any other Act of Parliament administered or enforced by the officer or any regulations made under it have been or might be contravened in respect of the goods.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Examination of abandoned goods</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An officer may, at any time, open or cause to be opened, examine and detain any goods, baggage, package or container that is found abandoned or that is not in the possession of any person in a customs controlled area.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 61</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>Subsection 107.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Passenger information</MarginalNote><Label>107.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, under prescribed circumstances and conditions, require any prescribed person or prescribed class of persons to provide, or to provide access to, within the prescribed time and in the prescribed manner, prescribed information about any person on board a conveyance.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 68</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Paragraph 127.1(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>il y a eu infraction, mais le ministre est d’avis qu’une erreur a été commise concernant la somme établie, versée ou réclamée en garantie et que celle-ci doit être réduite.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 75</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>Subsection 139.1(4) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Signification au ministre</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Au plus tard le quinzième jour précédant la date d’audition de la requête, le requérant signifie au ministre, ou à l’agent que celui-ci désigne pour l’application du présent article, un avis de la requête et de l’audition.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 38, s. 82</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>Section 149.1 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Preuve de l’absence d’appel</MarginalNote><Label>149.1</Label><Text>Constitue la preuve des énonciations qui y sont renfermées l’affidavit d’un agent — souscrit en présence d’un commissaire ou d’une autre personne autorisée à le recevoir — indiquant qu’il a la charge des registres pertinents, qu’il a connaissance de la pratique de l’Agence ou de l’Agence du revenu du Canada, selon le cas, qu’un examen des registres démontre qu’un avis de cotisation prévu à la partie V.1 a été posté ou autrement envoyé à une personne un jour donné, en application de la présente loi, et que, après avoir fait un examen attentif des registres et y avoir pratiqué des recherches, il lui a été impossible de constater qu’un avis d’opposition ou d’appel concernant la cotisation a été reçu dans le délai imparti à cette fin.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 85(1)</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Text>Paragraph 164(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 164:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference</MarginalNote><Label>164.1</Label><Text>A regulation made under this Act may incorporate by reference any material regardless of its source and either as it exists on a particular date or as amended from time to time.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>