<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>S-3</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>57-58</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2009</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Energy Efficiency Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Energy Efficiency Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Energy Efficiency</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2009</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>8</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2009</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2008-4-30">90466</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Energy Efficiency Act</XRefExternal> to</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>clarify that classes of energy-using products may be established based on their common energy-consuming characteristics, the intended use of the products or the conditions under which the products are normally used;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require that all interprovincial shipments of energy-using products meet the requirements of that Act;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require dealers to provide the Minister of Natural Resources with prescribed information respecting the shipment or importation of energy-using products;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the authority to prescribe as energy-using products manufactured products, or classes of manufactured products, that affect or control energy consumption;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>broaden the scope of the labelling provisions; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>broaden the scope of the Minister’s report.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to ensuring sustained improvement in the efficient use of energy in all sectors of the Canadian economy;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1992, c. 36</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Energy Efficiency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Meaning of <DefinedTermEn>class</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>2.1</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a reference in this Act to a <DefinedTermEn>class</DefinedTermEn> in relation to energy-using products includes classes based on common energy-consuming characteristics, the intended use of the products or the conditions under which the products are normally used.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Subsection 4(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Interprovincial trade and importation</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No dealer shall, for the purpose of sale or lease, ship an energy-using product from one province to another province, or import an energy-using product into Canada, unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the product complies with the energy efficiency standard; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the product or its package is labelled in accordance with the regulations, if any.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Information to be provided by dealers</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every dealer who ships or imports energy-using products as described in subsection 4(1) shall provide the Minister, in the prescribed form and manner and at the prescribed time, with prescribed information respecting those products, including their energy efficiency, their shipment or their importation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A dealer is not required to provide prescribed information in respect of the energy efficiency of any particular energy-using products if the Minister is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the information has previously been provided under subsection (1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>information has previously been provided under subsection (1) in respect of the energy efficiency of comparable energy-using products that differ from those products only in a manner that does not relate to energy efficiency.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Sections 7 and 8 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Retention of documents and records</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>Every dealer required by section 5 to provide the Minister with prescribed information shall keep, at the dealer’s place of business or other prescribed place in Canada, documents and records sufficient to enable the Minister to verify the accuracy and completeness of the information provided.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Period of retention</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>Every dealer required by section 7 to keep documents and records shall, unless authorized by the Minister, retain each one of those documents or records until the expiry of six years after the day on which the Minister is provided with the prescribed information.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing as an energy-using product any manufactured product, or class of manufactured products, that is designed to operate using electricity, oil, natural gas or any other form or source of energy or that affects or controls energy consumption;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing energy efficiency standards for energy-using products or classes of energy-using products;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 20(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the labelling of energy-using products or their packages, or classes of energy-using products or their packages;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>Section 36 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 36(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Comparison of energy efficiency standards</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Once every three years, in the report referred to in subsection (1), the Minister shall demonstrate the extent to which the energy efficiency standards prescribed under this Act are as stringent as comparable standards established by a province, the United Mexican States, the United States of America or a state of the United States of America.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Section 37 of the Act and the headings before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Report on extent energy efficiency standards established</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Text>Within four years after the day on which this section comes into force, the Minister shall, in the report referred to in subsection 36(1), demonstrate the extent to which energy efficiency standards have been prescribed under this Act for all energy-using products whose use has a significant impact on energy consumption in Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>