<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret1?><Identification><BillNumber>C-17</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>40</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>57-58</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2009</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to recognize Beechwood Cemetery as the national cemetery of Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">National Cemetery of Canada Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Cemetery of Canada</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2009</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>5</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2009</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2009-2-5">90489</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment provides for the recognition of Beechwood Cemetery as the national cemetery of Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Beechwood Cemetery is a national place of tribute;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Beechwood Cemetery is recognized by the Canadian Forces as its national military cemetery;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Beechwood Cemetery is recognized by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police as its memorial cemetery;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Beechwood Cemetery contains a national historic site of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Beechwood Cemetery has demonstrated commitment to respecting the linguistic duality of Canada by means of a consistent and balanced approach to the use and display of Canada’s two official languages;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Beechwood Cemetery reflects the multicultural, multi-faith nature of Canadian society;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Parliament considers a national cemetery to be a worthy final resting place for Governors General, Prime Ministers and recipients of the Canadian Victoria Cross;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas Parliament considers that Ottawa, the seat of Canada’s national government and focal point for national memorial events such as those that take place on Remembrance Day, is a fitting location for a national cemetery;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas a national cemetery is a symbol of national gratitude, pride and unity;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Cemetery of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>National cemetery</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>Beechwood Cemetery is given honorary recognition as the national cemetery of Canada.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Description</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>For the purpose of section 2, Beechwood Cemetery is, under the registry system of Ontario, the area composed of Part of Lot 3, Concession Junction Gore, Part of Lot 2, Concession Junction Gore, Part of Block 23, Plan 92, Part of Blocks 15A and Btn Rds, Plan 92, Ottawa and Vanier.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>