<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-21</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63-64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014-2015</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to control the administrative burden that regulations impose on businesses</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Red Tape Reduction Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Red Tape Reduction</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2015</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><?Pub Caret1?><AnnualStatuteNumber>12</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2015</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-1-28">90720</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Red Tape Reduction Act</XRefExternal>, which establishes controls on the amount of administrative burden that regulations impose on businesses.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canadians and small businesses have expressed concerns about how the increased administrative burden imposed by regulations has affected the cost of doing business;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas on April 1, 2012 the Government of Canada established a rule that each increase in the administrative burden on businesses must be offset with a corresponding decrease, one-for-one, and considers that it is desirable to establish that rule in legislation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the one-for-one rule must not compromise public health, public safety or the Canadian economy;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas the Government of Canada recognizes the importance of being transparent with regard to the implementation of the one-for-one rule;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Red Tape Reduction Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>administrative burden</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>fardeau administratif</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>administrative burden</DefinedTermEn> means anything that is necessary to demonstrate compliance with a regulation, including the collecting, processing, reporting and retaining of information and the completing of forms.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>business</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>entreprise</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>business</DefinedTermEn> means a person or entity that engages in commercial activities in Canada, other than for a public purpose. </Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>regulation</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>règlement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>regulation</DefinedTermEn> means an instrument that is registered as a regulation under section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>APPLICATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>This Act applies to regulations made by or with the approval of the Governor in Council, the Treasury Board or a minister of the Crown.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PURPOSE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to control the administrative burden that regulations impose on businesses.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>RULE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Control of administrative burden</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a regulation is made that imposes a new administrative burden on a business, one or more regulations must be amended or repealed to offset the cost of that new burden against the cost of an existing administrative burden on a business.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Repeal of regulation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a regulation is made  —  other than one that only amends a regulation  —  that imposes a new administrative burden on a business, a regulation must be repealed, unless one has already been repealed in accordance with subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Policies and directives</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The President of the Treasury Board may establish policies or issue directives respecting the manner in which section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> is to be applied.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, for the purpose of section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal>, make regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the manner of calculating the cost of an administrative burden;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the period within which measures must be taken to comply with that section;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the taking into account of regulations that are amended or repealed before a new administrative burden is imposed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the application of that section to any regulation made, amended or repealed on or after April 1, 2012; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the regulations that the Treasury Board may exempt from the application of that section and the categories for which, and the circumstances in which, such an exemption may be granted.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>GENERAL</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No action or other proceeding may be brought against Her Majesty in right of Canada for anything done or omitted to be done, or for anything purported to be done or omitted to be done, under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Validity of regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No regulation is invalid by reason only of a failure to comply with this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ANNUAL REPORT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report  — application of section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal></MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>The President of the Treasury Board must prepare and make public each year a report on the application of section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> during the 12-month period ending on March 31 of the year in which the report is to be made public.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the information to be included in the report and respecting the report’s form.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>REVIEW OF ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Five-year review</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Five years after the day on which this Act comes into force, the President of the Treasury Board must cause a review of this Act to be conducted.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>