<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-452</BillNumber><Parliament><?Pub Caret1?><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63-64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014-2015</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (exploitation and trafficking in persons)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (exploitation and trafficking in persons)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code (exploitation and trafficking in persons)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2015</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>16</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2015</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2010-09-27">411641</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> in order to provide consecutive sentences for offences related to trafficking in persons and create a presumption regarding the exploitation of one person by another.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>It also adds the offence of trafficking in persons to the list of offences to which the forfeiture of proceeds of crime apply.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1.</Label><Text>Section 279.01 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Presumption</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsections (1) and 279.011(1), evidence that a person who is not exploited lives with or is habitually in the company of a person who is exploited is, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, proof that the person exercises control, direction or influence over the movements of that person for the purpose of exploiting them or facilitating their exploitation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Subsection 279.04(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Exploitation</MarginalNote><Label>279.04</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Pour l’application des articles 279.01 à 279.03, une personne en exploite une autre si elle l’amène à fournir ― ou à offrir de fournir ― son travail ou ses services, par des agissements dont il est raisonnable de s’attendre, compte tenu du contexte, à ce qu’ils lui fassent croire qu’un refus de sa part mettrait en danger sa sécurité ou celle d’une personne qu’elle connaît.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 279.04:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Sentences to be served consecutively</MarginalNote><Label>279.05</Label><Text>A sentence imposed on a person for an offence under sections 279.01 to 279.03 shall be served consecutively to any other punishment imposed on the person for an offence arising out of the same event or series of events and to any other sentence to which the person is subject at the time the sentence is imposed on the person for an offence under any of those sections.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Subsection 462.37(2.02) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under any of sections 279.01 to 279.03.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>