<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-40</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63-64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014-2015</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the Rouge National Urban Park</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Rouge National Urban Park Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Rouge National Urban Park</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2015</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>10</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2015</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-6-11">90723</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment establishes the Rouge National Urban Park, a new type of federal protected area, and provides for the protection and presentation of its natural and cultural resources and the encouragement of sustainable farming practices within the Park. The enactment confers a broad range of regulatory powers for the management and administration of the Park. It also makes consequential amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Lands Surveys Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Species at Risk Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Environmental Violations Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Rouge Valley contains some of the last remnants of the Carolinian forest in Canada, significant geological features and a combination of diverse habitats linking Lake Ontario to the Oak Ridges Moraine;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the foresight, dedication and engagement of community visionaries and various levels of government have laid the foundation for the creation of a park in the Rouge Valley, an area that is rich in natural and cultural resources and is readily accessible to the population of Canada’s largest metropolitan area;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas there is a unique opportunity to connect Canadians with the natural and cultural heritage of the Rouge Valley and with the history of its early Aboriginal inhabitants and others who shaped its landscapes;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas Parliament wishes</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>to protect natural ecosystems and maintain native wildlife in the Rouge Valley,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>to provide meaningful opportunities for Canadians to experience and enjoy the diverse landscapes of the Rouge Valley,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>to engage local communities and businesses, Aboriginal organizations and youth, as well as other Canadians, to become stewards and ambassadors of the park,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>to provide a wide range of recreational, interpretive, volunteer and learning activities to attract a diverse urban population to the park,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>to enable youth and other visitors to connect with nature in an urban setting,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>to protect the cultural landscapes of the park and identify its heritage values to facilitate an understanding and appreciation of the history of the region,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>to encourage sustainable farming practices to support the preservation of agricultural lands in the park and celebrate the agricultural heritage of the region, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>to promote the park as a place of discovery, enjoyment and learning, and as a gateway to all of Canada’s national protected heritage areas;</Text></Provision><?Pub Caret?></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rouge National Urban Park Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>enforcement officer</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>agent de l’autorité</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>enforcement officer</DefinedTermEn> means any person designated under section <XRefInternal>24</XRefInternal> or belonging to a class of persons so designated.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister responsible for the Parks Canada Agency.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>national historic site</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>lieu historique national</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>national historic site</DefinedTermEn> means a site, building or other place of national historic interest or significance that is commemorated under section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Park</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>parc</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Park</DefinedTermEn> means the Rouge National Urban Park, established by section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>park warden</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>garde de parc</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>park warden</DefinedTermEn> means a person designated under section <XRefInternal>23</XRefInternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>public lands</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>terres domaniales</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>public lands</DefinedTermEn> means lands, including submerged lands, belonging to Her Majesty in right of Canada or of which the Government of Canada has the power to dispose, regardless of whether that disposal is subject to any agreement between the Government of Canada and the Government of Ontario.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>superintendent</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>directeur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>superintendent</DefinedTermEn> means a person appointed under subsection 13(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal> who holds the office of superintendent of the Park, and includes any other person appointed under that Act who is authorized by the superintendent to act on his or her behalf.</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>HER MAJESTY</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Binding on Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>This Act is binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PARK ESTABLISHED</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Park established</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>Rouge National Urban Park, which is described in the schedule, is established for the purposes of protecting and presenting, for current and future generations, the natural and cultural heritage of the Park and its diverse landscapes, promoting a vibrant farming community and encouraging Canadians to discover and connect with their national protected heritage areas.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>MANAGEMENT OF THE PARK</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Management by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Minister is responsible for the administration, management and control of the Park, including the administration of public lands in the Park and, for that purpose, the Minister may use and occupy those lands.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Minister must, in the management of the Park, take into consideration the protection of its natural ecosystems and cultural landscapes and the maintenance of its native wildlife and of the health of those ecosystems.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>National historic sites</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The Minister must, in relation to any national historic site in the Park, ensure</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that cultural resources are not impaired or under threat;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that cultural resources are maintained in a manner that will prevent or slow their deterioration and that any intervention carried out is in accordance with national conservation standards; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that he or she does not take any action, including the making of a payment or the granting of any financial assistance or any authorization, that would have an adverse effect on cultural resources or on the communication to the public of the reasons for the commemoration of the national historic site.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Advisory committee</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>The Minister may establish a committee to advise the Minister on the management of the Park. The advisory committee may include representatives from local governments, Aboriginal or regional organizations and other organizations that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Management plan</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within five years after the establishment of the Park, the Minister must prepare a management plan that sets out a long-term vision for the Park and provides for management objectives and performance evaluation. The Minister must cause the management plan to be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Area management approach</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The management plan must set out a management approach, by area, that includes the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the protection and presentation of natural and cultural heritage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the presentation of agricultural heritage and the encouragement of sustainable farming practices; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the installation and maintenance of infrastructure, buildings and other improvements.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review of management plan</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must review the management plan at least every 10 years and must cause any amendments to the plan to be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Public consultation</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>The Minister must provide opportunities for public participation, including by Aboriginal organizations, in the development of the management plan and in relation to any other matters that the Minister considers relevant.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>The Minister may, for the purposes of the management of the Park, enter into agreements with federal and provincial ministers and agencies, local governments, Aboriginal organizations and other persons and organizations.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Clearing of land for installation or maintenance of infrastructure</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>The superintendent may issue, amend, suspend and revoke any permit or other authorization for the clearing of public lands in the Park for the purpose of installing or maintaining public infrastructure, including public utilities or transportation corridors.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PARK LANDS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Public lands</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in respect of public lands in the Park, enter into leases, grant easements and issue licences of occupation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Use of lands</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Public lands in the Park in which a right or interest is held for any purpose under this Act remain part of the Park and that right or interest reverts to Her Majesty in right of Canada if those lands cease to be used for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Termination, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in respect of public lands in the Park, terminate or accept the surrender of a lease and terminate or accept the relinquishment of an easement or a licence of occupation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expropriation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal> applies in respect of the acquisition of an interest in public lands in the Park for the purposes of this Act if the holder of the interest does not consent and there is no cause for termination under subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of terms</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (4), the Minister is deemed to be a Minister referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal> and the Parks Canada Agency is deemed to be a department named in Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No other expropriation</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Despite the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal>, no interest in land may be acquired by expropriation by Her Majesty in right of Canada for the purpose of enlarging the Park.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Amendment to schedule</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of enlarging the Park, the Governor in Council may, by order, amend the schedule by altering the description of the Park, if the Governor in Council is satisfied that Her Majesty in right of Canada has title to the lands that are to be included in the Park, regardless of whether there are any charges on title.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Judicial finding as to title</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a court of competent jurisdiction finds that Her Majesty in right of Canada does not have title to lands in the Park, the Governor in Council may, by order, amend the schedule by altering the description of the Park to remove those lands from the Park.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No disposition without authority</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>It is prohibited to dispose of public lands or a right or interest in public lands in the Park, except as permitted under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Authority to dispose</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Public lands or a right or interest in public lands in the Park may be disposed of to a federal or provincial authority, including the Toronto and Region Conservation Authority, or to a municipal authority, if the disposal is required for the purposes of the installation or maintenance of public infrastructure, including public utilities or transportation corridors.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) ceases to apply in respect of the transfer of the fee simple in the public lands when the total amount of lands in which fee simple has been transferred under that subsection reaches an area of 200 hectares.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment to schedule</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend the schedule by altering the description of the Park to remove the lands that have been disposed of.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reversion</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Lands disposed of under subsection (1) revert to Her Majesty in right of Canada if those lands cease to be used for the purposes for which they were disposed of.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>POLLUTION CLEAN-UP</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Mitigation of risks</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a substance that is capable of degrading the natural environment, injuring natural or cultural resources or endangering human health is discharged or deposited in the Park, any person who has charge, management or control of the substance and any person who caused or contributed to the discharge or deposit must take reasonable measures to prevent any degradation of the natural environment and any danger to natural or cultural resources or to human health that may result from the discharge or deposit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of superintendent and Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the superintendent is of the opinion that a person is not taking the required measures, the superintendent may order the person to take those measures and, if the person fails to do so, the Minister may take those measures on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expenses of clean-up</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who fails to comply with an order given by the superintendent is liable for the expenses reasonably incurred by Her Majesty in right of Canada in taking the measures, and those expenses may be recovered from that person, with costs, in proceedings brought in the name of Her Majesty in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PROHIBITED ACTIVITIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>hunt</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>chasser</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>hunt</DefinedTermEn> means to kill, injure, seize, capture or trap a wild animal, or to attempt to do so, and includes to pursue, stalk, track, search for, lie in wait for or shoot at a wild animal for any of those purposes.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>possess</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>possession</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>possess</DefinedTermEn> includes, in relation to any person, knowingly having any thing in any place, whether or not that place belongs to or is occupied by the person, for his or her own use or benefit or for that of another person.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>traffic</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>trafic</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>traffic</DefinedTermEn> means to sell, offer for sale, buy, offer to buy, exchange, give, send, transport or deliver.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>wild animal</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>animal sauvage</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>wild animal</DefinedTermEn> means any individual of the animal kingdom that is not — or is no longer — domesticated, whether living or dead, at any developmental stage — including any egg or embryo — and any part or any derivative of such an individual.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibited activities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except as permitted under this Act, it is prohibited to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>traffic in a wild animal, a plant, a part of a plant, any other naturally occurring object or product of natural phenomena or a cultural, historical or archaeological resource, whether it is in the Park or has been removed from it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>hunt a wild animal in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>remove a wild animal, a plant, a part of a plant or any other naturally occurring object or product of natural phenomena from the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>possess a wild animal, a plant, a part of a plant or any other naturally occurring object or product of natural phenomena that is in the Park or that has been removed from it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>disturb, harm or destroy a wild animal or disturb, damage or destroy a plant, a part of a plant or any other naturally occurring object or product of natural phenomena that is in the Park or that has been removed from it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>harvest timber in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>explore for minerals, oil or gas, or conduct an extractive activity, including mining, in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>dump or dispose of any substance in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>disturb a cultural, historical or archaeological resource in the Park, remove one from it or, whether it is in the Park or has been removed from it, damage, alter, destroy or possess one; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>remove a park facility or other park property from the Park or, whether it is in the Park or has been removed from it, damage, alter or destroy a park facility or other park property.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — superintendent</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not apply to the superintendent when he or she is performing his or her functions related to the management of the Park or to any other person authorized by the superintendent when they are performing those functions on the superintendent’s behalf.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — rescue and rehabilitation of animals</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not apply to activities carried out by an organization whose purpose is the rescue and rehabilitation of wild animals if that organization has been authorized by the Minister to carry out those activities.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — recreational fishing</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Recreational fishing is permitted in the Park, subject to any regulations that may be made under paragraph <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>AGRICULTURAL ACTIVITIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsections <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(1) and <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>(2) do not prevent the carrying out of agricultural activities by a lessee of public lands in the Park in accordance with their lease.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>REGULATIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the preservation, control and management of the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the protection of flora, fauna, soil, waters, fossils, natural features and air quality;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the protection, management, acquisition, disposition, disturbance, altering, removal or destruction of cultural, historical or archaeological resources;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the taking of specimens of flora or fauna for scientific or propagation purposes, and the destruction or removal of dangerous or superabundant flora or fauna;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the authorization of the use of lands in the Park, and the use or removal of flora and other natural objects, by Aboriginal people for traditional spiritual or ceremonial purposes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the management and regulation of fishing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the prevention and remedying of any pollution of land or water or any obstruction of waterways;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the prevention and extinguishment of fires in the Park or threatening the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the issuance, amendment and termination of leases, licences of occupation and easements or servitudes, and the acceptance of the surrender of leases and the relinquishment of licences of occupation and easements or servitudes, of or over public lands in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the restriction or prohibition of activities in the Park and the control of the use of resources and facilities in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the establishment, operation, maintenance and administration and use of works and services of a public character, such as water, sewage, electricity, telephone, gas, fire protection and garbage removal and disposal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the establishment, maintenance, administration and use of roads, streets, highways, parking areas, sidewalks, streetworks, trails, wharves, docks, bridges and other improvements, and the circumstances under which they must be open or may be closed to public traffic or use;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the control of traffic on roads, streets and highways and elsewhere in the Park, including the regulation of the speed, operation and parking of vehicles;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the control of the location, standards, design, materials, construction, maintenance, removal and demolition of buildings, structures, facilities, signs and other improvements and the establishment of zones governing uses of land and buildings;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the control of agriculture, businesses, trades, occupations, amusements, sports and other activities or undertakings, and the places where those activities or undertakings may be carried on;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the preservation of public health and the prevention of disease;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the inspection of buildings, structures, facilities and other improvements for the purpose of the enforcement of regulations made under paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the abatement and prevention of nuisances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">s</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the use, transportation and storage of pesticides and other toxic substances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">t</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>public safety, including the control of firearms;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">u</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the control of domestic animals, including the impounding or destruction of such animals found at large;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">v</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the control of access to the Park by aircraft;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">w</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the summary removal from the Park, by park wardens or enforcement officers, of persons found contravening specified provisions of this Act, the regulations or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, and the exclusion from the Park for prescribed periods of those persons or persons convicted of offences under those provisions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">x</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the acquisition or the sale of souvenirs, consumer articles and publications; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">y</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the removal of private property and the disposal of abandoned property.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Superintendent’s powers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under this section may authorize the superintendent, in the circumstances and subject to the limits that may be specified in the regulations,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to vary any requirement of the regulations for purposes of public safety or the protection of natural, cultural, historical or archaeological resources in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to issue, amend, suspend and revoke permits, licences and other authorizations in relation to any matter that is the subject of the regulations and to set their terms and conditions; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to order the taking of any action to counter any threat to public health or to remedy the consequences of any breach of the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Land claims agreements</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the carrying on of traditional renewable resource harvesting activities in any area of the Park in the case where an agreement for the settlement of an Aboriginal land claim entered into by the Government of Canada makes provision for those activities in that area or where Aboriginal people have existing Aboriginal or treaty rights to those activities in that area.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Variation by superintendent</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under this section may authorize the superintendent, in the circumstances and subject to the limits that may be specified in the regulations, to vary any requirement of the regulations for purposes of public safety or the protection of natural, cultural, historical or archaeological resources in the Park.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Regulations made under this Act may incorporate by reference any documents produced by a person or body other than the Minister or the superintendent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reproduced or translated material</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under this Act may incorporate by reference documents that the Minister or the superintendent reproduces or translates from documents produced by a body or person other than the Minister or the superintendent</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with any adaptations of form and reference that will facilitate their incorporation into the regulations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in a form that sets out only the parts of them that apply for the purposes of the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Jointly produced documents</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Regulations made under this Act may incorporate by reference documents that the Minister or the superintendent produces jointly with another government for the purpose of harmonizing the regulations with other laws.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Internally produced standards</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Regulations made under this Act may incorporate by reference technical or explanatory documents that the Minister or the superintendent produces, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>specifications, classifications, illustrations, graphs or other information of a technical nature; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>test methods, procedures, operational standards, safety standards or performance standards of a technical nature.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Incorporation as amended from time to time</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Documents may be incorporated by reference as amended from time to time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) to (5) are for greater certainty and do not limit any authority to make regulations incorporating material by reference that exists apart from those subsections.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accessibility</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Minister must ensure that any document that is incorporated by reference in the regulations is accessible.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Defence</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>A person is not liable to be found guilty of an offence or subjected to an administrative sanction for any contravention in respect of which a document that is incorporated by reference in the regulations is relevant unless, at the time of the alleged contravention, the document was accessible as required by subsection (7) or it was otherwise accessible to the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No registration or publication</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a document that is incorporated by reference in the regulations is not required to be transmitted for registration or published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> by reason only that it is incorporated by reference.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ENFORCEMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of park wardens</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>The Minister may designate persons appointed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal> whose duties include law enforcement to be park wardens for the enforcement of the provisions of this Act and the regulations and for the preservation and maintenance of the public peace in the Park, and for those purposes park wardens are peace officers within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Designation of enforcement officers</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>The Minister may designate persons or classes of persons who are employed in the federal public administration or by a provincial, municipal or local authority or an Aboriginal government and whose duties include law enforcement to be enforcement officers for the purposes of the enforcement of specified provisions of this Act or the regulations, and for those purposes enforcement officers have the powers of, and are entitled to the protection provided by law to, peace officers within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may designate persons or classes of persons employed in the federal public administration or by a provincial, municipal or local authority or an Aboriginal government for the purpose of the enforcement of the provisions of this Act and the regulations that relate to offences that have been designated as contraventions under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitations regarding designations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may specify that a designation is in respect of all or specified offences under this Act that have been designated as contraventions under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Certificate of designation and oath</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every park warden and enforcement officer and every person designated under section <XRefInternal>25</XRefInternal> must be provided with a certificate of designation in a form approved by the Minister and must take and subscribe an oath prescribed by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitations must be specified</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The certificate must specify the limitations, if any, to which the designation is subject.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of passage</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>In the discharge of their duties, park wardens and enforcement officers and any persons accompanying them may enter on and pass through or over private property without being liable for doing so and without any person having the right to object to that use of the property.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>Park wardens and enforcement officers are not personally liable for any thing done or omitted to be done in good faith in the exercise or performance of their powers, duties or functions under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Arrest without warrant</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>A park warden or enforcement officer may, in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code,</XRefExternal> arrest without warrant any person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>whom the warden or officer finds committing an offence under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>who the warden or officer believes, on reasonable grounds, has committed or is about to commit an offence under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Search and seizure</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A park warden or enforcement officer may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enter and search any place and open and examine any package or receptacle in accordance with a warrant issued under subsection (2) at any time during the day or, if so specified in the warrant, during the night; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>seize any thing that the warden or officer believes on reasonable grounds is a thing described in subsection (2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to issue warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A justice of the peace may, on <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application, issue a warrant authorizing a park warden or enforcement officer named in the warrant to, subject to any conditions specified in it, enter and search any place, including any building or any vehicle, vessel or other conveyance, or open and examine any package or receptacle, if the justice of the peace is satisfied by information on oath that there are reasonable grounds to believe that there is in the place, package or receptacle</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any thing in relation to which there are reasonable grounds to believe an offence under this Act has been committed; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any thing that there are reasonable grounds to believe will afford evidence with respect to the commission of such an offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Warrant not necessary</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A park warden or enforcement officer may exercise any powers under subsection (1) without a warrant if the conditions for obtaining a warrant exist but by reason of exigent circumstances it would not be practical to obtain one.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Custody of things seized</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3) and sections <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>44</XRefInternal>, if a park warden or enforcement officer seizes a thing under this Act or under a warrant issued under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>sections 489.1 and 490 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> apply; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the warden or officer, or any person that the warden or officer designates, must retain custody of the thing, subject to any order made under section 490 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Forfeiture if ownership not ascertainable</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the lawful ownership of or entitlement to a seized thing cannot be ascertained within 30 days after its seizure, the thing or any proceeds of its disposition are forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada, if the thing was seized by a park warden or by an enforcement officer employed in the federal public administration, or to Her Majesty in right of a province, if the thing was seized by an enforcement officer employed by a provincial, municipal or local authority or an Aboriginal government.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Perishable things</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a seized thing is perishable, the park warden or enforcement officer may dispose of it or destroy it, and any proceeds of its disposition must be paid to the lawful owner or person lawfully entitled to possession of the thing, unless proceedings under this Act are commenced within 90 days after its seizure, in which case they must be retained by the warden or officer pending the outcome of those proceedings.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Liability for costs</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>If a thing is seized under this Act, the person who owned the thing at the time that it was seized, the person who had charge or control of the thing immediately before it was seized and the person who possessed it immediately before it was seized are jointly and severally, or solidarily, liable for all the costs of seizure, detention, maintenance and forfeiture, including any destruction or disposal costs, incurred by Her Majesty in right of Canada in relation to the thing in excess of any proceeds of its disposition.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OFFENCES AND PENALTIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(1) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $15,000 and not more than $1,000,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $30,000 and not more than $2,000,000,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation, other than one referred to in subparagraph (iii),</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $500,000 and not more than $6,000,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $1,000,000 and not more than $12,000,000, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation that the court has determined under section 36 to be a small revenue corporation,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $75,000 and not more than $4,000,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $150,000 and not more than $8,000,000; or</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on summary conviction,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $5,000 and not more than $300,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $10,000 and not more than $600,000,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation, other than one referred to in subparagraph (iii),</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $100,000 and not more than $4,000,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $200,000 and not more than $8,000,000, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation that the court has determined under section 36 to be a small revenue corporation,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $25,000 and not more than $2,000,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $50,000 and not more than $4,000,000.</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes paragraph <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $7,500 and not more than $500,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $15,000 and not more than $1,000,000,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation, other than one referred to in subparagraph (iii),</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $400,000 and not more than $5,000,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $800,000 and not more than $10,000,000, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation that the court has determined under section <XRefInternal>36</XRefInternal> to be a small revenue corporation,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $25,000 and not more than $3,000,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $50,000 and not more than $6,000,000; or</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on summary conviction,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $4,000 and not more than $225,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $8,000 and not more than $450,000,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation, other than one referred to in subparagraph (iii),</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $50,000 and not more than $3,000,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $100,000 and not more than $6,000,000, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation that the court has determined under section <XRefInternal>36</XRefInternal> to be a small revenue corporation,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not less than $15,000 and not more than $1,250,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not less than $30,000 and not more than $2,500,000.</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes any of paragraphs <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal>(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>), any provision of the regulations or any condition of a permit, licence or other authorization issued under the regulations or under section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal> is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $100,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $200,000,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation, other than one referred to in subparagraph (iii),</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $500,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $1,000,000, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation that the court has determined under section <XRefInternal>36</XRefInternal> to be a small revenue corporation,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $250,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $500,000; or</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on summary conviction,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $25,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $50,000,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation, other than one referred to in subparagraph (iii),</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $250,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $500,000, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation that the court has determined under section <XRefInternal>36</XRefInternal> to be a small revenue corporation,</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>for a first offence, to a fine of not more than $50,000, and</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>for a second or subsequent offence, to a fine of not more than $100,000.</Text></Clause></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Offences involving more than one animal, plant or object</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an offence involves more than one wild animal, plant or object, the fine to be imposed in respect of that offence may, despite section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>, be the total of the fines that would have been imposed if each of the wild animals, plants or objects had been the subject of a separate information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Continuing offences</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an offence is committed or continued on more than one day, it constitutes a separate offence for each day on which it is committed or continued.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming — second and subsequent offence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>, a conviction for a particular offence under this Act is deemed to be a conviction for a second or subsequent offence if the court is satisfied that the offender has been previously convicted of a substantially similar offence under federal or provincial legislation that relates to environmental or wildlife protection or conservation or to the protection of natural, cultural, historical or archaeological resources.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (3), only previous convictions on indictment or on summary conviction, or under any similar procedure under any Act of the legislature of a province, are to be considered as previous convictions.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Due diligence defence</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>A person is not to be found guilty of an offence under this Act if they establish that they exercised due diligence to prevent its commission.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Determination of small revenue corporation status</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>For the purpose of section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>, a court may determine a corporation to be a small revenue corporation if the court is satisfied that the corporation’s gross revenues for the 12 months immediately before the day on which the subject matter of the proceedings arose — or, if it arose on more than one day, for the 12 months immediately before the first day on which the subject matter of the proceedings arose — were not more than $5,000,000.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Fundamental purpose of sentencing</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Text>The fundamental purpose of sentencing for offences under this Act is to contribute to respect for the law establishing and protecting the Park through the imposition of just sanctions that have as their objectives</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to deter the offender and any other person from committing offences under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to denounce unlawful conduct that damages or creates a risk of damage to the Park; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to restore resources in the Park.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Sentencing principles</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In addition to the principles and factors that the court is otherwise required to consider, including those set out in sections 718.1 to 718.21 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the court must consider the following principles when sentencing a person who is convicted of an offence under this Act:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of the fine should be increased to account for every aggravating factor associated with the offence, including the aggravating factors set out in subsection (2); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of the fine should reflect the gravity of each aggravating factor associated with the offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aggravating factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The aggravating factors are the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offence caused damage or risk of damage to resources in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offence caused damage or risk of damage to any unique, rare, particularly important or vulnerable resources in the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the damage caused by the offence is extensive, persistent or irreparable;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offender committed the offence intentionally or recklessly;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>by committing the offence or failing to take action to prevent its commission, the offender increased their revenue or decreased their costs or intended to increase their revenue or decrease their costs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offender committed the offence despite having been warned by the superintendent, a park warden or an enforcement officer of the circumstances that subsequently became the subject of the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the offender has a history of non-compliance with federal or provincial legislation that relates to environmental or wildlife protection or conservation or to the protection of natural, cultural, historical or archaeological resources; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>after the commission of the offence, the offender</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>attempted to conceal its commission,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>failed to take prompt action to prevent, mitigate or remediate its effects, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>failed to take prompt action to reduce the risk of committing similar offences in the future.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence of aggravating factor</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The absence of an aggravating factor set out in subsection (2) is not a mitigating factor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of <DefinedTermEn>damage</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), <DefinedTermEn>damage</DefinedTermEn> includes loss of use value and non-use value.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court is satisfied of the existence of one or more of the aggravating factors set out in subsection (2) but decides not to increase the amount of the fine because of that factor, it must give reasons for that decision.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Relief from minimum fine</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>The court may impose a fine that is less than the minimum amount provided for in section <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal> if it is satisfied, on the basis of evidence submitted to the court, that the minimum fine would cause undue financial hardship. The court must provide reasons if it imposes a fine that is less than the minimum amount provided for in that section.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Additional fine</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under this Act and the court is satisfied that, as a result of the commission of the offence, the person acquired any property, benefit or advantage, the court must order the person to pay an additional fine in an amount of money equal to the court’s estimation of the value of that property, benefit or advantage. The additional fine may exceed the maximum amount of any fine that may otherwise be imposed under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to shareholders</MarginalNote><Label>41.</Label><Text>If a corporation that has shareholders is convicted of an offence under this Act, the court must make an order directing the corporation to notify its shareholders, in the manner and within the time directed by the court, of the facts relating to the commission of the offence and of the details of the punishment imposed.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Liability of directors, officers, etc., of corporations</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a corporation commits an offence under this Act, any director, officer, agent or mandatary of the corporation who directed, authorized, assented to, acquiesced in or participated in the commission of the offence is a party to and guilty of the offence and is liable on conviction to the penalty provided for by this Act for an individual in respect of the offence committed by the corporation, whether or not the corporation has been prosecuted or convicted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties of directors and officers of corporations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every director and officer of a corporation must take all reasonable care to ensure that the corporation complies with</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>orders made by a court or the superintendent under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>43.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence, the court may, in addition to any punishment imposed, order that any seized thing, or any proceeds of its disposition, be forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return if no forfeiture ordered</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the court does not order the forfeiture, the seized thing or the proceeds of its disposition must be returned or paid to its owner or the person lawfully entitled to it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retention or sale</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a fine is imposed on a person convicted of an offence, any seized thing, or any proceeds of its disposition, may be retained until the fine is paid or the thing may be sold in satisfaction of the fine and the proceeds applied, in whole or in part, in payment of the fine.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Disposition by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>44.</Label><Text>Any seized thing that has been forfeited under this Act to Her Majesty in right of Canada or abandoned by its owner may be dealt with and disposed of as the Minister may direct.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application of fines</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>All fines received by the Receiver General in respect of the commission of an offence under this Act, other than fines collected under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal>, are to be credited to the Environmental Damages Fund, an account in the accounts of Canada, and used for purposes related to protecting, conserving or restoring the Park or for administering that Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recommendations of court</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court imposing the fine may recommend to the Minister that all or a portion of the fine credited to the Environmental Damages Fund be paid to a person or organization specified by the court for a purpose referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Orders of court</MarginalNote><Label>46.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under this Act, the court may, in addition to any punishment imposed and having regard to the nature of the offence and the circumstances surrounding its commission, make an order having any or all of the following effects:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prohibiting the person from doing any act or engaging in any activity that may, in the opinion of the court, result in the continuation or repetition of the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to take any action that the court considers appropriate to remedy or avoid any damage to any resources in the Park that resulted or may result from the commission of the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to compensate any person, monetarily or otherwise, in whole or in part, for the cost of any remedial or preventive action that is taken, that is caused to be taken or that is to be taken as a result of the act or omission that constituted the offence, including the costs of assessing the appropriate remedial or preventive action;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to post a bond or pay into court an amount of money that the court considers appropriate for the purpose of ensuring compliance with any prohibition, direction or requirement mentioned in this section;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to prepare and implement a pollution prevention plan or an environmental emergency plan;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to carry out, in the manner established by the Minister, monitoring of the environmental effects of any activity or works on resources in the Park or directing the person to pay, in the manner specified by the court, an amount of money for that purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to implement an environmental management system approved by the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to have an environmental audit conducted by a person of a class specified by the Minister at the times specified by the Minister and to remedy any deficiencies revealed during the audit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to pay to Her Majesty in right of Canada an amount of money that the court considers appropriate for the purpose of promoting the protection, conservation or restoration of the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to publish, in the manner specified by the court, the facts relating to the commission of the offence and the details of the punishment imposed, including any orders made under this subsection;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to notify, at the person’s own cost and in the manner specified by the court, any person aggrieved or affected by the person’s conduct of the facts relating to the commission of the offence and of the details of the punishment imposed, including any orders made under this subsection;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to submit to the Minister, if requested to do so by the Minister at any time within three years after the date of conviction, any information with respect to the person’s activities that the court considers appropriate in the circumstances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to perform community service, subject to any reasonable conditions that are imposed in the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to pay, in the manner specified by the court, an amount of money to enable research to be conducted into the protection, conservation or restoration of the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring the person to surrender to the Minister any permit, licence or other authorization issued to the person under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prohibiting the person from applying for any new permit, licence or other authorization under this Act during any period that the court considers appropriate;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to pay, in the manner specified by the court, an amount of money to environmental or other groups, to assist in their work related to the Park;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>directing the person to pay, in the manner specified by the court, an amount of money to an educational institution, including for scholarships for students enrolled in studies related to the environment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">s</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring the person to comply with any other conditions that the court considers appropriate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Suspended sentence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of an offence under this Act and the court suspends the passing of sentence under paragraph 731(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the court may, in addition to any probation order made under that paragraph, make an order referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Imposition of sentence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a person does not comply with an order made under subsection (2) or is convicted of another offence, the court may, within three years after the order was made, on the application of the prosecution, impose any sentence that could have been imposed if the passing of sentence had not been suspended.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a person fails to comply with an order made under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>), the Minister may, in the manner that the court directed the person to do so, publish the facts relating to the commission of the offence and the details of the punishment imposed and recover the costs of publication from the person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Debt due to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the court makes an order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) directing a person to pay an amount of money to Her Majesty in right of Canada, or if the Minister incurs publication costs under subsection (4), the amount or the costs, as the case may be, constitute a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada and may be recovered in any court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Enforcement</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the court makes an order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) directing a person to pay an amount of money to any person other than Her Majesty in right of Canada and the amount is not paid without delay, that other person may, by filing the order, enter as a judgment, in the superior court of the province in which the trial was held, the amount ordered to be paid, and that judgment is enforceable against the person who was directed to pay the amount in the same manner as if it were a judgment rendered against the offender in that court in civil proceedings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cancellation or suspension of permits, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the court makes an order under paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>), any permit, licence or other authorization to which the order relates is cancelled unless the court makes an order suspending it for any period that the court considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Coming into force and duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (1) comes into force on the day on which it is made or on any other day that the court may determine and must not continue in force for more than three years after that day unless the court provides otherwise in the order.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Compensation for loss of property</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person has been convicted of an offence under this Act, the court may, at the time sentence is imposed and on the application of the person aggrieved, order the offender to pay to the aggrieved person an amount of money by way of satisfaction or compensation for loss of or damage to property suffered by that person as a result of the commission of the offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Enforcement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the amount ordered to be paid under subsection (1) is not paid without delay, the aggrieved person may, by filing the order, enter as a judgment, in the superior court of the province in which the trial was held, the amount ordered to be paid, and that judgment is enforceable against the offender in the same manner as if it were a judgment rendered against the offender in that court in civil proceedings.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Compensation for cost of remedial or preventive action</MarginalNote><Label>48.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A court must not, under paragraph <XRefInternal>46</XRefInternal>(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), order a person convicted of an offence to compensate another person for the cost of any remedial or preventive action referred to in that paragraph if the other person is entitled to make a claim for compensation for that cost under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Liability Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compensation for loss or damage — property</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A court must not, under subsection <XRefInternal>47</XRefInternal>(1), order a person convicted of an offence to pay to another person an amount of money by way of satisfaction or compensation for loss of or damage to property if the other person is entitled to make a claim for compensation for that loss or damage under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Marine Liability Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>49.</Label><Text>No proceedings by way of summary conviction in respect of an offence under this Act may be instituted more than five years after the day on which the subject matter of the proceedings arose, unless the prosecutor and the defendant agree that they may be instituted after the five years.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>50.</Label><Text>If an offence under this Act is designated as a contravention under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Contraventions Act</XRefExternal>, subsection 8(5) of that Act does not apply in respect of the fine that may be established for that contravention.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Publication of information about contraventions</MarginalNote><Label>51.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of encouraging compliance with this Act, the Minister must publish, in a registry accessible to the public, information about all convictions of corporations for offences under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retention</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Information in the registry is to be maintained for a minimum of five years.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>52.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, 10 years after the day on which this section comes into force and every 10 years after that, undertake a review of sections <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>51</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must, no later than one year after the day on which the review is undertaken, cause a report on the review to be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>NON-APPLICATION OF STATUTORY INSTRUMENTS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>53.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a permit, licence or other authorization issued under this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>CLAIM IN RESPECT OF ABORIGINAL RIGHTS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Aboriginal resource harvesting</MarginalNote><Label>54.</Label><Text>If an area of the Park is subject to a claim in respect of Aboriginal rights that has been accepted for negotiation by the Government of Canada, nothing in this Act precludes the carrying on of traditional renewable resource harvesting activities in that area by the Aboriginal people who have made that claim.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. L-6</MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Lands Surveys Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 7, s. 101</MarginalNote><Label>55.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 24(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Lands Surveys Act</XRefExternal> before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any lands belonging to Her Majesty in right of Canada or of which the Government of Canada has power to dispose that are situated in Yukon, the Northwest Territories or Nunavut and any lands that are</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 24(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any lands belonging to Her Majesty in right of Canada or of which the Government of Canada has power to dispose that are situated in any National Park of Canada or in the Rouge National Urban Park established by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rouge National Urban Park Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1998, c. 31</MarginalNote><TitleText>Parks Canada Agency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>56.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>other protected heritage areas</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parks Canada Agency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by deleting “and” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b.1</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Rouge National Urban Park; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 2, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>57.</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>areas of natural or historical significance to the nation, including national parks, national marine conservation areas, national historic sites, historic canals, historic museums established under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal>, Saguenay-St. Lawrence Marine Park and Rouge National Urban Park;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 18, s. 40</MarginalNote><Label>58.</Label><Text>Subsection 32(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Management plans</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In addition to the duties in relation to management plans under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</XRefExternal>, the Chief Executive Officer shall, within five years after the establishment of a national historic site or other protected heritage area, other than the Rouge National Urban Park, or within five years after the coming into force of this section, whichever is later, provide the Minister with a management plan for that national historic site or other protected heritage area in respect of any matter that the Minister deems appropriate, including, but not limited to, commemorative and ecological integrity, resource protection or visitor use, and that plan shall be tabled in each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>59.</Label><Text>Part 1 of the schedule to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Rouge National Urban Park Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur le parc urbain national de la Rouge</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 29</MarginalNote><TitleText>Species at Risk Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>60.</Label><Text>Subsection 58(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Species at Risk Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protected areas</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the critical habitat or a portion of the critical habitat is in a national park of Canada named and described in Schedule 1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal>, the Rouge National Urban Park established by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rouge National Urban Park Act</XRefExternal>, a marine protected area under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Oceans Act</XRefExternal>, a migratory bird sanctuary under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Migratory Birds Convention Act, 1994</XRefExternal> or a national wildlife area under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Wildlife Act</XRefExternal>, the competent Minister must, within 90 days after the recovery strategy or action plan that identified the critical habitat is included in the public registry, publish in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> a description of the critical habitat or portion that is in that park, area or sanctuary.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2009, c. 14, s. 126</MarginalNote><TitleText>Environmental Violations Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 19, s. 53(1)</MarginalNote><Label>61.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Environmental Act</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Environmental Violations Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Environmental Act</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>loi environnementale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Environmental Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Antarctic Environmental Protection Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Water Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Wildlife Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Assessment Act, 2012</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Environmental Protection Act, 1999</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International River Improvements Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Migratory Birds Convention Act, 1994</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rouge National Urban Park Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Saguenay-St. Lawrence Marine Park Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with respect to violations that relate to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Marine Conservation Areas Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada National Parks Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Rouge National Urban Park Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Saguenay-St. Lawrence Marine Park Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister responsible for the Parks Canada Agency.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>62.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal> and subsection <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal>(3))</OriginatingRef><TitleText>ROUGE NATIONAL URBAN PARK</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In the Province of Ontario, in the Geographic Township of Markham, all of those lands, including all mines and minerals, more particularly described as follows:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Firstly;</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 1 on Plan 102393 CLSR recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, being part of the West half of Lot 31, Concession 9,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>containing 17.07 hectares, more or less;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Secondly;</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 1 on Plan 102394 CLSR recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, being part of Lots 26, 27, 28 and 29, Concession 8,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>containing 25.56 hectares, more or less;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Thirdly;</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Parcel 1 on Plan 102395 CLSR recorded in the Canada Lands Surveys Records at Ottawa, being part of Lots 18, 19 and 20, Concession 9,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>containing 163.30 hectares, more or less.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision></Schedule></Bill>