<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-42</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>2</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>62-63-64</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2013-2014-2015</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Firearms Act and the Criminal Code and to make a related amendment and a consequential amendment to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Common Sense Firearms Licensing Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Common Sense Firearms Licensing</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2015</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>27</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2015</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-10-6">90749</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> to simplify and clarify the firearms licensing regime for individuals, to limit the discretionary authority of chief firearms officers and to provide for the sharing of information on commercial importations of firearms.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to strengthen the provisions relating to orders prohibiting the possession of weapons, including firearms, when a person is sentenced for an offence involving domestic violence. Lastly, it defines <DefinedTermEn>non-restricted firearm</DefinedTermEn> and gives the Governor in Council authority to prescribe a firearm to be non-restricted and expanded authority to prescribe a firearm to be restricted.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Common Sense Firearms Licensing Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">FIREARMS ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 9(1)</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermFr>autorisation de transport</DefinedTermFr> in subsection 2(1) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>autorisation de transport</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>authorization to transport</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermFr>autorisation de transport</DefinedTermFr> Toute autorisation prévue à l’article 19.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>To be interpreted with <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided, words and expressions used in this Act have the meanings assigned to them by section 2 or 84 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>. Subsections 117.15(3) and (4) of that Act apply to those words and expressions.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Subsection 5(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (2), in determining whether a non-resident who is 18 years old or older and by or on behalf of whom an application is made for a 60-day licence authorizing the non-resident to possess non-restricted firearms is eligible to hold a licence under subsection (1), a chief firearms officer or, on a reference under section 74, a provincial court judge may but need not have regard to the criteria described in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 7(1) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Cours sur la sécurité des armes à feu</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>La délivrance d’un permis à un particulier est subordonnée à l’une des conditions suivantes :</Text><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>la réussite du Cours canadien de sécurité dans le maniement des armes à feu, contrôlé par l’examen y afférent, dont est chargé un instructeur désigné par le contrôleur des armes à feu;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>passed, before the commencement day, the tests, as administered by an instructor who is designated by a chief firearms officer, that form part of that Course;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 7(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>avant le 1<Sup>er</Sup> janvier 1995, la réussite d’un cours agréé<?Pub Caret?> — au cours de la période commençant le 1<Sup>er</Sup> janvier 1993 et se terminant le 31 décembre 1994 — par le procureur général de la province où il a eu lieu pour l’application de l’article 106 de la loi antérieure;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>avant le 1<Sup>er</Sup> janvier 1995, la réussite d’un examen agréé — au cours de la période commençant le 1<Sup>er</Sup> janvier 1993 et se terminant le 31 décembre 1994 — par le procureur général de la province où il a eu lieu pour l’application de l’article 106 de la loi antérieure.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on the commencement day, was an individual referred to in paragraph 7(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) as it read immediately before that day and held a licence.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 7(2) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cours sur la sécurité des armes à feu à autorisation restreinte</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>La délivrance d’un permis de possession d’une arme à feu prohibée ou d’une arme à feu à autorisation restreinte à un particulier est subordonnée à l’une des conditions suivantes :</Text><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>la réussite d’un cours sur la sécurité des armes à feu à autorisation restreinte, agréé par le ministre fédéral et contrôlé par un examen, dont est chargé un instructeur désigné par le contrôleur des armes à feu;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>passed, before the commencement day, a restricted firearms safety test, as administered by an instructor who is designated by a chief firearms officer, that is approved by the federal Minister.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsection 7(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on the commencement day, was an individual referred to in paragraph 7(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) as it read immediately before that day and held a licence authorizing the individual to possess prohibited firearms or restricted firearms.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is a non-resident who is 18 years old or older and by or on behalf of whom an application is made for a 60-day licence authorizing the non-resident to possess non-restricted firearms.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 12</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>Subsection 9(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Employees — firearms</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3.1), a business other than a carrier is eligible to hold a licence that authorizes the possession of firearms only if every employee of the business who, in the course of duties of employment, handles or would handle firearms is the holder of a licence authorizing the holder to acquire non-restricted firearms.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 16(3)</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Subsection 19(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Target practice or competition</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>In the case of an authorization to transport issued for a reason referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) within the province where the holder of the authorization resides, the specified places must include all shooting clubs and shooting ranges that are approved under section 29 and that are located in that province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception for prohibited firearms other than prohibited handguns</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), an individual must not be authorized to transport a prohibited firearm, other than a handgun referred to in subsection 12(6.1), between specified places except for the purposes referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Automatic authorization to transport — licence renewal</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2.3), an individ­ual who holds a licence authorizing the individual to possess prohibited firearms or restricted firearms must, if the licence is renewed, be authorized to transport them within the individual’s province of residence</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to and from all shooting clubs and shooting ranges that are approved under section 29;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to and from any place a peace officer, firearms officer or chief firearms officer is located, for verification, registration or disposal in accordance with this Act or Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to and from a business that holds a licence authorizing it to repair or appraise prohibited firearms or restricted firearms;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to and from a gun show; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to a port of exit in order to take them outside Canada, and from a port of entry.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Automatic authorization to transport — transfer</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2.3), if a chief firearms officer has authorized the transfer of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm to an individual who holds a licence authorizing the individual to possess prohibited firearms or restricted firearms, the individual must be authorized</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to transport the firearm within the individual’s province of residence from the place where the individual acquires it to the place where they may possess it under section 17; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to transport their prohibited firearms and restricted firearms within the individual’s province of residence to and from the places referred to in any of paragraphs (2.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>An individual must not be authorized under subsection (2.1) or (2.2) to transport the following firearms to or from the places referred to in paragraph (2.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>):</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a prohibited firearm, other than a handgun referred to in subsection 12(6.1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a restricted firearm or a handgun referred to in subsection 12(6.1) whose transfer was approved, in accordance with subparagraph 28(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii), for the purpose of forming part of a gun collection.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 6, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The portion of section 23 of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization to transfer non-restricted firearms</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>A person may transfer a non-restricted firearm if, at the time of the transfer,</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 35(4) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-compliance</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a non-restricted firearm is declared at a customs office to a customs officer and</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 6, s. 16</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>Paragraph 36(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the expiry of 60 days after the importation, in the case of a non-restricted firearm; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following in numerical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to provide information</MarginalNote><Label>42.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A business may import a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm only if the business completes the prescribed form containing the prescribed information and provides it by electronic or other means to the Registrar before the importation and to a customs officer before or at the time of the importation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information sharing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Registrar and a customs officer may provide each other with any form or information that they receive under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 36</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>Subsection 54(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Applications</MarginalNote><Label>54.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A licence, registration certificate or authorization, other than an authorization referred to in subsection 19(2.1) or (2.2), may be issued only on application made in the prescribed form — which form may be in writing or electronic — or in the prescribed manner. The application must set out the prescribed information and be accompanied by payment of the prescribed fees.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 58 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — licence or authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>However, a chief firearms officer’s power to attach a condition to a licence, an authorization to carry or an authorization to transport is subject to the regulations.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 58(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mineurs : consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Dans le cas d’un particulier âgé de moins de dix-huit ans qui n’est pas admissible au permis prévu au paragraphe 8(2) (chasse de subsistance par les mineurs), le contrôleur des armes à feu consulte le père ou la mère du particulier ou la personne qui en a la garde avant d’assortir le permis d’une condition.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 61 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Automatic authorization to transport</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>An authorization to transport referred to in subsection 19(1.1), (2.1) or (2.2) must take the form of a condition attached to a licence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 61(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Businesses</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A licence that is issued to a business must specify each particular activity that the licence authorizes in relation to firearms, cross-bows, prohibited weapons, restricted weapons, prohibited devices, ammunition or prohibited ammunition.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 8, s. 40(1)</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>Subsection 64(1.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension period</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), if a licence for firearms is not renewed before it expires, the licence is extended for a period of six months beginning on the day on which it would have expired under that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No use or acquisition</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>The holder of a licence that is extended under subsection (1.1) must not, until the renewal of their licence, use their firearms or acquire any firearms or ammunition.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorizations — no extension</MarginalNote><Label>(1.3)</Label><Text>The extension of a licence under subsection (1.1) does not result in the extension of any authorization to carry or authorization to transport beyond the day on which the licence would have expired under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorizations — issuance</MarginalNote><Label>(1.4)</Label><Text>During the extension period, the following authorizations must not be issued to the holder of the licence:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an authorization to carry; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an authorization to transport, unless it is issued</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for a reason referred to in subparagraph 19(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) or (ii), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>because the holder wishes to transport a firearm for disposal through sale or exportation.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>Subsection 83(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>all information provided to the Registrar under section 42.2;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Text>Section 117 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the possession and transportation of firearms during the extension period referred to in subsection 64(1.1);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>Subsection 121(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorizations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A permit that is deemed to be a licence authorizes the holder to possess non-restricted firearms.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">CRIMINAL CODE</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>Subsection 84(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>non-restricted firearm</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>arme à feu sans restriction</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>non-restricted firearm</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a firearm that is neither a prohibited firearm nor a restricted firearm, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a firearm that is prescribed to be a non-restricted firearm;</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 6, s. 2(1)</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 91(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized possession of firearm</MarginalNote><Label>91.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), every person commits an offence who possesses a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm or a non-restricted firearm without being the holder of</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 91(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who possesses a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition while the person is under the direct and immediate supervision of a person who may lawfully possess it, for the purpose of using it in a manner in which the supervising person may lawfully use it; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139(E); 2012, c. 6, s. 2(2)(F)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 91(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who comes into possession of a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition by the operation of law and who, within a reasonable period after acquiring possession of it,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 6, s. 3(1)</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 92(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Possession of firearm knowing its possession is unauthorized</MarginalNote><Label>92.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), every person commits an offence who possesses a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm or a non-restricted firearm knowing that the person is not the holder of</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 92(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who possesses a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition while the person is under the direct and immediate supervision of a person who may lawfully possess it, for the purpose of using it in a manner in which the supervising person may lawfully use it; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139(E); 2012, c. 6, s. 3(2)(F)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 92(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who comes into possession of a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition by the operation of law and who, within a reasonable period after acquiring possession of it,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 6</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 93(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Possession at unauthorized place</MarginalNote><Label>93.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), every person commits an offence who, being the holder of an authorization or a licence under which the person may possess a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or prohibited ammunition, possesses them at a place that is</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139; 2012, c. 6, s. 4(1)</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 94(1) of the Act before subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized possession in motor vehicle</MarginalNote><Label>94.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (4), every person commits an offence who is an occupant of a motor vehicle in which the person knows there is a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, other than a replica firearm, or any prohibited ammunition, unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm or a non-restricted firearm,</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 94(3) and (4) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to an occupant of a motor vehicle who, on becoming aware of the presence of the firearm, weapon, device or ammunition in the motor vehicle, attempted to leave the motor vehicle, to the extent that it was feasible to do so, or actually left the motor vehicle.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply to an occupant of a motor vehicle when the occupant or any other occupant of the motor vehicle is a person who came into possession of the firearm, weapon, device or ammunition by the operation of law.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 99(1) of the Act after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, any ammunition or any prohibited ammunition knowing that the person is not authorized to do so under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> or any other Act of Parliament or any regulations made under any Act of Parliament.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 10</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 99(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment — firearm</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) when the object in question is a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited device, any ammunition or any prohibited ammunition is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 100(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Possession for purpose of weapons trafficking</MarginalNote><Label>100.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who possesses a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, any ammunition or any prohibited ammunition for the purpose of</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 11</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 100(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment — firearm</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) when the object in question is a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited device, any ammunition or any prohibited ammunition is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Subsection 101(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer without authority</MarginalNote><Label>101.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who transfers a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, any ammunition or any prohibited ammunition to any person otherwise than under the authority of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> or any other Act of Parliament or any regulations made under an Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 103(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 12</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 103(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment — firearm</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) when the object in question is a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>Paragraph 104(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 105(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>having lost a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, any prohibited ammunition, an authorization, a licence or a registration certificate, or having had it stolen from the person’s possession, does not with reasonable despatch report the loss to a peace officer, to a firearms officer or a chief firearms officer; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on finding a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device or any prohibited ammunition that the person has reasonable grounds to believe has been lost or abandoned, does not with reasonable despatch deliver it to a peace officer, a firearms officer or a chief firearms officer or report the finding to a peace officer, a firearms officer or a chief firearms officer.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>Subsection 107(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>False statements</MarginalNote><Label>107.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person commits an offence who knowingly makes, before a peace officer, firearms officer or chief firearms officer, a false report or statement concerning the loss, theft or destruction of a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm, a non-restricted firearm, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, any prohibited ammunition, an authorization, a licence or a registration certificate.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Text>Subsection 109(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an indictable offence in the commission of which violence was used, threatened or attempted against</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the person’s current or former intimate partner,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a child or parent of the person or of anyone referred to in subparagraph (i), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any person who resides with the person or with anyone referred to in subparagraph (i) or (ii),</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 110(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence, other than an offence referred to in any of paragraphs 109(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), in the commission of which violence against a person was used, threatened or attempted, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 110 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (2), an order made under subsection (1) may be imposed for life or for any shorter duration if, in the commission of the offence, violence was used, threatened or attempted against</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person’s current or former intimate partner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a child or parent of the person or of anyone referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any person who resides with the person or with anyone referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 110:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>intimate partner</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>110.1</Label><Text>In sections 109 and 110, <DefinedTermEn>intimate partner</DefinedTermEn> includes a spouse, a common-law partner and a dating partner.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 6, s. 8</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>Paragraph 117.03(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person in possession of a prohibited firearm, a restricted firearm or a non-restricted firearm who fails, on demand, to produce, for inspection by the peace officer, an authorization or a licence under which the person may lawfully possess the firearm and, in the case of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm, a registration certificate for it, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34.</Label><Text>Section 117.15 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-restricted firearm</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite the definitions <DefinedTermEn>prohibited firearm</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>restricted firearm</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 84(1), a firearm that is prescribed to be a non-restricted firearm is deemed not to be a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restricted firearm</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite the definition <DefinedTermEn>prohibited firearm</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 84(1), a firearm that is prescribed to be a restricted firearm is deemed not to be a prohibited firearm.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>RELATED AMENDMENT TO THE <XRefExternal reference-type="act">CUSTOMS ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>35.</Label><Text>Subsection 107(5) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an official solely for the purpose of administering or enforcing the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2012, c. 6</MarginalNote><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENT TO THE <XRefExternal reference-type="act">ENDING THE LONG-GUN REGISTRY ACT</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>36.</Label><Text>Subsection 30(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal> is amended by replac­ing the paragraph 36(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) that it enacts with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the expiry of 60 days after the importation, in the case of a non-restricted firearm; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISION</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Conversion of possession only licence</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Text>A licence that is issued under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> and that is held by an individual referred to in paragraph 7(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of that Act, as it read immediately before the day on which this section comes into force, authorizes the holder to acquire any firearms that they are authorized to possess under the licence and that are acquired by the holder on or after that day and before the expiration or revocation of the licence.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(4), (7) and (8) and section <XRefInternal>37</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subection <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>(1), sections <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal> and subsection <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal>(1) come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>35</XRefInternal> come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>