<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-13</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>43</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>68-69</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2019-2020</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting certain measures in response to COVID-19</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">COVID-19 Emergency Response Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>COVID-19 Emergency Response Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2020</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>5</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2020</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2020-3-25">90924</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting certain measures in response to COVID-19</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 implements, as part of the response to the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), certain income tax measures by</Text><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>introducing a one-time additional payment under the GST/HST tax credit;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>providing temporary additional amounts under the Canada Child Benefit;</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>reducing required minimal withdrawals from registered retirement income funds by 25% for 2020; and</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>providing eligible small employers a temporary wage subsidy for a period of three months.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 2 enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the making of income support payments to workers who suffer a loss of income for reasons related to the coronavirus disease 2019.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 3 enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Health Events of National Concern Payments Act</XRefExternal>, which authorizes payments to be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund in relation to public health events of national concern. It also provides for the repeal of the Act on September 30, 2020.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 4 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal> to allow the Minister of Finance to increase the deposit insurance coverage limit until September 30, 2020.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 5 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the Minister of Finance, with the approval of the Governor in Council, to make payments to the Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund for the purpose of increasing the Corporation’s capital.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 6 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal> to broaden the purposes for which Export Development Canada is established and to permit the Minister of Finance, until September 30, 2020, to determine the amount of Export Development Canada’s authorized capital as well as the amount of certain limits applicable to Export Development Canada. It broadens the transactions for which the Minister of International Trade, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, may grant an authorization. It also provides for the suspension of certain provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Export Development Canada Exercise of Certain Powers Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 7 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> to authorize additional payments to the provinces and territories for the fiscal year beginning on April 1, 2019.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 8 amends Part IV of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the Minister of Finance, until September 30, 2020, to borrow money under that Act for certain payments without the authorization of the Governor in Council, and it also amends that Part to extend the time for the tabling of the report on that Minister’s plans in relation to the management of the public debt. It also amends Part IV.1 of that Act to authorize that Minister to make payments to an entity and to procure the incorporation of a corporation or establish an entity, other than a corporation, for the purposes of promoting the stability or maintaining the efficiency of the financial system in Canada. Finally, it makes related amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Borrowing Authority Act</XRefExternal> and a consequential amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 9 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, authorize the Governor in Council to make regulations</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>requiring persons to provide information to the Minister of Health; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>preventing shortages of therapeutic products in Canada or alleviating those shortages or their effects, in order to protect human health.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 10 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to, among other things, create a regime which provides for a leave related to COVID-19 of up to 16 weeks. It also amends that Act to provide for the repeal of that regime and to provide for a quarantine leave under the medical leave regime.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 11 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Housing Act</XRefExternal> to increase, for a period of five years, the maximum total for the outstanding insured amounts of all insured loans.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 12 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Patent Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things, provide that the Commissioner must, on the application of the Minister of Health, authorize the Government of Canada and any person specified in the application to make, construct, use and sell a patented invention to the extent necessary to respond to a public health emergency that is a matter of national concern.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 13 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Student Loans Act</XRefExternal> to provide that, during the period that begins on March 30, 2020 and ends on September 30, 2020, no interest is payable by a borrower on a guaranteed student loan and no amount on account of principal or interest is required to be paid by the borrower.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 14 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Farm Credit Canada Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the Minister of Finance to determine the limit on the amounts that the Minister of Finance may pay to Farm Credit Canada out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 15 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Student Financial Assistance Act</XRefExternal> to provide that, during the period that begins on March 30, 2020 and ends on September 30, 2020, no interest is payable by a borrower on a student loan and no amount on account of principal or interest is required to be paid by the borrower.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 16 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Business Development Bank of Canada Act</XRefExternal> to authorize the Minister of Finance to determine the limit on the aggregate of the paid-in capital — and any related contributed surplus — of the Business Development Bank and any proceeds prescribed as equity.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 17 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Apprentice Loans Act</XRefExternal> to provide that, during the period that begins on March 30, 2020 and ends on September 30, 2020, no interest is payable by a borrower on an apprentice loan and no amount on account of principal or interest is required to be paid by a borrower.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Division 1 of Part 18 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> to give the Minister of Employment and Social Development the power to make interim orders for the purpose of mitigating the economic effects of COVID-19.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Division 2 of Part 18 provides that every reference in any provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> and of regulations made under it to a certificate issued by a medical doctor or other medical professional or medical practitioner or by a nurse practitioner is deemed to be of no effect and that any benefit that would have been payable to a claimant had such a certificate been issued is payable to the claimant if the Canada Employment Insurance Commission is satisfied that the claimant is entitled to the benefit.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">COVID-19 Emergency Response Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> and <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Income Tax Regulations</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 122.5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>COVID-19 — additional deemed payment</MarginalNote><Label>(3.001)</Label><Text>An eligible individual in relation to a month specified for a taxation year who files a return of income for the taxation year is deemed to have paid during the specified month on account of their tax payable under this Part for the taxation year an amount determined by the formula</Text><FormulaGroup><Formula><FormulaText>0.5(A − B)</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>A</FormulaTerm><Text>is the total of</Text><FormulaParagraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>$580,</Text></FormulaParagraph><FormulaParagraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>$580 for the qualified relation, if any, of the individual in relation to the specified month,</Text></FormulaParagraph><FormulaParagraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the individual has no qualified relation in relation to the specified month and is entitled to deduct an amount for the taxation year under subsection 118(1) because of paragraph (b) of the description of B in that subsection in respect of a qualified dependant of the individual in relation to the specified month, $580,</Text></FormulaParagraph><FormulaParagraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>$306 times the number of qualified dependants of the individual in relation to the specified month, other than a qualified dependant in respect of whom an amount is included under paragraph (c) in computing the total for the specified month,</Text></FormulaParagraph><FormulaParagraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>if the individual has no qualified relation and has one or more qualified dependants, in relation to the specified month, $306, and</Text></FormulaParagraph><FormulaParagraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>if the individual has no qualified relation and no qualified dependant, in relation to the specified month, the lesser of $306 and 2% of the amount, if any, by which the individual’s income for the taxation year exceeds $9,412; and</Text></FormulaParagraph></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>B</FormulaTerm><Text>is 5% of the amount, if any, by which the individual’s adjusted income for the taxation year in relation to the specified month exceeds $37,789.</Text></FormulaDefinition></FormulaGroup></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 122.5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3.01):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>COVID-19 — shared-custody parent</MarginalNote><Label>(3.02)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (3.001), if an eligible individual is a <DefinitionRef>shared-custody parent</DefinitionRef> (within the meaning assigned by section 122.6, but with the words <DefinitionRef>qualified dependant</DefinitionRef> in that section having the meaning assigned by subsection (1)) in respect of one or more qualified dependants at the beginning of a month, the amount deemed by subsection (3.001) to have been paid during the specified month is equal to the amount determined by the following formula:</Text><FormulaGroup><Formula><FormulaText>0.5(A + B)</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>A</FormulaTerm><Text>is the amount determined by the formula in subsection (3.001), calculated without reference to this subsection; and</Text></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>B</FormulaTerm><Text>is the amount determined by the formula in subsection (3.001), calculated without reference to this subsection and subparagraph (b)(ii) of the definition <DefinitionRef>eligible individual</DefinitionRef> in section 122.6.</Text></FormulaDefinition></FormulaGroup></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 122.5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>COVID-19 — month specified</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsection (4) and for the purposes of this section, the month specified in subsection (3.001) is May 2020 (or an earlier month designated by the Minister) and the taxation year is the 2018 taxation year.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 122.61 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>COVID-19 — additional amount</MarginalNote><Label>(1.01)</Label><Text>If the month referred to in subsection (1) is May 2020, each amount expressed in dollars referred to in paragraphs (a) and (b) of the description of E in subsection (1) is deemed, for that month, to be equal to that amount (as adjusted under subsection (5)) plus an additional amount of $3,600. For greater certainty, the adjustment in subsection (5) shall not take into account this additional amount.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 146.3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Adjusted minimum amount for 2020</MarginalNote><Label>(1.4)</Label><Text>The minimum amount under a retirement income fund for 2020 is 75% of the amount that would, in the absence of this subsection, be the minimum amount under the fund for the year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exceptions</MarginalNote><Label>(1.5)</Label><Text>Subsection (1.4) does not apply to a retirement income fund for the purposes of subsections (5.1) and 153(1) and the definition <DefinitionRef>periodic pension payment</DefinitionRef> in section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Conventions Interpretation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 152(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount of tax, if any, deemed by subsection 120(2) or (2.2), 122.5(3) or (3.001), 122.51(2), 122.7(2) or (3), 122.8(4), 122.9(2), 122.91(1), 125.4(3), 125.5(3), 125.6(2), 127.1(1), 127.41(3) or 210.2(3) or (4) to be paid on account of the taxpayer’s tax payable under this Part for the year.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 152(1.2)(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if the Minister determines the amount deemed by subsection 122.5(3) or (3.001) to have been paid by an individual for a taxation year to be nil, subsection (2) does not apply to the determination unless the individual requests a notice of determination from the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 152(4.2)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>redetermine the amount, if any, deemed by subsection 120(2) or (2.2), 122.5(3) or (3.001), 122.51(2), 122.7(2) or (3), 122.8(4), 122.9(2), 122.91(1), 127.1(1), 127.41(3) or 210.2(3) or (4) to be paid on account of the taxpayer’s tax payable under this Part for the year or deemed by subsection 122.61(1) to be an overpayment on account of the taxpayer’s liability under this Part for the year.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 153 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.01):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>COVID-19 — deemed remittance</MarginalNote><Label>(1.02)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, if an eligible employer pays, at a particular time that is within the eligible period, eligible remuneration in respect of which a particular amount is required to be deducted or withheld under subsection (1), then the eligible employer is deemed to have remitted to the Receiver General at the particular time in respect of the particular amount, an amount equal to the least of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the amount determined by the formula</Text><FormulaGroup><Formula><FormulaText>A − B</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>A</FormulaTerm><Text>is the prescribed amount, and</Text></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>B</FormulaTerm><Text>is the total of all amounts, each of which is an amount deemed to have been remitted by the eligible employer under this subsection prior to the particular time (and, if more than one such payment is made at the particular time, the eligible employer may designate the order in which the amounts are considered to have been paid),</Text></FormulaDefinition></FormulaGroup></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount determined by the formula</Text><FormulaGroup><Formula><FormulaText>C × D</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>C</FormulaTerm><Text>is the prescribed percentage, and</Text></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>D</FormulaTerm><Text>is the amount of the eligible remuneration, and</Text></FormulaDefinition></FormulaGroup></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the amount determined by the formula</Text><FormulaGroup><Formula><FormulaText>E × F</FormulaText></Formula><FormulaConnector>where</FormulaConnector><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>E</FormulaTerm><Text>is the prescribed amount, and</Text></FormulaDefinition><FormulaDefinition><FormulaTerm>F</FormulaTerm><Text>is the total number of eligible employees employed by the eligible employer during the eligible period.</Text></FormulaDefinition></FormulaGroup></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions — subsection (1.02)</MarginalNote><Label>(1.03)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply for the purposes of this subsection and subsection (1.02).</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible employee</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is employed in Canada. (<DefinedTermFr>employé admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible employer</DefinedTermEn> means a person or partnership that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>employs one or more eligible employees;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has, on March 18, 2020, a business number in respect of which the person or partnership is registered with the Minister to make remittances required under this section; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>is any of</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a Canadian-controlled private corporation for the purposes of section 125 that</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>would have a business limit for its last taxation year that ended before the start of the eligible period greater than nil, if the amount determined for paragraph 125(5.1)(b) were deemed to be nil, or</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>if the corporation does not have a taxation year that ended before the start of the eligible period, would meet the condition in clause (A) if its taxation year ended immediately before the start of the eligible period,</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an individual (other than a trust),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>a partnership, all of the members of which are described in subparagraphs (i) to (iii) or (v),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>a person exempt from tax under Part I because of paragraph 149(1)(l), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>a registered charity. (<DefinedTermFr>employeur admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible period</DefinedTermEn> means the period beginning on March 18, 2020 and that ends on June 19, 2020. (<DefinedTermFr>période d’admissibilité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>eligible remuneration</DefinedTermEn> means salary, wages or other remuneration paid to an eligible employee during the eligible period. (<DefinedTermFr>rémunération admissible</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed remittances under subsection (1.02)</MarginalNote><Label>(1.04)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, amounts deemed under subsection (1.02) to have been remitted to the Receiver General are deemed to not be held in trust under subsections 227(4) and (4.1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>C.R.C., c. 945</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Income Tax Regulations</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 8506 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Income Tax Regulations</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (7):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><Label>(7.1)</Label><Text>The minimum amount for a member’s account under a money purchase provision of a registered pension plan for 2020 is 75% of the amount that would, in the absence of this subsection, be the minimum amount for the account for the year.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment of Act</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal> is enacted as follows:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="yes"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act respecting income support payments for workers (coronavirus disease 2019)</LongTitle><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Emergency Response Benefit Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>COVID-19</DefinedTermEn> means the coronavirus disease 2019. (<DefinedTermFr>COVID-19</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Employment and Social Development. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>week</DefinedTermEn> means the period of seven consecutive days beginning on and including Sunday. (<DefinedTermFr>semaine</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>worker</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is at least 15 years of age, who is resident in Canada and who, for 2019 or in the 12-month period preceding the day on which they make an application under section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal>, has a total income of at least $5,000 — or, if another amount is fixed by regulation, of at least that amount — from the following sources:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>employment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>self-employment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>benefits paid to the person under any of subsections 22(1), 23(1), 152.04(1) and 152.05(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>allowances, money or other benefits paid to the person under a provincial plan because of pregnancy or in respect of the care by the person of one or more of their new-born children or one or more children placed with them for the purpose of adoption. (<DefinedTermFr>travailleur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations — definition of <DefinitionRef>worker</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>With the consent of the Minister of Finance, the Minister may, by regulation, fix an amount for the purposes of the definition <DefinitionRef>worker</DefinitionRef> in section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payment</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The Minister must make an income support payment to a worker who makes an application under section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> and who is eligible for the payment.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A worker may, in the form and manner established by the Minister, apply for an income support payment for any four-week period falling within the period beginning on March 15, 2020 and ending on October 3, 2020.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No worker is permitted to file an application after December 2, 2020.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An applicant must provide the Minister with any information that the Minister may require in respect of the application.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Eligibility</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A worker is eligible for an income support payment if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the worker, whether employed or self-employed, ceases working for reasons related to COVID-19 for at least 14 consecutive days within the four-week period in respect of which they apply for the payment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>they do not receive, in respect of the consecutive days on which they have ceased working,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subject to the regulations, income from employment or self-employment,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>benefits</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>allowances, money or other benefits paid to the worker under a provincial plan because of pregnancy or in respect of the care by the worker of one or more of their new-born children or one or more children placed with them for the purpose of adoption, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>any other income that is prescribed by regulation.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exclusion</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An employed worker does not cease work for the purpose of paragraph (1)(a) if they quit their employment voluntarily.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by regulation,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>exclude a class of income from the application of subparagraph (1)(b)(i); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prescribe any other income for the purposes of subparagraph (1)(b)(iv).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Amount of payment</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The amount of an income support payment for a week is the amount fixed by regulation for that week.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>With the consent of the Minister of Finance, the Minister may, by regulation, fix the amount of an income support payment for a week specified in the regulation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distinguishing — classes</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Regulations made under subsection (2) may distinguish among different classes of workers.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Maximum number of weeks</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The maximum number of weeks for which income support payments may be made to a worker is 16 weeks or, if another number of weeks is fixed by regulation, that number of weeks.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>With the consent of the Minister of Finance, the Minister may, by regulation, fix a number of weeks for the purpose of subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Social Insurance Number</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The Minister is authorized to collect and use, for the purposes of the administration and enforcement of this Act, the Social Insurance Number of a person who makes an application under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provision of information and documents</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The Minister may, for any purpose related to verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with this Act, by notice served personally or by confirmed delivery service, require that any person provide any information or document within the reasonable time that is stated in the notice.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Payments cannot be charged, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>An income support payment</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is not subject to the operation of any law relating to bankruptcy or insolvency;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cannot be assigned, charged, attached or given as security;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>cannot be retained by way of deduction, set-off or compensation under any Act of Parliament other than this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>is not garnishable moneys for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Family Orders and Agreements Enforcement Assistance Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Return of erroneous payment or overpayment</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister determines that a person has received an income support payment to which the person is not entitled, or an amount in excess of the amount of such a payment to which the person is entitled, the person must repay the amount of the payment or the excess amount, as the case may be, as soon as is feasible.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recovery as debt due to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The amount of the erroneous payment or overpayment, as determined by the Minister, constitutes a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada, as of the day on which it was paid, that may be recovered by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate of default</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The amount of any debt referred to in subsection (2) may be certified by the Minister, and registration of the certificate in the Federal Court has the same effect as a judgment of that Court for the amount specified in the certificate and all related registration costs.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Limitation or prescription period</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) to (7), no action or proceedings are to be taken to recover money owing under this Act after the expiry of the six-year limitation or prescription period that begins on the day on which the money becomes due and payable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deduction, set-off or compensation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Money owing by a person under this Act may be recovered at any time by way of deduction from, set-off against or compensation against any sum of money, including an income support payment under this Act, that may be due or payable by Her Majesty in right of Canada to the person, other than an amount payable under section 122.61 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Acknowledgment of liability</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a person’s liability for money owing under this Act is acknowledged in accordance with subsection (5), the time during which the limitation or prescription period has run before the acknowledgment does not count in the calculation of that period.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Acknowledgment after expiry of limitation or prescription period</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a person’s liability for money owing under this Act is acknowledged in accordance with subsection (5) after the expiry of the limitation or prescription period, an action or proceedings to recover the money may, subject to subsections (3) and (6), be brought within six years after the date of the acknowledgment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Types of acknowledgment</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An acknowledgment of liability means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a promise to pay the money owing, made by the person or their agent, mandatary or other representative;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an acknowledgment of the money owing, made by the person or their agent, mandatary or other representative, whether or not a promise to pay can be implied from it and whether or not it contains a refusal to pay;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a part payment by the person or their agent, mandatary or other representative of any money owing; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an acknowledgment of the money owing, made in the course of proceedings under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> or any other legislation dealing with the payment of debts by the person, their agent, mandatary or other representative or the trustee or administrator.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation or prescription period suspended</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The running of a limitation or prescription period in respect of money owing under this Act is suspended during any period in which it is prohibited to commence or continue an action or other proceedings against the person to recover money owing under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Enforcement proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>This section does not apply in respect of an action or proceedings relating to the execution, renewal or enforcement of a judgment.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No interest payable</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>No interest is payable on any amount owing to Her Majesty in right of Canada under this Act as a result of an erroneous payment or overpayment.</Text></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Health Events of National Concern Payments Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Enactment of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Health Events of National Concern Payments Act</XRefExternal> is enacted as follows:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="yes"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act to authorize the making of payments in relation to public health events of national concern</LongTitle><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Health Events of National Concern Payments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Public Health Event of National Concern</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Payments — public health event of national concern</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, after consulting with the Chief Public Health Officer, appointed under subsection 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Health Agency of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, and any of the officers in the provinces and territories occupying a similar position that the Minister of Health considers appropriate in the circumstances, the Minister of Health determines that there is a public health event of national concern, then there may be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, on the requisition of a federal minister and with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance and the Minister of Health, all money required to do anything in relation to that public health event of national concern.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Examples</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Things that may be done in relation to a public health event of national concern include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>acquiring medical supplies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>providing assistance to provinces and territories to help cover the cost of safety and emergency response needs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>providing income support, including the Canada emergency response benefit; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>funding public health-related federal programs or covering expenses incurred by federal departments and agencies.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>public health event of national concern</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>public health event of national concern</DefinedTermEn> means an extraordinary event that constitutes a public health risk to Canadians through the spread of an infectious disease, such as the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), that requires a coordinated national or international response to prevent or control its spread or to protect against it.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Health Events of National Concern Payments Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>September 30, 2020</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>10</XRefInternal> comes into force on September 30, 2020.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 4</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-3</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 12(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>so much of any one deposit as exceeds the amount set out in subsection 12.01(1).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 12(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>so much of any one deposit as exceeds one hundred thousand dollars.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 12:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Amount</MarginalNote><Label>12.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The amount referred to in paragraph 12(c) is one hundred thousand dollars, unless the Minister determines a greater amount, in which case the amount referred to in that paragraph is the amount that the Minister determines.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after making a determination under subsection (1), the Minister shall publish the amount in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Section 12.01 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>October 1, 2020</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal>(2) and section <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal> come into force on October 1, 2020.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 5</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-7</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Section 16 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Mortgage and Housing Corporation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Capital of Corporation</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The capital of the Corporation consists of the amount obtained by adding twenty-five million dollars and the aggregate of any amounts paid under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to make capital payments</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>At the request of the Corporation, the Minister of Finance may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, pay to the Corporation, out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, amounts not exceeding the aggregate of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>ten billion dollars, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any additional amounts that may be authorized from time to time under an appropriation Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 6</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-20; 2001, c. 33, s. 2(F)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 10(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following before paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>supporting and developing, directly or indirectly, domestic business, at the request of the Minister and the Minister of Finance for a period specified by those Ministers;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 10 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(1.01)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after a request is made under paragraph (1)(a), the Minister shall publish in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> a notice of that fact as well as the dates on which the period to which the request relates begins and ends.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Complementary to commercial products and services</MarginalNote><Label>(1.02)</Label><Text>The Corporation shall carry out its purposes, with regard to domestic business, in a manner that complements the products and services available from commercial financial institutions and commercial insurance providers.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 10(3) and (3.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limit of liability</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (4), the contingent liability of the Corporation in respect of the principal amount owing under all outstanding arrangements entered into under paragraph (1.1)(b) shall at no time exceed</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for the period beginning on the day on which this subsection comes into force and ending on September 30, 2020, the amount that the Minister of Finance determines during that period, or, if that Minister redetermines the amount during that period, the most recently determined amount; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on and after October 1, 2020, an amount equal to the amount determined by the Minister of Finance under paragraph (a), or, if that Minister redetermined the amount under that paragraph, an amount equal to the last amount so determined.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after determining or redetermining an amount under paragraph (3)(a), the Minister of Finance shall publish a notice of that amount in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subsection 11(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorized capital</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The authorized capital of the Corporation is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for the period beginning on the day on which this subsection comes into force and ending on September 30, 2020, the amount that the Minister of Finance determines during that period, or, if that Minister redetermines the amount during that period, the most recently determined amount; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on and after October 1, 2020, an amount equal to the amount determined by the Minister of Finance under paragraph (a), or, if that Minister redetermined the amount under that paragraph, an amount equal to the last amount so determined.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>Each share has a par value of $100.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after determining or redetermining an amount under paragraph (1)(a), the Minister of Finance shall publish a notice of that amount in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>Subsection 23(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization of the Minister</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Corporation advises the Minister that it will not, without an authorization made under this section, enter into any transaction or class of transactions that it has the power to enter into under subsection 10(1.1) and the Minister is of the opinion that it is in the national interest that the Corporation enter into any such transaction or class of transactions, the Minister, with the concurrence of the Minister of Finance, may authorize the Corporation to do so.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 24(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Limit of liability</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), in respect of transactions entered into under section 23, the total of the following liabilities and obligations shall at no time exceed the amount referred to in paragraph (1.1)(a) or (b), as the case may be:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 24 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Determination of amount</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The amount which the total liabilities and obligations referred to in subsection (1) shall at no time exceed is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for the period beginning on the day on which this subsection comes into force and ending on September 30, 2020, the amount that the Minister of Finance determines during that period, or, if that Minister redetermines the amount during that period, the most recently determined amount; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on and after October 1, 2020, an amount equal to the amount determined by the Minister of Finance under paragraph (a), or, if that Minister redetermined the amount under that paragraph, an amount equal to the last amount so determined.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after determining or redetermining an amount under paragraph (1.1)(a), the Minister of Finance shall publish a notice of that amount in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Suspension of Certain Provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Export Development Canada Exercise of Certain Powers Regulations</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Suspension</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the <DefinitionRef>Minister</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal>, and the Minister of Finance specify a period under paragraph 10(1)(a) of that Act, subsections 5(2) and 6(2) and (3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Export Development Canada Exercise of Certain Powers Regulations</XRefExternal> do not apply for that period.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transactions entered into during specified period</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 5(2) and 6(2) and (3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Export Development Canada Exercise of Certain Powers Regulations</XRefExternal> do not apply to a new transaction that Export Development Canada enters into during a period referred to in subsection (1), even after the expiry of that period. Even after the expiry of that period, Export Development Canada may take any steps and do anything that it considers necessary or desirable to implement the transaction or that it considers related to the transaction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Arrangement entered into before expiry of specified period</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The expiry of a period referred to in subsection (1) has no effect on any arrangement Export Development Canada entered into in order to carry out its purpose referred to in paragraph 10(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Export Development Act</XRefExternal>. Even after the expiry of that period, Export Development Canada may take any steps and do anything that it considers necessary or desirable to implement the arrangement or that it considers related to the arrangement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 7</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-8; 1995, c. 17, s. 45</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal-Provincial Fiscal Arrangements Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 24.703:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Additional Payments for Fiscal Year 2019–2020</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Total payment of $500 million</MarginalNote><Label>24.71</Label><Text>The Minister may pay an additional cash payment for the fiscal year beginning on April 1, 2019 equal to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for Ontario, $193,721,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>for Quebec, $112,871,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>for Nova Scotia, $12,922,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>for New Brunswick, $10,340,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>for Manitoba, $18,216,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>for British Columbia, $67,464,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>for Prince Edward Island, $2,089,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>for Saskatchewan, $15,627,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>for Alberta, $58,141,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>for Newfoundland and Labrador, $6,952,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>for Yukon, $543,000;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>for the Northwest Territories, $598,000; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>for Nunavut, $516,000.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 8</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>Section 44 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Maximum — exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Any money borrowed under section 47 is not to be taken into account for the purpose of calculating the aggregate principal amount of money borrowed by the Minister under this section in any fiscal year.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 46.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>47</Label><Text>During the period beginning on the day on which this section comes into force and ending on September 30, 2020, the Minister may borrow money for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the payment of any amount that is required to be paid in that period in respect of any money borrowed under the authority of this Act or any other Act of Parliament; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the payment, by Her Majesty, of any amount in extraordinary circumstances, including in the event of a natural disaster or to promote the stability or maintain the efficiency of the financial system in Canada, if the Minister is of the opinion that the borrowing of money is necessary in those circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 49(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (a.1) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.2)</Label><Text>the money that is borrowed under paragraph 47(b) and that is due; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 49(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report on Minister’s plans</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause to be tabled in each House of Parliament for every fiscal year, not later than the 30th day on which that House is sitting after the start of the fiscal year to which the report relates, a report on the Minister’s plans in relation to the following:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 49(2)(a) and (b) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the money to be borrowed in that fiscal year and the purposes for which the moneys will be borrowed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the management of the public debt in that fiscal year.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>Section 49.1 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 49.1(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report — borrowings in respect of extraordinary circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause to be tabled in each House of Parliament a report on the money borrowed or to be borrowed under paragraph 47(b) within the first 30 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the Minister first borrows money under that paragraph.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 60.2(1) of the Act before the first definition is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>60.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Part.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>entity</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 60.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>entity</DefinedTermEn> means an entity, including a trust, that, in the Minister’s opinion, is operating in Canada. (<DefinedTermFr>entité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 60.2(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contracts and payments</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), the Minister may, taking into account the interests of taxpayers,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with the Governor in Council’s authorization, enter into, on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada, any contract that in the Minister’s opinion is necessary to promote the stability or maintain the efficiency of the financial system in Canada, including such a contract to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>purchase, acquire, hold, lend or sell or otherwise dispose of securities of an entity,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>create a charge on, or right or interest in, securities of an entity held by the Minister,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>make a loan to an entity,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>provide a line of credit to an entity,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>guarantee any debt, obligation or financial asset of an entity, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>provide loan insurance or credit insurance for the benefit of an entity in respect of any debt, obligation or financial asset of the entity; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>make payments to a province or territory — or, after consultation with a province or territory, to an entity — for the purposes of responding to a situation of significant and systemic economic and financial distress.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contract with Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into a contract under paragraph (2)(a) with Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Without Governor in Council’s authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into a contract under paragraph (2)(a) without the Governor in Council’s authorization until September 30, 2020.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Accountability to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>The Minister is to exercise his or her powers under subsection (2) within the framework of the Minister’s accountability to Parliament.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 60.2(3) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application to certain entities</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (2)(a)(i) does not apply to</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsections 60.2(4) to (6) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Section 90 does not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 90 does not apply if the Minister purchases, acquires or sells or otherwise disposes, under subparagraph (2)(a)(i), of shares within the meaning of that section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Section 61 and <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Surplus Crown Assets Act</XRefExternal> do not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section 61 and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Surplus Crown Assets Act</XRefExternal> do not apply if the Minister holds, loans or sells or otherwise disposes of securities under subparagraph (2)(a)(i).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Any amount payable under or in connection with a contract entered into under this section or any payment made under paragraph (2)(b) may be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, on the requisition of the Minister, at the times and in the manner that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 60.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Incorporation</MarginalNote><Label>60.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in the Minister’s opinion, it is necessary to promote the stability or maintain the efficiency of the financial system in Canada, the Minister may, with the Governor in Council’s authorization, procure the incorporation of a corporation, all of the shares of which are held by the Minister on behalf of Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not agent of Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The corporation is not an agent of Her Majesty in right of Canada unless it is declared to be an agent of Her Majesty under an Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of Part X</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to any regulations made under subsection (4), Part X does not apply to the corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may make regulations respecting the governance of the corporation, including regulations that adapt any provisions of this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> and any regulations made under those Acts for the purpose of applying those provisions as adapted to the corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Directives</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister may give a directive to the corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Implementation</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The directors of the corporation shall ensure that a directive is implemented in a prompt and efficient manner.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Best interests</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Compliance by the corporation with a directive is deemed to be in the best interests of the corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terms and conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by order, establish terms and conditions in accordance with which the corporation shall enter into financial transactions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contract with Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The corporation may enter into a contract with Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>The Minister may make payments to the corporation out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, at the times and in the manner that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loans to corporation</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>The Minister may, out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, lend money to the corporation on any terms and conditions that the Minister may fix.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Powers of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>The Minister may merge, sell, wind-up or dissolve the corporation, dispose of any or all shares of the corporation or take other similar measures in respect of the corporation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a directive given under subsection (5) or to an order made under subsection (8).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(14)</Label><Text>The Minister shall publish a directive given under subsection (5) or an order made under subsection (8) in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Entity other than corporation</MarginalNote><Label>60.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, in the Minister’s opinion, it is necessary to promote the stability or maintain the efficiency of the financial system in Canada, the Minister may, with the Governor in Council’s authorization, establish an entity, other than a corporation, on any terms and conditions that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payments out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may make payments to the entity out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, at the times and in the manner that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Loans to entity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may, out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund, lend money to the entity on any terms and conditions that the Minister may fix.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 20, s. 103</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Related Amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Borrowing Authority Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>Section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Borrowing Authority Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (a) and by replacing paragraph (b) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>amounts borrowed by the Minister under an order made under paragraph 46.1(a) of that Act for the payment of any amount in respect of a debt that was originally incurred under</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>an order made under paragraph 46.1(c) of that Act, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 47(b) of that Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>amounts borrowed by the Minister under paragraph 47(b) of that Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>amounts borrowed by the Minister under paragraph 47(a) of that Act for the payment of any amount in respect of a debt that was originally incurred under paragraph 47(b) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Exception — maximum amount exceeded</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The Minister may borrow an amount under an order made under paragraph 46.1(a) or (b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> or an amount under paragraph 47(a) of that Act even if that borrowing causes the maximum amount referred to in section 4 of this Act to be exceeded.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Text>Subsection 8(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b) and by adding the following after that paragraph:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>the total amount of money borrowed under each of paragraphs 47(a) and (b) of that Act; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-3</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Consequential Amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 10.1(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Deposit Insurance Corporation Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Total indebtedness</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The total principal indebtedness outstanding at any time in respect of borrowings by the Corporation under subsections (1) and (2), excluding the borrowings under subparagraph 60.2(2)(a)(iii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, shall not exceed</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 9</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 30(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Food and Drugs Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (k.1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k.2)</Label><Text>requiring persons to provide information to the Minister in respect of food, drugs, cosmetics or devices — or in respect of activities related to food, drugs, cosmetics or devices — in circumstances other than those provided for in this Act and authorizing the Minister to determine the information to be provided and the time and manner in which it is to be provided;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 30(1)(k.2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 30 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1.3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations — preventing or alleviating shortages</MarginalNote><Label>(1.4)</Label><Text>Without limiting the power conferred by any other subsection of this section, the Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary for the purpose of preventing shortages of therapeutic products in Canada or alleviating those shortages or their effects, in order to protect human health.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 30(1.4) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 37(1.2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), any prescribed provision of the regulations applies to any food, drug, cosmetic or device.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 37(1.2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), any prescribed provision of the regulations respecting the method of manufacture, preparation, preserving, packaging, storing and testing of any food, drug, cosmetic or device applies to any packaged food, drug, cosmetic or device.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>October 1, 2020</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Text>Subsections <XRefInternal>33</XRefInternal>(2) and (4) and <XRefInternal>34</XRefInternal>(2) come into force on October 1, 2020.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 10</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 168:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Leave — entitlement without certificate</MarginalNote><Label>168.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any provision of this Part and the regulations made under this Part, an employee may exercise their entitlement to and shall be granted a leave of absence under section 206.3, 206.4 or 239 even if a certificate is not issued by a health care practitioner. The conditions and requirements in those sections with respect to such a certificate are deemed to be of no effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Documentation not required</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 207.3(4), an employee is not required to provide the employer with any documentation referred to in that subsection in respect of a leave of absence taken under section 206.4.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>This section is repealed on September 30, 2020.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 187.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Interruption</MarginalNote><Label>187.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An employee may interrupt a vacation granted to them under this Division in order to permit them to take a leave of absence under Division VII or VIII or section 247.5 or to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1), 239.01(1) or 239.1(1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 187.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Interruption</MarginalNote><Label>187.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An employee may interrupt a vacation granted to them under this Division in order to permit them to take a leave of absence under Division VII or VIII or section 247.5 or to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1) or (1.1) or 239.1(1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 187.1(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of subsection 239(7)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an employee interrupts a vacation to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1) or (1.1) and resumes the vacation immediately at the end of that leave, subsection 239(7) applies to them as if they did not resume the vacation before returning to work.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 187.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of subsection 239.01(7)</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>If an employee interrupts a vacation to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239.01(1) and resumes the vacation immediately at the end of that leave, subsection 239.01(7) applies to them as if they did not resume the vacation before returning to work.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 187.1(3.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 187.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Postponement</MarginalNote><Label>187.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph 185(a) or any term or condition of employment, an employee may postpone their vacation until after the day on which a leave of absence taken under Division VII or VIII or section 247.5, or an absence due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1), 239.01(1) or 239.1(1), ends.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 187.2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Postponement</MarginalNote><Label>187.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph 185(a) or any term or condition of employment, an employee may postpone their vacation until after the day on which a leave of absence taken under Division VII or VIII or section 247.5, or an absence due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1) or (1.1) or 239.1(1), ends.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 206.1(2.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension of period</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The period referred to in subsection (2) is extended by the number of weeks during which the employee is on leave under any of sections 206.3 to 206.5 and 206.9, is absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1), 239.01(1) or 239.1(1) or is on leave under any of paragraphs 247.5(1)(a), (b) and (d) to (g).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 206.1(2.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension of period</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The period referred to in subsection (2) is extended by the number of weeks during which the employee is on leave under any of sections 206.3 to 206.5 and 206.9, is absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1) or (1.1) or 239.1(1) or is on leave under any of paragraphs 247.5(1)(a), (b) and (d) to (g).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 206.1(2.4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interruption</MarginalNote><Label>(2.4)</Label><Text>The employee may interrupt the leave referred to in subsection (1) in order to permit the employee to take leave under any of sections 206.3 to 206.5 and 206.9, to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1), 239.01(1) or 239.1(1) or to take leave under any of paragraphs 247.5(1)(a), (b) and (d) to (g).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 206.1(2.4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interruption</MarginalNote><Label>(2.4)</Label><Text>The employee may interrupt the leave referred to in subsection (1) in order to permit the employee to take leave under any of sections 206.3 to 206.5 and 206.9, to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1) or (1.1) or 239.1(1) or to take leave under any of paragraphs 247.5(1)(a), (b) and (d) to (g).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 206.1(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — medical leave</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Except to the extent that it is inconsistent with subsection 239(7), section 209.1 applies to an employee who interrupted the leave referred to in subsection (1) in order to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1) or (1.1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Section 206.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — leave related to COVID-19</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Except to the extent that it is inconsistent with subsection 239.01(7), section 209.1 applies to an employee who interrupted the leave referred to in subsection (1) in order to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239.01(1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsection 206.1(4.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 207.02(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Interruption</MarginalNote><Label>207.02</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An employee may interrupt a leave of absence referred to in any of sections 206.3 to 206.5 in order to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1), 239.01(1) or 239.1(1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 207.02(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Interruption</MarginalNote><Label>207.02</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An employee may interrupt a leave of absence referred to in any of sections 206.3 to 206.5 in order to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1) or (1.1) or 239.1(1).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 207.02(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — medical leave</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Except to the extent that it is inconsistent with subsection 239(7), section 209.1 applies to an employee who interrupted the leave in order to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239(1) or (1.1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 207.02 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — leave related to COVID-19</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>Except to the extent that it is inconsistent with subsection 239.01(7), section 209.1 applies to an employee who interrupted the leave in order to be absent due to a reason referred to in subsection 239.01(1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 207.02(3.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>Section 239 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Entitlement to leave — quarantine</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Every employee is entitled to and shall be granted a medical leave of absence from employment of up to 16 weeks as a result of quarantine.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 239:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION XIII.01</Label><TitleText>Leave Related to COVID-19</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Entitlement to leave</MarginalNote><Label>239.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), every employee is entitled to and shall be granted a leave of absence from employment of up to 16 weeks — or, if another number of weeks is fixed by regulation, that number of weeks — if the employee is unable or unavailable to work for reasons related to the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to employer</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An employee who intends to take a leave of absence under this Division must, as soon as possible, give written notice to the employer of the reasons for the leave and the length of the leave that they intend to take.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Change in length of leave</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An employee must, as soon as possible, give written notice to the employer of any change in the length of the leave of absence taken under this Division.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Written declaration</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The employer may require an employee to provide a written declaration in support of the reasons for the leave of absence taken under this Division and of any change in the length of that leave.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Employment opportunities</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An employee is entitled, on written request, to be informed in writing of every employment, promotion or training opportunity that arises during the period when the employee is on a leave of absence under this Division and for which the employee is qualified, and on receiving that request, the employer must provide the information to the employee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (7), an employer is prohibited from dismissing, suspending, laying off, demoting or disciplining an employee because the employee intends to take or has taken a leave of absence under this Division or taking such an intention or absence into account in any decision to promote or train the employee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>An employer may assign to a different position, with different terms and conditions of employment, any employee who, after a leave of absence under this Division, is unable to perform the work performed by the employee prior to the absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Benefits continue</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The pension, health and disability benefits and the seniority of an employee who is absent from work due to a leave of absence under this Division accumulate during the entire period of the leave.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contributions by employee</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>If contributions are required from an employee in order for the employee to be entitled to a benefit referred to in subsection (8), the employee is responsible for and must, within a reasonable time, pay those contributions for the period of any leave of absence under this Division unless, at the commencement of the absence or within a reasonable time after, the employee notifies the employer of the employee’s intention to discontinue contributions during that period.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contributions by employer</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>An employer who pays contributions in respect of a benefit referred to in subsection (8) must continue to pay those contributions during an employee’s leave of absence under this Division in at least the same proportion as if the employee were not absent, unless the employee does not pay the employee’s contributions, if any, within a reasonable time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Failure to pay contributions</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>For the purposes of calculating the pension, health and disability benefits of an employee in respect of whom contributions have not been paid as required by subsections (9) and (10), the benefits do not accumulate during the leave of absence under this Division and employment on the employee’s return to work is deemed to be continuous with employment before the employee’s absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deemed continuous employment</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>For the purposes of calculating benefits, other than benefits referred to in subsection (8), of an employee who is absent from work due to a leave of absence under this Division, employment on the employee’s return to work is to be deemed to be continuous with employment before the employee’s absence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by regulation,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>define terms for the purposes of this Division; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>fix a number of weeks for the purpose of subsection (1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Division XIII.01 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 246.1(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the employer has taken action against the employee in contravention of subsection 173.01(5), 174.1(4) or 177.1(7) or of section 208, 209.3, 238, 239, 239.01, 239.1 or 247.96;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 246.1(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the employer has taken action against the employee in contravention of subsection 173.01(5), 174.1(4) or 177.1(7) or of section 208, 209.3, 238, 239, 239.1 or 247.96;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2018, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Consequential Amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2018, No. 2</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>44</Label><Text>Section 493 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2018, No. 2</XRefExternal> is amended by replacing the paragraph 246.1(1)(a) that it enacts with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the employer has taken action against the employee in contravention of subsection 173.01(5), 174.1(4), 177.1(7), 182.2(3) or 203.3(3) or of section 208, 209.3, 238, 239, 239.01, 239.1 or 247.96;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2018, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>45</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>other Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2018, No. 2</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 493 of the other Act comes into force before subsection <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then, on the day on which that subsection <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(2) comes into force, paragraph 246.1(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the employer has taken action against the employee in contravention of subsection 173.01(5), 174.1(4), 177.1(7), 182.2(3) or 203.3(3) or of section 208, 209.3, 238, 239, 239.1 or 247.96;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act comes into force before section 493 of the other Act, then, on the day on which that section 493 comes into force, paragraph 246.1(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the employer has taken action against the employee in contravention of subsection 173.01(5), 174.1(4), 177.1(7), 182.2(3) or 203.3(3) or of section 208, 209.3, 238, 239, 239.1 or 247.96;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act and section 493 of the other Act come into force on the same day, then that subsection <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(2) is deemed to come into force before that section 493 and subsection (3) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>October 1, 2020</MarginalNote><Label>46</Label><Text>Subsections <XRefInternal>37</XRefInternal>(2), (3) and (5), <XRefInternal>38</XRefInternal>(2), <XRefInternal>39</XRefInternal>(2), (4), (5) and (7) and <XRefInternal>40</XRefInternal>(2), (3) and (5), section <XRefInternal>41</XRefInternal> and subsections <XRefInternal>42</XRefInternal>(2) and <XRefInternal>43</XRefInternal>(2) come into force on October 1, 2020.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 11</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Housing Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>47</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Housing Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>three hundred billion dollars, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 11(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>one hundred and fifty billion dollars, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 11:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Maximum total as of day section comes into force</MarginalNote><Label>11.1</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the amount that the total of the outstanding insured amounts of all insured loans may not exceed is, as of the day on which this section comes into force, seven hundred and fifty billion dollars.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49</Label><Text>Section 11.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Fifth anniversary</MarginalNote><Label>50</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>47</XRefInternal>(2) and section <XRefInternal>49</XRefInternal> come into force on the fifth anniversary of the day on which subsection <XRefInternal>47</XRefInternal>(1) comes into force.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 12</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Patent Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Patent Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 19.3:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>19.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall, on the application of the Minister of Health, authorize the Government of Canada and any person specified in the application to make, construct, use and sell a patented invention to the extent necessary to respond to the public health emergency described in the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>set out the name of the patentee and the number, as recorded in the Patent Office, of the patent issued in respect of the patented invention;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>include a confirmation that the Chief Public Health Officer, appointed under subsection 6(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Health Agency of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, believes that there is a public health emergency that is a matter of national concern;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>include a description of the public health emergency; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>specify a person, if any, that is to be authorized to make, construct, use and sell the patented invention for the purposes of responding to the public health emergency.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cessation of effect</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The authorization ceases to have effect the earlier of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the day on which the Minister of Health notifies the Commissioner that the authorization is no longer necessary to respond to the public health emergency set out in the application, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>one year after the day on which it is granted.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall notify the patentee of any authorization that is granted under this section and provide them with the information referred to in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment of remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Government of Canada and any person authorized under subsection (1) shall pay the patentee any amount that the Commissioner considers to be adequate remuneration in the circumstances, taking into account the economic value of the authorization and the extent to which they make, construct, use and sell the patented invention.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authorization not transferable</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An authorization granted under this section is not transferable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the use or sale, in relation to a public health emergency, of a patented invention that is made or constructed in accordance with an authorization granted under this section is not an infringement of the patent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power of Federal Court</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>On the application of the patentee, the Federal Court may make an order requiring the Government of Canada or any person authorized under subsection (1) to cease making, constructing, using or selling the patented invention in a manner that is inconsistent with the authorization granted under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The Commissioner shall not make an authorization under subsection (1) after September 30, 2020.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 13</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. S-23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Student Loans Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Student Loans Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 11.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Period — March 30, 2020 to September 30, 2020</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Suspension of interest and payments</MarginalNote><Label>11.2</Label><Text>During the period that begins on March 30, 2020 and ends on September 30, 2020,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no interest is payable by a borrower on a guaranteed student loan; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>no amount on account of principal and interest in respect of a guaranteed student loan is required to be paid by the borrower.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 14</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1993, c. 14; 2001, c. 22, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Farm Credit Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>53</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 11(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Farm Credit Canada Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Capital payments</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the request of the Corporation, the Minister of Finance may pay to the Corporation out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for the period beginning on the day on which this subsection comes into force and ending on September 30, 2020, amounts not exceeding in the aggregate the amount that the Minister of Finance determines during that period, or, if that Minister redetermines the amount during that period, the most recently determined amount; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on and after October 1, 2020, amounts not exceeding in the aggregate an amount equal to the amount determined by the Minister of Finance under paragraph (a), or, if that Minister redetermined the amount under that paragraph, the last amount so determined.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after determining or redetermining an amount under paragraph (1)(a), the Minister of Finance shall publish a notice of that amount in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 11(2) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Capital</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le total des versements visés au paragraphe (1) constitue, avec le montant des bénéfices non répartis de la Société — lequel peut être négatif —, le capital de celle-ci.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 11(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 15</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1994, c. 28</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Student Financial Assistance Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>54</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Student Financial Assistance Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 9.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Period — March 30, 2020 to September 30, 2020</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Suspension of interest and payments</MarginalNote><Label>9.3</Label><Text>During the period that begins on March 30, 2020 and ends on September 30, 2020,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no interest is payable by a borrower on a student loan prescribed by regulations made under paragraph 15(1)(j); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>no amount on account of principal and interest in respect of a student loan prescribed by regulations made under paragraph 15(1)(j) is required to be paid by the borrower.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 16</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 28</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Business Development Bank of Canada Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>55</Label><Text>Subsection 23(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Business Development Bank of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorized capital</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The authorized capital of the Bank consists of an unlimited number of common shares with a par value of $100 each and an unlimited number of preferred shares without par value, but the paid-in capital of the Bank, together with any contributed surplus relating to it and any proceeds referred to in paragraph 30(2)(d) that have been prescribed as equity, must not at any time exceed</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for the period beginning on the day on which this subsection comes into force and ending on September 30, 2020, the amount that the Minister of Finance determines during that period, or, if that Minister redetermines the amount during that period, the most recently determined amount; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on and after October 1, 2020, an amount equal to the amount determined by the Minister of Finance under paragraph (a), or, if that Minister redetermined the amount under that paragraph, an amount equal to the last amount so determined.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication in <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after determining or redetermining an amount under paragraph (1)(a), the Minister of Finance shall publish a notice of that amount in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 17</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 20, s. 483</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Apprentice Loans Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>56</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Apprentice Loans Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 8:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Period — March 30, 2020 to September 30, 2020</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Suspension of interest and payments</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Text>During the period that begins on March 30, 2020 and ends on September 30, 2020,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no interest is payable by a borrower on an apprentice loan; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>no amount on account of principal and interest in respect of an apprentice loan is required to be paid by a borrower.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 18</Label><TitleText>Employment Insurance</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 1</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>57</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 153.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART VIII.3</Label><TitleText>Interim Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>COVID-19</MarginalNote><Label>153.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, for the purpose of mitigating the economic effects of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), make interim orders that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>add provisions, including provisions that provide for new benefits, to this Act or any regulation made under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>adapt provisions of this Act or any regulation made under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>provide that any provisions of this Act or a regulation made under this Act do not apply in whole or in part.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An interim order is not to be made under subsection (1) in respect of Part IV or VII or in respect of a regulation made under this Act for the purposes of those Parts.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Condition precedent — Minister of Finance</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An interim order is not to be made under subsection (1) without the consent of the Minister of Finance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Condition precedent — President of the Treasury Board</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An interim order is not to be made under subsection (1) in respect of Part III or in respect of a regulation made under this Act for the purposes of that Part without the additional consent of the President of the Treasury Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consultation with Commission</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Minister may consult the Commission before making an interim order under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retroactive effect</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>An interim order made under subsection (1) may, if it so provides, have retroactive effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Cessation of effect</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>An interim order made under subsection (1) must contain provisions that cause any provision added under paragraph (1)(a), any adaptation made under paragraph (1)(b) and any non-application provision made under paragraph (1)(c) to cease to apply on the earliest of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the day, if any, specified in the interim order,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which the interim order is repealed, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Saturday after the first anniversary of the day on which the interim order takes effect.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conflict</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If an interim order made under subsection (1) or a provision added under paragraph (1)(a) provides that it applies despite any provision of this Act or any regulation made under this Act, the interim order or added provision prevails to the extent that it conflicts with this Act or any regulation made under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The power to make an interim order under subsection (1) is not to be exercised after September 30, 2020.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Accessory orders</MarginalNote><Label>153.4</Label><Text>The Minister may make orders for the purpose of ensuring that interim orders made under subsection 153.3(1) only have temporary effect, including orders that repeal any provision added under paragraph 153.3(1)(a).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 2</Label><TitleText>Medical Certificates</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Medical certificates</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite any provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> and of any regulations made under it,</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>every reference in any provision of that Act or those regulations to a certificate issued by a medical doctor or other medical professional or medical practitioner or by a nurse practitioner is deemed to be of no effect; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any benefit that would have been payable to a claimant had such a certificate been issued is payable to them if the Commission is satisfied that they are entitled to the benefit.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Application of provisions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Commission is authorized to apply the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> and of the regulations in the manner that it considers most appropriate for the purpose of applying subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Duration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) apply until September 30, 2020.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Words and expressions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Words and expressions used in this section and section <XRefInternal>60</XRefInternal> have the same meaning as in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>58</XRefInternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transitional provision</MarginalNote><Label>60</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>58</XRefInternal>, as it read immediately before the day fixed under section <XRefInternal>61</XRefInternal>, continues to apply in respect of any claimant whose benefit period begins before that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>October 1, 2020</MarginalNote><Label>61</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>59</XRefInternal> comes into force on October 1, 2020.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>