<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-10</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to give effect to the Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement, to amend the Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act and the Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to give effect to the Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement, to amend the Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act and the Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to give effect to the Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>9</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2022</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-6-7">91011</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal> and makes related and consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 2 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>include certain elements typically provided for in self-government agreements;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>specify elements that must be included in the shíshálh Nation’s constitution and set out an obligation to make publicly accessible amendments to the constitution as well as shíshálh laws and amendments to those laws;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>take into account changes to the names of the Indigenous collective and of certain entities referred to in that Act to better align with the Indigenous language of the collective;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>clarify that the council of the shíshálh Nation may make laws relating to child and family services;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>specify the manner in which and the conditions under which lands in British Columbia may become shíshálh lands;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>allow the Minister of Crown-Indigenous Relations to enter into an agreement with the Nation for the establishment of a shíshálh Lands Register;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>ensure that entering into funding agreements no longer requires the approval of the Governor in Council; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>specify that the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal> applies to the Council, the shíshálh Nation Government District Council and to any administrative bodies and agencies assisting in the administration of the affairs of the Nation.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends transitional provisions and makes consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 3 amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act</XRefExternal> to ensure that entering into funding agreements no longer requires the approval of the Governor in Council.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Enactment of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, whose text is as follows and whose schedule is set out in the schedule to this Act, is enacted:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="yes"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act to give effect to the Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to achieving reconciliation with First Nations through renewed nation-to-nation relationships based on recognition of rights, respect, cooperation and partnership;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada recognizes that the inherent right of self-government is a right of the Indigenous peoples of Canada recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement specifies that the First Nations and the Anishinabek Nation may enact laws in respect of governance, as well as in respect of Anishinabek culture and languages;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Agreement provides that the parties may enter into additional self-government agreements in relation to other law-making powers, and that those agreements would become part of the Agreement, unless the parties agree otherwise;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to implementing the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples and the parties to the Agreement view it as contributing to the implementation of that declaration;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas ratification of the Agreement requires the coming into force of an Act of Parliament that gives effect to it;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement, signed on April 6, 2022, including any amendments made to it. (<DefinedTermFr>accord</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Anishinabek law</DefinedTermEn> means a law made by a First Nation or the Anishinabek Nation under section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>texte législatif anishinabe</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Anishinabek Nation Government</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 1.1 of the Agreement. (<DefinedTermFr>gouvernement de la Nation des Anishinabes</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>band</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>citizen</DefinedTermEn> means a citizen — an “E’Dbendaagzijig” — of a First Nation, within the meaning of section 1.1 of the Agreement, or of the Anishinabek Nation, under section 4.15 of the Agreement.  (<DefinedTermFr>citoyen</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>constitution</DefinedTermEn> means a constitution ratified by a First Nation or the Anishinabek Nation in accordance with the Agreement. (<DefinedTermFr>constitution</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>First Nation</DefinedTermEn> means, except in subsection <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal>(1), a band that is named in the schedule. (<DefinedTermFr>première nation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>First Nation Government</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 1.1 of the Agreement. (<DefinedTermFr>gouvernement de la première nation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous peoples of Canada</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by the definition <DefinitionRef>aboriginal peoples of Canada</DefinitionRef> in subsection 35(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>peuples autochtones du Canada</DefinedTermFr>) </Text></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Not a treaty</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Agreement is not a treaty within the meaning of section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Agreement</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement given effect</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights and obligations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a person or body has the powers, rights, privileges and benefits conferred on the person or body by the Agreement and must perform the duties, and is subject to the liabilities, imposed on the person or body by the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement binding</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Agreement is binding on, and may be relied on by, all persons and bodies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement prevails</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the event of any inconsistency or conflict between the Agreement and the provisions of any Act of Parliament, or of any regulation made under an Act of Parliament, the Agreement prevails to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Act prevails</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the event of any inconsistency or conflict between the provisions of this Act and the provisions of any other Act of Parliament, or of any regulation made under any other Act of Parliament, the provisions of this Act prevail to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Anishinabek Laws</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Power to enact laws</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>A First Nation or the Anishinabek Nation, as the case may be, may, in accordance with the applicable constitution and the Agreement, make laws respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the selection of government representatives;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the determination of who is a citizen, as well as the rights, privileges and responsibilities associated with being a citizen;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the management and operation of government;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the preservation, promotion and development of culture and language; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any other matters covered by any additional self-government agreements entered into by the First Nations, the Anishinabek Nation and the Government of Canada in accordance with Chapter 13 of the Agreement.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Application of Other Acts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) to (4), the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> continues to apply in respect of every First Nation, its citizens and its reserve as of the day of coming into force of section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> — sections 8 to 14</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 8 to 14 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> cease to apply in respect of the First Nation and its members on the day on which a law referred to in paragraph <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(b) made by that First Nation comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> — sections 74 to 79</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Sections 74 to 79 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> cease to apply in respect of the First Nation and its members on the day on which a law referred to in paragraph <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(a) made by that First Nation comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> — section 80</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 80 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> ceases to apply in respect of First Nations and their members on the day on which section <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> — definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the continuing application of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> under this section, the definitions <DefinitionRef>band</DefinitionRef>, <DefinitionRef>council of the band</DefinitionRef> and <DefinitionRef>member of a band</DefinitionRef> in subsection 2(1) of that Act have the meaning assigned to<DefinitionRef> First Nation,</DefinitionRef> <DefinitionRef>First Nation Government</DefinitionRef> and <DefinitionRef>citizen</DefinitionRef>, respectively, in section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Elections Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Elections Act</XRefExternal> ceases to apply in respect of a First Nation and its members on the day on which a law referred to in paragraph <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>(a) made by that First Nation comes into force.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>An Anishinabek law and any regulation or order made under it are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice — Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice must be taken of the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agreement must be published by the Queen’s Printer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A copy of the Agreement published by the Queen’s Printer is evidence of the Agreement and of its contents, and a copy purporting to be published by the Queen’s Printer is presumed to be so published unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice — Anishinabek laws</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice must be taken of an Anishinabek law that is registered in the official registry of laws maintained by a First Nation or the Anishinabek Nation in accordance with the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A copy of an Anishinabek law purporting to be registered in an official registry of laws referred to in subsection (1) is evidence of that law and of its contents, unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an issue arises in any judicial or administrative proceeding in respect of the interpretation or validity of a provision of the Agreement, this Act or an Anishinabek law, then the issue must not be decided until the party raising the issue has served notice</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on the Attorney General of Canada and the Anishinabek Nation Government, in the case of a provision of the Agreement or this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on the Anishinabek Nation Government, in the case of a provision of a law of the Anishinabek Nation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>on the First Nation Government, in the case of a provision of a law of a First Nation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content and timing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The notice must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>describe the proceeding;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>state the subject matter of the issue;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>state the day on which the issue is to be argued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>give the particulars that are necessary to show the point to be argued; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>be served at least 30 days before the day on which the issue is to be argued, unless the court or tribunal authorizes a shorter period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Participation in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In any proceeding, the recipient of a notice may appear and participate as a party with the same rights as any other party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsections (2) and (3) do not require that an oral hearing be held if one is not otherwise required.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Orders and Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make any orders or regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary for the purpose of carrying out the Agreement or other agreements related to the implementation of the Agreement.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Amendment of Schedule</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Addition of name of First Nation</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, add the name of any First Nation to the schedule if the Governor in Council is satisfied that the First Nation has, in a manner consistent with the Agreement, ratified the Agreement and has a constitution.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amendment or removal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, amend the schedule to amend or remove the name of a First Nation if the Governor in Council is satisfied that consent to the amendment or removal was obtained in a manner consistent with the Agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 32</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Related Amendment to the Anishinabek Nation Education Agreement Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Education Agreement Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Act prevails</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), in the event of an inconsistency or conflict between the provisions of this Act and the provisions of any other Act of Parliament, or of any regulation made under any other Act of Parliament, the provisions of this Act prevail to the extent of the inconsistency or conflict.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal> prevail over the provisions of this Act, and of any regulation made under this Act, to the extent of any inconsistency or conflict between them.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (h), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (i) and by adding the following after paragraph (i):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>First Nation Government</DefinitionRef> or the <DefinitionRef>Anishinabek Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, or an Anishinaabe Institution, within the meaning of section 1.1 of the <DefinitionRef>Agreement</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 32, s. 18(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 8(2)(f) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>for the purpose of administering or enforcing any law or carrying out a lawful investigation, under an agreement or arrangement between the Government of Canada or any of its institutions and any of the following entities or any of their institutions:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the government of a foreign state,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an international organization of states or an international organization established by the governments of states,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the government of a province,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the council of the Westbank First Nation,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>council of a participating First Nation</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">First Nations Jurisdiction over Education in British Columbia Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>the council of a <DefinitionRef>participating First Nation</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Education Agreement Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>First Nation Government</DefinitionRef> or the <DefinitionRef>Anishinabek Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, or an Anishinaabe Institution, within the meaning of section 1.1 of the <DefinitionRef>Agreement</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(7) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (h), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (i) and by adding the following after paragraph (i):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>First Nation Government</DefinitionRef> or the <DefinitionRef>Anishinabek Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, or an Anishinaabe Institution, within the meaning of section 1.1 of the <DefinitionRef>Agreement</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 19(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (e), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (f) and by adding the following after paragraph (f):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>First Nation Government</DefinitionRef> or the <DefinitionRef>Anishinabek Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, or an Anishinaabe Institution, within the meaning of section 1.1 of the <DefinitionRef>Agreement</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2013, c. 25</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>other Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yale First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 20 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (i), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (j) and by adding the following after paragraph (j):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>First Nation Government</DefinitionRef> or the <DefinitionRef>Anishinabek Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, or an Anishinaabe Institution, within the meaning of section 1.1 of the <DefinitionRef>Agreement</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 20 of the other Act, then that section 20 is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (i), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (j) and by adding the following after paragraph (j):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>Yale First Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yale First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 20 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section 20 is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal> and subsection (2) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If section 23 of the other Act comes into force before subsection <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then that subsection <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(2) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(7) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (i), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (j) and by adding the following after paragraph (j):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>a <DefinitionRef>First Nation Government</DefinitionRef> or the <DefinitionRef>Anishinabek Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, or an Anishinaabe Institution, within the meaning of section 1.1 of the <DefinitionRef>Agreement</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act comes into force before section 23 of the other Act, then that section 23 is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>Subsection 8(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (i), by adding “or’’ at the end of paragraph (j) and by adding the following after paragraph (j):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>Yale First Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yale First Nation Final Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If section 23 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subsection <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act, then that section 23 is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(2) and subsection (5) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>This Part, other than section <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>, comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1986, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>The long title of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><LongTitle>An Act respecting shíshálh Nation self-government</LongTitle></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>The preamble to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is committed to</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>achieving reconciliation with the shíshálh Nation and other First Nations, through renewed nation-to-nation relationships based on recognition of rights, respect, cooperation and partnership,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>responding, to the extent of its authority, to the Calls to Action in the Final Report of the Truth and Reconciliation Commission of Canada and the Calls for Justice in the Final Report of the National Inquiry into Missing and Murdered Indigenous Women and Girls, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>implementing the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada recognizes that the inherent right of self-government is a right recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada also recognizes the shíshálh Nation’s unique connection to the land and resources, and that maintaining this connection is essential to the preservation of the Nation’s culture, health, economy, laws, systems of governance and, consequently, to the future of the Nation;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the members of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Sechelt band, in a referendum held on March 15, 1986, approved of</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the enactment of legislation substantially as set out in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, as it read on October 9, 1986, for the purpose of enabling the Sechelt Indian Band to exercise self-government over its lands, and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the transfer by Her Majesty in right of Canada to the Sechelt Indian Band of fee simple title in all Sechelt reserve lands, recognizing that the Sechelt Indian Band would assume complete responsibility, in accordance with <XRefExternal reference-type="act">the Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, as it read on that date, for the management, administration and control of all Sechelt lands;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas it is appropriate, based on collaborative exchanges between the Government of Canada and the shíshálh Nation, to include in this Act certain elements provided for in self-government agreements;</Text></Provision></Preamble></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Section 1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">shíshálh Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>The heading before section 2 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Définitions et interprétation</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Band</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Sechelt lands</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Council</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>District</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Council</DefinedTermEn> means the council continued by subsection 8(1) under the name <Emphasis style="italic">hiwus Ɂiy te hihewhiwus</Emphasis> and referred to in Part II of the constitution of the shíshálh Nation as amended by Order in Council P.C. 2019-1225 of August 17, 2019; (<DefinedTermFr>conseil</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>District</DefinedTermEn> means the shíshálh Nation Government District referred to in section 17; (<DefinedTermFr>district</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>District Council</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>District Council</DefinedTermEn> means the shíshálh Nation Government District Council established by subsection 19(1); (<DefinedTermFr>conseil de district</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>former Act</DefinedTermEn> means this Act as it read immediately before the coming into force of section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to give effect to the Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement, to amend the Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act and the Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>loi antérieure</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Indigenous peoples of Canada</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by the definition <DefinitionRef>aboriginal peoples of Canada</DefinitionRef> in subsection 35(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>peuples autochtones du Canada</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Sechelt Indian Band</DefinedTermEn> means the Band established by subsection 5(1) of the former Act; (<DefinedTermFr>bande indienne sechelte</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>shíshálh lands</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>lands transferred to the Sechelt Indian Band on October 9, 1986 under section 23 of the former Act, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>lands described in declarations referred to in section 25.1; (<DefinedTermFr>terres shishalhes</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>shíshálh law</DefinedTermEn> means a law made by the Council under section 14 or 28. (<DefinedTermFr>loi shishalhe</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>shíshálh Nation</DefinedTermEn> means the Nation referred to in section 5; (<DefinedTermFr>Nation shishalhe</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Lands ceasing to be shíshálh lands</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any shíshálh lands to which the title is sold or otherwise transferred cease to be shíshálh lands.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Rights of Indigenous peoples</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>This Act shall be construed as upholding the Aboriginal rights of the shíshálh Nation and the rights of any other Indigenous peoples of Canada recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>, and not as abrogating or derogating from them.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rights of shíshálh Nation</MarginalNote><Label>3.1</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in this Act shall be construed as</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>limiting or restricting the position of the shíshálh Nation or any other person with respect to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>any Aboriginal rights, including the inherent right of self-government and the Aboriginal title, of the Nation that are recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the Nation’s identity as an Indigenous people of Canada; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>restricting the Nation from participating in any process that may be established to implement the inherent right of self-government, including on a regional or national basis.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Sections 4 and 5 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Purposes</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The purposes of this Act are to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>support the exercise of aspects of the shíshálh Nation’s inherent right of self-government;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>support the Nation in its control over and administration of the resources and services available to its members; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>contribute to the implementation of the United Nations Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples as it relates to the self-government of the Nation.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>shíshálh Nation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Continuation</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Sechelt Indian Band, established under subsection 5(1) of the former Act, is continued under the name “shíshálh Nation” and, for greater certainty,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the rights, titles, interests, assets, obligations and liabilities of the Sechelt Indian Band, including those of its council, are those of the Nation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the members of the Sechelt Indian Band are the members of the Nation.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>The heading before section 6 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Capacity and Powers of shíshálh Nation</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 6 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Capacity of Nation</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>The shíshálh Nation is a legal entity and has, subject to this Act, the capacity, rights, powers and privileges of a natural person and, without restricting the generality of the foregoing, may</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 6(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>acquire and hold property or any right or interest in it, and sell or otherwise dispose of that property, right or interest;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>Sections 7 to 9 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Nation subject to its constitution</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>The powers and duties of the shíshálh Nation shall be carried out in accordance with its constitution.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Council of shíshálh Nation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Governing body</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Sechelt Indian Band Council, referred to in section 8 of the former Act, is continued as the council and governing body of the shíshálh Nation under the name <Emphasis style="italic">hiwus Ɂiy te hihewhiwus</Emphasis>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Election of members</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The members of the council continued under subsection (1) shall be elected in accordance with the constitution of the Nation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Nation to act through Council</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The shíshálh Nation shall act through the Council in exercising its powers and carrying out its duties and functions.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>The heading before section 10 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Constitution of shíshálh Nation</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 10(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Elements of constitution</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The constitution of the shíshálh Nation shall be in writing and shall</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 10(1)(b) and (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>establish the procedures or processes to be followed by the Council in exercising the Nation’s powers and carrying out its duties;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>provide for a system of financial accountability of the Council to the members of the Nation, including audit arrangements and the publication of financial reports;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>provide for appeals in relation to decisions of the Council and administrative bodies created to assist in the administration of the affairs of the Nation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c.2)</Label><Text>provide for conflict of interest rules;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 10(1)(d) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>include a membership code for the Nation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 10(1)(e) and (f) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>establish rules and procedures relating to the holding of referenda referred to in section 12 or paragraph 21(2)(b) or provided for in the constitution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>establish rules and procedures to be followed in respect of the disposition of rights or interests in shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 10(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (g) and by replacing paragraph (h) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g.1)</Label><Text>establish rules and procedures for the making and amending of shíshálh laws; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>provide for any other matters relating to the exercise of powers and carrying out of duties and functions of the Nation under this Act, including matters related to the government of the Nation or its members, or the management of shíshálh lands, to the extent that the Nation is of the opinion that such matters should be reflected in the constitution.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsection 10(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Membership code</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any membership code established in the constitution of the shíshálh Nation shall respect rights to membership in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Sechelt band acquired under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> immediately prior to the coming into force of the first membership code established after the coming into force of the former Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Sections 11 to 13 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Amendment to constitution</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The Council may declare an amendment to the constitution of the shíshálh Nation to be in force if the amendment has been approved in a referendum held in accordance with the constitution.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Publication of amendments</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>The Council shall, as soon as practicable after making a declaration under section 12, make any amendment to the constitution publicly accessible</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on the shíshálh Nation’s website;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">First Nations Gazette</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in any other manner that the Council considers equivalent and that allows the public to readily access the amendment.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 14(1) of the Act before paragraph (b) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Legislative powers</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Council has, to the extent that it is authorized by the constitution of the shíshálh Nation to do so, the power to make laws in relation to matters coming within any of the following classes of matters:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>access to and residence on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 14(1)(b) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>zoning and land use planning in respect of shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 14(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>the creation and regulation of rights or interests in shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the expropriation by the Nation, for community purposes, of rights or interests in shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 14(1)(d) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the use, construction, maintenance, repair and demolition of buildings and structures on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 14(1)(e) to (h) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the taxation, for local purposes, of rights or interests in shíshálh lands, and of occupants and tenants of shíshálh lands in respect of their rights or interests in those lands, including assessment, collection and enforcement procedures, as well as appeals relating to such matters;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the administration and management of property belonging to the Nation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the education of members of the Nation on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>social and welfare services with respect to members of the Nation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h.1)</Label><Text>child and family services with respect to the Nation’s families and children, including the custody, placement and care of the Nation’s children;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 14(1)(i) to (n) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>health services on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the preservation and management of natural resources on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the preservation, protection and management of fur-bearing animals, fish and game on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>public order and safety on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>the construction, maintenance and management of roads and the regulation of traffic on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>the operation of businesses, professions and trades on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 14(1)(o) to (r) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>the prohibition of the sale, barter, supply, manufacture or possession of intoxicants on shíshálh lands and any exceptions to a prohibition of possession;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (2), the imposition on summary conviction of fines or imprisonment for the contravention of any shíshálh laws;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>the devolution, by testate or intestate succession, of real property of members of the Nation on shíshálh lands and personal property of members of the Nation ordinarily resident on shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(r)</Label><Text>financial administration of the Nation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Paragraph 14(1)(s) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(s)</Label><Text>the conduct of the Nation’s elections and referenda;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 14(1)(t) and (u) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>the creation of administrative bodies and agencies to assist in the administration of the affairs of the Nation; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(u)</Label><Text>matters related to the good government of the Nation, its members or shíshálh lands.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Section 14 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, neither paragraph (1)(h.1) nor the making of any law under that paragraph prevents the shíshálh Nation from making any laws in relation to child and family services referred to in <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting First Nations, Inuit and Métis children, youth and families</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 14:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Publication of shíshálh laws</MarginalNote><Label>14.1</Label><Text>The Council shall, as soon as practicable after a shíshálh law, or any amendment to it, is made, make that law or amendment publicly accessible</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on the shíshálh Nation’s website;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">First Nations Gazette</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in any other manner that the Council considers equivalent and that allows the public to readily access the laws and any amendment to them.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>Sections 16 and 17 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Constitution prevails</MarginalNote><Label>15.1</Label><Text>In the event of an inconsistency between the provisions of a shíshálh law and the provisions of the constitution of the shíshálh Nation, the provisions of the constitution prevail to the extent of the inconsistency.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Non-application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a shíshálh law.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>shíshálh Nation Government District</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Continuation</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>The Sechelt Indian Government District, recognized and deemed to have been established under section 17 of the former Act, is continued under the name “shíshálh Nation Government District” and its jurisdiction — resulting from any transfer under subsections 21(1) and (2) — may be exercised over shíshálh lands, subject to subsections 21(3) to (5).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 18 of the French version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Capacité</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>Le district est une entité juridique dotée de la capacité et des droits, pouvoirs et privilèges d’une personne physique. Il peut notamment :</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 18(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>acquire and hold property or any right or interest in it, and sell or otherwise dispose of that property, right or interest;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Text>Subsection 19(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Continuation</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Sechelt Indian Government District Council, established under subsection 19(1) of the former Act, is continued as the governing body of the District under the name “shíshálh Nation Government District Council.”</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>Section 21 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer to District</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the advice of the Minister, by order, transfer any of the powers, duties or functions of the shíshálh Nation or the Council under this Act or the constitution of the Nation to the District, except those relating to membership in the Nation and the disposition of rights or interests in shíshálh lands.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions for order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall not make an order under subsection (1) unless he or she is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the legislature of British Columbia has passed legislation respecting the District and that legislation is in force; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the transfer of the powers, duties and functions specified in the order has been approved in a referendum held in accordance with the constitution of the Nation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfer — legislation amended</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the advice of the Minister, by order, transfer to the Nation or the Council, as the case may be, any of the powers, duties and functions that were transferred to the District under subsection (1) or under subsection 21(2) of the former Act, if the legislation referred to in paragraph (2)(a) is amended.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Condition for order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall not make an order under subsection (3) unless he or she is satisfied that the transfer of powers, duties and functions specified in the order has been approved in a referendum held in accordance with the constitution of the Nation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfer — legislation repealed</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the advice of the Minister, by order, declare that sections 17 to 20 are no longer in force and transfer, to the Nation or the Council, as the case may be, the powers, duties and functions that were transferred to the District under subsection (1) or under subsection 21(2) of the former Act, if the legislation referred to in paragraph (2)(a) is no longer in force.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>Section 23 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 24 of the Act before paragraph (b) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Limitations</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>The fee simple title of the shíshálh Nation in the lands transferred to it under section 23 of the former Act is subject to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any rights or interests recognized or established by the agreement entered into between Canada and British Columbia on January 26, 1943, relating to the ownership and exploitation of minerals, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">British Columbia Indian Reserves Mineral Resources Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 19 of the Statutes of Canada, 1943-44 and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Reserve Mineral Resource Act</XRefExternal> of British Columbia, R.S.B.C. 1979, c. 192;</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 24(c) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>c)</Label><Text>aux droits ou intérêts conférés par tout titre — hypothèque, bail, permis d’occupation, certificat de possession ou autre — en cours de validité à l’égard des terres à l’entrée en vigueur du présent article.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>Sections 25 to 28 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Lands for use and benefit of Nation</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>The shíshálh Nation holds shíshálh lands for the use and benefit of the Nation and its members.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Lands Declared to be shíshálh Lands</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Federal and provincial declarations</MarginalNote><Label>25.1</Label><Text>Lands in British Columbia are shíshálh lands if they are declared to be shíshálh lands for the purposes of this Act by both</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Governor in Council, by order; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Lieutenant Governor in Council of British Columbia.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Disposition of shíshálh Lands</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Power of the Nation</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Text>The shíshálh Nation has full power to dispose of any shíshálh lands and any rights or interests in those lands but shall not do so except in accordance with the procedure established in its constitution.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Registration of shíshálh Lands</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Reserve Land Register</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), particulars relating to all transactions respecting shíshálh lands shall be entered in the Reserve Land Register kept under section 21 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This section does not apply with respect to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any shíshálh lands that are registered pursuant to section 28; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the rights or interests in shíshálh lands referred to in sections 30.1 to 30.4.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Laws on registration</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Text>The Council may make laws authorizing the registration, in accordance with the laws of British Columbia, of estates or interests in any shíshálh lands specified in the laws of the Council, and for that purpose may make laws making any laws of British Columbia applicable to those shíshálh lands.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 29(2) of the Act before subparagraph (b)(i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Minister to provide particulars to Council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall without delay, and in any event not later than 30 days after receipt of notice of a law under subsection (1) in respect of any shíshálh lands,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>cause to be provided to the Council a list of all particulars entered on the Reserve Land Register kept under section 21 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> in respect of those lands; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cause to be sent to any person who appears from the Reserve Land Register to have any right or interest in those lands, at the person’s latest known address, a notice indicating that</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 29(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>List to be posted</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Council shall, immediately on receipt of the list referred to in paragraph (2)(a), cause the list or a copy of it to be posted in a conspicuous place on both the lands to which it relates and at another location on shíshálh lands, and shall indicate on the list that a person can request a modification of the Reserve Land Register only if they do so within 30 days after a date indicated on the list, which date is the date on which the list was provided to the Council.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 30(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Final list of rights or interests</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause to be prepared, within 10 days after the end of the period referred to in subsection 29(3), a final list of all rights or interests in shíshálh lands in respect of which a shíshálh law is made under section 28.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 30(3) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Caractère de la liste</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>La liste définitive est la seule référence quant aux droits ou intérêts sur les terres qu’elle vise à compter de la date de son établissement.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Text>Section 31 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement — shíshálh Lands Register</MarginalNote><Label>30.1</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement with the shíshálh Nation respecting the establishment of a register, to be known as the shíshálh Lands Register, for the registration of the legal descriptions of shíshálh lands and of rights or interests in those lands.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of Register</MarginalNote><Label>30.2</Label><Text>The Minister shall establish the shíshálh Lands Register in accordance with any agreement entered into under section 30.1.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulation-making powers</MarginalNote><Label>30.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations respecting the shíshálh Lands Register, including regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the administration of the Register;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the registration of legal descriptions of shíshálh lands;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the registration of rights or interests in shíshálh lands and the effects of their registration, including priorities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the recording of any other matter; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the transfer of the administration of the Register to any person or body.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Adaptation of sections 28 to 30</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Minister, make regulations respecting the manner in which sections 28 to 30 apply in the case of the establishment of the shíshálh Lands Register under section 30.2, and adapting those sections for the purposes of that application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Collaboration with Nation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall ensure that the shíshálh Nation is afforded a meaningful opportunity to collaborate in policy development leading to the making of regulations under subsection (1) or (2).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rights or interests continued</MarginalNote><Label>30.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the day on which the shíshálh Lands Register is established, rights or interests in shíshálh lands that are registered in the register referred to in section 27 continue in accordance with their terms.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recording of continued rights or interests</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The shíshálh Nation shall, as soon as practicable after the shíshálh Lands Register is established, record the rights or interests in shíshálh lands continued under subsection (1) in that register.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recording of new rights or interests</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>From the day on which the shíshálh Lands Register is established, any registration of new rights or interests in shíshálh lands shall be recorded in that register and not in the register referred to in section 27.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>This section does not apply with respect to any shíshálh lands that are registered pursuant to section 28.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>shíshálh Lands</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Class 24 of section 91</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, shíshálh lands are lands reserved for the Indians within the meaning of Class 24 of section 91 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, lands that cease to be shíshálh lands under subsection 2(2) are not lands reserved for the Indians within the meaning of Class 24 of section 91 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>Section 32 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Administration of transferred moneys</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>Moneys transferred under subsection 32(1) of the former Act shall be administered in accordance with the constitution of the shíshálh Nation and shíshálh laws.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>Section 33 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements between Minister and Nation</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement with the shíshálh Nation under which funding would be provided by the Government of Canada to the Nation in the form of grants over such period of time, and subject to such terms as are specified in the agreement.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>Sections 35 and 36 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to section 36, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> applies, with any necessary modifications, in respect of the shíshálh Nation, its members, the Council and shíshálh lands except to the extent that the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> is inconsistent with this Act, the constitution of the Nation or a shíshálh law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Indians</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> applies for the purpose of determining which members of the Nation are Indians within the meaning of that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Taxation provisions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, section 87 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> applies, with any necessary modifications, in respect of the Nation and its members who are Indians within the meaning of that Act, subject to any shíshálh law in relation to the class of matters set out in paragraph 14(1)(e).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Non-application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, on the advice of the Minister, by order,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>declare that the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> or any provision of that Act does not apply to the shíshálh Nation, its members or any portion of shíshálh lands; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>revoke any such order.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Text>Section 37 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Federal laws of general application</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Text>All federal laws of general application in force in Canada apply in respect of the shíshálh Nation, its members and shíshálh lands except to the extent that those laws are inconsistent with this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>37.1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal> applies in respect of the Council, the District Council and any administrative bodies and agencies referred to in paragraph 14(1)(t) in respect of matters within their authority under this Act or the constitution of the shíshálh Nation, with due regard for section 25 of the Charter which provides that the guarantee in the Charter of certain rights and freedoms shall not be construed so as to abrogate or derogate from any aboriginal, treaty or other rights or freedoms that pertain to the aboriginal peoples of Canada.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Section 38 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Provincial laws of general application</MarginalNote><Label>38</Label><Text>Laws of general application of British Columbia apply in respect of the members of the shíshálh Nation except to the extent that those laws are inconsistent with the terms of any treaty, this or any other Act of Parliament, the constitution of the Nation or a shíshálh law.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Text>Sections 39 to 42 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Oil and Gas Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Oil and Gas Act</XRefExternal> applies, with any necessary modifications, in respect of the shíshálh Nation, its members, the Council and shíshálh lands.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Federal law relating to mineral resources</MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">British Columbia Indian Reserves Mineral Resources Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 19 of the Statutes of Canada, 1943-44, applies in respect of shíshálh lands.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provincial law relating to mineral resources</MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Reserve Mineral Resource Act</XRefExternal> of British Columbia, R.S.B.C. 1979, c. 192, applies in respect of shíshálh lands.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Application of Former Laws and By-laws</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application on shíshálh lands</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Text>Laws of the Sechelt Indian Band and by-laws of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Sechelt band referred to in section 42 of the former Act — as well as laws or by-laws of the Sechelt Indian Government District made following the transfer or granting of legislative powers under section 21 or 22 of the former Act — that applied to Sechelt lands, as defined in section 2 of the former Act, on the day on which section <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to give effect to the Anishinabek Nation Governance Agreement, to amend the Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act and the Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</XRefExternal> comes into force, remain in force and apply to shíshálh lands and in respect of the members of the shíshálh Nation except to the extent that the laws or by-laws are inconsistent with this Act, the constitution of the Nation or a shíshálh law.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Text>Section 43 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Powers, functions and duties in constitution</MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Text>The Governor in Council or any Minister of the Crown may exercise any powers and carry out any functions or duties that the Governor in Council or Minister is authorized under the constitution of the shíshálh Nation to exercise or carry out.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>Sections 44 to 46 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>References to former Act and terminology</MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Text>Unless the context otherwise requires, in any law of the Sechelt Indian Band and by-law of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Sechelt band, referred to in section 42 of the former Act, laws or by-laws of the Sechelt Indian Government District made following the transfer or granting of legislative powers under section 21 or 22 of the former Act, as well as in documents, including licences and other authorizations, contracts and other instruments that were issued, granted, entered into or made in accordance with the former Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any reference to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, or any provision of that Act, is to be read as a reference to this Act or any relevant provision of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any reference to the Sechelt Indian Band is to be read as a reference to the shíshálh Nation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any reference to the Sechelt Indian Band Council is to be read as a reference to the council of the Nation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>any reference to the constitution of the Sechelt Indian Band, or any provision of that constitution, is to be read as a reference to the constitution of the Nation or any relevant provision of that constitution;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any reference to a law of the Sechelt Indian Band, or any provision of that law, is to be read as a reference to a relevant shíshálh law or any relevant provision of that law;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any reference to a law or by-law of the Sechelt Indian Government District, or any provision of that law or by-law, is to be read as a reference to a relevant law or by-law of the shíshálh Nation Government District or any relevant provision of that law or by-law; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any reference to Sechelt lands is to be read as a reference to shíshálh lands.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 20 (2nd Supp.), s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Text>Subsection 4(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No right or interest in lands that are <DefinitionRef>shíshálh lands</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">shíshálh Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, may be expropriated under this Part without the consent of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-24</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fishing and Recreational Harbours Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 20 (2nd Supp.), s. 3</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Text>Paragraph (c) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>agency</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fishing and Recreational Harbours Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>Council</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">shíshálh Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, and</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Lands Surveys Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 20 (2nd Supp.), s. 4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Text>Subparagraph 24(1)(a)(iii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Lands Surveys Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>shíshálh lands</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">shíshálh Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. M-13; 2000, c. 8, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 20 (2nd Supp.), s. 5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Text>Paragraph (d) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>taxing authority</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>Council</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">shíshálh Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>, if it levies and collects a real property tax or a frontage or area tax in respect of <DefinitionRef>shíshálh lands</DefinitionRef>, as defined in that subsection,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Text>Paragraph 8(6)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>shíshálh Nation</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">shíshálh Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2008, c. 22</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>46</Label><Text>The reference to</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Sechelt Indian Band Self-Government Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la bande indienne sechelte</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>in Part 1 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>shíshálh Nation Self-Government Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’autonomie gouvernementale de la Nation shishalhe</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 28, s. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>47</Label><Text>Paragraph 317(3)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>shíshálh lands</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">shíshálh Nation Self-Government Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1994, c. 35</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>48</Label><Text>Section 24 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Funding agreements</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>The Minister may, subject to appropriations by Parliament, enter into an agreement with a first nation named in Schedule II for the provision of funding by the Government of Canada to the first nation over the period of time and subject to the terms and conditions specified in the agreement.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal>)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Schedule bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 14)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>First Nations</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Magnetawan First Nation </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Première Nation Magnetawan </BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Moose Deer Point First Nation </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Première Nation Moose Deer Point </BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Nipissing First Nation </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Première Nation Nipissing</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Wahnapitae First Nation </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Première Nation Wahnapitae</BilingualItemFr><BilingualItemEn>Zhiibaahaasing First Nation </BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Première Nation Zhiibaahaasing </BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Schedule></Schedule></Bill>