<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-28</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (self-induced extreme intoxication)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (self-induced extreme intoxication)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (self-induced extreme intoxication)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2022</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-6-16">91101</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to provide for criminal liability for violent crimes of general intent committed by a person while in a state of negligent self-induced extreme intoxication.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 32, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 33.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Self-induced Extreme Intoxication</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offences of violence by negligence</MarginalNote><Label>33.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who, by reason of self-induced extreme intoxication, lacks the general intent or voluntariness ordinarily required to commit an offence referred to in subsection (3), nonetheless commits the offence if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>all the other elements of the offence are present; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>before they were in a state of extreme intoxication, they departed markedly from the standard of care expected of a reasonable person in the circumstances with respect to the consumption of intoxicating substances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Marked departure — foreseeability of risk and other circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of determining whether the person departed markedly from the standard of care, the court must consider the objective foreseeability of the risk that the consumption of the intoxicating substances could cause extreme intoxication and lead the person to harm another person. The court must, in making the determination, also consider all relevant circumstances, including anything that the person did to avoid the risk.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offences</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>This section applies in respect of an offence under this Act or any other Act of Parliament that includes as an element an assault or any other interference or threat of interference by a person with the bodily integrity of another person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>extreme intoxication</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>extreme intoxication</DefinedTermEn> means intoxication that renders a person unaware of, or incapable of consciously controlling, their behaviour.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>