<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-14</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Constitution Act, 1867 (electoral representation)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Preserving Provincial Representation in the House of Commons Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Preserving Provincial Representation in the House of Commons Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2022</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>23</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>6</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2022</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-3-23">91079</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Constitution Act, 1867 (electoral representation)</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends section 51 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> to provide that, when the number of members of the House of Commons and the representation of the provinces in that House are readjusted on the completion of each decennial census, a province will not have fewer members assigned to it than were assigned during the 43rd Parliament. It also includes transitional measures providing for the application of that amendment to the readjustment of electoral boundaries under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal> following the 2021 decennial census.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Alternative Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Alternative title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Preserving Provincial Representation in the House of Commons Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>30-31 Vict., c. 3 (U.K.); 1982, c. 11 (U.K.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Constitution Act, 1867</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2011, c. 26, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Rule 2 of subsection 51(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Provision first-line-indent="1" language-align="no" list-item="yes" subsequent-line-indent="3"><Label>2.</Label><Text>If the number of members assigned to a province by the application of rule 1 and section 51A is less than the total number assigned to that province during the 43rd Parliament, there shall be added to the number of members so assigned the number of members that will result in the province having the same number of members as were assigned during that Parliament.</Text></Provision></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Deemed reference</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>A reference to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Acts, 1867 to 1982</XRefExternal> is deemed to include a reference to section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Loi</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>old calculation</DefinedTermEn> means the calculation of the number of members of the House of Commons to be assigned to each province done by the Chief Electoral Officer under subsection 14(1) of the Act, the statement of the results of which was published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> on October 16, 2021. (<DefinedTermFr>calcul antérieur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Words and expressions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless the context otherwise requires, words and expressions used in this section and section <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> have the same meaning as in the Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>New calculation</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as feasible after the day on which this section comes into force, the Chief Electoral Officer must calculate the number of members of the House of Commons to be assigned to each province under subsection 14(1) of the Act, subject and according to the provisions of section 51 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1867</XRefExternal> and the rules set out in that section as they are amended by section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal>, and on completing that calculation must cause a statement to be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> setting out the results.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Province with different number of members resulting from new calculation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the calculation referred to in subsection (1) results in a different number of members of the House of Commons for a province than was obtained under the old calculation,</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any report referred to in subsection 14(2) of the Act that is prepared in respect of the province on the basis of the old calculation, and anything done under sections 19 to 23 of the Act on the basis of the report, are nullities;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the commission established for the province under section 3 of the Act in respect of the most recent decennial census must prepare a report under subsection 14(2) of the Act in respect of the province on the basis of the calculation referred to in subsection (1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the duties and functions set out in sections 19 to 23 of the Act are to be performed in respect of the province following the preparation of the report under paragraph (b), and the 10-month period referred to in subsection 20(1) of the Act is, in respect of the province, deemed to begin on the day on which the statement referred to in subsection (1) is published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>No representation order before coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If, before the day on which this section comes into force, no representation order was prepared and transmitted under subsection 24(1) of the Act on the basis of the old calculation, the Chief Electoral Officer must — without waiting for the report prepared under subsection 20(1) of the Act for a province referred to in subsection (2) — prepare and transmit a representation order under subsection 24(1) of the Act that applies in respect of all provinces other than that province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Representation order before coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If, before the day on which this section comes into force, a representation order was prepared and transmitted under subsection 24(1) of the Act on the basis of the old calculation, that representation order and any proclamation made under subsection 25(1) of the Act that declares it to be in force are nullities only in respect of a province referred to in subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Representation order and proclamation — province referred to in subsection (2)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If subsection (3) or (4) applies, a representation order is to be prepared under subsection 24(1) of the Act, and a proclamation is to be made under subsection 25(1) of the Act, in respect of a province referred to in subsection (2) and on the basis of the calculation referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Previous representation order applies</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the representation order annexed to the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Proclamation Declaring the Representation Order to be in Force Effective on the First Dissolution of Parliament that Occurs after May 1, 2014</XRefExternal>, registered as SI/2013-102, continues to apply in respect of a province referred to in subsection (2) until the representation order referred to in subsection (5) becomes effective under subsection 25(1) or (2) of the Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Administrative consolidation</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>When the representation order and proclamation referred to in subsection (5) are published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> under section 26 of the Act, the Chief Electoral Officer must publish on their website an administrative consolidation consisting of that representation order and the portion of the representation order referred to in subsection (3) or (4), as the case may be, that applies in respect of all provinces other than a province referred to in subsection (2). The consolidation must set out, in respect of each province, the day on which the applicable representation order came into force.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>