<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Statute lims:pit-date="2014-04-01" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-04-01" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73093" lims:id="73093" bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" in-force="yes" xml:lang="en" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73094" lims:id="73094"><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73095" lims:id="73095">An Act for the preservation and enhancement of multiculturalism in Canada</LongTitle><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73096" lims:id="73096" status="official">Canadian Multiculturalism Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73097" lims:id="73097">Canadian Multiculturalism</RunningHead><BillHistory lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73098" lims:id="73098"><Stages lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73100" lims:id="73100"><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">C-18.7</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="yes"><AnnualStatuteNumber>24 (4th Supp.)</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>1985</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><ReaderNote><Note status="official" xml:space="default">[<Emphasis style="italic">1988, c. 31, assented to 21st July, 1988</Emphasis>]</Note></ReaderNote></Identification><Introduction lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73101" lims:id="73101"><Preamble lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73102" lims:id="73102" salutation="no"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73103" lims:id="73103" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73104" lims:id="73104">Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>WHEREAS the Constitution of Canada provides that every individual is equal before and under the law and has the right to the equal protection and benefit of the law without discrimination and that everyone has the freedom of conscience, religion, thought, belief, opinion, expression, peaceful assembly and association and guarantees those rights and freedoms equally to male and female persons;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73105" lims:id="73105" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS the Constitution of Canada recognizes the importance of preserving and enhancing the multicultural heritage of Canadians;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73106" lims:id="73106" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS the Constitution of Canada recognizes rights of the aboriginal peoples of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73107" lims:id="73107" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS the Constitution of Canada and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="O-3.01">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal> provide that English and French are the official languages of Canada and neither abrogates nor derogates from any rights or privileges acquired or enjoyed with respect to any other language;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73108" lims:id="73108" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-29">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> provides that all Canadians, whether by birth or by choice, enjoy equal status, are entitled to the same rights, powers and privileges and are subject to the same obligations, duties and liabilities;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73109" lims:id="73109" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="H-6">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal> provides that every individual should have an equal opportunity with other individuals to make the life that the individual is able and wishes to have, consistent with the duties and obligations of that individual as a member of society, and, in order to secure that opportunity, establishes the Canadian Human Rights Commission to redress any proscribed discrimination, including discrimination on the basis of race, national or ethnic origin or colour;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73110" lims:id="73110" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS Canada is a party to the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination</XRefExternal>, which Convention recognizes that all human beings are equal before the law and are entitled to equal protection of the law against any discrimination and against any incitement to discrimination, and to the <XRefExternal reference-type="other">International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights</XRefExternal>, which Covenant provides that persons belonging to ethnic, religious or linguistic minorities shall not be denied the right to enjoy their own culture, to profess and practise their own religion or to use their own language;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73111" lims:id="73111" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS the Government of Canada recognizes the diversity of Canadians as regards race, national or ethnic origin, colour and religion as a fundamental characteristic of Canadian society and is committed to a policy of multiculturalism designed to preserve and enhance the multicultural heritage of Canadians while working to achieve the equality of all Canadians in the economic, social, cultural and political life of Canada;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73112" lims:id="73112"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73113" lims:id="73113" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73114" lims:id="73114"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73115" lims:id="73115" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73116" lims:id="73116"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73117" lims:id="73117">Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-18.7">Canadian Multiculturalism Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73118" lims:id="73118" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73119" lims:id="73119"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73120" lims:id="73120">Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act,</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73121" lims:id="73121"><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal institution</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following institutions of the Government of Canada:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73122" lims:id="73122"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a department, board, commission or council, or other body or office, established to perform a governmental function by or pursuant to an Act of Parliament or by or under the authority of the Governor in Council, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73123" lims:id="73123"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a departmental corporation or Crown corporation as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="F-11">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedDefinition lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73124" lims:id="73124"><Text>but does not include</Text></ContinuedDefinition><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73125" lims:id="73125"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any institution of the Legislative Assembly or government of Yukon, the Northwest Territories or Nunavut, as the case may be, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73126" lims:id="73126"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>any Indian band, band council or other body established to perform a governmental function in relation to an Indian band or other group of aboriginal people; (<DefinedTermFr>institutions fédérales</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73127" lims:id="73127"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means such member of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada as is designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this Act. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2014-04-01" lims:fid="73129" lims:id="73129">R.S., 1985, c. 24 (4th Supp.), s. 2; 1993, c. 28, s. 78; 2002, c. 7, s. 129; 2014, c. 2, s. 38</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73130" lims:id="73130" level="1"><TitleText>Multiculturalism Policy of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73131" lims:id="73131"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73132" lims:id="73132">Multiculturalism policy</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73133" lims:id="73133"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>It is hereby declared to be the policy of the Government of Canada to</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73134" lims:id="73134"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>recognize and promote the understanding that multiculturalism reflects the cultural and racial diversity of Canadian society and acknowledges the freedom of all members of Canadian society to preserve, enhance and share their cultural heritage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73135" lims:id="73135"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>recognize and promote the understanding that multiculturalism is a fundamental characteristic of the Canadian heritage and identity and that it provides an invaluable resource in the shaping of Canada’s future;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73136" lims:id="73136"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>promote the full and equitable participation of individuals and communities of all origins in the continuing evolution and shaping of all aspects of Canadian society and assist them in the elimination of any barrier to that participation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73137" lims:id="73137"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>recognize the existence of communities whose members share a common origin and their historic contribution to Canadian society, and enhance their development;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73138" lims:id="73138"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>ensure that all individuals receive equal treatment and equal protection under the law, while respecting and valuing their diversity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73139" lims:id="73139"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>encourage and assist the social, cultural, economic and political institutions of Canada to be both respectful and inclusive of Canada’s multicultural character;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73140" lims:id="73140"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>promote the understanding and creativity that arise from the interaction between individuals and communities of different origins;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73141" lims:id="73141"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>foster the recognition and appreciation of the diverse cultures of Canadian society and promote the reflection and the evolving expressions of those cultures;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73142" lims:id="73142"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>preserve and enhance the use of languages other than English and French, while strengthening the status and use of the official languages of Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73143" lims:id="73143"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>advance multiculturalism throughout Canada in harmony with the national commitment to the official languages of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73144" lims:id="73144"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73145" lims:id="73145">Federal institutions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>It is further declared to be the policy of the Government of Canada that all federal institutions shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73146" lims:id="73146"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>ensure that Canadians of all origins have an equal opportunity to obtain employment and advancement in those institutions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73147" lims:id="73147"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>promote policies, programs and practices that enhance the ability of individuals and communities of all origins to contribute to the continuing evolution of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73148" lims:id="73148"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>promote policies, programs and practices that enhance the understanding of and respect for the diversity of the members of Canadian society;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73149" lims:id="73149"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>collect statistical data in order to enable the development of policies, programs and practices that are sensitive and responsive to the multicultural reality of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73150" lims:id="73150"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>make use, as appropriate, of the language skills and cultural understanding of individuals of all origins; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73151" lims:id="73151"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>generally, carry on their activities in a manner that is sensitive and responsive to the multicultural reality of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73152" lims:id="73152" level="1"><TitleText>Implementation of the Multiculturalism Policy of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73153" lims:id="73153"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73154" lims:id="73154">General responsibility for coordination</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The Minister, in consultation with other ministers of the Crown, shall encourage and promote a coordinated approach to the implementation of the multiculturalism policy of Canada and may provide advice and assistance in the development and implementation of programs and practices in support of the policy.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73155" lims:id="73155"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73156" lims:id="73156">Specific mandate</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73157" lims:id="73157"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall take such measures as the Minister considers appropriate to implement the multiculturalism policy of Canada and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73158" lims:id="73158"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>encourage and assist individuals, organizations and institutions to project the multicultural reality of Canada in their activities in Canada and abroad;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73159" lims:id="73159"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>undertake and assist research relating to Canadian multiculturalism and foster scholarship in the field;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73160" lims:id="73160"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>encourage and promote exchanges and cooperation among the diverse communities of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73161" lims:id="73161"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>encourage and assist the business community, labour organizations, voluntary and other private organizations, as well as public institutions, in ensuring full participation in Canadian society, including the social and economic aspects, of individuals of all origins and their communities, and in promoting respect and appreciation for the multicultural reality of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73162" lims:id="73162"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>encourage the preservation, enhancement, sharing and evolving expression of the multicultural heritage of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73163" lims:id="73163"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>facilitate the acquisition, retention and use of all languages that contribute to the multicultural heritage of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73164" lims:id="73164"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>assist ethno-cultural minority communities to conduct activities with a view to overcoming any discriminatory barrier and, in particular, discrimination based on race or national or ethnic origin;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73165" lims:id="73165"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>provide support to individuals, groups or organizations for the purpose of preserving, enhancing and promoting multiculturalism in Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73166" lims:id="73166"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>undertake such other projects or programs in respect of multiculturalism, not by law assigned to any other federal institution, as are designed to promote the multiculturalism policy of Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73167" lims:id="73167"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73168" lims:id="73168">Provincial agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement or arrangement with any province respecting the implementation of the multiculturalism policy of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73169" lims:id="73169"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73170" lims:id="73170">International agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, enter into an agreement or arrangement with the government of any foreign state in order to foster the multicultural character of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73171" lims:id="73171"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73172" lims:id="73172">Responsibilities of other Ministers</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73173" lims:id="73173"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The ministers of the Crown, other than the Minister, shall, in the execution of their respective mandates, take such measures as they consider appropriate to implement the multiculturalism policy of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73174" lims:id="73174"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73175" lims:id="73175">Provincial agreements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A minister of the Crown, other than the Minister, may enter into an agreement or arrangement with any province respecting the implementation of the multiculturalism policy of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73176" lims:id="73176"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73177" lims:id="73177">Canadian multiculturalism advisory committee</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73178" lims:id="73178"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may establish an advisory committee to advise and assist the Minister on the implementation of this Act and any other matter relating to multiculturalism and, in consultation with such organizations representing multicultural interests as the Minister deems appropriate, may appoint the members and designate the chairman and other officers of the committee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73179" lims:id="73179"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73180" lims:id="73180">Remuneration and expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each member of the advisory committee shall be paid such remuneration for the member’s services as may be fixed by the Minister and is entitled to be paid the reasonable travel and living expenses incurred by the member while absent from the member’s ordinary place of residence in connection with the work of the committee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73181" lims:id="73181"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73182" lims:id="73182">Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The chairman of the advisory committee shall, within four months after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the Minister a report on the activities of the committee for that year and on any other matter relating to the implementation of the multiculturalism policy of Canada that the chairman considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73183" lims:id="73183" level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73184" lims:id="73184"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73185" lims:id="73185">Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause to be laid before each House of Parliament, not later than the fifth sitting day of that House after January 31 next following the end of each fiscal year, a report on the operation of this Act for that fiscal year.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73186" lims:id="73186"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="73187" lims:id="73187">Permanent review by a Parliamentary committee</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The operation of this Act and any report made pursuant to section 8 shall be reviewed on a permanent basis by such committee of the House, of the Senate or of both Houses of Parliament as may be designated or established for the purpose.</Text></Section></Body></Statute>