<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Statute lims:pit-date="2003-11-04" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-11-04" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78908" lims:id="78908" bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78909" lims:id="78909"><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78910" lims:id="78910">An Act to give effect to certain conventions for the unification of certain rules relating to international carriage by air</LongTitle><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78911" lims:id="78911" status="official">Carriage by Air Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78912" lims:id="78912">Carriage by Air</RunningHead><BillHistory lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78913" lims:id="78913"><Stages lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78915" lims:id="78915"><ConsolidatedNumber official="yes">C-26</ConsolidatedNumber></Chapter></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78916" lims:id="78916"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78917" lims:id="78917"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78918" lims:id="78918">Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-26">Carriage by Air Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78920" lims:id="78920">R.S., c. C-14, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78921" lims:id="78921"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78922" lims:id="78922">Definition of “party”</MarginalNote><Label>1.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78923" lims:id="78923"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>party</DefinedTermEn> includes a High Contracting Party, as defined in Article 40A of the Convention set out in Schedule I.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78924" lims:id="78924"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78925" lims:id="78925">Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, any reference to “agent” in the English version of Schedule I shall be read as a reference to “servant or agent”.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78927" lims:id="78927">1999, c. 21, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78928" lims:id="78928"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78929" lims:id="78929">Implementing Conventions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78930" lims:id="78930"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, the provisions of the Convention set out in Schedule I and of the Convention set out in Schedule V, in so far as they relate to the rights and liabilities of carriers, carriers’ servants and agents, passengers, consignors, consignees and other persons, have the force of law in Canada in relation to any carriage by air to which the provisions apply, irrespective of the nationality of the aircraft performing that carriage.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78931" lims:id="78931"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78932" lims:id="78932">Implementing amendments to Convention</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, the provisions of the Convention set out in Schedule I, as amended by the Protocol set out in Schedule III or by the Protocols set out in Schedules III and IV, in so far as they relate to the rights and liabilities of carriers, carriers’ servants and agents, passengers, consignors, consignees and other persons, have the force of law in Canada in relation to any carriage by air to which the provisions apply, irrespective of the nationality of the aircraft performing that carriage.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78933" lims:id="78933"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78934" lims:id="78934">Implementing Convention</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, the provisions of the Convention set out in Schedule VI, in so far as they relate to the rights and liabilities of carriers, carriers' servants and agents, passengers, consignors, consignees and other persons, have the force of law in Canada in relation to any carriage by air to which the provisions apply, irrespective of the nationality of the aircraft performing that carriage.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78935" lims:id="78935"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78936" lims:id="78936">Proclamation by Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may from time to time, by proclamation published in the 
<Emphasis style="italic">Canada Gazette</Emphasis>, certify who are the parties to any convention or protocol set out in a schedule to this Act, in respect of what territories they are respectively parties, to what extent they have availed themselves of the Additional Protocol to the Convention set out in Schedule I, which of those parties have made a declaration under the Protocol set out in Schedule III or IV and which of those parties have made a declaration under the Convention set out in Schedule VI.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78937" lims:id="78937"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78938" lims:id="78938">Reference to territories</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any reference in Schedule I to the territory of any party shall be construed as a reference to the territories subject to its sovereignty, suzerainty, mandate or authority, in respect of which it is a party.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78939" lims:id="78939"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78940" lims:id="78940">Liability under Convention for death of passenger</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Any liability imposed by Article 17 of Schedule I or Article 17 of Schedule VI on a carrier in respect of the death of a passenger shall be in substitution for any liability of the carrier in respect of the death of that passenger under any law in force in Canada, and the provisions set out in Schedule II shall have effect with respect to the persons by whom and for whose benefit the liability so imposed is enforceable and with respect to the manner in which it may be enforced.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78941" lims:id="78941"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78942" lims:id="78942">Damages in francs to be converted into dollars</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Any sum in francs mentioned in Article 22 of Schedule I shall, for the purposes of any action against a carrier, be converted into Canadian dollars at the rate of exchange prevailing on the date on which the amount of any damage to be paid by the carrier is ascertained by a court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78943" lims:id="78943"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78944" lims:id="78944">Conversion of francs or SDRs into dollars</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (6), the Canadian dollar equivalents of francs or Special Drawing Rights, as defined in Article 22 of the Convention set out in Schedule I, are determined by</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78945" lims:id="78945"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>converting francs into Special Drawing Rights at the rate of one Special Drawing Right for 15.075 francs; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78946" lims:id="78946"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>converting Special Drawing Rights into Canadian dollars at the rate established by the International Monetary Fund.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78948" lims:id="78948">R.S., 1985, c. C-26, s. 2; 1999, c. 21, s. 2; 2001, c. 31, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78949" lims:id="78949"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78950" lims:id="78950">Jurisdiction of Canadian courts</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78951" lims:id="78951"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every party to the Convention set out in Schedule I that has not availed itself of the provisions of the Additional Protocol set out in that Schedule is, for the purposes of any action brought in a court in Canada in accordance with the provisions of Article 28 of that Schedule to enforce a claim in respect of carriage undertaken by it, deemed to have explicitly submitted to the jurisdiction of that court under paragraph 4(2)(a) of the 
<XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-18">State Immunity Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78952" lims:id="78952"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78953" lims:id="78953">Jurisdiction of Canadian courts</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except to the extent of a declaration made by a party under the Convention set out in Schedule VI, every party to that Convention is, for the purposes of any action brought in a court in Canada in accordance with the provisions of Article 33 of that Schedule to enforce a claim in respect of carriage undertaken by it, deemed to have explicitly submitted to the jurisdiction of that court under paragraph 4(2)(a) of the 
<XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-18">State Immunity Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78955" lims:id="78955">R.S., 1985, c. C-26, s. 3; 1999, c. 21, s. 3; 2001, c. 31, s. 3</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78956" lims:id="78956"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78957" lims:id="78957">Orders and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make orders or regulations applying the provisions of Schedule I, V or VI and any provision of section 2 to any carriage by air, not being international carriage as defined in Schedule I, that may be specified in the order or regulations, subject to any exceptions, adaptations and modifications so specified.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="78959" lims:id="78959">R.S., 1985, c. C-26, s. 4; 1999, c. 21, s. 3; 2001, c. 31, s. 4</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78960" lims:id="78960"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78961" lims:id="78961">References to Schedule I</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>In this Act, except subsections 1.1(2) and 2(1) to (4), a reference to Schedule I or to any of its provisions shall be read as if for the provisions of the Convention set out in Schedule I there were substituted the provisions of the Convention</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78962" lims:id="78962"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>as amended by the Protocol set out in Schedule III or by the Protocols set out in Schedules III and IV in relation to any carriage by air to which the Convention as amended by that Protocol or those Protocols applies; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78963" lims:id="78963"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>as amended by the Protocols set out in Schedules III and IV in relation to any carriage by air, not being international carriage as defined in Schedule I, to which that Schedule or any provision of section 2 applies.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78965" lims:id="78965">R.S., 1985, c. C-26, s. 5; 1999, c. 21, s. 3</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78966" lims:id="78966"><Label>6</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 1999, c. 21, s. 3]</Repealed></Text></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78967" lims:id="78967" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78968" lims:id="78968"><Label>SCHEDULE I</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 and Sch. II)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78969" lims:id="78969"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78970" lims:id="78970" first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="no"><Text>Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air. Signed at Warsaw, October 12, 1929</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78971" lims:id="78971" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The President of the German Reich, the Federal President of the Republic of Austria, His Majesty the King of the Belgians, the President of the United States of Brazil, His Majesty the King of the Bulgarians, the President of the National Government of the Republic of China, His Majesty the King of Denmark and Iceland, His Majesty the King of Egypt, His Majesty the King of Spain, the Chief of State of the Republic of Estonia, the President of the Republic of Finland, the President of the French Republic, His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, the President of the Hellenic Republic, His Most Serene Highness the Regent of the Kingdom of Hungary, His Majesty the King of Italy, His Majesty the Emperor of Japan, the President of the Republic of Latvia, Her Royal Highness the Grand Duchess of Luxemburg, the President of the United States of Mexico, His Majesty the King of Norway, Her Majesty the Queen of the Netherlands, the President of the Republic of Poland, His Majesty the King of Roumania, His Majesty the King of Sweden, the Swiss Federal Council, the President of the Czechoslovak Republic, the Central Executive Committee of the Union of the Soviet Socialist Republics, the President of the United States of Venezuela, His Majesty the King of Yugoslavia;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78972" lims:id="78972" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Having recognized the advantage of regulating in a uniform manner the conditions of international carriage by air in respect of the documents to be used for such carriage and of the liability of the carrier, have nominated to this end their respective Plenipotentiaries, who, being thereto duly authorized, have concluded and signed the following convention: —</Text></Provision><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78973" lims:id="78973"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78974" lims:id="78974" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER I</Label><TitleText>Scope — Definitions</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78975" lims:id="78975"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78976" lims:id="78976" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 1</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78977" lims:id="78977" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Convention applies to all international carriage of persons, baggage or cargo performed by aircraft for reward. It applies equally to gratuitous carriage by aircraft performed by an air transport undertaking.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78978" lims:id="78978" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">For the purposes of this Convention the expression “international carriage” means any carriage in which, according to the agreement between the parties, the place of departure and the place of destination, whether or not there be a break in the carriage or a transhipment, are situated either within the territories of two High Contracting Parties, or within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, if there is an agreed stopping place within a territory subject to the sovereignty, suzerainty, mandate or authority of another Power, even though that Power is not a party to this Convention. A carriage without such an agreed stopping place between territories subject to the sovereignty, suzerainty, mandate or authority of the same High Contracting Party is not deemed to be international for the purposes of this Convention</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78979" lims:id="78979" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">A carriage to be performed by several successive air carriers is deemed, for the purposes of this Convention, to be one undivided carriage, if it has been regarded by the parties as a single operation, whether it had been agreed upon under the form of a single contract or of a series of contracts, and it does not lose its international character merely because one contract or a series of contracts is to be performed entirely within a territory subject to the sovereignty, suzerainty, mandate or authority of the same High Contracting Party</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78980" lims:id="78980" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[Note: The paragraphs of the Convention shown in italics were deleted and replaced (except in the case of paragraph (2) of Article 20) by the Protocol set out in Schedule III, <Emphasis style="italic">infra</Emphasis>.]</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78981" lims:id="78981"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78982" lims:id="78982" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 2</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78983" lims:id="78983" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Convention applies to carriage performed by the State or by legally constituted public bodies provided it falls within the conditions laid down in Article 1.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78984" lims:id="78984" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">This Convention does not apply to carriage performed under the terms of any international postal Convention</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78985" lims:id="78985"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78986" lims:id="78986" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER II</Label><TitleText>Documents of Carriage</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78987" lims:id="78987"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78988" lims:id="78988" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText>Section 1. — Passenger Ticket</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78989" lims:id="78989"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78990" lims:id="78990" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 3</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78991" lims:id="78991" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">For the carriage of passengers the carrier must deliver a passenger ticket which shall contain the following particulars</Emphasis>:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78992" lims:id="78992" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the place and date of issue</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78993" lims:id="78993" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the place of departure and of destination</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78994" lims:id="78994" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the agreed stopping places, provided that the carrier may reserve the right to alter the stopping places in case of necessity, and that if he exercises that right, the alteration shall not have the effect of depriving the carriage of its international character</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78995" lims:id="78995" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the name and address of the carrier or carriers</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78996" lims:id="78996" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">a statement that the carriage is subject to the rules relating to liability established by this Convention</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78997" lims:id="78997" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The absence, irregularity or loss of the passenger ticket does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage, which shall none the less be subject to the rules of this Convention. Nevertheless, if the carrier accepts a passenger without a passenger ticket having been delivered he shall not be entitled to avail himself of those provisions of this Convention which exclude or limit his liability</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78998" lims:id="78998"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="78999" lims:id="78999" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText>Section 2. — Baggage Check</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79000" lims:id="79000"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79001" lims:id="79001" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 4</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79002" lims:id="79002" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">For the carriage of baggage, other than small personal objects of which the passenger takes charge himself, the carrier must deliver a baggage check</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79003" lims:id="79003" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The baggage check shall be made out in duplicate, one part for the passenger and the other part for the carrier</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79004" lims:id="79004" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The baggage check shall contain the following particulars</Emphasis>:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79005" lims:id="79005" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the place and date of issue</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79006" lims:id="79006" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the place of departure and of destination</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79007" lims:id="79007" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the name and address of the carrier or carriers</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79008" lims:id="79008" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the number of the passenger ticket</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79009" lims:id="79009" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">a statement that delivery of the baggage will be made to the bearer of the baggage check</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79010" lims:id="79010" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the number and weight of the packages</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79011" lims:id="79011" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the amount of the value declared in accordance with Article 22(2)</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79012" lims:id="79012" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(h)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">a statement that the carriage is subject to the rules relating to liability established by this Convention</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79013" lims:id="79013" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The absence, irregularity or loss of the baggage check does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage, which shall none the less be subject to the rules of this Convention. Nevertheless, if the carrier accepts baggage without a baggage check having been delivered, or if the baggage check does not contain the particulars set out at (3)(d), (f) and (h), the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of those provisions of the Convention which exclude or limit his liability</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79014" lims:id="79014"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79015" lims:id="79015" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText>Section 3. — Air Waybill</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79016" lims:id="79016"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79017" lims:id="79017" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 5</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79018" lims:id="79018" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every carrier of cargo has the right to require the consignor to make out and hand over to him a document called an “air waybill”; every consignor has the right to require the carrier to accept this document.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79019" lims:id="79019" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The absence, irregularity or loss of this document does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage which shall, subject to the provisions of Article 9, be none the less governed by the rules of this Convention.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79020" lims:id="79020"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79021" lims:id="79021" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 6</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79022" lims:id="79022" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The air waybill shall be made out by the consignor in three original parts and be handed over with the cargo.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79023" lims:id="79023" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The first part shall be marked “for the carrier”, and shall be signed by the consignor. The second part shall be marked “for the consignee”; it shall be signed by the consignor and by the carrier and shall accompany the cargo. The third part shall be signed by the carrier and handed by him to the consignor after the cargo has been accepted.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79024" lims:id="79024" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The carrier shall sign on acceptance of the cargo</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79025" lims:id="79025" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The signature of the carrier may be stamped; that of the consignor may be printed or stamped.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79026" lims:id="79026" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If, at the request of the consignor, the carrier makes out the air waybill, he shall be deemed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have done so on behalf of the consignor.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79027" lims:id="79027"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79028" lims:id="79028" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 7</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79029" lims:id="79029" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The carrier of cargo has the right to require the consignor to make out separate air waybills when there is more than one package.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79030" lims:id="79030"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79031" lims:id="79031" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 8</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79032" lims:id="79032" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The air waybill shall contain the following particulars</Emphasis>:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79033" lims:id="79033" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the place and date of its execution</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79034" lims:id="79034" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the place of departure and of destination</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79035" lims:id="79035" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the agreed stopping places, provided that the carrier may reserve the right to alter the stopping places in case of necessity, and that if he exercises that right the alteration shall not have the effect of depriving the carriage of its international character</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79036" lims:id="79036" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the name and address of the consignor</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79037" lims:id="79037" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the name and address of the first carrier</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79038" lims:id="79038" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the name and address of the consignee, if the case so requires</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79039" lims:id="79039" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(g)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the nature of the cargo</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79040" lims:id="79040" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(h)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the number of the packages, the method of packing and the particular marks or numbers upon them</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79041" lims:id="79041" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(i)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the weight, the quantity and the volume or dimensions of the cargo</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79042" lims:id="79042" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(j)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the apparent condition of the cargo and of the packing</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79043" lims:id="79043" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(k)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the freight, if it has been agreed upon, the date and place of payment, and the person who is to pay it</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79044" lims:id="79044" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(l)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">if the cargo is sent for payment on delivery, the price of the cargo, and, if the case so requires, the amount of the expenses incurred</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79045" lims:id="79045" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(m)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the amount of the value declared in accordance with Article 22(2)</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79046" lims:id="79046" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(n)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the number of parts of the air waybill</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79047" lims:id="79047" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(o)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the documents handed to the carrier to accompany the air waybill</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79048" lims:id="79048" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(p)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">the time fixed for the completion of the carriage and a brief note of the route to be followed, if these matters have been agreed upon</Emphasis>;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79049" lims:id="79049" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(q)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">a statement that the carriage is subject to the rules relating to liability established by this Convention</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79050" lims:id="79050"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79051" lims:id="79051" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 9</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79052" lims:id="79052" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">If the carrier accepts cargo without an air waybill having been made out, or if the air waybill does not contain all the particulars set out in Article 8(a) to (i) inclusive and (q), the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of this Convention which exclude or limit his liability.</Emphasis></Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79053" lims:id="79053"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79054" lims:id="79054" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 10</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79055" lims:id="79055" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The consignor is responsible for the correctness of the particulars and statements relating to the cargo which he inserts in the air waybill.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79056" lims:id="79056" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The consignor will be liable for all damage suffered by the carrier or any other person by reason of the irregularity, incorrectness or incompleteness of the said particulars and statements</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79057" lims:id="79057"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79058" lims:id="79058" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 11</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79059" lims:id="79059" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The air waybill is <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> evidence of the conclusion of the contract, of the receipt of the cargo and of the conditions of carriage.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79060" lims:id="79060" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The statements in the air waybill relating to the weight, dimensions and packing of the cargo, as well as those relating to the number of packages, are <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> evidence of the facts stated; those relating to the quantity, volume and condition of the cargo do not constitute evidence against the carrier except so far as they both have been, and are stated in the air waybill to have been, checked by him in the presence of the consignor, or relate to the apparent condition of the cargo.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79061" lims:id="79061"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79062" lims:id="79062" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 12</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79063" lims:id="79063" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to his liability to carry out all his obligations under the contract of carriage, the consignor has the right to dispose of the cargo by withdrawing it at the aerodrome of departure or destination, or by stopping it in the course of the journey on any landing, or by calling for it to be delivered at the place of destination or in the course of the journey to a person other than the consignee named in the air waybill, or by requiring it to be returned to the aerodrome of departure. He must not exercise this right of disposition in such a way as to prejudice the carrier or other consignors and he must repay any expenses occasioned by the exercise of this right.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79064" lims:id="79064" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If it is impossible to carry out the orders of the consignor the carrier must so inform him forthwith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79065" lims:id="79065" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the carrier obeys the orders of the consignor for the disposition of the cargo without requiring the production of the part of the air waybill delivered to the latter, he will be liable, without prejudice to his right of recovery from the consignor, for any damage which may be caused thereby to any person who is lawfully in possession of that part of the air waybill.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79066" lims:id="79066" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The right conferred on the consignor ceases at the moment when that of the consignee begins in accordance with Article 13. Nevertheless, if the consignee declines to accept the waybill or the cargo, or if he cannot be communicated with, the consignor resumes his right of disposition.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79067" lims:id="79067"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79068" lims:id="79068" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 13</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79069" lims:id="79069" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except in the circumstances set out in the preceding Article, the consignee is entitled, on arrival of the cargo at the place of destination, to require the carrier to hand over to him the air waybill and to deliver the cargo to him, on payment of the charges due and on complying with the conditions of carriage set out in the air waybill.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79070" lims:id="79070" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless it is otherwise agreed, it is the duty of the carrier to give notice to the consignee as soon as the cargo arrives.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79071" lims:id="79071" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the carrier admits the loss of the cargo, or if the cargo has not arrived at the expiration of seven days after the date on which it ought to have arrived, the consignee is entitled to put into force against the carrier the rights which flow from the contract of carriage.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79072" lims:id="79072"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79073" lims:id="79073" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 14</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79074" lims:id="79074" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The consignor and the consignee can respectively enforce all the rights given them by Articles 12 and 13, each in his own name, whether he is acting in his own interest or in the interest of another, provided that he carries out the obligations imposed by the contract.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79075" lims:id="79075"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79076" lims:id="79076" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 15</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79077" lims:id="79077" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Articles 12, 13 and 14 do not affect either the relations of the consignor or the consignee with each other or the mutual relations of third parties whose rights are derived either from the consignor or from the consignee.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79078" lims:id="79078" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The provisions of Articles 12, 13 and 14 can only be varied by express provision in the air waybill.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79079" lims:id="79079" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[Note: A new paragraph numbered as paragraph (3) was added by Article IX of the Protocol set out in Schedule III, <Emphasis style="italic">infra</Emphasis>.]</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79080" lims:id="79080"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79081" lims:id="79081" format-ref="group3-subdivision"><Label>Article 16</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79082" lims:id="79082" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The consignor must furnish such information and attach to the air waybill such documents as are necessary to meet the formalities of customs, octroi or police before the cargo can be delivered to the consignee. The consignor is liable to the carrier for any damage occasioned by the absence, insufficiency or irregularity of any such information or documents, unless the damage is due to the fault of the carrier or his agents.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79083" lims:id="79083" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The carrier is under no obligation to enquire into the correctness or sufficiency of such information or documents.</Text></Provision></Group></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79084" lims:id="79084"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79085" lims:id="79085" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER III</Label><TitleText>Liability of the Carrier</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79086" lims:id="79086"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79087" lims:id="79087" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 17</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79088" lims:id="79088" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the death or wounding of a passenger or any other bodily injury suffered by a passenger, if the accident which caused the damage so sustained took place on board the aircraft or in the course of any of the operations of embarking or disembarking.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79089" lims:id="79089"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79090" lims:id="79090" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 18</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79091" lims:id="79091" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the destruction or loss of, or of damage to, any registered baggage or any cargo, if the occurrence which caused the damage so sustained took place during the carriage by air.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79092" lims:id="79092" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The carriage by air within the meaning of the preceding paragraph comprises the period during which the baggage or cargo is in charge of the carrier, whether in an aerodrome or on board an aircraft, or, in the case of a landing outside an aerodrome, in any place whatsoever.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79093" lims:id="79093" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The period of the carriage by air does not extend to any carriage by land, by sea or by river performed outside an aerodrome. If, however, such a carriage takes place in the performance of a contract for carriage by air, for the purpose of loading, delivery or transhipment, any damage is presumed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have been the result of an event which took place during the carriage by air.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79094" lims:id="79094"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79095" lims:id="79095" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 19</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79096" lims:id="79096" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The carrier is liable for damage occasioned by delay in the carriage by air of passengers, baggage or cargo.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79097" lims:id="79097"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79098" lims:id="79098" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 20</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79099" lims:id="79099" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The carrier is not liable if he proves that he and his agents have taken all necessary measures to avoid the damage or that it was impossible for him or them to take such measures.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79100" lims:id="79100" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">In the carriage of cargo and baggage the carrier is not liable if he proves that the damage was occasioned by negligent pilotage or negligence in the handling of the aircraft or in navigation and that, in all other respects, he and his agents have taken all necessary measures to avoid the damage.</Emphasis></Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79101" lims:id="79101"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79102" lims:id="79102" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 21</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79103" lims:id="79103" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>If the carrier proves that the damage was caused by or contributed to by the negligence of the injured person the Court may, in accordance with the provisions of its own law, exonerate the carrier wholly or partly from his liability.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79104" lims:id="79104"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79105" lims:id="79105" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 22</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79106" lims:id="79106" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">In the carriage of passengers the liability of the carrier for each passenger is limited to the sum of 125,000 francs. Where, in accordance with the law of the Court seized of the case, damages may be awarded in the form of periodical payments, the equivalent capital value of the said payments shall not exceed 125,000 francs. Nevertheless, by special contract, the carrier and the passenger may agree to a higher limit of liability</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79107" lims:id="79107" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">In the carriage of registered baggage and of cargo, the liability of the carrier is limited to a sum of 250 francs per kilogram, unless the consignor has made, at the time when the package was handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of the value at delivery and has paid a supplementary sum if the case so requires. In that case the carrier will be liable to pay a sum not exceeding the declared sum, unless he proves that that sum is greater than the actual value to the consignor at delivery</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79108" lims:id="79108" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">As regards objects of which the passenger takes charge himself the liability of the carrier is limited to 5,000 francs per passenger</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79109" lims:id="79109" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The sums mentioned above shall be deemed to refer to the French franc consisting of 65The sums mentioned above shall be deemed to refer to the French franc consisting of 65
½
milligrams gold of millesimal fineness 900. These sums may be converted into any national currency in round figuresThe sums mentioned above shall be deemed to refer to the French franc consisting of 65
½
  milligrams gold of millesimal fineness 900. These sums may be converted into any national currency in round figures</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79110" lims:id="79110"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79111" lims:id="79111" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 23</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79112" lims:id="79112" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any provision tending to relieve the carrier of liability or to fix a lower limit than that which is laid down in this Convention shall be null and void, but the nullity of any such provision does not involve the nullity of the whole contract, which shall remain subject to the provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79113" lims:id="79113" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[Note: This provision was renumbered as paragraph (1) and another provision added as paragraph (2) by Article XII of the Protocol set out in Schedule III, <Emphasis style="italic">infra</Emphasis>.]</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79114" lims:id="79114"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79115" lims:id="79115" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 24</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79116" lims:id="79116" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the cases covered by Articles 18 and 19 any action for damages, however founded, can only be brought subject to the conditions and limits set out in this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79117" lims:id="79117" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the cases covered by Article 17 the provisions of the preceding paragraph also apply, without prejudice to the questions as to who are persons who have the right to bring suit and what are their respective rights.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79118" lims:id="79118"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79119" lims:id="79119" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 25</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79120" lims:id="79120" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">The carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of this Convention which exclude or limit his liability, if the damage is caused by his wilful misconduct or by such default on his part as, in accordance with the law of the Court seized of the case, is considered to be equivalent to wilful misconduct</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79121" lims:id="79121" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">Similarly the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the said provisions, if the damage is caused as aforesaid by any agent of the carrier acting within the scope of his employment</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79122" lims:id="79122" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[Note: A new article numbered as Article 25A was added by Article XIV of the Protocol set out in Schedule III, <Emphasis style="italic">infra</Emphasis>.]</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79123" lims:id="79123"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79124" lims:id="79124" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 26</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79125" lims:id="79125" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Receipt by the person entitled to delivery of baggage or cargo without complaint is <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> evidence that the same has been delivered in good condition and in accordance with the document of carriage.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79126" lims:id="79126" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Emphasis style="italic">In the case of damage, the person entitled to delivery must complain to the carrier forthwith after the discovery of the damage, and, at the latest, within three days from the date of receipt in the case of baggage and seven days from the date of receipt in the case of cargo. In the case of delay the complaint must be made at the latest within fourteen days from the date on which the baggage or cargo has been placed at his disposal</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79127" lims:id="79127" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every complaint must be made in writing upon the document of carriage or by separate notice in writing despatched within the times aforesaid.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79128" lims:id="79128" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Failing complaint within the times aforesaid, no action shall lie against the carrier, save in the case of fraud on his part.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79129" lims:id="79129"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79130" lims:id="79130" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 27</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79131" lims:id="79131" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In the case of the death of the person liable, an action for damages lies in accordance with the terms of this Convention against those legally representing his estate.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79132" lims:id="79132"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79133" lims:id="79133" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 28</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79134" lims:id="79134" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An action for damages must be brought, at the option of the plaintiff, in the territory of one of the High Contracting Parties, either before the Court having jurisdiction where the carrier is ordinarily resident, or has his principal place of business, or has an establishment by which the contract has been made or before the Court having jurisdiction at the place of destination.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79135" lims:id="79135" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Questions of procedure shall be governed by the law of the Court seized of the case.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79136" lims:id="79136"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79137" lims:id="79137" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 29</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79138" lims:id="79138" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The right to damages shall be extinguished if an action is not brought within two years, reckoned from the date of arrival at the destination, or from the date on which the aircraft ought to have arrived, or from the date on which the carriage stopped.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79139" lims:id="79139" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The method of calculating the period of limitation shall be determined by the law of the Court seized of the case.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79140" lims:id="79140"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79141" lims:id="79141" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 30</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79142" lims:id="79142" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the case of carriage to be performed by various successive carriers and falling within the definition set out in the third paragraph of Article 1, each carrier who accepts passengers, baggage or cargo is subjected to the rules set out in this Convention, and is deemed to be one of the contracting parties to the contract of carriage in so far as the contract deals with that part of the carriage which is performed under his supervision.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79143" lims:id="79143" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the case of carriage of this nature, the passenger or his representative can take action only against the carrier who performed the carriage during which the accident or the delay occurred, save in the case where, by express agreement, the first carrier has assumed liability for the whole journey.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79144" lims:id="79144" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As regards baggage or cargo, the passenger or consignor will have a right of action against the first carrier, and the passenger or consignee who is entitled to delivery will have a right of action against the last carrier, and further, each may take action against the carrier who performed the carriage during which the destruction, loss, damage or delay took place. These carriers will be jointly and severally liable to the passenger or to the consignor or consignee.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79145" lims:id="79145"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79146" lims:id="79146" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER IV</Label><TitleText>Provisions Relating to Combined Carriage</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79147" lims:id="79147"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79148" lims:id="79148" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 31</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79149" lims:id="79149" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the case of combined carriage performed partly by air and partly by any other mode of carriage, the provisions of this Convention apply only to the carriage by air, provided that the carriage by air falls within the terms of Article 1.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79150" lims:id="79150" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Convention shall prevent the parties in the case of combined carriage from inserting in the document of air carriage conditions relating to other modes of carriage, provided that the provisions of this Convention are observed as regards the carriage by air.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79151" lims:id="79151"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79152" lims:id="79152" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER V</Label><TitleText>General and Final Provisions</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79153" lims:id="79153"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79154" lims:id="79154" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 32</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79155" lims:id="79155" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any clause contained in the contract and all special agreements entered into before the damage occurred by which the parties purport to infringe the rules laid down by this Convention, whether by deciding the law to be applied, or by altering the rules as to jurisdiction, shall be null and void. Nevertheless for the carriage of cargo arbitration clauses are allowed, subject to this Convention, if the arbitration is to take place within one of the jurisdictions referred to in the first paragraph of Article 28.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79156" lims:id="79156"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79157" lims:id="79157" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 33</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79158" lims:id="79158" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Nothing contained in this Convention shall prevent the carrier either from refusing to enter into any contract of carriage, or from making regulations which do not conflict with the provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79159" lims:id="79159"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79160" lims:id="79160" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 34</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79161" lims:id="79161" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="italic">This Convention does not apply to international carriage by air performed by way of experimental trial by air navigation undertakings with the view to the establishment of a regular line of air navigation, nor does it apply to carriage performed in extraordinary circumstances outside the normal scope of an air carrier’s business</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79162" lims:id="79162"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79163" lims:id="79163" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 35</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79164" lims:id="79164" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The expression “days” when used in this Convention means current days not working days.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79165" lims:id="79165"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79166" lims:id="79166" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 36</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79167" lims:id="79167" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Convention is drawn up in French in a single copy which shall remain deposited in the archives of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs of Poland and of which one duly certified copy shall be sent by the Polish Government to the Government of each of the High Contracting Parties.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79168" lims:id="79168"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79169" lims:id="79169" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 37</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79170" lims:id="79170" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Convention shall be ratified. The instruments of ratification shall be deposited in the archives of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs of Poland, which will notify the deposit to the Government of each of the High Contracting Parties.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79171" lims:id="79171" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As soon as this Convention shall have been ratified by five of the High Contracting Parties it shall come into force as between them on the ninetieth day after the deposit of the fifth ratification. Thereafter it shall come into force between the High Contracting Parties who shall have ratified and the High Contracting Party who deposits his instrument of ratification on the ninetieth day after the deposit.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79172" lims:id="79172" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>It shall be the duty of the Government of the Republic of Poland to notify to the Government of each of the High Contracting Parties the date on which this Convention comes into force as well as the date of the deposit of each ratification.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79173" lims:id="79173"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79174" lims:id="79174" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 38</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79175" lims:id="79175" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Convention shall, after it has come into force, remain open for accession by any State.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79176" lims:id="79176" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The accession shall be effected by a notification addressed to the Government of the Republic of Poland, which will inform the Government of each of the High Contracting Parties thereof.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79177" lims:id="79177" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The accession shall take effect as from the ninetieth day after the notification made to the Government of the Republic of Poland.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79178" lims:id="79178"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79179" lims:id="79179" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 39</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79180" lims:id="79180" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any one of the High Contracting Parties may denounce this Convention by a notification addressed to the Government of the Republic of Poland, which will at once inform the Government of each of the High Contracting Parties.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79181" lims:id="79181" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Denunciation shall take effect six months after the notification of denunciation, and shall operate only as regards the party who shall have proceeded to denunciation.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79182" lims:id="79182"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79183" lims:id="79183" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 40</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79184" lims:id="79184" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any High Contracting Party may, at the time of signature or of deposit of ratification or of accession declare that the acceptance which he gives to this Convention does not apply to all or any of his colonies, protectorates, territories under mandate, or any other territory subject to his sovereignty or his authority, or any territory under his suzerainty.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79185" lims:id="79185" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Accordingly any High Contracting Party may subsequently accede separately in the name of all or any of his colonies, protectorates, territories under mandate or any other territory subject to his sovereignty or to his authority or any territory under his suzerainty which has been thus excluded by his original declaration.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79186" lims:id="79186" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any High Contracting Party may denounce this Convention, in accordance with its provisions, separately or for all or any of his colonies, protectorates, territories under mandate or any other territory subject to his sovereignty or to his authority, or any other territory under his suzerainty.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79187" lims:id="79187" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[Note: A new article numbered as Article 40A was added by Article XVII of the Protocol set out in Schedule III, <Emphasis style="italic">infra</Emphasis>.]</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79188" lims:id="79188"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79189" lims:id="79189" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article 41</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79190" lims:id="79190" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any High Contracting Party shall be entitled not earlier than two years after the coming into force of this Convention to call for the assembling of a new international Conference in order to consider any improvements which may be made in this Convention. To this end he will communicate with the Government of the French Republic which will take the necessary measures to make preparations for such Conference.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79191" lims:id="79191" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This Convention done at Warsaw on the 12th October, 1929, shall remain open for signature until the 31st January, 1930.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79192" lims:id="79192" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[Here follow the signatures on behalf of the Governments of Germany, Austria, Belgium, Brazil, Denmark, Spain, France, Great Britain and Northern Ireland, the Commonwealth of Australia, the Union of South Africa, Greece, Italy, Japan, Latvia, Luxembourg, Norway, the Netherlands, Poland, Roumania, Switzerland, Czechoslovakia, the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, and Yugoslavia.]</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79193" lims:id="79193"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79194" lims:id="79194" format-ref="group1-part"><TitleText>Additional Protocol</TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79195" lims:id="79195" format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">With reference to Article 2</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79196" lims:id="79196" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The High Contracting Parties reserve to themselves the right to declare at the time of ratification or of accession that the first paragraph of Article 2 of this Convention shall not apply to international carriage by air performed directly by the State, its colonies, protectorates or mandated territories or by any other territory under its sovereignty, suzerainty or authority.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79197" lims:id="79197" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[This Additional Protocol was signed on behalf of the same countries as those above mentioned.]</Text></Provision></Group></DocumentInternal><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79199" lims:id="79199">R.S., c. C-14, Sch. I</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79200" lims:id="79200" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79201" lims:id="79201"><Label>SCHEDULE II</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Provisions as to Liability of Carrier in the Event of the Death of a Passenger</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79202" lims:id="79202"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79203" lims:id="79203" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The liability shall be enforceable for the benefit of such of the members of the passenger’s family as sustained damage by reason of the death of the passenger.</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79204" lims:id="79204" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In this paragraph, “member of the passenger’s family” means the passenger’s spouse or a person who was cohabiting with the passenger in a conjugal relationship for a period of at least one year immediately before the death of the passenger, a parent, step-parent, grandparent, brother, sister, child, adopted child, stepchild, grandchild, or any person for whom the passenger stood in the place of a parent.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79205" lims:id="79205" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>An action to enforce the liability may be brought by</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79206" lims:id="79206" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any person who, under the law in force in the province in which action is brought, is entitled to act or is recognized as the personal representative of the passenger;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79207" lims:id="79207" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any person for whose benefit the liability is, under paragraph 1, enforceable; or</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79208" lims:id="79208" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any person who, under the law in force in the province in which action is brought, is entitled to act or is recognized as the representative for any one or more of the persons for whose benefit the liability is, under paragraph 1, enforceable.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79209" lims:id="79209" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The Court before which any action referred to in paragraph 2 is brought may, at any stage of the proceedings, make any orders that appear to the Court to be just and equitable in view of the provisions of Schedule I limiting the liability of a carrier and in view of any proceedings that may have been or are likely to be commenced in another province or outside Canada in respect of the death of the passenger in question and, without restricting the generality of the foregoing, the Court may</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79210" lims:id="79210" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide for representation of all interested persons;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79211" lims:id="79211" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>stay proceedings, with a view to avoiding multiplicity of actions, whether within the province or elsewhere, in respect of the death of the passenger in question; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79212" lims:id="79212" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>divide the amount recovered, after deducting any costs not recovered from the defendant, between the persons entitled, in such proportion as the Court or, where the action is tried by a jury, the jury may direct.</Text></Provision></Provision></DocumentInternal><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79214" lims:id="79214">R.S., 1985, c. C-26, Sch. II; 2000, c. 12, s. 73</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79215" lims:id="79215" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79216" lims:id="79216"><Label>SCHEDULE III</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 6)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79217" lims:id="79217"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79218" lims:id="79218" first-line-indent="0" language-align="yes" subsequent-line-indent="2" list-item="no"><Text>Protocol to Amend the Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air Signed at Warsaw on 12 October 1929</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79219" lims:id="79219" format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>THE HAGUE</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79220" lims:id="79220" format-ref="centered" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>28 September 1955</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79221" lims:id="79221" format-ref="indent-0-1" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Governments Undersigned</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79222" lims:id="79222" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Considering that it is desirable to amend the Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air signed at Warsaw on 12 October 1929,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79223" lims:id="79223" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Have Agreed as follows:</Text></Provision><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79224" lims:id="79224"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79225" lims:id="79225" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER I</Label><TitleText>Amendments to the Convention</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79226" lims:id="79226"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79227" lims:id="79227" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article I</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79228" lims:id="79228" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 1 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79229" lims:id="79229" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph (2) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Convention, the expression <Emphasis style="italic">international carriage</Emphasis> means any carriage in which, according to the agreement between the parties, the place of departure and the place of destination, whether or not there be a break in the carriage or a transhipment, are situated either within the territories of two High Contracting Parties or within the territory of a single High Contracting Party if there is an agreed stopping place within the territory of another State, even if that State is not a High Contracting Party. Carriage between two points within the territory of a single High Contracting Party without an agreed stopping place within the territory of another State is not international carriage for the purposes of this Convention.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79230" lims:id="79230" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraph (3) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(3)</Label><Text>Carriage to be performed by several successive air carriers is deemed, for the purposes of this Convention, to be one undivided carriage if it has been regarded by the parties as a single operation, whether it had been agreed upon under the form of a single contract or of a series of contracts, and it does not lose its international character merely because one contract or a series of contracts is to be performed entirely within the territory of the same State.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79231" lims:id="79231"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79232" lims:id="79232" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article II</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79233" lims:id="79233" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 2 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79234" lims:id="79234" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraph (2) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>This Convention shall not apply to carriage of mail and postal packages.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79235" lims:id="79235"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79236" lims:id="79236" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article III</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79237" lims:id="79237" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 3 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79238" lims:id="79238" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph (1) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(1)</Label><Text>In respect of the carriage of passengers a ticket shall be delivered containing:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indication of the places of departure and destination;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a notice to the effect that, if the passenger’s journey involves an ultimate destination or stop in a country other than the country of departure, the Warsaw Convention may be applicable and that the Convention governs and in most cases limits the liability of carriers for death or personal injury and in respect of loss of or damage to baggage.”</Text></Provision></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79239" lims:id="79239" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraph (2) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>The passenger ticket shall constitute <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> evidence of the conclusion and conditions of the contract of carriage. The absence, irregularity or loss of the passenger ticket does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage which shall, none the less, be subject to the rules of this Convention. Nevertheless, if, with the consent of the carrier, the passenger embarks without a passenger ticket having been delivered, or if the ticket does not include the notice required by paragraph (1)(c) of this Article, the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of Article 22.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79240" lims:id="79240"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79241" lims:id="79241" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article IV</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79242" lims:id="79242" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 4 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79243" lims:id="79243" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraphs (1), (2) and (3) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(1)</Label><Text>In respect of the carriage of registered baggage, a baggage check shall be delivered, which, unless combined with or incorporated in a passenger ticket which complies with the provisions of Article 3, paragraph (1), shall contain:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indication of the places of departure and destination;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a notice to the effect that, if the carriage involves an ultimate destination or stop in a country other than the country of departure, the Warsaw Convention may be applicable and that the Convention governs and in most cases limits the liability of carriers in respect of loss of or damage to baggage.”</Text></Provision></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79244" lims:id="79244" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraph (4) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>The baggage check shall constitute <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> evidence of the registration of the baggage and of the conditions of the contract of carriage. The absence, irregularity or loss of the baggage check does not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage which shall, none the less, be subject to the rules of this Convention. Nevertheless, if the carrier takes charge of the baggage without a baggage check having been delivered or if the baggage check (unless combined with or incorporated in the passenger ticket which complies with the provisions of Article 3, paragraph (1)(c)) does not include the notice required by paragraph (1)(c) of this Article, he shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of Article 22, paragraph (2).”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79245" lims:id="79245"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79246" lims:id="79246" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article V</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79247" lims:id="79247" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 6 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79248" lims:id="79248" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraph (3) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(3)</Label><Text>The carrier shall sign prior to the loading of the cargo on board the aircraft.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79249" lims:id="79249"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79250" lims:id="79250" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article VI</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79251" lims:id="79251" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 8 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>“The air waybill shall contain:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indication of the places of departure and destination;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a notice to the consignor to the effect that, if the carriage involves an ultimate destination or stop in a country other than the country of departure, the Warsaw Convention may be applicable and that the Convention governs and in most cases limits the liability of carriers in respect of loss of or damage to cargo.”</Text></Provision></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79252" lims:id="79252"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79253" lims:id="79253" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article VII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79254" lims:id="79254" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 9 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Text>“If, with the consent of the carrier, cargo is loaded on board the aircraft without an air waybill having been made out, or if the air waybill does not include the notice required by Article 8, paragraph (c), the carrier shall not be entitled to avail himself of the provisions of Article 22, paragraph (2).”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79255" lims:id="79255"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79256" lims:id="79256" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article VIII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79257" lims:id="79257" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 10 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79258" lims:id="79258" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraph (2) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>The consignor shall indemnify the carrier against all damage suffered by him, or by any other person to whom the carrier is liable, by reason of the irregularity, incorrectness or incompleteness of the particulars and statements furnished by the consignor.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79259" lims:id="79259"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79260" lims:id="79260" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article IX</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79261" lims:id="79261" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>To Article 15 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79262" lims:id="79262" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the following paragraph shall be added:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(3)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Convention prevents the issue of a negotiable air waybill.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79263" lims:id="79263"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79264" lims:id="79264" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article X</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79265" lims:id="79265" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Paragraph (2) of Article 20 of the Convention shall be deleted.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79266" lims:id="79266"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79267" lims:id="79267" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XI</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79268" lims:id="79268" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 22 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>“<Emphasis style="italic">Article 22</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the carriage of persons the liability of the carrier for each passenger is limited to the sum of two hundred and fifty thousand francs. Where, in accordance with the law of the court seised of the case, damages may be awarded in the form of periodical payments, the equivalent capital value of the said payments shall not exceed two hundred and fifty thousand francs. Nevertheless, by special contract, the carrier and the passenger may agree to a higher limit of liability.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(2) (a)</Label><Text>In the carriage of registered baggage and of cargo, the liability of the carrier is limited to a sum of two hundred and fifty francs per kilogramme, unless the passenger or consignor has made, at the time when the package was handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of interest in delivery at destination and has paid a supplementary sum if the case so requires. In that case the carrier will be liable to pay a sum not exceeding the declared sum, unless he proves that that sum is greater than the passenger’s or consignor’s actual interest in delivery at destination.</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>In the case of loss, damage or delay of part of registered baggage or cargo, or of any object contained therein, the weight to be taken into consideration in determining the amount to which the carrier’s liability is limited shall be only the total weight of the package or packages concerned. Nevertheless, when the loss, damage or delay of a part of the registered baggage or cargo, or of an object contained therein, affects the value of other packages covered by the same baggage check or the same air waybill, the total weight of such package or packages shall also be taken into consideration in determining the limit of liability.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As regards objects of which the passenger takes charge himself the liability of the carrier is limited to five thousand francs per passenger.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The limits prescribed in this article shall not prevent the court from awarding, in accordance with its own law, in addition, the whole or part of the court costs and of the other expenses of the litigation incurred by the plaintiff. The foregoing provision shall not apply if the amount of the damages awarded, excluding court costs and other expenses of the litigation, does not exceed the sum which the carrier has offered in writing to the plaintiff within a period of six months from the date of the occurrence causing the damage, or before the commencement of the action, if that is later.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The sums mentioned in francs in this Article shall be deemed to refer to a currency unit consisting of sixty-five and a half milligrammes of gold of millesimal fineness nine hundred. These sums may be converted into national currencies in round figures. Conversion of the sums into national currencies other than gold shall, in case of judicial proceedings, be made according to the gold value of such currencies at the date of the judgment.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79269" lims:id="79269"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79270" lims:id="79270" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79271" lims:id="79271" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 23 of the Convention, the existing provision shall be renumbered as paragraph 1 and another paragraph shall be added as follows:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (1) of this Article shall not apply to provisions governing loss or damage resulting from the inherent defect, quality or vice of the cargo carried.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79272" lims:id="79272"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79273" lims:id="79273" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XIII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79274" lims:id="79274" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 25 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79275" lims:id="79275" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraphs (1) and (2) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Text>“The limits of liability specified in Article 22 shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the carrier, his servants or agents, done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result; provided that, in the case of such act or omission of a servant or agent, it is also proved that he was acting within the scope of his employment.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79276" lims:id="79276"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79277" lims:id="79277" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XIV</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79278" lims:id="79278" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>After Article 25 of the Convention, the following article shall be inserted:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>“<Emphasis style="italic">Article 25 A</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an action is brought against a servant or agent of the carrier arising out of damage to which this Convention relates, such servant or agent, if he proves that he acted within the scope of his employment, shall be entitled to avail himself of the limits of liability which that carrier himself is entitled to invoke under Article 22.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The aggregate of the amounts recoverable from the carrier, his servants and agents, in that case, shall not exceed the said limits.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraphs (1) and (2) of this article shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the servant or agent done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79279" lims:id="79279"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79280" lims:id="79280" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XV</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79281" lims:id="79281" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 26 of the Convention —</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79282" lims:id="79282" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>paragraph (2) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“(2)</Label><Text>In the case of damage, the person entitled to delivery must complain to the carrier forthwith after the discovery of the damage, and, at the latest, within seven days from the date of receipt in the case of baggage and fourteen days from the date of receipt in the case of cargo. In the case of delay the complaint must be made at the latest within twenty-one days from the date on which the baggage or cargo have been placed at his disposal.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79283" lims:id="79283"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79284" lims:id="79284" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XVI</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79285" lims:id="79285" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 34 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Text>“The provisions of Articles 3 to 9 inclusive relating to documents of carriage shall not apply in the case of carriage performed in extraordinary circumstances outside the normal scope of an air carrier’s business.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79286" lims:id="79286"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79287" lims:id="79287" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XVII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79288" lims:id="79288" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>After Article 40 of the Convention, the following Article shall be inserted:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered"><Text>“<Emphasis style="italic">Article 40 A</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In Article 37, paragraph (2) and Article 40, paragraph (1), the expression <Emphasis style="italic">High Contracting Party</Emphasis> shall mean <Emphasis style="italic">State</Emphasis>. In all other cases, the expression <Emphasis style="italic">High Contracting Party</Emphasis> shall mean a State whose ratification of or adherence to the Convention has become effective and whose denunciation thereof has not become effective.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the Convention the word <Emphasis style="italic">territory</Emphasis> means not only the metropolitan territory of a State but also all other territories for the foreign relations of which that State is responsible.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79289" lims:id="79289"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79290" lims:id="79290" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER II</Label><TitleText>Scope of Application of the Convention as Amended</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79291" lims:id="79291"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79292" lims:id="79292" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XVIII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79293" lims:id="79293" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Convention as amended by this Protocol shall apply to international carriage as defined in Article 1 of the Convention, provided that the places of departure and destination referred to in that Article are situated either in the territories of two parties to this Protocol or within the territory of a single party to this Protocol with an agreed stopping place within the territory of another State.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79294" lims:id="79294"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79295" lims:id="79295" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER III</Label><TitleText>Final Clauses</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79296" lims:id="79296"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79297" lims:id="79297" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XIX</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79298" lims:id="79298" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>As between the Parties to this Protocol, the Convention and the Protocol shall be read and interpreted together as one single instrument and shall be known as the <Emphasis style="italic">Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955</Emphasis>.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79299" lims:id="79299"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79300" lims:id="79300" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XX</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79301" lims:id="79301" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Until the date on which this Protocol comes into force in accordance with the provisions of Article XXII, paragraph (1), it shall remain open for signature on behalf of any State which up to that date has ratified or adhered to the Convention or which has participated in the Conference at which this Protocol was adopted.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79302" lims:id="79302"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79303" lims:id="79303" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XXI</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79304" lims:id="79304" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Protocol shall be subject to ratification by the signatory States.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79305" lims:id="79305" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Ratification of this Protocol by any State which is not a Party to the Convention shall have the effect of adherence to the Convention as amended by this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79306" lims:id="79306" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Government of the People’s Republic of Poland.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79307" lims:id="79307"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79308" lims:id="79308" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XXII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79309" lims:id="79309" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as thirty signatory States have deposited their instruments of ratification of this Protocol, it shall come into force between them on the ninetieth day after the deposit of the thirtieth instrument of ratification. It shall come into force for each State ratifying thereafter on the ninetieth day after the deposit of its instrument of ratification.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79310" lims:id="79310" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As soon as this Protocol comes into force it shall be registered with the United Nations by the Government of the People’s Republic of Poland.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79311" lims:id="79311"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79312" lims:id="79312" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XXIII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79313" lims:id="79313" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Protocol shall, after it has come into force, be open for adherence by any non-signatory State.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79314" lims:id="79314" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Adherence to this Protocol by any State which is not a Party to the Convention shall have the effect of adherence to the Convention as amended by this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79315" lims:id="79315" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Adherence shall be effected by the deposit of an instrument of adherence with the Government of the People’s Republic of Poland and shall take effect on the ninetieth day after the deposit.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79316" lims:id="79316"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79317" lims:id="79317" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XXIV</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79318" lims:id="79318" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any Party to this Protocol may denounce the Protocol by notification addressed to the Government of the People’s Republic of Poland.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79319" lims:id="79319" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Denunciation shall take effect six months after the date of receipt by the Government of the People’s Republic of Poland of the notification of denunciation.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79320" lims:id="79320" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As between the Parties to this Protocol, denunciation by any of them of the Convention in accordance with Article 39 thereof shall not be construed in any way as a denunciation of the Convention as amended by this Protocol.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79321" lims:id="79321"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79322" lims:id="79322" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XXV</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79323" lims:id="79323" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Protocol shall apply to all territories for the foreign relations of which a State Party to this Protocol is responsible, with the exception of territories in respect of which a declaration has been made in accordance with paragraph (2) of this Article.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79324" lims:id="79324" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any State may, at the time of deposit of its instrument of ratification or adherence, declare that its acceptance of this Protocol does not apply to any one or more of the territories for the foreign relations of which such State is responsible.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79325" lims:id="79325" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any State may subsequently, by notification to the Government of the People’s Republic of Poland, extend the application of this Protocol to any or all of the territories regarding which it has made a declaration in accordance with paragraph (2) of this Article. The notification shall take effect on the ninetieth day after its receipt by that Government.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79326" lims:id="79326" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any State Party to this Protocol may denounce it, in accordance with the provisions of Article XXIV, paragraph (1), separately for any or all of the territories for the foreign relations of which such State is responsible.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79327" lims:id="79327"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79328" lims:id="79328" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XXVI</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79329" lims:id="79329" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>No reservation may be made to this Protocol except that a State may at any time declare by a notification addressed to the Government of the People’s Republic of Poland that the Convention as amended by this Protocol shall not apply to the carriage of persons, cargo and baggage for its military authorities on aircraft, registered in that State, the whole capacity of which has been reserved by or on behalf of such authorities.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79330" lims:id="79330"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79331" lims:id="79331" format-ref="group2-division"><Label><Emphasis style="italic">Article XXVII</Emphasis></Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79332" lims:id="79332" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Government of the People’s Republic of Poland shall give immediate notice to the Governments of all States signatories to the Convention or this Protocol, all States Parties to the Convention or this Protocol, and all States Members of the International Civil Aviation Organization or of the United Nations and to the International Civil Aviation Organization:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79333" lims:id="79333" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>of any signature of this Protocol and the date thereof;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79334" lims:id="79334" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>of the deposit of any instrument of ratification or adherence in respect of this Protocol and the date thereof;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79335" lims:id="79335" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>of the date on which this Protocol comes into force in accordance with Article XXII, paragraph (1);</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79336" lims:id="79336" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>of the receipt of any notification of denunciation and the date thereof;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79337" lims:id="79337" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>of the receipt of any declaration or notification made under Article XXV and the date thereof; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79338" lims:id="79338" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>of the receipt of any notification made under Article XXVI and the date thereof.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group></Group><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79339" lims:id="79339" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>In Witness Whereof the undersigned Plenipotentiaries, having been duly authorized, have signed this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79340" lims:id="79340" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Done at The Hague on the twenty-eighth day of the month of September of the year One Thousand Nine Hundred and Fifty-five, in three authentic texts in the English, French and Spanish languages. In the case of any inconsistency, the text in the French language, in which language the Convention was drawn up, shall prevail.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79341" lims:id="79341" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>This Protocol shall be deposited with the Government of the People’s Republic of Poland with which, in accordance with Article XX, it shall remain open for signature, and that Government shall send certified copies thereof to the Governments of all States signatories to the Convention or this Protocol, all States Parties to the Convention or this Protocol, and all States Members of the International Civil Aviation Organization or of the United Nations, and to the International Civil Aviation Organization.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79342" lims:id="79342" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>[Here follow the signatures on behalf of the Governments of Belgium, Brazil, Republic of Czechoslovakia, Egypt, France, Federal Republic of Germany, Greece, Hungarian People’s Republic, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Laos, Liechtenstein, Luxembourg, Mexico, Norway, Netherlands, Philippines, Polish People’s Republic, Portugal, Roumanian People’s Republic, Salvador, Sweden, Switzerland, Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, and Venezuela.]</Text></Provision></DocumentInternal><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79344" lims:id="79344">R.S., c. C-14, Sch. III</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79345" lims:id="79345" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79346" lims:id="79346"><Label>SCHEDULE IV</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 5)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Montreal Protocol No. 4 To Amend the Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air, Signed at Warsaw on 12 October 1929, as Amended by the Protocol Done at the Hague on 28 September 1955</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79347" lims:id="79347" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>THE GOVERNMENTS UNDERSIGNED</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79348" lims:id="79348" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>CONSIDERING that it is desirable to amend the Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air signed at Warsaw on 12 October 1929 as amended by the Protocol done at The Hague on 28 September 1955,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79349" lims:id="79349" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>HAVE AGREED as follows:</Text></Provision><DocumentInternal lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79350" lims:id="79350"><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79351" lims:id="79351"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79352" lims:id="79352" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER I</Label><TitleText>Amendments to the Convention</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79353" lims:id="79353"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79354" lims:id="79354" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article I</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79355" lims:id="79355" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Convention which the provisions of the present Chapter modify is the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague in 1955.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79356" lims:id="79356"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79357" lims:id="79357" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article II</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79358" lims:id="79358" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 2 of the Convention, paragraph 2 shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>“2</Label><Text>In the carriage of postal items the carrier shall be liable only to the relevant postal administration in accordance with the rules applicable to the relationship between the carriers and the postal administrations.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Except as provided in paragraph 2 of this Article, the provisions of this Convention shall not apply to the carriage of postal items.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79359" lims:id="79359"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79360" lims:id="79360" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article III</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79361" lims:id="79361" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Chapter II of the Convention, Section III (Articles 5 to 16) shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“Section III. — Documentation relating to cargo</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 5</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>In respect of the carriage of cargo an air waybill shall be delivered.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any other means which would preserve a record of the carriage to be performed may, with the consent of the consignor, be substituted for the delivery of an air waybill. If such other means are used, the carrier shall, if so requested by the consignor, deliver to the consignor a receipt for the cargo permitting identification of the consignment and access to the information contained in the record preserved by such other means.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The impossibility of using, at points of transit and destination, the other means which would preserve the record of the carriage referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article does not entitle the carrier to refuse to accept the cargo for carriage.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 6</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The air waybill shall be made out by the consignor in three original parts.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The first part shall be marked “for the carrier”; it shall be signed by the consignor. The second part shall be marked “for the consignee”; it shall be signed by the consignor and by the carrier. The third part shall be signed by the carrier and handed by him to the consignor after the cargo has been accepted.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>The signature of the carrier and that of the consignor may be printed or stamped.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>If, at the request of the consignor, the carrier makes out the air waybill, he shall be deemed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have done so on behalf of the consignor.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 7</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>When there is more than one package:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the carrier of cargo has the right to require the consignor to make out separate air waybills;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the consignor has the right to require the carrier to deliver separate receipts when the other means referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 5 are used.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 8</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The air waybill and the receipt for the cargo shall contain:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indication of the places of departure and destination;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single High Contracting Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an indication of the weight of the consignment.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 9</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Non-compliance with the provisions of Articles 5 to 8 shall not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage, which shall, none the less, be subject to the rules of this Convention including those relating to limitation of liability.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 10</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The consignor is responsible for the correctness of the particulars and statements relating to the cargo inserted by him or on his behalf in the air waybill or furnished by him or on his behalf to the carrier for insertion in the receipt for the cargo or for insertion in the record preserved by the other means referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 5.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The consignor shall indemnify the carrier against all damage suffered by him, or by any other person to whom the carrier is liable, by reason of the irregularity, incorrectness or incompleteness of the particulars and statements furnished by the consignor or on his behalf.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, the carrier shall indemnify the consignor against all damage suffered by him, or by any other person to whom the consignor is liable, by reason of the irregularity, incorrectness or incompleteness of the particulars and statements inserted by the carrier or on his behalf in the receipt for the cargo or in the record preserved by the other means referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 5.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 11</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The air waybill or the receipt for the cargo is <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> evidence of the conclusion of the contract, of the acceptance of the cargo and of the conditions of carriage mentioned therein.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any statements in the air waybill or the receipt for the cargo relating to the weight, dimensions and packing of the cargo, as well as those relating to the number of packages, are <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language> evidence of the facts stated; those relating to the quantity, volume and condition of the cargo do not constitute evidence against the carrier except so far as they both have been, and are stated in the air waybill to have been, checked by him in the presence of the consignor, or relate to the apparent condition of the cargo.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 12</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to his liability to carry out all his obligations under the contract of carriage, the consignor has the right to dispose of the cargo by withdrawing it at the airport of departure or destination, or by stopping it in the course of the journey on any landing, or by calling for it to be delivered at the place of destination or in the course of the journey to a person other than the consignee originally designated, or by requiring it to be returned to the airport of departure. He must not exercise this right of disposition in such a way as to prejudice the carrier or other consignors and he must repay any expenses occasioned by the exercise of this right.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>If it is impossible to carry out the orders of the consignor the carrier must so inform him forthwith.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>If the carrier obeys the orders of the consignor for the disposition of the cargo without requiring the production of the part of the air waybill or the receipt for the cargo delivered to the latter, he will be liable, without prejudice to his right of recovery from the consignor, for any damage which may be caused thereby to any person who is lawfully in possession of that part of the air waybill or the receipt for the cargo.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>The right conferred on the consignor ceases at the moment when that of the consignee begins in accordance with Article 13. Nevertheless, if the consignee declines to accept the cargo, or if he cannot be communicated with, the consignor resumes his right of disposition.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 13</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Except when the consignor has exercised his right under Article 12, the consignee is entitled, on arrival of the cargo at the place of destination, to require the carrier to deliver the cargo to him, on payment of the charges due and on complying with the conditions of carriage.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>Unless it is otherwise agreed, it is the duty of the carrier to give notice to the consignee as soon as the cargo arrives.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>If the carrier admits the loss of the cargo, or if the cargo has not arrived at the expiration of seven days after the date on which it ought to have arrived, the consignee is entitled to enforce against the carrier the rights which flow from the contract of carriage.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 14</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The consignor and the consignee can respectively enforce all the rights given them by Articles 12 and 13, each in his own name, whether he is acting in his own interest or in the interest of another, provided that he carries out the obligations imposed by the contract of carriage.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 15</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>Articles 12, 13 and 14 do not affect either the relations of the consignor and the consignee with each other or the mutual relations of third parties whose rights are derived either from the consignor or from the consignee.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The provisions of Articles 12, 13 and 14 can only be varied by express provision in the air waybill or the receipt for the cargo.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 16</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The consignor must furnish such information and such documents as are necessary to meet the formalities of customs, octroi or police before the cargo can be delivered to the consignee. The consignor is liable to the carrier for any damage occasioned by the absence, insufficiency or irregularity of any such information or documents, unless the damage is due to the fault of the carrier, his servants or agents.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The carrier is under no obligation to enquire into the correctness or sufficiency of such information or documents.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79362" lims:id="79362"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79363" lims:id="79363" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article IV</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79364" lims:id="79364" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 18 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 18</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the destruction or loss of, or damage to, any registered baggage, if the occurrence which caused the damage so sustained took place during the carriage by air.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the destruction or loss of, or damage to, cargo upon condition only that the occurrence which caused the damage so sustained took place during the carriage by air.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>3</Label><Text>However, the carrier is not liable if he proves that the destruction, loss of, or damage to, the cargo resulted solely from one or more of the following:</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>inherent defect, quality or vice of that cargo;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>defective packing of that cargo performed by a person other than the carrier or his servants or agents;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an act of war or an armed conflict;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an act of public authority carried out in connexion with the entry, exit or transit of the cargo.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>4</Label><Text>The carriage by air within the meaning of the preceding paragraphs of this Article comprises the period during which the baggage or cargo is in the charge of the carrier, whether in an airport or on board an aircraft, or, in the case of a landing outside an airport, in any place whatsoever.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>5</Label><Text>The period of the carriage by air does not extend to any carriage by land, by sea or by river performed outside an airport. If, however, such carriage takes place in the performance of a contract for carriage by air, for the purpose of loading, delivery or transhipment, any damage is presumed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have been the result of an event which took place during the carriage by air.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79365" lims:id="79365"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79366" lims:id="79366" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article V</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79367" lims:id="79367" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 20 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 20</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>In the carriage of passengers and baggage, and in the case of damage occasioned by delay in the carriage of cargo, the carrier shall not be liable if he proves that he and his servants and agents have taken all necessary measures to avoid the damage or that it was impossible for them to take such measures.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79368" lims:id="79368"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79369" lims:id="79369" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article VI</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79370" lims:id="79370" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 21 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 21</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>In the carriage of passengers and baggage, if the carrier proves that the damage was caused by or contributed to by the negligence of the person suffering the damage the Court may, in accordance with the provisions of its own law, exonerate the carrier wholly or partly from his liability.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the carriage of cargo, if the carrier proves that the damage was caused by or contributed to by the negligence or other wrongful act or omission of the person claiming compensation, or the person from whom he derives his rights, the carrier shall be wholly or partly exonerated from his liability to the claimant to the extent that such negligence or wrongful act or omission caused or contributed to the damage.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79371" lims:id="79371"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79372" lims:id="79372" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article VII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79373" lims:id="79373" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 22 of the Convention,</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79374" lims:id="79374" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in paragraph 2(a) the words “and of cargo” shall be deleted;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79375" lims:id="79375" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>after paragraph 2(a) the following paragraph shall be inserted:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-2-2" language-align="no"><Label>“(b)</Label><Text>In the carriage of cargo, the liability of the carrier is limited to a sum of 17 Special Drawing Rights per kilogramme, unless the consignor has made, at the time when the package was handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of interest in delivery at destination and has paid a supplementary sum if the case so requires. In that case the carrier will be liable to pay a sum not exceeding the declared sum, unless he proves that the sum is greater than the consignor’s actual interest in delivery at destination.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79376" lims:id="79376" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>paragraph 2(b) shall be designated as paragraph 2(c);</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79377" lims:id="79377" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>after paragraph 5 the following paragraph shall be inserted:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Label>“6</Label><Text>The sums mentioned in terms of the Special Drawing Right in this Article shall be deemed to refer to the Special Drawing Right as defined by the International Monetary Fund. Conversion of the sums into national currencies shall, in case of judicial proceedings, be made according to the value of such currencies in terms of the Special Drawing Right at the date of the judgment. The value of a national currency, in terms of the Special Drawing Right, of a High Contracting Party which is a Member of the International Monetary Fund, shall be calculated in accordance with the method of valuation applied by the International Monetary Fund, in effect at the date of the judgment, for its operations and transactions. The value of a national currency, in terms of the Special Drawing Right, of a High Contracting Party which is not a Member of the International Monetary Fund, shall be calculated in a manner determined by that High Contracting Party.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no"><Text>Nevertheless, those States which are not Members of the International Monetary Fund and whose law does not permit the application of the provisions of paragraph 2(b) of Article 22 may, at the time of ratification or accession or at any time thereafter, declare that the limit of liability of the carrier in judicial proceedings in their territories is fixed at a sum of two hundred and fifty monetary units per kilogramme. This monetary unit corresponds to sixty-five and a half milligrammes of gold of millesimal fineness nine hundred. This sum may be converted into the national currency concerned in round figures. The conversion of this sum into the national currency shall be made according to the law of the State concerned.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79378" lims:id="79378"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79379" lims:id="79379" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article VIII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79380" lims:id="79380" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 24 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 24</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>1</Label><Text>In the carriage of passengers and baggage, any action for damages, however founded, can only be brought subject to the conditions and limits set out in this Convention, without prejudice to the question as to who are the persons who have the right to bring suit and what are their respective rights.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the carriage of cargo, any action for damages, however founded, whether under this Convention or in contract or in tort or otherwise, can only be brought subject to the conditions and limits of liability set out in this Convention without prejudice to the question as to who are the persons who have the right to bring suit and what are their respective rights. Such limits of liability constitute maximum limits and may not be exceeded whatever the circumstances which gave rise to the liability.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79381" lims:id="79381"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79382" lims:id="79382" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article IX</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79383" lims:id="79383" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 25 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 25</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>In the carriage of passengers and baggage, the limits of liability specified in Article 22 shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the carrier, his servants or agents, done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result; provided that, in the case of such act or omission of a servant or agent, it is also proved that he was acting within the scope of his employment.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79384" lims:id="79384"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79385" lims:id="79385" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article X</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79386" lims:id="79386" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In Article 25A of the Convention, paragraph 3 shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Label>“3</Label><Text>In the carriage of passengers and baggage, the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the servant or agent done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79387" lims:id="79387"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79388" lims:id="79388" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XI</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79389" lims:id="79389" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>After Article 30 of the Convention, the following Article shall be inserted:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 30A</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Nothing in this Convention shall prejudice the question whether a person liable for damage in accordance with its provisions has a right of recourse against any other person.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79390" lims:id="79390"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79391" lims:id="79391" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79392" lims:id="79392" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 33 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 33</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Except as provided in paragraph 3 of Article 5, nothing in this Convention shall prevent the carrier either from refusing to enter into any contract of carriage or from making regulations which do not conflict with the provisions of this Convention.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79393" lims:id="79393"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79394" lims:id="79394" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XIII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79395" lims:id="79395" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Article 34 of the Convention shall be deleted and replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedContent><Provision format-ref="centered" language-align="yes"><Text>“<Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article 34</Emphasis></Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The provisions of Articles 3 to 8 inclusive relating to documents of carriage shall not apply in the case of carriage performed in extraordinary circumstances outside the normal scope of an air carrier’s business.”</Text></Provision></AmendedContent></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79396" lims:id="79396"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79397" lims:id="79397" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER II</Label><TitleText>Scope of Application of the Convention as Amended</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79398" lims:id="79398"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79399" lims:id="79399" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XIV</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79400" lims:id="79400" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague in 1955 and by this Protocol shall apply to international carriage as defined in Article 1 of the Convention, provided that the places of departure and destination referred to in that Article are situated either in the territories of two Parties to this Protocol or within the territory of a single Party to this Protocol with an agreed stopping place in the territory of another State.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79401" lims:id="79401"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79402" lims:id="79402" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>CHAPTER III</Label><TitleText>Final Clauses</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79403" lims:id="79403"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79404" lims:id="79404" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XV</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79405" lims:id="79405" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>As between the Parties to this Protocol, the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague in 1955 and this Protocol shall be read and interpreted together as one single instrument and shall be known as the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, and by Protocol No. 4 of Montreal, 1975.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79406" lims:id="79406"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79407" lims:id="79407" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XVI</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79408" lims:id="79408" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Until the date on which this Protocol comes into force in accordance with the provisions of Article XVIII, it shall remain open for signature by any State.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79409" lims:id="79409"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79410" lims:id="79410" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XVII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79411" lims:id="79411" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Protocol shall be subject to ratification by the signatory States.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79412" lims:id="79412" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Ratification of this Protocol by any State which is not a Party to the Warsaw Convention or by any State which is not a Party to the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, shall have the effect of accession to the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, and by Protocol No. 4 of Montreal, 1975.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79413" lims:id="79413" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Government of the Polish People’s Republic.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79414" lims:id="79414"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79415" lims:id="79415" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XVIII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79416" lims:id="79416" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>As soon as thirty signatory States have deposited their instruments of ratification of this Protocol, it shall come into force between them on the ninetieth day after the deposit of the thirtieth instrument of ratification. It shall come into force for each State ratifying thereafter on the ninetieth day after the deposit of its instrument of ratification.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79417" lims:id="79417" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>As soon as this Protocol comes into force it shall be registered with the United Nations by the Government of the Polish People’s Republic.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79418" lims:id="79418"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79419" lims:id="79419" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XIX</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79420" lims:id="79420" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Protocol, after it has come into force, shall be open for accession by any non-signatory State.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79421" lims:id="79421" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Accession to this Protocol by any State which is not a Party to the Warsaw Convention or by any State which is not a Party to the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, shall have the effect of accession to the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, and by Protocol No. 4 of Montreal, 1975.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79422" lims:id="79422" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Accession shall be effected by the deposit of an instrument of accession with the Government of the Polish People’s Republic and shall take effect on the ninetieth day after the deposit.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79423" lims:id="79423"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79424" lims:id="79424" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XX</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79425" lims:id="79425" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any Party to this Protocol may denounce the Protocol by notification addressed to the Government of the Polish People’s Republic.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79426" lims:id="79426" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Denunciation shall take effect six months after the date of receipt by the Government of the Polish People’s Republic of the notification of denunciation.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79427" lims:id="79427" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>As between the Parties to this Protocol, denunciation by any of them of the Warsaw Convention in accordance with Article 39 thereof or of The Hague Protocol in accordance with Article XXIV thereof shall not be construed in any way as a denunciation of the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, and by Protocol No. 4 of Montreal, 1975.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79428" lims:id="79428"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79429" lims:id="79429" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XXI</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79430" lims:id="79430" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Only the following reservations may be made to this Protocol:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79431" lims:id="79431" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a State may at any time declare by a notification addressed to the Government of the Polish People’s Republic that the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, and by Protocol No. 4 of Montreal, 1975, shall not apply to the carriage of persons, baggage and cargo for its military authorities on aircraft, registered in that State, the whole capacity of which has been reserved by or on behalf of such authorities; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79432" lims:id="79432" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any State may declare at the time of ratification of or accession to the Additional Protocol No. 3 of Montreal, 1975, or at any time thereafter, that it is not bound by the provisions of the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, and by Protocol No. 4 of Montreal, 1975, in so far as they relate to the carriage of passengers and baggage. Such declaration shall have effect ninety days after the date of receipt of the declaration by the Government of the Polish People’s Republic.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79433" lims:id="79433" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any State having made a reservation in accordance with the preceding paragraph may at any time withdraw such reservation by notification to the Government of the Polish People’s Republic.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79434" lims:id="79434"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79435" lims:id="79435" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XXII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79436" lims:id="79436" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Government of the Polish People’s Republic shall promptly inform all States Parties to the Warsaw Convention or to that Convention as amended, all signatory or acceding States to the present Protocol, as well as the International Civil Aviation Organization, of the date of each signature, the date of deposit of each instrument of ratification or accession, the date of coming into force of this Protocol, and other relevant information.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79437" lims:id="79437"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79438" lims:id="79438" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XXIII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79439" lims:id="79439" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>As between the Parties to this Protocol which are also Parties to the Convention, Supplementary to the Warsaw Convention, for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air Performed by a Person Other than the Contracting Carrier, signed at Guadalajara on 18 September 1961 (hereinafter referred to as the “Guadalajara Convention”) any reference to the “Warsaw Convention” contained in the Guadalajara Convention shall include reference to the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, and by Protocol No. 4 of Montreal, 1975, in cases where the carriage under the agreement referred to in Article 1, paragraph (b) of the Guadalajara Convention is governed by this Protocol.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79440" lims:id="79440"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79441" lims:id="79441" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XXIV</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79442" lims:id="79442" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>If two or more States are Parties both to this Protocol and to the Guatemala City Protocol, 1971, or to the Additional Protocol No. 3 of Montreal, 1975, the following rules shall apply between them:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79443" lims:id="79443" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the provisions resulting from the system established by this Protocol, concerning cargo and postal items, shall prevail over the provisions resulting from the system established by the Guatemala City Protocol, 1971, or by the Additional Protocol No. 3 of Montreal, 1975;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79444" lims:id="79444" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the provisions resulting from the system established by the Guatemala City Protocol, 1971, or by the Additional Protocol No. 3 of Montreal, 1975, concerning passengers and baggage, shall prevail over the provisions resulting from the system established by this Protocol.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79445" lims:id="79445"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79446" lims:id="79446" format-ref="group2-division"><Label>Article XXV</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79447" lims:id="79447" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Protocol shall remain open for signature until 1 January 1976 at the Headquarters of the International Civil Aviation Organization and thereafter until it comes into force in accordance with Article XVIII at the Ministry for Foreign Affairs of the Polish People’s Republic. The International Civil Aviation Organization shall promptly inform the Government of the Polish People’s Republic of any signature and the date thereof during the time that the Protocol shall be open for signature at the Headquarters of the International Civil Aviation Organization.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79448" lims:id="79448" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned Plenipotentiaries, having been duly authorized, have signed this Protocol.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79449" lims:id="79449" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>DONE AT MONTREAL on the twenty-fifth day of September of the year One Thousand Nine Hundred and Seventy-five in four authentic texts in the English, French, Russian and Spanish languages. In the case of any inconsistency, the text in the French language, in which language the Warsaw Convention of 12 October 1929 was drawn up, shall prevail.</Text></Provision></DocumentInternal><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79451" lims:id="79451">1999, c. 21, s. 4</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79452" lims:id="79452" bilingual="no" spanlanguages="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79453" lims:id="79453"><Label>SCHEDULE V</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 2 and 4)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Convention, Supplementary to the Warsaw Convention, for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air Performed by a Person Other than the Contracting Carrier</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79454" lims:id="79454" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>THE STATES SIGNATORY TO THE PRESENT CONVENTION</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79455" lims:id="79455" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>NOTING that the Warsaw Convention does not contain particular rules relating to international carriage by air performed by a person who is not a party to the agreement for carriage</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79456" lims:id="79456" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>CONSIDERING that it is therefore desirable to formulate rules to apply in such circumstances</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79457" lims:id="79457" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</Text></Provision><DocumentInternal lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79458" lims:id="79458"><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79459" lims:id="79459"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79460" lims:id="79460" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> I</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79461" lims:id="79461" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In this Convention:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79462" lims:id="79462" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>“<DefinedTermEn>Warsaw Convention</DefinedTermEn>” means the Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air signed at Warsaw on 12 October 1929, or the Warsaw Convention as amended at The Hague, 1955, according to whether the carriage under the agreement referred to in paragraph (b) is governed by the one or by the other;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79463" lims:id="79463" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>“<DefinedTermEn>contracting carrier</DefinedTermEn>” means a person who as a principal makes an agreement for carriage governed by the Warsaw Convention with a passenger or consignor or with a person acting on behalf of the passenger or consignor;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79464" lims:id="79464" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>“<DefinedTermEn>actual carrier</DefinedTermEn>” means a person, other than the contracting carrier, who, by virtue of authority from the contracting carrier, performs the whole or part of the carriage contemplated in paragraph (b) but who is not with respect to such part a successive carrier within the meaning of the Warsaw Convention. Such authority is presumed in the absence of proof to the contrary.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79465" lims:id="79465"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79466" lims:id="79466" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> II</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79467" lims:id="79467" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>If an actual carrier performs the whole or part of carriage which, according to the agreement referred to in Article I, paragraph (b), is governed by the Warsaw Convention, both the contracting carrier and the actual carrier shall, except as otherwise provided in this Convention, be subject to the rules of the Warsaw Convention, the former for the whole of the carriage contemplated in the agreement, the latter solely for the carriage which he performs.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79468" lims:id="79468"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79469" lims:id="79469" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> III</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79470" lims:id="79470" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The acts and omissions of the actual carrier and of his servants and agents acting within the scope of their employment shall, in relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, be deemed to be also those of the contracting carrier.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79471" lims:id="79471" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The acts and omissions of the contracting carrier and of his servants and agents acting within the scope of their employment shall, in relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, be deemed to be also those of the actual carrier. Nevertheless, no such act or omission shall subject the actual carrier to liability exceeding the limits specified in Article 22 of the Warsaw Convention. Any special agreement under which the contracting carrier assumes obligations not imposed by the Warsaw Convention or any waiver of rights conferred by that Convention or any special declaration of interest in delivery at destination contemplated in Article 22 of the said Convention, shall not affect the actual carrier unless agreed to by him.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79472" lims:id="79472"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79473" lims:id="79473" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> IV</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79474" lims:id="79474" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any complaint to be made or order to be given under the Warsaw Convention to the carrier shall have the same effect whether addressed to the contracting carrier or to the actual carrier. Nevertheless, orders referred to in Article 12 of the Warsaw Convention shall only be effective if addressed to the contracting carrier.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79475" lims:id="79475"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79476" lims:id="79476" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> V</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79477" lims:id="79477" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, any servant or agent of that carrier or of the contracting carrier shall, if he proves that he acted within the scope of his employment, be entitled to avail himself of the limits of liability which are applicable under this Convention to the carrier whose servant or agent he is unless it is proved that he acted in a manner which, under the Warsaw Convention, prevents the limits of liability from being invoked.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79478" lims:id="79478"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79479" lims:id="79479" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> VI</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79480" lims:id="79480" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, the aggregate of the amounts recoverable from that carrier and the contracting carrier, and from their servants and agents acting within the scope of their employment, shall not exceed the highest amount which could be awarded against either the contracting carrier or the actual carrier under this Convention, but none of the persons mentioned shall be liable for a sum in excess of the limit applicable to him.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79481" lims:id="79481"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79482" lims:id="79482" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> VII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79483" lims:id="79483" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, an action for damages may be brought, at the option of the plaintiff, against that carrier or the contracting carrier, or against both together or separately. If the action is brought against only one of those carriers, that carrier shall have the right to require the other carrier to be joined in the proceedings, the procedure and effects being governed by the law of the court seised of the case.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79484" lims:id="79484"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79485" lims:id="79485" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> VIII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79486" lims:id="79486" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any action for damages contemplated in Article VII of this Convention must be brought, at the option of the plaintiff, either before a court in which an action may be brought against the contracting carrier, as provided in Article 28 of the Warsaw Convention, or before the court having jurisdiction at the place where the actual carrier is ordinarily resident or has his principal place of business.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79487" lims:id="79487"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79488" lims:id="79488" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> IX</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79489" lims:id="79489" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any contractual provision tending to relieve the contracting carrier or the actual carrier of liability under this Convention or to fix a lower limit than that which is applicable according to this Convention shall be null and void, but the nullity of any such provision does not involve the nullity of the whole agreement, which shall remain subject to the provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79490" lims:id="79490" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In respect of the carriage performed by the actual carrier, the preceding paragraph shall not apply to contractual provisions governing loss or damage resulting from the inherent defect, quality or vice of the cargo carried.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79491" lims:id="79491" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Any clause contained in an agreement for carriage and all special agreements entered into before the damage occurred by which the parties purport to infringe the rules laid down by this Convention, whether by deciding the law to be applied, or by altering the rules as to jurisdiction, shall be null and void. Nevertheless, for the carriage of cargo arbitration clauses are allowed, subject to this Convention, if the arbitration is to take place in one of the jurisdictions referred to in Article VIII.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79492" lims:id="79492"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79493" lims:id="79493" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> X</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79494" lims:id="79494" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Except as provided in Article VII, nothing in this Convention shall affect the rights and obligations of the two carriers between themselves.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79495" lims:id="79495"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79496" lims:id="79496" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> XI</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79497" lims:id="79497" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Until the date on which the Convention comes into force in accordance with the provisions of Article XIII, it shall remain open for signature on behalf of any State which at that date is a Member of the United Nations or of any of the Specialized Agencies.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79498" lims:id="79498"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79499" lims:id="79499" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> XII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79500" lims:id="79500" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall be subject to ratification by the signatory States.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79501" lims:id="79501" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Government of the United States of Mexico.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79502" lims:id="79502"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79503" lims:id="79503" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> XIII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79504" lims:id="79504" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>As soon as five of the signatory States have deposited their instruments of ratification of this Convention, it shall come into force between them on the ninetieth day after the date of the deposit of the fifth instrument of ratification. It shall come into force for each State ratifying thereafter on the ninetieth day after the deposit of its instrument of ratification.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79505" lims:id="79505" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>As soon as this Convention comes into force, it shall be registered with the United Nations and the International Civil Aviation Organization by the Government of the United States of Mexico.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79506" lims:id="79506"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79507" lims:id="79507" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> XIV</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79508" lims:id="79508" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall, after it has come into force, be open for accession by any State Member of the United Nations or of any of the Specialized Agencies.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79509" lims:id="79509" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The accession of a State shall be effected by the deposit of an instrument of accession with the Government of the United States of Mexico and shall take effect as from the ninetieth day after the date of such deposit.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79510" lims:id="79510"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79511" lims:id="79511" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> XV</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79512" lims:id="79512" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any Contracting State may denounce this Convention by notification addressed to the Government of the United States of Mexico.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79513" lims:id="79513" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Denunciation shall take effect six months after the date of receipt by the Government of the United States of Mexico of the notification of denunciation.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79514" lims:id="79514"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79515" lims:id="79515" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> XVI</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79516" lims:id="79516" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any Contracting State may at the time of its ratification of or accession to this Convention or at any time thereafter declare by notification to the Government of the United States of Mexico that the Convention shall extend to any of the territories for whose international relations it is responsible.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79517" lims:id="79517" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The Convention shall, ninety days after the date of the receipt of such notification by the Government of the United States of Mexico, extend to the territories named therein.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79518" lims:id="79518" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Any Contracting State may denounce this Convention, in accordance with the provisions of Article XV, separately for any or all of the territories for the international relations of which such State is responsible.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79519" lims:id="79519"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79520" lims:id="79520" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> XVII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79521" lims:id="79521" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>No reservation may be made to this Convention.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79522" lims:id="79522"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79523" lims:id="79523" format-ref="group1-part"><Label><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Article</Emphasis> XVIII</Label></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79524" lims:id="79524" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The Government of the United States of Mexico shall give notice to the International Civil Aviation Organization and to all States Members of the United Nations or of any of the Specialized Agencies:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79525" lims:id="79525" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>of any signature of this Convention and the date thereof;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79526" lims:id="79526" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>of the deposit of any instrument of ratification or accession and the date thereof;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79527" lims:id="79527" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>of the date on which this Convention comes into force in accordance with Article XIII, paragraph 1;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79528" lims:id="79528" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>of the receipt of any notification of denunciation and the date thereof;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79529" lims:id="79529" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>of the receipt of any declaration or notification made under Article XVI and the date thereof.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79530" lims:id="79530" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned Plenipotentiaries, having been duly authorized, have signed this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79531" lims:id="79531" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>DONE at Guadalajara on the eighteenth day of September One Thousand Nine Hundred and Sixty-one in three authentic texts drawn up in the English, French and Spanish languages. In case of any inconsistency, the text in the French language, in which language the Warsaw Convention of 12 October 1929 was drawn up, shall prevail. The Government of the United States of Mexico will establish an official translation of the text of the Convention in the Russian language.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79532" lims:id="79532" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Convention shall be deposited with the Government of the United States of Mexico with which, in accordance with Article XI, it shall remain open for signature, and that Government shall send certified copies thereof to the International Civil Aviation Organization and to all States Members of the United Nations or of any Specialized Agency.</Text></Provision></DocumentInternal><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="79534" lims:id="79534">1999, c. 21, s. 4</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79535" lims:id="79535" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79536" lims:id="79536"><Label>SCHEDULE VI</Label><OriginatingRef>(Subsections 2(2.1), (3) and (5) and 3(2) and section 4)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules for International Carriage by Air</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><DocumentInternal lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79537" lims:id="79537"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79538" lims:id="79538" format-ref="centered" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>THE STATES PARTIES TO THIS CONVENTION</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79539" lims:id="79539" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>RECOGNIZING the significant contribution of the Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air signed in Warsaw on 12 October 1929, hereinafter referred to as the “Warsaw Convention”, and other related instruments to the harmonization of private international air law;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79540" lims:id="79540" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>RECOGNIZING the need to modernize and consolidate the Warsaw Convention and related instruments;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79541" lims:id="79541" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>RECOGNIZING the importance of ensuring protection of the interests of consumers in international carriage by air and the need for equitable compensation based on the principle of restitution;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79542" lims:id="79542" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>REAFFIRMING the desirability of an orderly development of international air transport operations and the smooth flow of passengers, baggage and cargo in accordance with the principles and objectives of the Convention on International Civil Aviation, done at Chicago on 7 December 1944;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79543" lims:id="79543" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>CONVINCED that collective State action for further harmonization and codification of certain rules governing international carriage by air through a new Convention is the most adequate means of achieving an equitable balance of interests;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79544" lims:id="79544" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>HAVE AGREED AS FOLLOWS:</Text></Provision><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79545" lims:id="79545"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79546" lims:id="79546" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>Chapter I</Label><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79547" lims:id="79547"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79548" lims:id="79548" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 1 — Scope of Application</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79549" lims:id="79549" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention applies to all international carriage of persons, baggage or cargo performed by aircraft for reward. It applies equally to gratuitous carriage by aircraft performed by an air transport undertaking.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79550" lims:id="79550" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Convention, the expression international carriage means any carriage in which, according to the agreement between the parties, the place of departure and the place of destination, whether or not there be a break in the carriage or a transhipment, are situated either within the territories of two States Parties, or within the territory of a single State Party if there is an agreed stopping place within the territory of another State, even if that State is not a State Party. Carriage between two points within the territory of a single State Party without an agreed stopping place within the territory of another State is not international carriage for the purposes of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79551" lims:id="79551" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Carriage to be performed by several successive carriers is deemed, for the purposes of this Convention, to be one undivided carriage if it has been regarded by the parties as a single operation, whether it had been agreed upon under the form of a single contract or of a series of contracts, and it does not lose its international character merely because one contract or a series of contracts is to be performed entirely within the territory of the same State.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79552" lims:id="79552" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>This Convention applies also to carriage as set out in Chapter V, subject to the terms contained therein.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79553" lims:id="79553"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79554" lims:id="79554" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 2 — Carriage Performed by State and Carriage of Postal Items</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79555" lims:id="79555" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention applies to carriage performed by the State or by legally constituted public bodies provided it falls within the conditions laid down in Article 1.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79556" lims:id="79556" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the carriage of postal items, the carrier shall be liable only to the relevant postal administration in accordance with the rules applicable to the relationship between the carriers and the postal administrations.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79557" lims:id="79557" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Except as provided in paragraph 2 of this Article, the provisions of this Convention shall not apply to the carriage of postal items.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79558" lims:id="79558"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79559" lims:id="79559" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>Chapter II</Label><TitleText>Documentation and Duties of the Parties Relating to the Carriage of Passengers, Baggage and Cargo</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79560" lims:id="79560"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79561" lims:id="79561" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 3 — Passengers and Baggage</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79562" lims:id="79562" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>In respect of carriage of passengers, an individual or collective document of carriage shall be delivered containing:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79563" lims:id="79563" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indication of the places of departure and destination;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79564" lims:id="79564" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single State Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79565" lims:id="79565" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any other means which preserves the information indicated in paragraph 1 may be substituted for the delivery of the document referred to in that paragraph. If any such other means is used, the carrier shall offer to deliver to the passenger a written statement of the information so preserved.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79566" lims:id="79566" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The carrier shall deliver to the passenger a baggage identification tag for each piece of checked baggage.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79567" lims:id="79567" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The passenger shall be given written notice to the effect that where this Convention is applicable it governs and may limit the liability of carriers in respect of death or injury and for destruction or loss of, or damage to, baggage, and for delay.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79568" lims:id="79568" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>Non-compliance with the provisions of the foregoing paragraphs shall not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage, which shall, nonetheless, be subject to the rules of this Convention including those relating to limitation of liability.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79569" lims:id="79569"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79570" lims:id="79570" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 4 — Cargo</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79571" lims:id="79571" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text> In respect of the carriage of cargo, an air waybill shall be delivered.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79572" lims:id="79572" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any other means which preserves a record of the carriage to be performed may be substituted for the delivery of an air waybill. If such other means are used, the carrier shall, if so requested by the consignor, deliver to the consignor a cargo receipt permitting identification of the consignment and access to the information contained in the record preserved by such other means.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79573" lims:id="79573"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79574" lims:id="79574" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 5 — Contents of Air Waybill or Cargo Receipt</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79575" lims:id="79575" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The air waybill or the cargo receipt shall include:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79576" lims:id="79576" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an indication of the places of departure and destination;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79577" lims:id="79577" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the places of departure and destination are within the territory of a single State Party, one or more agreed stopping places being within the territory of another State, an indication of at least one such stopping place; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79578" lims:id="79578" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an indication of the weight of the consignment.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79579" lims:id="79579"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79580" lims:id="79580" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 6 — Document Relating to the Nature of the Cargo</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79581" lims:id="79581" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The consignor may be required, if necessary to meet the formalities of customs, police and similar public authorities, to deliver a document indicating the nature of the cargo. This provision creates for the carrier no duty, obligation or liability resulting therefrom.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79582" lims:id="79582"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79583" lims:id="79583" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 7 — Description of Air Waybill</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79584" lims:id="79584" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The air waybill shall be made out by the consignor in three original parts.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79585" lims:id="79585" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The first part shall be marked “for the carrier”; it shall be signed by the consignor. The second part shall be marked “for the consignee”; it shall be signed by the consignor and by the carrier. The third part shall be signed by the carrier who shall hand it to the consignor after the cargo has been accepted.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79586" lims:id="79586" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The signature of the carrier and that of the consignor may be printed or stamped.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79587" lims:id="79587" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>If, at the request of the consignor, the carrier makes out the air waybill, the carrier shall be deemed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have done so on behalf of the consignor.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79588" lims:id="79588"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79589" lims:id="79589" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 8 — Documentation for Multiple Packages</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79590" lims:id="79590" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>When there is more than one package:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79591" lims:id="79591" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the carrier of cargo has the right to require the consignor to make out separate air waybills;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79592" lims:id="79592" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the consignor has the right to require the carrier to deliver separate cargo receipts when the other means referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 4 are used.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79593" lims:id="79593"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79594" lims:id="79594" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 9 — Non-compliance with Documentary Requirements</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79595" lims:id="79595" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Non-compliance with the provisions of Articles 4 to 8 shall not affect the existence or the validity of the contract of carriage, which shall, nonetheless, be subject to the rules of this Convention including those relating to limitation of liability.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79596" lims:id="79596"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79597" lims:id="79597" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 10 — Responsibility for Particulars of Documentation</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79598" lims:id="79598" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The consignor is responsible for the correctness of the particulars and statements relating to the cargo inserted by it or on its behalf in the air waybill or furnished by it or on its behalf to the carrier for insertion in the cargo receipt or for insertion in the record preserved by the other means referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 4. The foregoing shall also apply where the person acting on behalf of the consignor is also the agent of the carrier.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79599" lims:id="79599" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The consignor shall indemnify the carrier against all damage suffered by it, or by any other person to whom the carrier is liable, by reason of the irregularity, incorrectness or incompleteness of the particulars and statements furnished by the consignor or on its behalf.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79600" lims:id="79600" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, the carrier shall indemnify the consignor against all damage suffered by it, or by any other person to whom the consignor is liable, by reason of the irregularity, incorrectness or incompleteness of the particulars and statements inserted by the carrier or on its behalf in the cargo receipt or in the record preserved by the other means referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 4.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79601" lims:id="79601"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79602" lims:id="79602" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 11 — Evidentiary Value of Documentation</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79603" lims:id="79603" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The air waybill or the cargo receipt is <Language xml:lang="la">prima facie</Language>evidence of the conclusion of the contract, of the acceptance of the cargo and of the conditions of carriage mentioned therein.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79604" lims:id="79604" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any statements in the air waybill or the cargo receipt relating to the weight, dimensions and packing of the cargo, as well as those relating to the number of packages, are prima facie evidence of the facts stated; those relating to the quantity, volume and condition of the cargo do not constitute evidence against the carrier except so far as they both have been, and are stated in the air waybill or the cargo receipt to have been, checked by it in the presence of the consignor, or relate to the apparent condition of the cargo.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79605" lims:id="79605"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79606" lims:id="79606" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 12 — Right of Disposition of Cargo</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79607" lims:id="79607" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text> Subject to its liability to carry out all its obligations under the contract of carriage, the consignor has the right to dispose of the cargo by withdrawing it at the airport of departure or destination, or by stopping it in the course of the journey on any landing, or by calling for it to be delivered at the place of destination or in the course of the journey to a person other than the consignee originally designated, or by requiring it to be returned to the airport of departure. The consignor must not exercise this right of disposition in such a way as to prejudice the carrier or other consignors and must reimburse any expenses occasioned by the exercise of this right.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79608" lims:id="79608" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>If it is impossible to carry out the instructions of the consignor, the carrier must so inform the consignor forthwith.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79609" lims:id="79609" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>If the carrier carries out the instructions of the consignor for the disposition of the cargo without requiring the production of the part of the air waybill or the cargo receipt delivered to the latter, the carrier will be liable, without prejudice to its right of recovery from the consignor, for any damage which may be caused thereby to any person who is lawfully in possession of that part of the air waybill or the cargo receipt.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79610" lims:id="79610" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The right conferred on the consignor ceases at the moment when that of the consignee begins in accordance with Article 13. Nevertheless, if the consignee declines to accept the cargo, or cannot be communicated with, the consignor resumes its right of disposition.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79611" lims:id="79611"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79612" lims:id="79612" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 13 — Delivery of the Cargo</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79613" lims:id="79613" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Except when the consignor has exercised its right under Article 12, the consignee is entitled, on arrival of the cargo at the place of destination, to require the carrier to deliver the cargo to it, on payment of the charges due and on complying with the conditions of carriage.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79614" lims:id="79614" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Unless it is otherwise agreed, it is the duty of the carrier to give notice to the consignee as soon as the cargo arrives.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79615" lims:id="79615" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>If the carrier admits the loss of the cargo, or if the cargo has not arrived at the expiration of seven days after the date on which it ought to have arrived, the consignee is entitled to enforce against the carrier the rights which flow from the contract of carriage.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79616" lims:id="79616"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79617" lims:id="79617" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 14 — Enforcement of the Rights of Consignor and Consignee</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79618" lims:id="79618" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The consignor and the consignee can respectively enforce all the rights given to them by Articles 12 and 13, each in its own name, whether it is acting in its own interest or in the interest of another, provided that it carries out the obligations imposed by the contract of carriage.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79619" lims:id="79619"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79620" lims:id="79620" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 15 — Relations of Consignor and Consignee or Mutual Relations of Third Parties</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79621" lims:id="79621" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Articles 12, 13 and 14 do not affect either the relations of the consignor and the consignee with each other or the mutual relations of third parties whose rights are derived either from the consignor or from the consignee.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79622" lims:id="79622" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The provisions of Articles 12, 13 and 14 can only be varied by express provision in the air waybill or the cargo receipt.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79623" lims:id="79623"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79624" lims:id="79624" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 16 — Formalities of Customs, Police or Other Public Authorities</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79625" lims:id="79625" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The consignor must furnish such information and such documents as are necessary to meet the formalities of customs, police and any other public authorities before the cargo can be delivered to the consignee. The consignor is liable to the carrier for any damage occasioned by the absence, insufficiency or irregularity of any such information or documents, unless the damage is due to the fault of the carrier, its servants or agents.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79626" lims:id="79626" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The carrier is under no obligation to enquire into the correctness or sufficiency of such information or documents.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79627" lims:id="79627"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79628" lims:id="79628" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>Chapter III</Label><TitleText>Liability of the Carrier and Extent of Compensation for Damage</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79629" lims:id="79629"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79630" lims:id="79630" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 17 — Death and Injury of Passengers — Damage to Baggage</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79631" lims:id="79631" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in case of death or bodily injury of a passenger upon condition only that the accident which caused the death or injury took place on board the aircraft or in the course of any of the operations of embarking or disembarking.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79632" lims:id="79632" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in case of destruction or loss of, or of damage to, checked baggage upon condition only that the event which caused the destruction, loss or damage took place on board the aircraft or during any period within which the checked baggage was in the charge of the carrier. However, the carrier is not liable if and to the extent that the damage resulted from the inherent defect, quality or vice of the baggage. In the case of unchecked baggage, including personal items, the carrier is liable if the damage resulted from its fault or that of its servants or agents.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79633" lims:id="79633" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>If the carrier admits the loss of the checked baggage, or if the checked baggage has not arrived at the expiration of twenty-one days after the date on which it ought to have arrived, the passenger is entitled to enforce against the carrier the rights which flow from the contract of carriage.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79634" lims:id="79634" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>Unless otherwise specified, in this Convention the term “baggage” means both checked baggage and unchecked baggage.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79635" lims:id="79635"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79636" lims:id="79636" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 18 — Damage to Cargo</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79637" lims:id="79637" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The carrier is liable for damage sustained in the event of the destruction or loss of, or damage to, cargo upon condition only that the event which caused the damage so sustained took place during the carriage by air.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79638" lims:id="79638" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>However, the carrier is not liable if and to the extent it proves that the destruction, or loss of, or damage to, the cargo resulted from one or more of the following:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79639" lims:id="79639" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>inherent defect, quality or vice of that cargo;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79640" lims:id="79640" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>defective packing of that cargo performed by a person other than the carrier or its servants or agents;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79641" lims:id="79641" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>an act of war or an armed conflict;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79642" lims:id="79642" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an act of public authority carried out in connection with the entry, exit or transit of the cargo.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79643" lims:id="79643" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The carriage by air within the meaning of paragraph 1 of this Article comprises the period during which the cargo is in the charge of the carrier.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79644" lims:id="79644" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The period of the carriage by air does not extend to any carriage by land, by sea or by inland waterway performed outside an airport. If, however, such carriage takes place in the performance of a contract for carriage by air, for the purpose of loading, delivery or transhipment, any damage is presumed, subject to proof to the contrary, to have been the result of an event which took place during the carriage by air. If a carrier, without the consent of the consignor, substitutes carriage by another mode of transport for the whole or part of a carriage intended by the agreement between the parties to be carriage by air, such carriage by another mode of transport is deemed to be within the period of carriage by air.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79645" lims:id="79645"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79646" lims:id="79646" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 19 — Delay</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79647" lims:id="79647" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The carrier is liable for damage occasioned by delay in the carriage by air of passengers, baggage or cargo. Nevertheless, the carrier shall not be liable for damage occasioned by delay if it proves that it and its servants and agents took all measures that could reasonably be required to avoid the damage or that it was impossible for it or them to take such measures.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79648" lims:id="79648"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79649" lims:id="79649" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 20 — Exoneration</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79650" lims:id="79650" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>If the carrier proves that the damage was caused or contributed to by the negligence or other wrongful act or omission of the person claiming compensation, or the person from whom he or she derives his or her rights, the carrier shall be wholly or partly exonerated from its liability to the claimant to the extent that such negligence or wrongful act or omission caused or contributed to the damage. When by reason of death or injury of a passenger compensation is claimed by a person other than the passenger, the carrier shall likewise be wholly or partly exonerated from its liability to the extent that it proves that the damage was caused or contributed to by the negligence or other wrongful act or omission of that passenger. This Article applies to all the liability provisions in this Convention, including paragraph 1 of Article 21.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79651" lims:id="79651"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79652" lims:id="79652" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 21 — Compensation in Case of Death or Injury of Passengers</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79653" lims:id="79653" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>For damages arising under paragraph 1 of Article 17 not exceeding 100 000 Special Drawing Rights for each passenger, the carrier shall not be able to exclude or limit its liability.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79654" lims:id="79654" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The carrier shall not be liable for damages arising under paragraph 1 of Article 17 to the extent that they exceed for each passenger 100 000 Special Drawing Rights if the carrier proves that:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79655" lims:id="79655" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>such damage was not due to the negligence or other wrongful act or omission of the carrier or its servants or agents; or</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79656" lims:id="79656" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>such damage was solely due to the negligence or other wrongful act or omission of a third party.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79657" lims:id="79657"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79658" lims:id="79658" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 22 — Limits of Liability in Relation to Delay, Baggage and Cargo</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79659" lims:id="79659" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>In the case of damage caused by delay as specified in Article 19 in the carriage of persons, the liability of the carrier for each passenger is limited to 4 150 Special Drawing Rights.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79660" lims:id="79660" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the carriage of baggage, the liability of the carrier in the case of destruction, loss, damage or delay is limited to 1 000 Special Drawing Rights for each passenger unless the passenger has made, at the time when the checked baggage was handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of interest in delivery at destination and has paid a supplementary sum if the case so requires. In that case the carrier will be liable to pay a sum not exceeding the declared sum, unless it proves that the sum is greater than the passenger's actual interest in delivery at destination.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79661" lims:id="79661" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>In the carriage of cargo, the liability of the carrier in the case of destruction, loss, damage or delay is limited to a sum of 17 Special Drawing Rights per kilogramme, unless the consignor has made, at the time when the package was handed over to the carrier, a special declaration of interest in delivery at destination and has paid a supplementary sum if the case so requires. In that case the carrier will be liable to pay a sum not exceeding the declared sum, unless it proves that the sum is greater than the consignor's actual interest in delivery at destination.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79662" lims:id="79662" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>In the case of destruction, loss, damage or delay of part of the cargo, or of any object contained therein, the weight to be taken into consideration in determining the amount to which the carrier's liability is limited shall be only the total weight of the package or packages concerned. Nevertheless, when the destruction, loss, damage or delay of a part of the cargo, or of an object contained therein, affects the value of other packages covered by the same air waybill, or the same receipt or, if they were not issued, by the same record preserved by the other means referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 4, the total weight of such package or packages shall also be taken into consideration in determining the limit of liability.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79663" lims:id="79663" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>The foregoing provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the carrier, its servants or agents, done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result; provided that, in the case of such act or omission of a servant or agent, it is also proved that such servant or agent was acting within the scope of its employment.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79664" lims:id="79664" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>The limits prescribed in Article 21 and in this Article shall not prevent the court from awarding, in accordance with its own law, in addition, the whole or part of the court costs and of the other expenses of the litigation incurred by the plaintiff, including interest. The foregoing provision shall not apply if the amount of the damages awarded, excluding court costs and other expenses of the litigation, does not exceed the sum which the carrier has offered in writing to the plaintiff within a period of six months from the date of the occurrence causing the damage, or before the commencement of the action, if that is later.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79665" lims:id="79665"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79666" lims:id="79666" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 23 — Conversion of Monetary Units</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79667" lims:id="79667" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The sums mentioned in terms of Special Drawing Right in this Convention shall be deemed to refer to the Special Drawing Right as defined by the International Monetary Fund. Conversion of the sums into national currencies shall, in case of judicial proceedings, be made according to the value of such currencies in terms of the Special Drawing Right at the date of the judgement. The value of a national currency, in terms of the Special Drawing Right, of a State Party which is a Member of the International Monetary Fund, shall be calculated in accordance with the method of valuation applied by the International Monetary Fund, in effect at the date of the judgement, for its operations and transactions. The value of a national currency, in terms of the Special Drawing Right, of a State Party which is not a Member of the International Monetary Fund, shall be calculated in a manner determined by that State.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79668" lims:id="79668" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Nevertheless, those States which are not Members of the International Monetary Fund and whose law does not permit the application of the provisions of paragraph 1 of this Article may, at the time of ratification or accession or at any time thereafter, declare that the limit of liability of the carrier prescribed in Article 21 is fixed at a sum of 1 500 000 monetary units per passenger in judicial proceedings in their territories; 62 500 monetary units per passenger with respect to paragraph 1 of Article 22; 15 000 monetary units per passenger with respect to paragraph 2 of Article 22; and 250 monetary units per kilogramme with respect to paragraph 3 of Article 22. This monetary unit corresponds to sixty-five and a half milligrammes of gold of millesimal fineness nine hundred. These sums may be converted into the national currency concerned in round figures. The conversion of these sums into national currency shall be made according to the law of the State concerned.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79669" lims:id="79669" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The calculation mentioned in the last sentence of paragraph 1 of this Article and the conversion method mentioned in paragraph 2 of this Article shall be made in such manner as to express in the national currency of the State Party as far as possible the same real value for the amounts in Articles 21 and 22 as would result from the application of the first three sentences of paragraph 1 of this Article. States Parties shall communicate to the depositary the manner of calculation pursuant to paragraph 1 of this Article, or the result of the conversion in paragraph 2 of this Article as the case may be, when depositing an instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval of or accession to this Convention and whenever there is a change in either.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79670" lims:id="79670"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79671" lims:id="79671" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 24 — Review of Limits</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79672" lims:id="79672" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Without prejudice to the provisions of Article 25 of this Convention and subject to paragraph 2 below, the limits of liability prescribed in Articles 21, 22 and 23 shall be reviewed by the Depositary at five-year intervals, the first such review to take place at the end of the fifth year following the date of entry into force of this Convention, or if the Convention does not enter into force within five years of the date it is first open for signature, within the first year of its entry into force, by reference to an inflation factor which corresponds to the accumulated rate of inflation since the previous revision or in the first instance since the date of entry into force of the Convention. The measure of the rate of inflation to be used in determining the inflation factor shall be the weighted average of the annual rates of increase or decrease in the Consumer Price Indices of the States whose currencies comprise the Special Drawing Right mentioned in paragraph 1 of Article 23.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79673" lims:id="79673" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>If the review referred to in the preceding paragraph concludes that the inflation factor has exceeded 10 per cent, the Depositary shall notify States Parties of a revision of the limits of liability. Any such revision shall become effective six months after its notification to the States Parties. If within three months after its notification to the States Parties a majority of the States Parties register their disapproval, the revision shall not become effective and the Depositary shall refer the matter to a meeting of the States Parties. The Depositary shall immediately notify all States Parties of the coming into force of any revision.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79674" lims:id="79674" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Notwithstanding paragraph 1 of this Article, the procedure referred to in paragraph 2 of this Article shall be applied at any time provided that one-third of the States Parties express a desire to that effect and upon condition that the inflation factor referred to in paragraph 1 has exceeded 30 per cent since the previous revision or since the date of entry into force of this Convention if there has been no previous revision. Subsequent reviews using the procedure described in paragraph 1 of this Article will take place at five-year intervals starting at the end of the fifth year following the date of the reviews under the present paragraph.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79675" lims:id="79675"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79676" lims:id="79676" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 25 — Stipulation on Limits</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79677" lims:id="79677" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>A carrier may stipulate that the contract of carriage shall be subject to higher limits of liability than those provided for in this Convention or to no limits of liability whatsoever.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79678" lims:id="79678"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79679" lims:id="79679" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 26 — Invalidity of Contractual Provisions</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79680" lims:id="79680" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any provision tending to relieve the carrier of liability or to fix a lower limit than that which is laid down in this Convention shall be null and void, but the nullity of any such provision does not involve the nullity of the whole contract, which shall remain subject to the provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79681" lims:id="79681"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79682" lims:id="79682" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 27 — Freedom to Contract</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79683" lims:id="79683" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Nothing contained in this Convention shall prevent the carrier from refusing to enter into any contract of carriage, from waiving any defences available under the Convention, or from laying down conditions which do not conflict with the provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79684" lims:id="79684"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79685" lims:id="79685" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 28 — Advance Payments</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79686" lims:id="79686" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In the case of aircraft accidents resulting in death or injury of passengers, the carrier shall, if required by its national law, make advance payments without delay to a natural person or persons who are entitled to claim compensation in order to meet the immediate economic needs of such persons. Such advance payments shall not constitute a recognition of liability and may be offset against any amounts subsequently paid as damages by the carrier.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79687" lims:id="79687"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79688" lims:id="79688" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 29 — Basis of Claims</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79689" lims:id="79689" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In the carriage of passengers, baggage and cargo, any action for damages, however founded, whether under this Convention or in contract or in tort or otherwise, can only be brought subject to the conditions and such limits of liability as are set out in this Convention without prejudice to the question as to who are the persons who have the right to bring suit and what are their respective rights. In any such action, punitive, exemplary or any other non-compensatory damages shall not be recoverable.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79690" lims:id="79690"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79691" lims:id="79691" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 30 — Servants, Agents — Aggregation of Claims</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79692" lims:id="79692" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>If an action is brought against a servant or agent of the carrier arising out of damage to which the Convention relates, such servant or agent, if they prove that they acted within the scope of their employment, shall be entitled to avail themselves of the conditions and limits of liability which the carrier itself is entitled to invoke under this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79693" lims:id="79693" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The aggregate of the amounts recoverable from the carrier, its servants and agents, in that case, shall not exceed the said limits.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79694" lims:id="79694" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Save in respect of the carriage of cargo, the provisions of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article shall not apply if it is proved that the damage resulted from an act or omission of the servant or agent done with intent to cause damage or recklessly and with knowledge that damage would probably result.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79695" lims:id="79695"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79696" lims:id="79696" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 31 — Timely Notice of Complaints</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79697" lims:id="79697" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Receipt by the person entitled to delivery of checked baggage or cargo without complaint is prima facie evidence that the same has been delivered in good condition and in accordance with the document of carriage or with the record preserved by the other means referred to in paragraph 2 of Article 3 and paragraph 2 of Article 4.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79698" lims:id="79698" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the case of damage, the person entitled to delivery must complain to the carrier forthwith after the discovery of the damage, and, at the latest, within seven days from the date of receipt in the case of checked baggage and fourteen days from the date of receipt in the case of cargo. In the case of delay, the complaint must be made at the latest within twenty-one days from the date on which the baggage or cargo have been placed at his or her disposal.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79699" lims:id="79699" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>Every complaint must be made in writing and given or dispatched within the times aforesaid.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79700" lims:id="79700" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>If no complaint is made within the times aforesaid, no action shall lie against the carrier, save in the case of fraud on its part.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79701" lims:id="79701"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79702" lims:id="79702" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 32 — Death of Person Liable</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79703" lims:id="79703" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In the case of the death of the person liable, an action for damages lies in accordance with the terms of this Convention against those legally representing his or her estate.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79704" lims:id="79704"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79705" lims:id="79705" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 33 — Jurisdiction</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79706" lims:id="79706" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>An action for damages must be brought, at the option of the plaintiff, in the territory of one of the States Parties, either before the court of the domicile of the carrier or of its principal place of business, or where it has a place of business through which the contract has been made or before the court at the place of destination.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79707" lims:id="79707" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In respect of damage resulting from the death or injury of a passenger, an action may be brought before one of the courts mentioned in paragraph 1 of this Article, or in the territory of a State Party in which at the time of the accident the passenger has his or her principal and permanent residence and to or from which the carrier operates services for the carriage of passengers by air, either on its own aircraft, or on another carrier's aircraft pursuant to a commercial agreement, and in which that carrier conducts its business of carriage of passengers by air from premises leased or owned by the carrier itself or by another carrier with which it has a commercial agreement.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79708" lims:id="79708" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph 2,</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79709" lims:id="79709" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>“commercial agreement” means an agreement, other than an agency agreement, made between carriers and relating to the provision of their joint services for carriage of passengers by air;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79710" lims:id="79710" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>“principal and permanent residence” means the one fixed and permanent abode of the passenger at the time of the accident. The nationality of the passenger shall not be the determining factor in this regard.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79711" lims:id="79711" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>Questions of procedure shall be governed by the law of the court seised of the case.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79712" lims:id="79712"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79713" lims:id="79713" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 34 — Arbitration</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79714" lims:id="79714" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Subject to the provisions of this Article, the parties to the contract of carriage for cargo may stipulate that any dispute relating to the liability of the carrier under this Convention shall be settled by arbitration. Such agreement shall be in writing.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79715" lims:id="79715" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The arbitration proceedings shall, at the option of the claimant, take place within one of the jurisdictions referred to in Article 33.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79716" lims:id="79716" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>The arbitrator or arbitration tribunal shall apply the provisions of this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79717" lims:id="79717" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>The provisions of paragraphs 2 and 3 of this Article shall be deemed to be part of every arbitration clause or agreement, and any term of such clause or agreement which is inconsistent therewith shall be null and void.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79718" lims:id="79718"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79719" lims:id="79719" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 35 — Limitation of Actions</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79720" lims:id="79720" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The right to damages shall be extinguished if an action is not brought within a period of two years, reckoned from the date of arrival at the destination, or from the date on which the aircraft ought to have arrived, or from the date on which the carriage stopped.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79721" lims:id="79721" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The method of calculating that period shall be determined by the law of the court seised of the case.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79722" lims:id="79722"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79723" lims:id="79723" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 36 — Successive Carriage</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79724" lims:id="79724" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>In the case of carriage to be performed by various successive carriers and falling within the definition set out in paragraph 3 of Article 1, each carrier which accepts passengers, baggage or cargo is subject to the rules set out in this Convention and is deemed to be one of the parties to the contract of carriage in so far as the contract deals with that part of the carriage which is performed under its supervision.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79725" lims:id="79725" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>In the case of carriage of this nature, the passenger or any person entitled to compensation in respect of him or her can take action only against the carrier which performed the carriage during which the accident or the delay occurred, save in the case where, by express agreement, the first carrier has assumed liability for the whole journey.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79726" lims:id="79726" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>As regards baggage or cargo, the passenger or consignor will have a right of action against the first carrier, and the passenger or consignee who is entitled to delivery will have a right of action against the last carrier, and further, each may take action against the carrier which performed the carriage during which the destruction, loss, damage or delay took place. These carriers will be jointly and severally liable to the passenger or to the consignor or consignee.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79727" lims:id="79727"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79728" lims:id="79728" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 37 — Right of Recourse against Third Parties</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79729" lims:id="79729" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Nothing in this Convention shall prejudice the question whether a person liable for damage in accordance with its provisions has a right of recourse against any other person.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79730" lims:id="79730"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79731" lims:id="79731" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>Chapter IV</Label><TitleText>Combined Carriage</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79732" lims:id="79732"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79733" lims:id="79733" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 38 — Combined Carriage</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79734" lims:id="79734" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>In the case of combined carriage performed partly by air and partly by any other mode of carriage, the provisions of this Convention shall, subject to paragraph 4 of Article 18, apply only to the carriage by air, provided that the carriage by air falls within the terms of Article 1.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79735" lims:id="79735" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Nothing in this Convention shall prevent the parties in the case of combined carriage from inserting in the document of air carriage conditions relating to other modes of carriage, provided that the provisions of this Convention are observed as regards the carriage by air.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79736" lims:id="79736"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79737" lims:id="79737" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>Chapter V</Label><TitleText>Carriage by Air Performed by a Person Other Than the Contracting Carrier</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79738" lims:id="79738"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79739" lims:id="79739" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 39 — Contracting Carrier — Actual Carrier</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79740" lims:id="79740" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The provisions of this Chapter apply when a person (hereinafter referred to as “the contracting carrier”) as a principal makes a contract of carriage governed by this Convention with a passenger or consignor or with a person acting on behalf of the passenger or consignor, and another person (hereinafter referred to as “the actual carrier”) performs, by virtue of authority from the contracting carrier, the whole or part of the carriage, but is not with respect to such part a successive carrier within the meaning of this Convention. Such authority shall be presumed in the absence of proof to the contrary.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79741" lims:id="79741"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79742" lims:id="79742" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 40 — Respective Liability of Contracting and Actual Carriers</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79743" lims:id="79743" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>If an actual carrier performs the whole or part of carriage which, according to the contract referred to in Article 39, is governed by this Convention, both the contracting carrier and the actual carrier shall, except as otherwise provided in this Chapter, be subject to the rules of this Convention, the former for the whole of the carriage contemplated in the contract, the latter solely for the carriage which it performs.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79744" lims:id="79744"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79745" lims:id="79745" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 41 — Mutual Liability</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79746" lims:id="79746" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>The acts and omissions of the actual carrier and of its servants and agents acting within the scope of their employment shall, in relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, be deemed to be also those of the contracting carrier.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79747" lims:id="79747" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>The acts and omissions of the contracting carrier and of its servants and agents acting within the scope of their employment shall, in relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, be deemed to be also those of the actual carrier. Nevertheless, no such act or omission shall subject the actual carrier to liability exceeding the amounts referred to in Articles 21, 22, 23 and 24. Any special agreement under which the contracting carrier assumes obligations not imposed by this Convention or any waiver of rights or defences conferred by this Convention or any special declaration of interest in delivery at destination contemplated in Article 22 shall not affect the actual carrier unless agreed to by it.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79748" lims:id="79748"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79749" lims:id="79749" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 42 — Addressee of Complaints and Instructions</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79750" lims:id="79750" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any complaint to be made or instruction to be given under this Convention to the carrier shall have the same effect whether addressed to the contracting carrier or to the actual carrier. Nevertheless, instructions referred to in Article 12 shall only be effective if addressed to the contracting carrier.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79751" lims:id="79751"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79752" lims:id="79752" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 43 — Servants and Agents</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79753" lims:id="79753" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, any servant or agent of that carrier or of the contracting carrier shall, if they prove that they acted within the scope of their employment, be entitled to avail themselves of the conditions and limits of liability which are applicable under this Convention to the carrier whose servant or agent they are, unless it is proved that they acted in a manner that prevents the limits of liability from being invoked in accordance with this Convention.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79754" lims:id="79754"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79755" lims:id="79755" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 44 — Aggregation of Damages</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79756" lims:id="79756" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, the aggregate of the amounts recoverable from that carrier and the contracting carrier, and from their servants and agents acting within the scope of their employment, shall not exceed the highest amount which could be awarded against either the contracting carrier or the actual carrier under this Convention, but none of the persons mentioned shall be liable for a sum in excess of the limit applicable to that person.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79757" lims:id="79757"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79758" lims:id="79758" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 45 — Addressee of Claims</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79759" lims:id="79759" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>In relation to the carriage performed by the actual carrier, an action for damages may be brought, at the option of the plaintiff, against that carrier or the contracting carrier, or against both together or separately. If the action is brought against only one of those carriers, that carrier shall have the right to require the other carrier to be joined in the proceedings, the procedure and effects being governed by the law of the court seised of the case.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79760" lims:id="79760"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79761" lims:id="79761" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 46 — Additional Jurisdiction</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79762" lims:id="79762" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any action for damages contemplated in Article 45 must be brought, at the option of the plaintiff, in the territory of one of the States Parties, either before a court in which an action may be brought against the contracting carrier, as provided in Article 33, or before the court having jurisdiction at the place where the actual carrier has its domicile or its principal place of business.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79763" lims:id="79763"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79764" lims:id="79764" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 47 — Invalidity of Contractual Provisions</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79765" lims:id="79765" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any contractual provision tending to relieve the contracting carrier or the actual carrier of liability under this Chapter or to fix a lower limit than that which is applicable according to this Chapter shall be null and void, but the nullity of any such provision does not involve the nullity of the whole contract, which shall remain subject to the provisions of this Chapter.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79766" lims:id="79766"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79767" lims:id="79767" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 48 — Mutual Relations of Contracting and Actual Carriers</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79768" lims:id="79768" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Except as provided in Article 45, nothing in this Chapter shall affect the rights and obligations of the carriers between themselves, including any right of recourse or indemnification.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79769" lims:id="79769"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79770" lims:id="79770" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>Chapter VI</Label><TitleText>Other Provisions</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79771" lims:id="79771"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79772" lims:id="79772" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 49 — Mandatory Application</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79773" lims:id="79773" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Any clause contained in the contract of carriage and all special agreements entered into before the damage occurred by which the parties purport to infringe the rules laid down by this Convention, whether by deciding the law to be applied, or by altering the rules as to jurisdiction, shall be null and void.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79774" lims:id="79774"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79775" lims:id="79775" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 50 — Insurance</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79776" lims:id="79776" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>States Parties shall require their carriers to maintain adequate insurance covering their liability under this Convention. A carrier may be required by the State Party into which it operates to furnish evidence that it maintains adequate insurance covering its liability under this Convention.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79777" lims:id="79777"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79778" lims:id="79778" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 51 — Carriage Performed in Extraordinary Circumstances</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79779" lims:id="79779" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The provisions of Articles 3 to 5, 7 and 8 relating to the documentation of carriage shall not apply in the case of carriage performed in extraordinary circumstances outside the normal scope of a carrier's business.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79780" lims:id="79780"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79781" lims:id="79781" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 52 — Definition of Days</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79782" lims:id="79782" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The expression “days” when used in this Convention means calendar days, not working days.</Text></Provision></Group></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79783" lims:id="79783"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79784" lims:id="79784" format-ref="group1-part"><Label>Chapter VII</Label><TitleText>Final Clauses</TitleText></GroupHeading><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79785" lims:id="79785"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79786" lims:id="79786" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 53 — Signature, Ratification and Entry into Force</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79787" lims:id="79787" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>This Convention shall be open for signature in Montreal on 28 May 1999 by States participating in the International Conference on Air Law held at Montreal from 10 to 28 May 1999. After 28 May 1999, the Convention shall be open to all States for signature at the Headquarters of the International Civil Aviation Organization in Montreal until it enters into force in accordance with paragraph 6 of this Article.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79788" lims:id="79788" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>This Convention shall similarly be open for signature by Regional Economic Integration Organisations. For the purpose of this Convention, a “Regional Economic Integration Organisation” means any organisation which is constituted by sovereign States of a given region which has competence in respect of certain matters governed by this Convention and has been duly authorized to sign and to ratify, accept, approve or accede to this Convention. A reference to a “State Party” or “States Parties” in this Convention, otherwise than in paragraph 2 of Article 1, paragraph 1(b) of Article 3, paragraph (b) of Article 5, Articles 23, 33, 46 and paragraph (b) of Article 57, applies equally to a Regional Economic Integration Organisation. For the purpose of Article 24, the references to “a majority of the States Parties” and “one-third of the States Parties” shall not apply to a Regional Economic Integration Organisation.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79789" lims:id="79789" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>This Convention shall be subject to ratification by States and by Regional Economic Integration Organisations which have signed it.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79790" lims:id="79790" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>4</Label><Text>Any State or Regional Economic Integration Organisation which does not sign this Convention may accept, approve or accede to it at any time.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79791" lims:id="79791" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>5</Label><Text>Instruments of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession shall be deposited with the International Civil Aviation Organization, which is hereby designated the Depositary.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79792" lims:id="79792" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>6</Label><Text>This Convention shall enter into force on the sixtieth day following the date of deposit of the thirtieth instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession with the Depositary between the States which have deposited such instrument. An instrument deposited by a Regional Economic Integration Organisation shall not be counted for the purpose of this paragraph.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79793" lims:id="79793" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>7</Label><Text>For other States and for other Regional Economic Integration Organisations, this Convention shall take effect sixty days following the date of deposit of the instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79794" lims:id="79794" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>8</Label><Text>The Depositary shall promptly notify all signatories and States Parties of:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79795" lims:id="79795" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>each signature of this Convention and date thereof;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79796" lims:id="79796" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>each deposit of an instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession and date thereof;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79797" lims:id="79797" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the date of entry into force of this Convention;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79798" lims:id="79798" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the date of the coming into force of any revision of the limits of liability established under this Convention;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79799" lims:id="79799" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>any denunciation under Article 54.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79800" lims:id="79800"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79801" lims:id="79801" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 54 — Denunciation</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79802" lims:id="79802" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>Any State Party may denounce this Convention by written notification to the Depositary.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79803" lims:id="79803" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Denunciation shall take effect one hundred and eighty days following the date on which notification is received by the Depositary.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79804" lims:id="79804"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79805" lims:id="79805" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 55 — Relationship with Other Warsaw Convention Instruments</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79806" lims:id="79806" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This Convention shall prevail over any rules which apply to international carriage by air:</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79807" lims:id="79807" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>between States Parties to this Convention by virtue of those States commonly being Party to</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79808" lims:id="79808" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the <Emphasis style="italic">Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air</Emphasis> Signed at Warsaw on 12 October 1929 (hereinafter called the Warsaw Convention);</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79809" lims:id="79809" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the <Emphasis style="italic">Protocol to Amend the Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air Signed at Warsaw on 12 October 1929</Emphasis>, Done at The Hague on 28 September 1955 (hereinafter called The Hague Protocol);</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79810" lims:id="79810" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the <Emphasis style="italic">Convention, Supplementary to the Warsaw Convention, for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air Performed by a Person Other Than the Contracting Carrier</Emphasis>, signed at Guadalajara on 18 September 1961 (hereinafter called the Guadalajara Convention);</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79811" lims:id="79811" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the <Emphasis style="italic">Protocol to Amend the Convention for the Unification of Certain Rules Relating to International Carriage by Air Signed at Warsaw on 12 October 1929 as Amended by the Protocol Done at The Hague on 28 September 1955</Emphasis> Signed at Guatemala City on 8 March 1971 (hereinafter called the Guatemala City Protocol);</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79812" lims:id="79812" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>Additional Protocol Nos. 1 to 3 and Montreal Protocol No. 4 to amend the Warsaw Convention as amended by The Hague Protocol or the Warsaw Convention as amended by both The Hague Protocol and the Guatemala City Protocol Signed at Montreal on 25 September 1975 (hereinafter called the Montreal Protocols); or</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79813" lims:id="79813" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>within the territory of any single State Party to this Convention by virtue of that State being Party to one or more of the instruments referred to in sub-paragraphs (a) to (e) above.</Text></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79814" lims:id="79814"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79815" lims:id="79815" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 56 — States with More Than One System of Law</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79816" lims:id="79816" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>1</Label><Text>If a State has two or more territorial units in which different systems of law are applicable in relation to matters dealt with in this Convention, it may at the time of signature, ratification, acceptance, approval or accession declare that this Convention shall extend to all its territorial units or only to one or more of them and may modify this declaration by submitting another declaration at any time.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79817" lims:id="79817" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>2</Label><Text>Any such declaration shall be notified to the Depositary and shall state expressly the territorial units to which the Convention applies.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79818" lims:id="79818" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>3</Label><Text>In relation to a State Party which has made such a declaration:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79819" lims:id="79819" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>references in Article 23 to “national currency” shall be construed as referring to the currency of the relevant territorial unit of that State; and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79820" lims:id="79820" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the reference in Article 28 to “national law” shall be construed as referring to the law of the relevant territorial unit of that State.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group><Group lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79821" lims:id="79821"><GroupHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79822" lims:id="79822" format-ref="group2-division"><TitleText><Emphasis style="italic">Article 57 — Reservations</Emphasis></TitleText></GroupHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79823" lims:id="79823" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>No reservation may be made to this Convention except that a State Party may at any time declare by a notification addressed to the Depositary that this Convention shall not apply to:</Text><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79824" lims:id="79824" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>international carriage by air performed and operated directly by that State Party for non-commercial purposes in respect to its functions and duties as a sovereign State; and/or</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79825" lims:id="79825" format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the carriage of persons, cargo and baggage for its military authorities on aircraft registered in or leased by that State Party, the whole capacity of which has been reserved by or on behalf of such authorities.</Text></Provision></Provision></Group></Group><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79826" lims:id="79826" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned Plenipotentiaries, having been duly authorized, have signed this Convention.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79827" lims:id="79827" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>DONE at Montreal on the 28th day of May of the year one thousand nine hundred and ninety-nine in the English, Arabic, Chinese, French, Russian and Spanish languages, all texts being equally authentic. This Convention shall remain deposited in the archives of the International Civil Aviation Organization, and certified copies thereof shall be transmitted by the Depositary to all States Parties to this Convention, as well as to all States Parties to the Warsaw Convention, The Hague Protocol, the Guadalajara Convention, the Guatemala City Protocol, and the Montreal Protocols.</Text></Provision></DocumentInternal><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-11-04" lims:fid="79829" lims:id="79829">2001, c. 31, s. 5</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule></Statute>