<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Statute lims:pit-date="2003-07-01" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-07-01" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202824" lims:id="202824" bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202825" lims:id="202825"><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202826" lims:id="202826">An Act respecting the export of certain articles</LongTitle><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202827" lims:id="202827" status="official">Export Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202828" lims:id="202828">Export</RunningHead><BillHistory lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202829" lims:id="202829"><Stages lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202831" lims:id="202831"><ConsolidatedNumber official="yes">E-18</ConsolidatedNumber></Chapter></Identification><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202832" lims:id="202832"><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202833" lims:id="202833"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202834" lims:id="202834">Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-18">Export Act</XRefExternal>.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202836" lims:id="202836">R.S., c. E-16, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202837" lims:id="202837"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202838" lims:id="202838">Export duties on certain logs and pulpwood</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202839" lims:id="202839"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If any country imposes a duty on any of the articles enumerated in the schedule when imported into that country from Canada, the Governor in Council may by proclamation declare an export duty chargeable on pine, Douglas fir, spruce, fir balsam, cedar and hemlock logs and pulpwood exported from Canada to that country.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202840" lims:id="202840"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202841" lims:id="202841">Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The export duty declared under subsection (1) shall not exceed three dollars per thousand feet, board measure, but in case of the export of logs or pulpwood in shorter lengths than nine feet, a rate per cord may be levied in the same manner not greater than the equivalent of the rate of three dollars per thousand feet, board measure.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202843" lims:id="202843">R.S., c. E-16, s. 2</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202844" lims:id="202844"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202845" lims:id="202845">Export duties on certain ores</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may by proclamation impose the following export duties on the following ores and metals:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202846" lims:id="202846"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on nickel contained in matte, in the ore or in any crude or partially manufactured state, when exported from Canada, an export duty not exceeding ten cents per pound;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202847" lims:id="202847"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on copper contained in any matte or ore that also contains nickel, when exported from Canada, an export duty not exceeding two cents per pound;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202848" lims:id="202848"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>on ores that contain copper or any metal other than nickel or lead, when exported from Canada, an export duty not exceeding fifteen per cent of the value of the ores; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202849" lims:id="202849"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>on lead ores, and on lead and silver ores, when exported from Canada to a country that imposes an import duty on lead in bars, or in the form of pig lead, in excess of the import duty on lead contained in lead ores, or in lead and silver ores, an export duty on the lead contained in the ores so exported from Canada to an amount per pound equivalent to the excess.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202851" lims:id="202851">R.S., c. E-16, s. 3</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202852" lims:id="202852"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202853" lims:id="202853">When duties chargeable</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202854" lims:id="202854"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The export duties provided for by this Act are chargeable after the publication of the proclamation by which they are declared chargeable or imposed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202855" lims:id="202855"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202856" lims:id="202856">Duties may be removed and reimposed</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may by proclamation remove and reimpose any export duty.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202858" lims:id="202858">R.S., c. E-16, s. 4</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202859" lims:id="202859"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202860" lims:id="202860">Prohibiting export</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202861" lims:id="202861"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may by regulation prohibit the exportation from Canada of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202862" lims:id="202862"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>petroleum in its crude or partly manufactured state; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202863" lims:id="202863"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>pulpwood of the variety, kind, place of origin or having the particulars of identification or ownership or production described in the regulation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202864" lims:id="202864"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202865" lims:id="202865">Laid before Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every regulation made pursuant to subsection (1) shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament within the first fifteen days of the session next after the date thereof, and the regulation shall remain in force until the day immediately succeeding the date of prorogation of that session of Parliament and no longer unless during the session it is approved by resolution of both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202867" lims:id="202867">R.S., c. E-16, s. 5</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202868" lims:id="202868"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202869" lims:id="202869">Restrictions on the movement of intoxicating liquors</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202870" lims:id="202870"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other statute or law, any regulation made thereunder or any bond, agreement or other instrument relating thereto,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202871" lims:id="202871"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no intoxicating liquor held in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-52.6">Customs Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-14">Excise Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="E-14.1">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal> shall be released or removed from any warehouse or other building or place in which the liquor is stored in any case in which the liquor proposed to be removed is destined for delivery in any country into which the importation of the liquor is prohibited by law;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202872" lims:id="202872"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>it is unlawful to grant a clearance to any vessel having on board any intoxicating liquor destined for delivery in any country into which the importation of the liquor is prohibited by law; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202873" lims:id="202873"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>it is unlawful to make any entry for exportation of any intoxicating liquor destined for delivery in any country into which the importation of the liquor is prohibited by law.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202874" lims:id="202874"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202875" lims:id="202875">Definition of <DefinedTermEn>intoxicating liquor</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>intoxicating liquor</DefinedTermEn> includes every spirituous or malt liquor, and every wine, and any and every combination of liquors or drinks that is intoxicating, and any mixed liquor capable of being used as a beverage, and part of which is spirituous or otherwise intoxicating.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202876" lims:id="202876"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202877" lims:id="202877">Orders and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make such orders and regulations as he may consider necessary for giving effect to any of the provisions of this section.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-07-01" lims:fid="202879" lims:id="202879">R.S., 1985, c. E-18, s. 6; R.S., 1985, c. 1 (2nd Supp.), s. 213; 2002, c. 22, s. 393</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202880" lims:id="202880" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202881" lims:id="202881"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 2)</OriginatingRef></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202882" lims:id="202882" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Timber or lumber or wood, namely: lumber and timber planks and boards of amaranth, cocoboral, boxwood, cherry, chestnut, walnut, gumwood, mahogany, pitch pine, rosewood, sandalwood, sycamore, spanish cedar, oak, hickory, whitewood, African teak, black-heart ebony, lignum vitae, red cedar, redwood, satinwood and white ash, when not otherwise manufactured than roughsawn or split or creosoted, vulcanized or treated by any other preserving process; sawed or split boards, planks, deals and other lumber when not further manufactured than dressed on one side only or creosoted, vulcanized or treated by any preserving process; pine and spruce clapboards; timber or lumber hewn or sawed, squared or sided or creosoted; laths, pickets and palings; staves not listed or jointed of wood of all kinds; firewood, handle, heading, stave, and shingle bolts, hop poles, fence posts, railroad ties; hubs for wheels, posts, last blocks, wagon, oar, gun, heading and all like blocks or sticks rough hewn, or sawed only; felloes of hickory wood, rough sawn to shape only, or rough sawn and bent to shape, not planed, smoothed or otherwise manufactured; hickory billets and hickory lumber, sawn to shape for spokes of wheels, but not further manufactured; hickory spokes, rough turned, not tenoned mitred, throated, faced, sized, cut to length, round tenoned or polished; shingles of wood; the wood of the persimmon and dogwood trees; and logs and round unmanufactured timber, ship timber or ship planking, not specially enumerated or provided for in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-54.011">Customs Tariff</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="202884" lims:id="202884">R.S., c. E-16, Sch</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule></Statute>