<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Statute lims:pit-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:current-date="2019-06-21" lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338333" lims:id="338333" bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338334" lims:id="338334"><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338335" lims:id="338335">An Act respecting Kingsmere Park</LongTitle><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338336" lims:id="338336" status="official">Kingsmere Park Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338337" lims:id="338337">Kingsmere Park</RunningHead><BillHistory lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338338" lims:id="338338"><Stages lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338340" lims:id="338340"><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">K-0.8</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="yes"><AnnualStatuteNumber>161</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>1952</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338341" lims:id="338341"><Preamble lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338342" lims:id="338342" salutation="no"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338343" lims:id="338343" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338344" lims:id="338344">Preamble</MarginalNote><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Whereas</Emphasis>, pursuant to the Will of the late the Right Honourable William Lyon Mackenzie King, P.C., O.M., there has been vested in His Majesty in right of Canada certain property at Kingsmere in the Province of Quebec hereinafter referred to as “Kingsmere Park”;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338345" lims:id="338345" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">And Whereas</Emphasis> it is advisable to make provision for the administration of that property in accordance with the terms of the Will;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338346" lims:id="338346"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338347" lims:id="338347" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Now</Emphasis>, <Emphasis style="smallcaps">Therefore</Emphasis>, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338348" lims:id="338348"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338349" lims:id="338349" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338350" lims:id="338350"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338351" lims:id="338351">Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="K-0.8">Kingsmere Park Act</XRefExternal>. <HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem>1951, c. 18, s. 1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338352" lims:id="338352"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338353" lims:id="338353">Federal District Commission to administer Kingsmere Park</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338354" lims:id="338354"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the Federal District Commission shall administer Kingsmere Park in accordance with the desires and purposes expressed in the late Mr. King’s Will (the relevant portion of which is set out in the Schedule).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338355" lims:id="338355"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338356" lims:id="338356">Buildings, orchards, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Works and Government Services shall manage and control the buildings in Kingsmere Park and the yards, orchards and gardens appurtenant thereto in such manner as, in his opinion, will realize the desires and purposes expressed in the Will.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338357" lims:id="338357"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338358" lims:id="338358">G. in C. may lease</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may authorize the lease or licence of any of the buildings in Kingsmere Park, with the yards, orchards and gardens appurtenant thereto, for the better conservation thereof or for the purpose of realizing the desires and purposes expressed in the Will.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338359" lims:id="338359"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338360" lims:id="338360">Demolition of buildings</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Works and Government Services may, with the approval of the Governor in Council, demolish any building in Kingsmere Park if he considers it advisable for the purpose of realizing the desires and purposes expressed in the Will.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338361" lims:id="338361"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338362" lims:id="338362">G. in C. may describe limits</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may describe the limits of Kingsmere Park for the purposes of this Act, and, in case of doubt, the Governor in Council may determine the limits of the yards, orchards and gardens appurtenant to the buildings in Kingsmere Park.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338364" lims:id="338364">R.S., 1952, c. 161, s. 2; 1996, c. 16, s. 60</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338365" lims:id="338365"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338366" lims:id="338366">Country home for Prime Minister</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338367" lims:id="338367"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, set aside any part of Kingsmere Park to be used, as suggested in the Will, as a country home for the holder of the office of Prime Minister of Canada and may revoke any order that has been so made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338368" lims:id="338368"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where any part of Kingsmere Park has been set aside by order made under subsection (1), the property so set aside shall, until the order is revoked, be deemed to be included in the properties described in the Schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Prime Minister’s Residence Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338370" lims:id="338370">1951, c. 18, s. 3</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338371" lims:id="338371"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338372" lims:id="338372">G. in C. may give directions</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other provision in this Act, the Minister of Public Works and Government Services and the Federal District Commission shall comply with any general or special direction of the Governor in Council as to the manner in which Kingsmere Park shall be administered or as to the manner in which the desires or purposes expressed in the Will shall be realized.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338374" lims:id="338374">R.S., 1952, c. 161, s. 4; 1996, c. 16, s. 60</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section></Body><Schedule lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:lastAmendedDate="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338375" lims:id="338375" spanlanguages="no" bilingual="no"><ScheduleFormHeading lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338376" lims:id="338376"><Label>SCHEDULE</Label><TitleText>Portions of Mr. King’s Will</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338377" lims:id="338377" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>“24</Label><Text>The cherished objective of being able to present my Kingsmere properties as a thank-offering for what has come to me in the way of opportunities of public service, I believe I have been able to realize, and I hereby bequeath to the Government of Canada as a public park in trust for the citizens of Canada, subject to certain reservations hereinafter referred to, my several properties at Kingsmere, in the Province of Quebec, amounting in all to nearly Five Hundred (500) acres, and the houses and other buildings erected thereon. The precise boundaries are set forth in the several deeds attached hereto.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338378" lims:id="338378" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>25</Label><Text>In making this bequest, I express the wish that the lands at Kingsmere may be maintained as nearly as possible in their present state; that they will be developed as parkland, and that they will form a wild life sanctuary and will continue to have the character of a natural forest reserve.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338379" lims:id="338379" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>26</Label><Text>Believing that my successors in the office of Prime Minister may find, as I have found, a renewal of strength in this quiet place, as well as exceptional opportunities for conference on national and international affairs, I hope that the Government of Canada will consider the possibility of setting aside a part of the Kingsmere property as a country home for the holder of the office of Prime Minister of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338380" lims:id="338380" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>27</Label><Text>Inasmuch as relatives and friends of mine have spent their summers, or part of them, at Kingsmere as my guests or tenants, I hope they may continue to enjoy the summer homes to which they have become accustomed; and that other appropriate use may be made of them. I would therefore ask that the Government should authorize my Trustees to provide that, for a period of three years after my death, the cottages and such of their contents as are mine and are not otherwise disposed of in accordance with this my Will shall be available, rent-free, for use by my sister and the members of her family, by the members of my late brother’s family, and by such other persons as may be designated by my Trustees.</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338381" lims:id="338381" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Label>28</Label><Text>My Trustees are hereby authorized to dispose of all my possessions in the cottages and other buildings or on the property as they believe will be most in accord with my own wishes; and to meet such expenses as may be necessarily incurred for the maintenance of these cottages for a period of three years.”</Text></Provision><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2003-01-01" lims:fid="338383" lims:id="338383">1951, c. 18, Sch</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Schedule></Statute>