<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Statute lims:pit-date="2022-12-15" hasPreviousVersion="true" lims:lastAmendedDate="2020-07-01" lims:current-date="2022-12-31" lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417986" lims:id="417986" bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en" in-force="yes" xmlns:lims="http://justice.gc.ca/lims"><Identification lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417987" lims:id="417987"><LongTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417988" lims:id="417988">An Act to protect human health and safety and the environment by regulating products used for the control of pests</LongTitle><ShortTitle lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417989" lims:id="417989" status="official">Pest Control Products Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417990" lims:id="417990">Pest Control Products</RunningHead><BillHistory lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417991" lims:id="417991"><Stages lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417992" lims:id="417992" stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2002</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>12</DD></Date></Stages><Stages lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" stage="consolidation"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>1</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417994" lims:id="417994"><ConsolidatedNumber official="no">P-9.01</ConsolidatedNumber><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="no"><AnnualStatuteNumber>28</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2002</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417995" lims:id="417995"><Preamble lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417996" lims:id="417996" salutation="no"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417997" lims:id="417997" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS the availability and use of pest control products pose potential risks, both directly and indirectly, to the health, safety and well-being of individuals in Canada and to the environment;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417998" lims:id="417998" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS pest management plays a significant role in diverse areas of the economy and other aspects of the quality of life throughout Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="417999" lims:id="417999" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS pest control products of acceptable risk and value can contribute significantly to the attainment of the goals of sustainable pest management;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418000" lims:id="418000" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS the goals of sustainable pest management are to meet society’s needs for human health protection, food and fibre production and resource utilization and to conserve or enhance natural resources and the quality of the environment for future generations, in an economically viable manner;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418001" lims:id="418001" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS Canada and the provinces and territories have traditionally administered complementary regulatory systems designed to protect individuals and the environment, including its biological diversity, from unacceptable risks posed by pest control products, and it is important that such an approach be continued in order to achieve mutually desired results efficiently, without regulatory conflict or duplication;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418002" lims:id="418002" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS it is in the national interest that the primary objective of the federal regulatory system be to prevent unacceptable risks to individuals and the environment from the use of pest control products,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418003" lims:id="418003" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the attainment of the objectives of the federal regulatory system continue to be pursued through a scientifically-based national registration system that addresses risks to human health and the environment both before and after registration and applies to the regulation of pest control products throughout Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418004" lims:id="418004" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>pest control products of acceptable risk be registered for use only if it is shown that their use would be efficacious and if conditions of registration can be established to prevent adverse health impact or pollution of the environment,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418005" lims:id="418005" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>in assessing risks to individuals, consideration be given to aggregate exposure to pest control products, cumulative effects of pest control products and the different sensitivities to pest control products of major identifiable subgroups, including pregnant women, infants, children, women and seniors,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418006" lims:id="418006" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>pest control products be regulated in a manner that supports sustainable development, being development that meets the needs of the present without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418007" lims:id="418007" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the federal regulatory system be designed to minimize health and environmental risks posed by pest control products and to encourage the development and implementation of innovative, sustainable pest management strategies, for example by facilitating access to pest control products that pose lower risks, and encouraging the development and use of alternative, non-toxic, ecological pest control approaches, strategies and products,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418008" lims:id="418008" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>applicable policies of the Government of Canada that are consistent with the objectives of this Act be duly reflected in decisions respecting the regulation of pest control products,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418009" lims:id="418009" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>there be cooperation among federal departments in the development of policies to pursue the attainment of the objectives of this Act, and that those policies take into account advice from diverse sources throughout the country,</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418010" lims:id="418010" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the provinces and territories and those persons whose interests and concerns are affected by the federal regulatory system be accorded a reasonable opportunity to parti­cipate in the regulatory system in ways that are consistent with the attainment of its objectives, and</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418011" lims:id="418011" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>the federal regulatory system be administered efficiently and effectively in accordance with the foregoing principles and objectives and in a manner that recognizes the various interests and concerns affected and, where consistent with the primary objective of the system, minimizes the negative impact on economic viability and competitiveness;</Text></Provision><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418012" lims:id="418012" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS Canada must be able to fulfil its international obligations in relation to pest management;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418013" lims:id="418013"><Provision lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418014" lims:id="418014" format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 28, Preamble; 2016, c. 9, s. 32.</HistoricalNote></Enacts></Introduction><Body lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418016" lims:id="418016"><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418017" lims:id="418017" level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418018" lims:id="418018"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418019" lims:id="418019">Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418020" lims:id="418020" level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418021" lims:id="418021"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418022" lims:id="418022">Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418023" lims:id="418023"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions in this subsection apply in this Act.</Text><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418024" lims:id="418024"><Text><DefinedTermEn>active ingredient</DefinedTermEn> means a component of a pest control product to which the intended effects of the product are attributed and includes a synergist but does not include a solvent, diluent, emulsifier or other component that is not primarily responsible for those effects. (<DefinedTermFr>principe actif</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418025" lims:id="418025"><Text><DefinedTermEn>advertise</DefinedTermEn> includes making a representation by any means for the purpose of directly or indirectly promoting the distribution of a pest control product. (<DefinedTermFr>publicité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418026" lims:id="418026"><Text><DefinedTermEn>analyst</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is appointed or designated as an analyst under section 45. (<DefinedTermFr>analyste</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418027" lims:id="418027"><Text><DefinedTermEn>biological diversity</DefinedTermEn> means the variability among living organisms from all sources, including, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, terrestrial and marine and other aquatic ecosystems and the ecological complexes of which they form a part and includes the diversity within and between species and of ecosystems. (<DefinedTermFr>diversité biologique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418028" lims:id="418028"><Text><DefinedTermEn>biotechnology</DefinedTermEn> means the application of science and engineering in the direct or indirect use of living organisms or parts or products of living organisms in their natural or modified forms. (<DefinedTermFr>biotechnologie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418029" lims:id="418029"><Text><DefinedTermEn>conditions of registration</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418030" lims:id="418030"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any conditions specified by the Minister under paragraph 8(1)(a) or subsection 8(2) or when amending the registration of a pest control product under this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418031" lims:id="418031"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other requirements stated by this Act or the regulations to be conditions of registration. (<DefinedTermFr>conditions d’homologation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418032" lims:id="418032"><Text><DefinedTermEn>confidential business information</DefinedTermEn> means information to which access may be refused under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-1">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> and that meets the requirements of subsection 43(4) or (5). (<DefinedTermFr>renseignements commerciaux confidentiels</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418033" lims:id="418033"><Text><DefinedTermEn>confidential test data</DefinedTermEn> means test data to which access may be refused under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-1">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>données d’essai confidentielles</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418034" lims:id="418034"><Text><DefinedTermEn>distribute</DefinedTermEn> means distribute in any way, whether or not for consideration, and includes sell, offer for sale or distribution, and expose, display or advertise for sale or distribution. (<DefinedTermFr>distribution</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418035" lims:id="418035"><Text><DefinedTermEn>document</DefinedTermEn> means anything on which information that is capable of being understood by a person, or read by a computer or other device, is recorded or marked. (<DefinedTermFr>document</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418036" lims:id="418036"><Text><DefinedTermEn>ecosystem</DefinedTermEn> means a dynamic complex of plant, animal and micro-organism communities and their non-living environment interacting as a functional unit. (<DefinedTermFr>écosystème</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418037" lims:id="418037"><Text><DefinedTermEn>environment</DefinedTermEn> means the components of the Earth and includes</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418038" lims:id="418038"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>air, land and water;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418039" lims:id="418039"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>all layers of the atmosphere;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418040" lims:id="418040"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>all organic and inorganic matter and living organisms; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418041" lims:id="418041"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the interacting natural systems that include components referred to in paragraphs (a) to (c). (<DefinedTermFr>environnement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418042" lims:id="418042"><Text><DefinedTermEn>environmental risk</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a pest control product, means the possibility of harm to the environment, including its biological diversity, resulting from exposure to or use of the product, taking into account its conditions or proposed conditions of registration. (<DefinedTermFr>risque environnemental</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418043" lims:id="418043"><Text><DefinedTermEn>formulant</DefinedTermEn> means any component of a pest control product that is added intentionally to the product and that is not an active ingredient. (<DefinedTermFr>formulant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418044" lims:id="418044"><Text><DefinedTermEn>government policy</DefinedTermEn> means the Toxic Substances Management Policy issued by the Government of Canada in June, 1995, as long as it remains in effect, and any other policies of the Government of Canada that are prescribed. (<DefinedTermFr>politique gouvernementale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418045" lims:id="418045"><Text><DefinedTermEn>health risk</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a pest control product, means the possibility of harm to human health resulting from exposure to or use of the product, taking into account its conditions or proposed conditions of registration. (<DefinedTermFr>risque sanitaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418046" lims:id="418046"><Text><DefinedTermEn>inspector</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who is appointed or designated as an inspector under section 45. (<DefinedTermFr>inspecteur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418047" lims:id="418047"><Text><DefinedTermEn>label</DefinedTermEn> includes any written, printed or graphic matter</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418048" lims:id="418048"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that is or is to be applied or attached to or included in, or that accompanies or is to accompany, a pest control product or a package; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418049" lims:id="418049"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that belongs to a pest control product and is transmitted electronically, in accordance with the regulations. (<DefinedTermFr>étiquette</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418050" lims:id="418050"><Text><DefinedTermEn>manufacture</DefinedTermEn> includes produce, formulate, package, label and prepare for distribution or use. (<DefinedTermFr>fabrication</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418051" lims:id="418051"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Health. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418052" lims:id="418052"><Text><DefinedTermEn>package</DefinedTermEn> includes a container, wrapping, covering or holder in which a pest control product is wholly or partly contained, placed or packed. (<DefinedTermFr>emballage</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418053" lims:id="418053"><Text><DefinedTermEn>penalty</DefinedTermEn> means an administrative monetary penalty imposed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-8.8">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal> for a violation. (<DefinedTermFr>pénalité</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418054" lims:id="418054"><Text><DefinedTermEn>person</DefinedTermEn> means Her Majesty, an individual or an <DefinitionRef>organization</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>personne</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418055" lims:id="418055"><Text><DefinedTermEn>pest</DefinedTermEn> means an animal, a plant or other organism that is injurious, noxious or troublesome, whether directly or indirectly, and an injurious, noxious or troublesome condition or organic function of an animal, a plant or other organism. (<DefinedTermFr>parasite</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418056" lims:id="418056"><Text><DefinedTermEn>pest control product</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418057" lims:id="418057"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a product, an organism or a substance, including a product, an organism or a substance derived through biotechnology, that consists of its active ingredient, formulants and contaminants, and that is manufactured, represented, distributed or used as a means for directly or indirectly controlling, destroying, attracting or repelling a pest or for mitigating or preventing its injurious, noxious or troublesome effects;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418058" lims:id="418058"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an active ingredient that is used to manufacture anything described in paragraph (a); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418059" lims:id="418059"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any other thing that is prescribed to be a pest control product. (<DefinedTermFr>produit antiparasitaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418060" lims:id="418060"><Text><DefinedTermEn>place</DefinedTermEn> includes a means of transport. (<DefinedTermFr>lieu</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418061" lims:id="418061"><Text><DefinedTermEn>prescribed</DefinedTermEn> means prescribed by regulation. (<DefinedTermFr>Version anglaise seulement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418062" lims:id="418062"><Text><DefinedTermEn>Register</DefinedTermEn> means the Register of Pest Control Products established and maintained under section 42. (<DefinedTermFr>Registre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418063" lims:id="418063"><Text><DefinedTermEn>registrant</DefinedTermEn> means a person in whose name a pest control product is registered. (<DefinedTermFr>titulaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418064" lims:id="418064"><Text><DefinedTermEn>test data</DefinedTermEn> means scientific or technical information respecting the health or environmental risks or the value of a pest control product. (<DefinedTermFr>données d’essai</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418065" lims:id="418065"><Text><DefinedTermEn>threshold effect</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a pest control product, means a harmful effect on human health for which the Minister is able to identify a level at which the product will not cause that effect. (<DefinedTermFr>effet de seuil</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418066" lims:id="418066"><Text><DefinedTermEn>value</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a pest control product, means the product’s actual or potential contribution to pest management, taking into account its conditions or proposed conditions of registration, and includes the product’s</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418067" lims:id="418067"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>efficacy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418068" lims:id="418068"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>effect on host organisms in connection with which it is intended to be used; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418069" lims:id="418069"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>health, safety and environmental benefits and social and economic impact. (<DefinedTermFr>valeur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418070" lims:id="418070"><Text><DefinedTermEn>violation</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following that may be proceeded with in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-8.8">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418071" lims:id="418071"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any contravention of any provision of this Act or of a regulation made under this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418072" lims:id="418072"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any refusal or neglect to perform any duty imposed by or under this Act. (<DefinedTermFr>violation</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418073" lims:id="418073"><Text><DefinedTermEn>workplace</DefinedTermEn> means a place where an individual works for remuneration. (<DefinedTermFr>lieu de travail</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418074" lims:id="418074"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418075" lims:id="418075">Acceptable risks</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, the health or environmental risks of a pest control product are acceptable if there is reasonable certainty that no harm to human health, future generations or the environment will result from exposure to or use of the product, taking into account its conditions or proposed conditions of registration.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418077" lims:id="418077">2002, c. 28, s. 2; 2016, c. 9, s. 33</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418078" lims:id="418078" level="1"><TitleText>Her Majesty</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418079" lims:id="418079"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418080" lims:id="418080">Binding on Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>This Act is binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418081" lims:id="418081" level="1"><TitleText>Mandate</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418082" lims:id="418082"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418083" lims:id="418083">Primary objective</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418084" lims:id="418084"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the administration of this Act, the Minister’s primary objective is to prevent unacceptable risks to individuals and the environment from the use of pest control products.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418085" lims:id="418085"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418086" lims:id="418086">Ancillary objectives</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Consistent with, and in furtherance of, the primary objective, the Minister shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418087" lims:id="418087"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>support sustainable development designed to enable the needs of the present to be met without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418088" lims:id="418088"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>seek to minimize health and environmental risks posed by pest control products and encourage the development and implementation of innovative, sustainable pest management strategies by facilitating access to pest control products that pose lower risks and by other appropriate measures;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418089" lims:id="418089"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>encourage public awareness in relation to pest control products by informing the public, facilitating public access to relevant information and public participation in the decision-making process; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418090" lims:id="418090"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>ensure that only those pest control products that are determined to be of acceptable value are approved for use in Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418092" lims:id="418092">2002, c. 28, s. 4; 2016, c. 9, s. 34</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418093" lims:id="418093"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418094" lims:id="418094">Protection of future generations</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Text>For greater certainty, protection and consideration afforded to children in this Act shall also extend to future generations.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418095" lims:id="418095" level="1"><TitleText>Advisory Council</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418096" lims:id="418096"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418097" lims:id="418097">Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418098" lims:id="418098"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In carrying out duties under this Act, the Minister may establish an advisory council of persons whose interests and concerns are affected by this Act, and may specify the functions of the council and the means by which it is to perform those functions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418099" lims:id="418099"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418100" lims:id="418100">Report to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The advisory council shall give any report that it makes, including its recommendations and the reasons for them, to the Minister, who shall place it in the Register.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418101" lims:id="418101" level="1"><TitleText>Prohibitions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418102" lims:id="418102"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418103" lims:id="418103">Unregistered pest control products</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418104" lims:id="418104"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall manufacture, possess, handle, store, transport, import, distribute or use a pest control product that is not registered under this Act, except as otherwise authorized under subsection 21(5) or 41(1), section 48 or 51, any of sections 53 to 59 or the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418105" lims:id="418105"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418106" lims:id="418106">Conditions of registration</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except as otherwise authorized under section 53.3 or 54, no person shall manufacture, import, export or distribute a registered pest control product unless it conforms to the conditions of registration respecting its composition and the person complies with the other conditions of registration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418107" lims:id="418107"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418108" lims:id="418108">Packaging and labelling</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Except as otherwise authorized under section 53, 53.3 or 54, no person shall store, import, export or distribute a pest control product that is not packaged and labelled in accordance with the regulations and, if it is registered, the conditions of registration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418109" lims:id="418109"><Label>(4)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2016, c. 9, s. 35]</Repealed></Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418110" lims:id="418110"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418111" lims:id="418111">Misuse of pest control products</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person shall handle, store, transport, use or dispose of a pest control product in a way that is inconsistent with</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418112" lims:id="418112"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the regulations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418113" lims:id="418113"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the product is registered, the directions on the label recorded in the Register, subject to the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418114" lims:id="418114"><Label>(6)</Label><Text><Repealed>[Repealed, 2016, c. 9, s. 35]</Repealed></Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418115" lims:id="418115"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418116" lims:id="418116">Packaging, labelling and advertisement</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>No person shall package, label or advertise a pest control product in a way that is false, misleading or likely to create an erroneous impression regarding its character, value, quantity, composition, safety or registration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418117" lims:id="418117"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418118" lims:id="418118">Activities that endanger health, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>No person shall manufacture, possess, handle, store, transport, distribute, use or dispose of a pest control product in a way that endangers human health or safety or the environment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418119" lims:id="418119"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418120" lims:id="418120">Alteration, destruction or falsification — required documents</MarginalNote><Label>(8.1)</Label><Text>No person shall alter, destroy or falsify a document that they are required under this Act to keep, maintain or provide.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418121" lims:id="418121"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418122" lims:id="418122">Alteration, possession or use — official documents</MarginalNote><Label>(8.2)</Label><Text>It is prohibited for a person to</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418123" lims:id="418123"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>alter a document issued or made — or in any manner given — under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418124" lims:id="418124"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>have in their possession, or use, a document issued or made — or in any manner given — under this Act that has been altered.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418125" lims:id="418125"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418126" lims:id="418126">Possession or use of documents that resemble official documents</MarginalNote><Label>(8.3)</Label><Text>It is prohibited for a person to have in their possession, or use, any document that has not been issued or made — or in any manner given — under this Act if the document so resembles a document issued or made — or in any manner given — under this Act that it is likely to be mistaken for such a document.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418127" lims:id="418127"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418128" lims:id="418128">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>A person who contravenes any provision of this section is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418129" lims:id="418129"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418130" lims:id="418130"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418132" lims:id="418132">2002, c. 28, s. 6; 2016, c. 9, s. 35</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418133" lims:id="418133" level="1"><TitleText>Registration of Pest Control Products</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418134" lims:id="418134" level="2"><TitleText>Applications for Registration or Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418135" lims:id="418135"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418136" lims:id="418136">Application to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418137" lims:id="418137"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An application to register a pest control product or to amend the product’s registration must be made to the Minister in the form and manner directed by the Minister and must include any information or other thing that is required by the regulations to accompany the application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418138" lims:id="418138"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418139" lims:id="418139">Use of information provided by registrants</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Minister determines that the active ingredient of the applicant’s pest control product is equivalent to the active ingredient of a registered pest control product, the Minister shall, subject to and in accordance with the regulations, permit the applicant to use or rely on any information referred to in subsection (1) that has been provided by any registrant if the Minister is satisfied that the information</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418140" lims:id="418140"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is relevant to the registered pest control product that contains the equivalent active ingredient; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418141" lims:id="418141"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is necessary to support the application.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418142" lims:id="418142"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418143" lims:id="418143">Foreign review or evaluation</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), the applicant may include information that is available from a review or evaluation of a pest control product conducted by the government of another member country of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development if the proposed use of the pest control product in Canada would be under conditions similar to those under which the foreign review or evaluation was conducted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418144" lims:id="418144"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418145" lims:id="418145">Evaluation of pest control product</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Minister is satisfied that the application has been made in accordance with subsection (1), (2) or (2.1), the Minister shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418146" lims:id="418146"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in accordance with the regulations, if any, conduct any evaluations that the Minister considers necessary with respect to the health or environmental risks or the value of the pest control product;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418147" lims:id="418147"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>expedite evaluations with respect to a pest control product that may reasonably be expected to pose lower health or environmental risks; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418148" lims:id="418148"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>carry out any consultation required by section 28.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418149" lims:id="418149"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418150" lims:id="418150">Other information</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by delivering a notice in writing, request an applicant to provide the Minister with other information in support of the application within the time and in the form specified in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418151" lims:id="418151"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418152" lims:id="418152">Denial of application</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister shall deny an application if the applicant does not comply with a notice under subsection (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418153" lims:id="418153"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418154" lims:id="418154">Burden of persuasion and consideration of information</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>During an evaluation,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418155" lims:id="418155"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the applicant has the burden of persuading the Minister that the health and environmental risks and the value of the pest control product are acceptable; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418156" lims:id="418156"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Minister shall consider the information provided by the applicant in support of the application and may consider additional information, but the Minister shall give the applicant a reasonable opportunity to make representations in respect of the additional information before completing the evaluation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418157" lims:id="418157"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418158" lims:id="418158">Scientific approach</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>In evaluating the health and environmental risks of a pest control product and in determining whether those risks are acceptable, the Minister shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418159" lims:id="418159"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>apply a scientifically based approach; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418160" lims:id="418160"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to health risks, if a decision referred to in paragraph 28(1)(a) or (b) is being made or has been made in relation to a pest control product,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418161" lims:id="418161"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>among other relevant factors, consider available information on aggregate exposure to the pest control product, namely dietary exposure and exposure from other non-occupational sources, including drinking water and use in and around homes and schools, and cumulative effects of the pest control product and other pest control products that have a common mechanism of toxicity,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418162" lims:id="418162"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>apply appropriate margins of safety to take into account, among other relevant factors, the use of animal experimentation data and the different sensitivities to pest control products of major identifiable subgroups, including pregnant women, infants, children, women and seniors, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418163" lims:id="418163"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of a threshold effect, if the product is proposed for use in or around homes or schools, apply a margin of safety that is ten times greater than the margin of safety that would otherwise be applicable under subparagraph (ii) in respect of that threshold effect, to take into account potential pre- and post-natal toxicity and completeness of the data with respect to the exposure of, and toxicity to, infants and children unless, on the basis of reliable scientific data, the Minister has determined that a different margin of safety would be appropriate.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418164" lims:id="418164"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418165" lims:id="418165">Government policy to be given effect in evaluation</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>In evaluating the health and environmental risks and the value of a pest control product, the Minister shall give effect to government policy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418166" lims:id="418166"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418167" lims:id="418167">Comparative risk and value assessment</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>In determining whether the health and environmental risks and the value of a pest control product are acceptable, the Minister may, in accordance with the regulations, if any, take into account information regarding the risks and value of other pest control products that are registered for the same use.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418168" lims:id="418168"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418169" lims:id="418169">Representations</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (9), the Minister shall, before making the determination, give the applicant a reasonable opportunity to make representations in respect of the information referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418171" lims:id="418171">2002, c. 28, s. 7; 2017, c. 6, s. 109</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418172" lims:id="418172"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418173" lims:id="418173">Registration or amendment</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418174" lims:id="418174"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister considers that the health and environmental risks and the value of the pest control product are acceptable after any required evaluations and consultations have been completed, the Minister shall register the product or amend its registration in accordance with the regulations, if any, by</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418175" lims:id="418175"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>specifying the conditions relating to its manufacture, handling, storage, transport, import, export, packaging, distribution, use or disposition, including conditions relating to its composition, and, subject to subsection (2), the conditions relating to its label;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418176" lims:id="418176"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>assigning a registration number to the product in the case of a new registration and, where the Minister considers it appropriate, in the case of an amendment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418177" lims:id="418177"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>specifying the period for which the registration or amended registration is valid, which period may be either finite or indefinite.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418178" lims:id="418178"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418179" lims:id="418179">Conditions relating to label</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may specify conditions relating to the label of a pest control product, otherwise than in accordance with the regulations, if the Minister is satisfied that the purposes of this Act can be met by so doing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418180" lims:id="418180"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418181" lims:id="418181">Provision of safety information to workplaces</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of paragraph (1)(a), the Minister shall specify, as a condition of registration, the requirement for product safety information, including a material safety data sheet for the product, to be provided to workplaces where the pest control product is used or manufactured, in accordance with the regulations made under paragraph 67(1)(s).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418182" lims:id="418182"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418183" lims:id="418183">Denial of application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall deny an application referred to in subsection 7(1) if the Minister does not consider that the health or environmental risks of a pest control product are, or its value is, acceptable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418184" lims:id="418184"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418185" lims:id="418185">Sales data</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A registrant of a pest control product shall, as a condition of registration, record, retain and report to the Minister information on sales of the product in the form and manner directed by the Minister and in accordance with the regulations made under paragraph 67(1)(u).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418186" lims:id="418186"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418187" lims:id="418187">Former registrants</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The obligation under subsection (5) to retain and report sales information in respect of a pest control product continues to apply to a former registrant after that product ceases to be registered.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418189" lims:id="418189">2002, c. 28, s. 8; 2016, c. 9, s. 36</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418190" lims:id="418190" level="2"><TitleText>Maximum Residue Limits</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418191" lims:id="418191"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418192" lims:id="418192">Specification at time of registration decision</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>When making a decision regarding the registration of a pest control product, the Minister shall, if necessary, specify any maximum residue limits for the product or for its components or derivatives that the Minister considers appropriate in the circumstances.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418193" lims:id="418193"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418194" lims:id="418194">Specification for unregistered products and uses</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418195" lims:id="418195"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may specify maximum residue limits for an unregistered pest control product or its components or derivatives, or for a registered pest control product or its components or derivatives with respect to a use that is not provided for by its registration, whether or not an application under subsection (2) is made for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418196" lims:id="418196"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418197" lims:id="418197">Application for specification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any person may make an application to the Minister to specify maximum residue limits pursuant to subsection (1). Section 7, with any necessary modifications, applies to that application.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418198" lims:id="418198"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418199" lims:id="418199">Evaluation of health risks</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>When specifying maximum residue limits for a pest control product or its components or derivatives pursuant to subsection (1), the Minister shall evaluate only the health risks of the product or its components or derivatives.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418200" lims:id="418200"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418201" lims:id="418201">Health risks to be considered acceptable</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418202" lims:id="418202"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The health risks associated with maximum residue limits specified by the Minister under sections 9 and 10 must be considered to be acceptable by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418203" lims:id="418203"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418204" lims:id="418204">Relevant factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a decision referred to in paragraph 28(1)(a) or (b) is being made or has been made in relation to a pest control product, the Minister shall, in evaluating and determining whether the health risks associated with maximum residue limits for that pest control product or its components or derivatives are acceptable under subsection (1),</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418205" lims:id="418205"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>among other relevant factors, consider available information on</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418206" lims:id="418206"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>aggregate exposure to the pest control product, namely dietary exposure and exposure from other non-occupational sources, including drinking water and use in and around homes and schools,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418207" lims:id="418207"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>cumulative effects of the pest control product and other pest control products that have a common mechanism of toxicity, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418208" lims:id="418208"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the different sensitivities to pest control products of major identifiable subgroups, including pregnant women, infants, children, women and seniors; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418209" lims:id="418209"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the case of a threshold effect, apply a margin of safety that is ten times greater than the margin of safety that would otherwise be applicable under subparagraph 7(7)(b)(ii) or 19(2)(b)(ii) in respect of that threshold effect, to take into account potential pre- and post-natal toxicity and completeness of the data with respect to the exposure of, and toxicity to, infants and children, unless, on the basis of reliable scientific data, the Minister has determined that a different margin of safety would be appropriate.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418210" lims:id="418210" level="2"><TitleText>Additional Information and Mandatory Reporting</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418211" lims:id="418211"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418212" lims:id="418212">Additional information</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418213" lims:id="418213"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by delivering a notice in writing, require a registrant</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418214" lims:id="418214"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to compile information, conduct tests and monitor experience with the pest control product for the purpose of obtaining additional information with respect to its effects on human health and safety or the environment or with respect to its value; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418215" lims:id="418215"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to report the additional information to the Minister within the time and in the form specified in the notice.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418216" lims:id="418216"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418217" lims:id="418217">Condition of registration</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A requirement under subsection (1) is a condition of registration.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418218" lims:id="418218"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418219" lims:id="418219">Mandatory reporting</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>An applicant for registration of a pest control product, a person who makes an application under subsection 10(2) or a registrant shall report any prescribed information that relates to the health or environmental risks or the value of the pest control product to the Minister within the prescribed time and in the form and manner directed by the Minister.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418220" lims:id="418220"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418221" lims:id="418221">Determination by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>After considering any information reported under section 12 or 13, the Minister shall determine whether a special review of the registration of the pest control product should be initiated.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418222" lims:id="418222"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418223" lims:id="418223">Public availability</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Text>After considering any information reported under section 13, the Minister shall place his or her conclusions in the Register and shall make public those conclusions if, in the Minister’s opinion,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418224" lims:id="418224"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the pest control product poses a significant health or environmental risk; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418225" lims:id="418225"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>it is in the public interest to do so.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418226" lims:id="418226" level="2"><TitleText>Re-evaluation and Special Review</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418227" lims:id="418227"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418228" lims:id="418228">Minister’s discretion to initiate re-evaluation</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418229" lims:id="418229"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may initiate the re-evaluation of a registered pest control product if the Minister considers that, since the product was registered, there has been a change in the information required, or the procedures used, for the evaluation of the health or environmental risks or the value of pest control products of the same class or kind.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418230" lims:id="418230"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418231" lims:id="418231">Minister required to initiate re-evaluation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of subsection (1),</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418232" lims:id="418232"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if a decision of a type referred to in paragraph 28(1)(a) or (b) was made in relation to a pest control product on or after April 1, 1995, the Minister shall initiate a re-evaluation of that product no later than one year after 15 years have elapsed since the most recent decision of that type; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418233" lims:id="418233"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the most recent decision of a type referred to in paragraph 28(1)(a) or (b) was made in relation to a pest control product before April 1, 1995, the Minister shall initiate a re-evaluation of that product no later than April 1, 2005 or the date that is one year after 15 years have elapsed since that decision, whichever date is later.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418234" lims:id="418234"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418235" lims:id="418235">Notice requesting information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Re-evaluation of a pest control product is initiated by the Minister delivering a notice in writing to the registrant explaining the reasons for initiating the re-evaluation and, if considered necessary by the Minister, requiring the registrant to provide information in the form and within the period specified in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418236" lims:id="418236"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418237" lims:id="418237">Request for information from departments and provinces</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>After the re-evaluation is initiated, the Minister shall deliver a notice to federal and provincial government departments and agencies whose interests and concerns are affected by the federal regulatory system requesting them to provide, in the form and within the period specified in the notice, information in respect of the health and environmental risks and the value of the product that is under re-evaluation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418238" lims:id="418238"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418239" lims:id="418239">Provision of information if more than one registrant</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If there is more than one registrant whose registered pest control products have active ingredients that the Minister has determined to be equivalent,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418240" lims:id="418240"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>two or more registrants may provide the information required under subsection (3) or paragraph 19(1)(a) jointly; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418241" lims:id="418241"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the Minister is satisfied that the information required under subsection (3) or paragraph 19(1)(a) has been provided by one or more registrants, the Minister shall, subject to and in accordance with the regulations, permit another registrant to use or rely on that information to meet the requirements under that subsection or paragraph.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418242" lims:id="418242"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418243" lims:id="418243">If active ingredients not equivalent</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>If the active ingredients of the registered pest control product that is subject to the re-evaluation are not equivalent to the active ingredients in another registrant’s registered pest control product, the Minister shall, subject to and in accordance with the regulations, permit the registrant whose product is subject to the re-evaluation to use or rely on information provided by the other registrant if the Minister is satisfied that the information is necessary for the re-evaluation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418244" lims:id="418244"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418245" lims:id="418245">Evaluation of pest control product</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>After the re-evaluation is initiated, the Minister shall, in accordance with the regulations, if any, conduct any evaluations that the Minister considers necessary with respect to the health or environmental risks or the value of the pest control product and shall carry out the consultations required by section 28.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418247" lims:id="418247">2002, c. 28, s. 16; 2017, c. 6, s. 110</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-21" lims:fid="418248" lims:id="418248"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418249" lims:id="418249">Initiation of special review by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418250" lims:id="418250"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall initiate a special review of the registration of a pest control product if the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that the health or environmental risks of the product are, or its value is, unacceptable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418251" lims:id="418251"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418252" lims:id="418252">Special review where OECD ban</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of subsection (1), when a member country of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development prohibits all uses of an active ingredient for health or environmental reasons, the Minister shall initiate a special review of registered pest control products containing that active ingredient.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418253" lims:id="418253"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418254" lims:id="418254">Special review where information from department or province</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Without limiting the generality of subsection (1), the Minister shall initiate a special review of the registration of a pest control product if a federal or provincial government department or agency has provided information to the Minister that relates to the health or environmental risks or the value of the product and if, after considering the information provided, the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that the health or environmental risks of the product are, or its value is, unacceptable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418255" lims:id="418255"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418256" lims:id="418256">Request for special review</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Any person may request a special review of the registration of a pest control product by making a request to the Minister in the form and manner directed by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418257" lims:id="418257"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418258" lims:id="418258">Decision</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Within a reasonable time after receiving a request, the Minister shall decide whether to initiate a special review and shall respond to the request with written reasons for the decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174356" lims:id="1174356"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174357" lims:id="1174357">Scope of special review</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, the Minister shall initiate a special review only in relation to the aspect of the pest control product that prompted the special review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174358" lims:id="1174358"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174359" lims:id="1174359">Addition of aspect</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the Minister has initiated a re-evaluation of, or a special review in relation to, a pest control product, the Minister may, at any time before the decision statement is made public under subsection 28(5), expand the scope of the re-evaluation or special review to include any aspect of the product that would otherwise prompt a new special review under subsection (1), (2) or (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174360" lims:id="1174360"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174361" lims:id="1174361">New or amended consultation statement</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>If the Minister expands the scope of a re-evaluation or special review under subsection (7) after the consultation statement relating to the re-evaluation or special review has been made public under subsection 28(2), the Minister shall make public a new or amended consultation statement under that subsection that takes into account the aspect referred to in subsection (7).</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174363" lims:id="1174363" lims:enactId="1156288" type="original">2002, c. 28, s. 17</HistoricalNoteSubItem><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174364" lims:id="1174364" lims:enactId="1156288">2019, c. 29, s. 217</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174374" lims:id="1174374"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174375" lims:id="1174375">Discretion of Minister — aspect already covered</MarginalNote><Label>17.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174376" lims:id="1174376"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite section 17, the Minister may decide not to initiate a special review in relation to a pest control product if a re-evaluation of, or a special review in relation to, the product has already been initiated that includes the aspect of the product that would otherwise prompt a special review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174377" lims:id="1174377"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174378" lims:id="1174378">Discretion of Minister — previous decision statement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 17(2), the Minister may decide not to initiate a special review of a registered pest control product under that subsection if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174379" lims:id="1174379"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Minister made public under subsection 28(5) a decision statement respecting a re-evaluation of, or a special review in relation to, that product;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174380" lims:id="1174380"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the aspect of the product that would otherwise prompt a special review was addressed by the re-evaluation or special review referred to in paragraph (a); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174381" lims:id="1174381"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Minister determines that there is no additional information in relation to the health or environmental risks of the product that provides the Minister with reasonable grounds to believe that those risks are unacceptable.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174383" lims:id="1174383" lims:enactId="1156290">2019, c. 29, s. 218</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174384" lims:id="1174384"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174385" lims:id="1174385">Duty to make decisions public</MarginalNote><Label>17.2</Label><Text>The Minister shall make public each of the following decisions and the reasons for it:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174386" lims:id="1174386"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a decision made under subsection 17(7) to expand the scope of a re-evaluation or special review to include an aspect that would otherwise prompt a new special review under subsection 17(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174387" lims:id="1174387"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a decision made under subsection 17.1(1) or (2) not to initiate a special review in relation to an aspect that would otherwise prompt such a review under subsection 17(2).</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174389" lims:id="1174389" lims:enactId="1156290">2019, c. 29, s. 218</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-06-21" lims:fid="418259" lims:id="418259"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418260" lims:id="418260">Notice requesting information</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418261" lims:id="418261"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A special review of a pest control product is initiated by the Minister delivering a notice in writing to the registrant explaining the reasons for initiating the special review and, if considered necessary by the Minister, requiring the registrant to provide information in the form and within the period specified in the notice.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418262" lims:id="418262"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418263" lims:id="418263">Request for information from departments and provinces</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After the special review is initiated, the Minister shall deliver a notice to federal and provincial government departments and agencies whose interests and concerns are affected by the federal regulatory system requesting them to provide, in the form and within the period specified in the notice, information in respect of the health and environmental risks and the value of the product that is under special review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418264" lims:id="418264"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418265" lims:id="418265">Provision of information if more than one registrant</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If there is more than one registrant whose registered pest control products have active ingredients that the Minister has determined to be equivalent,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418266" lims:id="418266"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>two or more registrants may provide the information required under subsection (1) or paragraph 19(1)(a) jointly; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418267" lims:id="418267"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the Minister is satisfied that the information required under subsection (1) or paragraph 19(1)(a) has been provided by one or more registrants, the Minister shall, subject to and in accordance with the regulations, permit another registrant to use or rely on that information to meet the requirements under that subsection or paragraph.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418268" lims:id="418268"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418269" lims:id="418269">If active ingredients not equivalent</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>If the active ingredients of a registered pest control product that is subject to the special review are not equivalent to the active ingredients in another registrant’s registered pest control product, the Minister shall, subject to and in accordance with the regulations, permit the registrant whose product is subject to the special review to use or rely on information provided by the other registrant if the Minister is satisfied that the information is necessary for the special review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="418270" lims:id="1174390"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174391" lims:id="1174391">Evaluation of pest control product</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>After the special review is initiated, the Minister shall, in accordance with the regulations, if any, evaluate only the aspects of the pest control product that are within the scope of the special review and shall carry out the consultations required by section 28.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418273" lims:id="418273">2002, c. 28, s. 18; 2017, c. 6, s. 111</HistoricalNoteSubItem><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-06-21" lims:enacted-date="2019-06-21" lims:fid="1174392" lims:id="1174392" lims:enactId="1156292">2019, c. 29, s. 219</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418274" lims:id="418274"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418275" lims:id="418275">Burden of persuasion and consideration of information</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418276" lims:id="418276"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>During an evaluation that is done in the course of a re-evaluation or special review,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418277" lims:id="418277"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Minister may, by delivering a notice in writing, require the registrant to provide, in the form and within the period specified in the notice, additional information that the Minister considers necessary for the evaluation;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418278" lims:id="418278"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the registrant has the burden of persuading the Minister that the health and environmental risks and the value of the pest control product are acceptable; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418279" lims:id="418279"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Minister shall consider the information provided by the registrant in support of the product and may consider any additional information, but the Minister shall give the registrant a reasonable opportunity to make representations in respect of the additional information before completing the evaluation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418280" lims:id="418280"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418281" lims:id="418281">Scientific approach</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In evaluating the health and environmental risks of a pest control product and in determining whether those risks are acceptable, the Minister shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418282" lims:id="418282"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>apply a scientifically based approach; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418283" lims:id="418283"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in relation to health risks,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418284" lims:id="418284"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>among other relevant factors, consider available information on aggregate exposure to the pest control product, namely dietary exposure and exposure from other non-occupational sources, including drinking water and use in and around homes and schools, and cumulative effects of the pest control product and other pest control products that have a common mechanism of toxicity,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418285" lims:id="418285"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>apply appropriate margins of safety to take into account, among other relevant factors, the use of animal experimentation data and the different sensitivities to pest control products of major identifiable subgroups, including pregnant women, infants, children, women and seniors, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418286" lims:id="418286"><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>in the case of a threshold effect, if the product is used in or around homes or schools, apply a margin of safety that is ten times greater than the margin of safety that would otherwise be applicable under subparagraph (ii) in respect of that threshold effect, to take into account potential pre- and post-natal toxicity and completeness of the data with respect to the exposure of, and toxicity to, infants and children, unless, on the basis of reliable scientific data, the Minister has determined that a different margin of safety would be appropriate.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418287" lims:id="418287"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418288" lims:id="418288">Government policy to be given effect in evaluation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In evaluating the health and environmental risks and the value of a pest control product, the Minister shall give effect to government policy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418289" lims:id="418289"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418290" lims:id="418290">Comparative risk and value assessment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In determining whether the health and environmental risks and the value of a pest control product are acceptable, the Minister may, in accordance with the regulations, if any, take into account information regarding the risks and value of other pest control products that are registered for the same use.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418291" lims:id="418291"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418292" lims:id="418292">Representations</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (4), the Minister shall, before making the determination, give any registrant whose product is under re-evaluation or special review a reasonable opportunity to make representations in respect of the information referred to in that subsection.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418293" lims:id="418293"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418294" lims:id="418294">Cancellation or amendment</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418295" lims:id="418295"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may cancel or amend the registration of a pest control product if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418296" lims:id="418296"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the registrant fails to satisfy a requirement under subsection 16(3) or 18(1) or paragraph 19(1)(a); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418297" lims:id="418297"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the course of a re-evaluation or special review, the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that the cancellation or amendment is necessary to deal with a situation that endangers human health or safety or the environment, taking into account the precautionary principle set out in subsection (2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418298" lims:id="418298"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418299" lims:id="418299">Precautionary principle</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where there are threats of serious or irreversible damage, lack of full scientific certainty shall not be used as a reason for postponing cost-effective measures to prevent adverse health impact or environmental degradation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418300" lims:id="418300"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418301" lims:id="418301">Rescission of action</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may rescind any action taken under subsection (1) if the circumstances that prompted it cease to exist.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418302" lims:id="418302"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418303" lims:id="418303">Refusal to consider applications</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the registration of a pest control product is cancelled or amended under paragraph (1)(a), the Minister may, for a prescribed period, refuse to consider any application made in respect of that product by the registrant.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418304" lims:id="418304"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418305" lims:id="418305">Confirmation</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418306" lims:id="418306"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Minister considers that the health and environmental risks and the value of a pest control product are acceptable after any required evaluations and consultations have been completed, the Minister shall confirm the registration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418307" lims:id="418307"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418308" lims:id="418308">Amendment or cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Minister does not consider that the health or environmental risks or value of a pest control product are acceptable, the Minister shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418309" lims:id="418309"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>amend the registration if the Minister considers that the health and environmental risks and value of the product would be acceptable after the amendment; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418310" lims:id="418310"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cancel the registration.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418311" lims:id="418311"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418312" lims:id="418312">Delay of effective date</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister may delay the effective date of the amendment or cancellation if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418313" lims:id="418313"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no suitable alternative to the use of the pest control product is available; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418314" lims:id="418314"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Minister considers that the health and environmental risks and value of the product are acceptable until the effective date of the amendment or cancellation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418315" lims:id="418315"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418316" lims:id="418316">Conditions on delay</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A delay is subject to any conditions that the Minister considers necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418317" lims:id="418317"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418318" lims:id="418318">Continued possession, etc., of existing stocks</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>When cancelling the registration of a pest control product under this section or any other provision of this Act, the Minister may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418319" lims:id="418319"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>allow the continued possession, handling, storage, distribution and use of stocks of the product in Canada at the time of cancellation, subject to any conditions, including disposal procedures, that the Minister considers necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418320" lims:id="418320"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>require the registrant to recall and dispose of the product in a manner specified by the Minister; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418321" lims:id="418321"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>seize and dispose of the product.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418322" lims:id="418322" level="2"><TitleText>Other Grounds for Cancellation or Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418323" lims:id="418323"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418324" lims:id="418324">Discontinuation of sale of product</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418325" lims:id="418325"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A registrant who intends to discontinue the sale of a pest control product for one or more uses for which it is registered shall notify the Minister of that intention in the form and manner directed by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418326" lims:id="418326"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418327" lims:id="418327">Reasons for discontinuation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may deliver a notice in writing to the registrant requiring the registrant to explain the reasons for the discontinuation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418328" lims:id="418328"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418329" lims:id="418329">Cancellation or amendment of registration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On receipt of notification under subsection (1), the Minister shall cancel or amend the registration, as the case may be, as of a date to be determined by the Minister and, pending that date, may impose any conditions that the Minister considers necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418330" lims:id="418330"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418331" lims:id="418331">Non-payment of fees, fines, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418332" lims:id="418332"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a registrant fails to pay a fee, fine, penalty, charge or cost that the registrant is liable to pay under or in relation to this Act, the Minister may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418333" lims:id="418333"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>cancel or amend any registration in the registrant’s name; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418334" lims:id="418334"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>refuse to consider any application made by the registrant under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418335" lims:id="418335"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418336" lims:id="418336">Representations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before taking any action under subsection (1) in relation to charges or costs, the Minister shall give the registrant a reasonable opportunity to make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418337" lims:id="418337"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418338" lims:id="418338">Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall immediately give written notice to the registrant of any action taken under subsection (1) and of the reasons for the action.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418339" lims:id="418339"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418340" lims:id="418340">Amendment with consent</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>The Minister may, with the written consent of the registrant, amend the registration of a pest control product for the purpose of reducing its health or environmental risks or increasing its value.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418341" lims:id="418341"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418342" lims:id="418342">Breach of conditions</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>The Minister may cancel or amend the registration of a pest control product if the registrant does not comply with the conditions of registration.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418343" lims:id="418343"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418344" lims:id="418344">Violation or offence</MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Text>If a person is found to have committed a violation or is convicted of an offence under this Act, the Minister may, having regard to the nature of the violation or offence and the circumstances surrounding its commission,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418345" lims:id="418345"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>cancel or amend the registration of the pest control product that was involved in the violation or offence where the person who committed the violation or offence is the registrant;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418346" lims:id="418346"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cancel or amend the registration of any other pest control product in respect of which the person is the registrant; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418347" lims:id="418347"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>refuse to consider any application made under this Act by the person during any period that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418348" lims:id="418348"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418349" lims:id="418349">Implementation of international agreement</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, cancel or amend the registration of a pest control product or a class of pest control products if the Governor in Council considers it necessary to do so to implement an international agreement.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418350" lims:id="418350" level="2"><TitleText>Public Consultation</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418351" lims:id="418351"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418352" lims:id="418352">Minister to consult</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418353" lims:id="418353"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall consult the public and federal and provincial government departments and agencies whose interests and concerns are affected by the federal regulatory system before making a decision</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418354" lims:id="418354"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to grant or deny an application</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418355" lims:id="418355"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to register a pest control product that is or contains an unregistered active ingredient, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418356" lims:id="418356"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>to register, or amend the registration of, a pest control product if the Minister considers that registration or amendment of the registration may result in significantly increased health or environmental risks;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418357" lims:id="418357"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>about the registration of a pest control product on completion of a re-evaluation or special review; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418358" lims:id="418358"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>about any other matter if the Minister considers it in the public interest to do so.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418359" lims:id="418359"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418360" lims:id="418360">Public notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>To initiate a consultation under subsection (1), the Minister shall make public a consultation statement and shall invite any person to send written comments on the proposed decision within the period specified in the statement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418361" lims:id="418361"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418362" lims:id="418362">Consultation statement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The consultation statement shall include</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418363" lims:id="418363"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a summary of any reports of the evaluation of the health and environmental risks and the value of the pest control product prepared or considered by the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418364" lims:id="418364"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the proposed decision and the reasons for it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418365" lims:id="418365"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>any other information that the Minister considers necessary in the public interest.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418366" lims:id="418366"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418367" lims:id="418367">Consideration of comments</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall consider any comments received pursuant to subsection (2) before making a decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418368" lims:id="418368"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418369" lims:id="418369">Decision statement</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>After making a decision, the Minister shall make public a decision statement that shall include the decision, the reasons for it and a summary of any comments that the Minister received on the proposed decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418370" lims:id="418370"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418371" lims:id="418371">Confidential test data</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A consultation statement referred to in subsection (2) and a decision statement referred to in subsection (5) shall contain any confidential test data that the Minister considers to be in the public interest.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418372" lims:id="418372" level="2"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418373" lims:id="418373"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418374" lims:id="418374">Failure to report information</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418375" lims:id="418375"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who does not comply with section 13 is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418376" lims:id="418376"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418377" lims:id="418377">Non-compliance with requirement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A registrant who does not comply with a requirement in a notice referred to in subsection 16(3) or 18(1), paragraph 19(1)(a) or subsection 22(2) is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418378" lims:id="418378"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418379" lims:id="418379">False or misleading information</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418380" lims:id="418380"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence if they knowingly provide the Minister with false or misleading information</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418381" lims:id="418381"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>about the health or environmental risks or the value of a pest control product; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418382" lims:id="418382"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in response to a notice delivered under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418383" lims:id="418383"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418384" lims:id="418384">False or misleading tests</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence if they falsely claim to have conducted a test relating to the health or environmental risks or the value of a pest control product, knowingly conduct such a test that is misleading or knowingly provide false or misleading information about such a test.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418385" lims:id="418385"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418386" lims:id="418386">Non-compliance with conditions of registration</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418387" lims:id="418387"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A registrant who does not comply with the conditions of registration is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418388" lims:id="418388"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418389" lims:id="418389">Non-compliance with other conditions and requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who does not comply with a condition imposed under subsection 21(4), paragraph 21(5)(a) or subsection 22(3) or with a requirement under paragraph 21(5)(b) is guilty of an offence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418390" lims:id="418390"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418391" lims:id="418391">Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under any of sections 29 to 31 is liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418392" lims:id="418392"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418393" lims:id="418393"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418394" lims:id="418394" level="1"><TitleText>Export Controls</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418395" lims:id="418395"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418396" lims:id="418396">Export control list</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418397" lims:id="418397"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, establish a Pest Control Products Export Control List consisting of pest control products that meet the prescribed criteria.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418398" lims:id="418398"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418399" lims:id="418399">Prohibition</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person shall export a pest control product that is on the Pest Control Products Export Control List, except as authorized under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418400" lims:id="418400"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418401" lims:id="418401">Application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An application for authorization to export a pest control product must be made to the Minister in the form and manner directed by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418402" lims:id="418402"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418403" lims:id="418403">Authorization</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may authorize an applicant to export a pest control product to a specified country if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418404" lims:id="418404"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the applicant satisfies the Minister that the prescribed requirements for the authorization are or will be met; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418405" lims:id="418405"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the proposed export is not prohibited under any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418406" lims:id="418406"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418407" lims:id="418407">Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The authorization is subject to any conditions that the Minister considers necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418408" lims:id="418408"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418409" lims:id="418409">Public notice</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister shall give public notice of the authorization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418410" lims:id="418410"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418411" lims:id="418411">Offence and punishment — subsection (2)</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (2) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418412" lims:id="418412"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418413" lims:id="418413"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418414" lims:id="418414"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418415" lims:id="418415">Offence and punishment — false or misleading information</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Every person who knowingly provides false or misleading information in connection with an authorization is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418416" lims:id="418416"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418417" lims:id="418417"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418419" lims:id="418419">2002, c. 28, s. 33; 2016, c. 9, s. 37</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418420" lims:id="418420"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418421" lims:id="418421">Amendment, suspension or cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>34</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418422" lims:id="418422"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may amend, suspend or cancel an authorization to export a pest control product if the Minister</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418423" lims:id="418423"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>has reasonable grounds to believe that a prescribed requirement of the authorization is not or will not be met;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418424" lims:id="418424"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has reasonable grounds to believe that the conditions to which the authorization is subject have not been or will not be met; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418425" lims:id="418425"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>becomes aware of additional information about the health or environmental risks of the pest control product.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418426" lims:id="418426"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418427" lims:id="418427">Representations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before amending or cancelling an authorization or after suspending one, the Minister shall give the authorized person a reasonable opportunity to make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418428" lims:id="418428"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418429" lims:id="418429">Decision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After considering any representations that may be made by the authorized person, the Minister shall reinstate, amend or cancel the authorization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418430" lims:id="418430"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418431" lims:id="418431">Public notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall give public notice of the amendment or cancellation of an authorization.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418432" lims:id="418432" level="1"><TitleText>Reconsideration of Decisions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418433" lims:id="418433"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418434" lims:id="418434">Notice of objection to registration decisions</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418435" lims:id="418435"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any person may file with the Minister, in the form and manner directed by the Minister, a notice of objection to a decision referred to in paragraph 28(1)(a) or (b) within 60 days after the decision statement referred to in subsection 28(5) is made public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418436" lims:id="418436"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418437" lims:id="418437">Notice of objection to authorization decisions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any person may file with the Minister, in the form and manner directed by the Minister, a notice of objection to a decision to authorize the export of a pest control product or to amend or cancel an authorization within 60 days after a notice referred to in subsection 33(6) or 34(4) is made public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418438" lims:id="418438"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418439" lims:id="418439">Establishment of review panel</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After receiving a notice of objection, the Minister may, in accordance with the regulations, if any, establish a panel of one or more individuals to review the decision and to recommend whether the decision should be confirmed, reversed or varied.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418440" lims:id="418440"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418441" lims:id="418441">Notice of review panel</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall give public notice of the establishment of a review panel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418442" lims:id="418442"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418443" lims:id="418443">Reasons to be provided if panel not established</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the Minister does not establish a panel, the Minister shall provide written reasons without delay to the person who filed the notice of objection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418444" lims:id="418444"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418445" lims:id="418445">Terms of reference and procedure</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Minister may determine the terms of reference of a review panel and the procedure for the review, and may at any time change them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418446" lims:id="418446"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418447" lims:id="418447">Representations</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>A review panel shall give any person a reasonable opportunity to make representations in respect of the decision under review, in accordance with the terms of reference.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418448" lims:id="418448"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418449" lims:id="418449">Public access</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections 44(3) and (6), the hearings of a review panel shall be open to the public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418450" lims:id="418450"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418451" lims:id="418451">Information to be placed in Register</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>A review panel shall give the information submitted to it to the Minister, who shall place it in the Register.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418453" lims:id="418453">2002, c. 28, s. 35; 2016, c. 9, s. 38</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418454" lims:id="418454"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418455" lims:id="418455">No automatic suspension of decisions</MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Text>The filing of a notice of objection or the establishment of a review panel does not suspend the decision under review, but the Minister may suspend the decision until a final decision is made on completion of the review or until the review panel is dissolved.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418456" lims:id="418456"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418457" lims:id="418457">Withdrawal of notice of objection</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Text>The Minister may dissolve a review panel if all notices of objection are withdrawn by the persons who filed them.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418458" lims:id="418458"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418459" lims:id="418459">Report</MarginalNote><Label>38</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418460" lims:id="418460"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after the conclusion of a review, the review panel shall submit to the Minister a report stating its recommendations and the reasons for them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418461" lims:id="418461"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418462" lims:id="418462">Register</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall place the review panel’s report in the Register.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418463" lims:id="418463"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418464" lims:id="418464">Confirmation, reversal or variation of decision</MarginalNote><Label>39</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418465" lims:id="418465"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>After considering the recommendations of a review panel, the Minister shall confirm, reverse or vary the decision under review, but the confirmation, reversal or variation must not result in the registration, either initial or continued, of a pest control product unless the Minister considers that its health and environmental risks and its value are acceptable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418466" lims:id="418466"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418467" lims:id="418467">Public notice of decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall make public the confirmation, reversal or variation of the decision, the reasons for confirmation, reversal or variation and a summary of the information considered by the Minister, including any confidential test data that the Minister considers to be in the public interest.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418468" lims:id="418468"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418469" lims:id="418469">False or misleading tests or information</MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418470" lims:id="418470"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence if they</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418471" lims:id="418471"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>knowingly provide a review panel with false or misleading information about the health or environmental risks or the value of a pest control product; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418472" lims:id="418472"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>falsely claim to have conducted a test relating to the health or environmental risks or value of a pest control product, knowingly conduct such a test that is misleading or knowingly provide false or misleading information about such a test.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418473" lims:id="418473"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418474" lims:id="418474">Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) is liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418475" lims:id="418475"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418476" lims:id="418476"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418477" lims:id="418477" level="1"><TitleText>Authorization to Use Unregistered Product</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418478" lims:id="418478"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418479" lims:id="418479">Authorization</MarginalNote><Label>41</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418480" lims:id="418480"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in accordance with the regulations and subject to any conditions that the Minister may specify, authorize a person to use an unregistered pest control product for a specified purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418481" lims:id="418481"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418482" lims:id="418482">Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall authorize the use of a pest control product if the Minister considers that use of the product for the specified purpose in accordance with any conditions specified does not pose unacceptable health or environmental risks.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418483" lims:id="418483"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418484" lims:id="418484">Suspension</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall suspend an authorization if the Minister has reasonable grounds to believe that the conditions to which the authorization is subject have not been or will not be met or that the continuance of the authorization poses unacceptable health or environmental risks.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418485" lims:id="418485"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418486" lims:id="418486">Representations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>After suspending an authorization, the Minister shall give the authorized person a reasonable opportunity to make representations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418487" lims:id="418487"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418488" lims:id="418488">Decision</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>After considering any representations that may be made by the authorized person, the Minister shall reinstate, amend or cancel the authorization.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418489" lims:id="418489"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418490" lims:id="418490">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with the conditions of an authorization issued under this section is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418491" lims:id="418491"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418492" lims:id="418492"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2019-07-12" lims:enacted-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="1192003" lims:id="1192003" level="1"><TitleText>Product Safety Information for Unregistered Products</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2019-07-12" lims:enacted-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-07-12" lims:fid="1192004" lims:id="1192004"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-07-12" lims:enacted-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="1192005" lims:id="1192005">Provision of safety information</MarginalNote><Label>41.1</Label><Text>A person who is authorized by the regulations to import an unregistered pest control product solely for the purpose of export or for a prescribed purpose and who imports such a product for that purpose shall provide, in accordance with the regulations, to workplaces where the pest control product is handled or stored, product safety information for the product that complies with the prescribed requirements.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-07-12" lims:enacted-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="1192007" lims:id="1192007" lims:enactId="1036391">2016, c. 9, s. 39</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418493" lims:id="418493" level="1"><TitleText>Access to Information</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:lastAmendedDate="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418494" lims:id="418494"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418495" lims:id="418495">Register</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418496" lims:id="418496"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall establish and maintain a Register of Pest Control Products in accordance with the regulations, if any, that contains information about pest control products, including information about applications, registrations, re-evaluations and special reviews.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418497" lims:id="418497"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418498" lims:id="418498">Contents of Register</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Register shall contain the following information:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418499" lims:id="418499"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>for each application to register or amend the registration of a pest control product,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418500" lims:id="418500"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the active ingredient of the product, proposed new uses for it or any uses proposed to be withdrawn, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418501" lims:id="418501"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>how the application was disposed of or whether it was withdrawn;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418502" lims:id="418502"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the conditions of registration, registration number and registration validity period for each registered pest control product;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418503" lims:id="418503"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>information, in respect of each registered pest control product, that is provided by applicants and registrants</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418504" lims:id="418504"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in support of an application for registration or for the amendment of a registration, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418505" lims:id="418505"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>for the purposes of a re-evaluation or special review;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418506" lims:id="418506"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>information provided by applicants and registrants that is used to specify maximum residue limits;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418507" lims:id="418507"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>information, in respect of each registered pest control product, that is considered by the Minister under paragraphs 7(6)(b) and 19(1)(c);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418508" lims:id="418508"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any reports of the evaluation of the health and environmental risks and the value of registered pest control products prepared by the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418509" lims:id="418509"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>any advice from a person or body referred to in paragraph 44(1)(f), unless disclosure of the advice may be refused under section 23 or 23.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-1">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418510" lims:id="418510"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the status, including cancelled status, of all registrations to which this Act applies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418511" lims:id="418511"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>information provided to the Minister pursuant to subsection 8(5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418512" lims:id="418512"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>notices delivered under subsections 12(1), 16(3) and 18(1) and paragraph 19(1)(a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418513" lims:id="418513"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>conclusions of the Minister that were made public under section 15;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418514" lims:id="418514"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>consultation statements and decision statements made public under subsections 28(2) and (5), respectively;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418515" lims:id="418515"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>notices of objection filed under subsections 35(1) and (2), public notices given under subsection 35(4) and the Minister’s decisions and reasons under subsections 35(5) and 39(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418516" lims:id="418516"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>authorizations under sections 33 and 41 and amendments and cancellations under sections 34 and 41; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418517" lims:id="418517"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>any other information required by this Act or the regulations to be included in the Register.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418518" lims:id="418518"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418519" lims:id="418519">Evaluation reports</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An evaluation report referred to in paragraph (2)(f) shall contain a summary of the information considered and shall contain any confidential test data and confidential business information that the Minister considers appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418520" lims:id="418520"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418521" lims:id="418521">Public access to information in the Register</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall allow the public to have access to, and copies of, any information in the Register that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418522" lims:id="418522"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is not confidential test data or confidential business information; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418523" lims:id="418523"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is confidential test data that has been made subject to public disclosure in accordance with the regulations made under paragraph 67(1)(m).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418524" lims:id="418524"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418525" lims:id="418525">Access to evaluation reports</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister shall allow the public to obtain a copy of any evaluation report in the Register, except for any confidential business information that it contains.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418526" lims:id="418526"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418527" lims:id="418527">Means of access to information in Register</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Information in the Register that the public may obtain a copy of under this Act or the regulations shall be made available to the public in as convenient a manner as practicable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418528" lims:id="418528"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418529" lims:id="418529">Electronic public registry</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The Minister shall establish an electronic public registry, which shall include</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418530" lims:id="418530"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the information referred to in subsection (6), as soon as reasonably practicable;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418531" lims:id="418531"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>memoranda of understanding among federal government departments relating to the regulation of pest control products;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418532" lims:id="418532"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>reports of international harmonization activities relating to the regulation of pest control products;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418533" lims:id="418533"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>regulations and proposed regulations under this Act when published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418534" lims:id="418534"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>policies, guidelines and codes of practice relating to the regulation of pest control products when proposed for public consultation, and their final texts when adopted.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2018-12-13" lims:fid="418536" lims:id="418536">2002, c. 28, s. 42; 2018, c. 27, s. 275</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418537" lims:id="418537"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418538" lims:id="418538">Consultation with public</MarginalNote><Label>42.1</Label><Text>The public shall be consulted as to policies, guidelines and codes of practice relating to the regulation of pest control products.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418539" lims:id="418539"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418540" lims:id="418540">Confidential test data</MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418541" lims:id="418541"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who wishes to inspect confidential test data in the Register must submit to the Minister</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418542" lims:id="418542"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>an application in the form and manner directed by the Minister; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418543" lims:id="418543"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an affidavit made under oath or a statutory declaration under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-5">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> made before a commissioner for oaths or for taking affidavits, stating</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418544" lims:id="418544"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the purpose of the inspection, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418545" lims:id="418545"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that the person does not intend to use the test data, or make the test data available to others, in order to register a pest control product in Canada or elsewhere or to amend a registration.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418546" lims:id="418546"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418547" lims:id="418547">Right to inspection</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall permit the person to inspect confidential test data in the Register if the Minister is satisfied that the person does not intend to</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418548" lims:id="418548"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>use the test data in order to register a pest control product in Canada or elsewhere, or to amend a registration; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418549" lims:id="418549"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>make the test data available to others for the purpose of registering a pest control product in Canada or elsewhere, or of amending a registration.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418550" lims:id="418550"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418551" lims:id="418551">Notice to registrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If the Minister permits a person to inspect confidential test data in the Register, the Minister shall make a reasonable effort to immediately notify any registrant who provided the data that the Minister has permitted a person to inspect the data.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418552" lims:id="418552"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418553" lims:id="418553">Denial of application</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister shall deny an application if the Minister is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418554" lims:id="418554"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the applicant intends to use the test data for a purpose referred to in subsection (2); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418555" lims:id="418555"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the applicant has used test data obtained from a prior inspection for a purpose referred to in subsection (2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418556" lims:id="418556"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418557" lims:id="418557">Confidential business information</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (5) and (6), confidential business information is information provided under this Act that is designated as confidential business information by the person who provided it, or information provided under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>, chapter P-9 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, and that concerns</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418558" lims:id="418558"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>manufacturing or quality control processes relating to a pest control product;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418559" lims:id="418559"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>methods for determining the composition of a pest control product; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418560" lims:id="418560"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the monetary value of sales of pest control products provided to the Minister pursuant to subsection 8(5) and other financial or commercial information provided to the Minister pursuant to this Act or the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418561" lims:id="418561"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418562" lims:id="418562">Formulants and contaminants</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Unless otherwise excluded by the regulations, if any, made under paragraph 67(1)(n), confidential business information also includes information that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418563" lims:id="418563"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is provided under this Act and is designated as confidential business information by the person who provided it or was provided under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>, chapter P-9 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418564" lims:id="418564"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>contains the identity and concentration of the formulants and contaminants in a pest control product, other than those that the Minister considers to be of health or environmental concern and are identified on a list to be established and maintained by the Minister and made available to the public.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418565" lims:id="418565"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418566" lims:id="418566">Designation not satisfactory</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>If the Minister decides that information designated under subsection (4) or (5) does not meet the requirements of that subsection, the information is not confidential business information for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418567" lims:id="418567"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418568" lims:id="418568">Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>If the Minister decides that designated information is not confidential business information, the Minister shall give written notice to the person who provided the information of the decision and the reasons for it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418569" lims:id="418569"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418570" lims:id="418570">Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act shall be construed as</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418571" lims:id="418571"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>preventing the Minister from refusing to disclose confidential test data or confidential business information under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-1">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418572" lims:id="418572"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>entitling a person to make or obtain a copy of confidential test data, other than confidential test data to which the public has access</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418573" lims:id="418573"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in documents referred to in subsections 28(6), 39(2) and 42(3), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418574" lims:id="418574"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>under the authority of the regulations made under paragraph 67(1)(m).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418575" lims:id="418575"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418576" lims:id="418576">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Every person who makes a false statement in an affidavit or a statutory declaration referred to in subsection (1) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418577" lims:id="418577"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418578" lims:id="418578"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418579" lims:id="418579"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418580" lims:id="418580">Permitted disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>44</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418581" lims:id="418581"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, in accordance with the regulations, if any, disclose confidential test data or confidential business information that has been provided under this Act or is in the Register to</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418582" lims:id="418582"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any person who provides services to Her Majesty in right of Canada for the purpose of protecting human health or safety or the environment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418583" lims:id="418583"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an international organization or the government of a province or a country that is a party to an agreement with Her Majesty in right of Canada or an agent of Her Majesty, relating to the exchange of information about pest control products;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418584" lims:id="418584"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a medical professional who requests the information for the purpose of making a medical diagnosis or giving medical treatment to an individual;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418585" lims:id="418585"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a department or an agency of the federal or a provincial government that requests the information in order to respond to a situation that endangers human health or safety or the environment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418586" lims:id="418586"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a review panel established by the Minister under subsection 35(3); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418587" lims:id="418587"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>any other person or body, including an advisory council established under subsection 5(1), from whom the Minister requests advice for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418588" lims:id="418588"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418589" lims:id="418589">Protection of disclosed information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Before disclosing information under paragraph (1)(b), the Minister must be satisfied that the party to the agreement, other than Her Majesty in right of Canada or an agent of Her Majesty, can provide protection from unfair commercial use or disclosure of the information that is consistent with the protection provided under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418590" lims:id="418590"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418591" lims:id="418591">Prohibition against disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall disclose information obtained under subsection (1) unless authorized by the person who provided the information to the Minister or unless authorized under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-1">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal>, this Act or the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418592" lims:id="418592"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418593" lims:id="418593">Prohibition against use</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No person shall use information obtained under subsection (1) for any purpose other than the purpose for which it was obtained, unless authorized by the person who provided the information to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418594" lims:id="418594"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418595" lims:id="418595">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (3) or (4) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418596" lims:id="418596"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418597" lims:id="418597"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418598" lims:id="418598"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418599" lims:id="418599">Security measures</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Every person who obtains information under subsection (1) shall comply with any prescribed security measures and take all reasonable precautions to avoid any prohibited disclosure of the information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418600" lims:id="418600"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418601" lims:id="418601">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (6) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418602" lims:id="418602"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418603" lims:id="418603"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418605" lims:id="418605">2002, c. 28, s. 44; 2016, c. 9, s. 40</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418606" lims:id="418606" level="1"><TitleText>Administration and Enforcement</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418607" lims:id="418607" level="2"><TitleText>Inspectors and Analysts</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418608" lims:id="418608"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418609" lims:id="418609">Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>45</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418610" lims:id="418610"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), inspectors and analysts shall be appointed for the purposes of this Act and the regulations in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-33.01">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418611" lims:id="418611"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418612" lims:id="418612">Designation of inspectors and analysts</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the administration and enforcement of this Act, the Minister may designate individuals or classes of individuals as inspectors or analysts to exercise powers or perform duties or functions in relation to any matter referred to in the designation, but</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418613" lims:id="418613"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no individual who is employed in a department other than the Department of Health may be designated without the approval of the minister responsible for the department in which the individual is employed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418614" lims:id="418614"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>no individual who is employed by the government of a province may be designated without the approval of that government.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418615" lims:id="418615"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418616" lims:id="418616">Inspector’s certificate of designation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An inspector shall be provided with a certificate in a form established by the Minister certifying the inspector’s designation and, on entering any place under the authority of this Act, the inspector shall show the certificate to the person in charge of the place if the person requests proof of the designation.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418618" lims:id="418618">2002, c. 28, s. 45; 2016, c. 9, s. 42</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418619" lims:id="418619"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418620" lims:id="418620">Obstruction of inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>46</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418621" lims:id="418621"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall resist or obstruct an inspector or make a false or misleading statement either orally or in writing to an inspector who is exercising powers or performing duties or functions under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418622" lims:id="418622"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418623" lims:id="418623">Inspection of records</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who is required by this Act or the regulations to keep records shall make them available to an inspector on request.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418624" lims:id="418624"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418625" lims:id="418625">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes this section is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418626" lims:id="418626"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418627" lims:id="418627"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418629" lims:id="418629">2002, c. 28, s. 46; 2016, c. 9, s. 43</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418630" lims:id="418630" level="2"><TitleText>Voluntary Reports</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418631" lims:id="418631"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418632" lims:id="418632">Report of contravention</MarginalNote><Label>47</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418633" lims:id="418633"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who knows about a contravention of this Act or the regulations, or the reasonable likelihood of such a contravention, may report any information relating to the contravention to an inspector.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418634" lims:id="418634"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418635" lims:id="418635">Confidentiality</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When making a report, the person may request that their identity and any information that could reasonably reveal their identity not be disclosed, and no person shall disclose or permit the disclosure of that identity or information unless the person who made the request authorizes the disclosure in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418636" lims:id="418636"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418637" lims:id="418637">Protection of individual</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, no person shall dismiss, suspend, demote, discipline, deny a benefit of employment to, harass or otherwise disadvantage an individual for having</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418638" lims:id="418638"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>made a report under subsection (1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418639" lims:id="418639"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>refused or stated an intention of refusing to do anything that the individual reasonably believed was or would be a contravention under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418640" lims:id="418640"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>done or stated an intention of doing anything that the individual reasonably believed was required by or under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418641" lims:id="418641"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418642" lims:id="418642">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (2) or (3) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418643" lims:id="418643"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418644" lims:id="418644"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418646" lims:id="418646">2002, c. 28, s. 47; 2016, c. 9, s. 44</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418647" lims:id="418647" level="2"><TitleText>Inspections</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418648" lims:id="418648"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418649" lims:id="418649">Powers of inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>48</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418650" lims:id="418650"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For a purpose related to verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with the provisions of this Act and the regulations, an inspector may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418651" lims:id="418651"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subject to section 49, at any reasonable time, enter and inspect any place, or stop any means of transport, in which the inspector believes on reasonable grounds there is a pest control product or other thing to which this Act or the regulations apply;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418652" lims:id="418652"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>open and examine any receptacle, package or other thing that the inspector believes on reasonable grounds contains a pest control product or other thing to which this Act or the regulations apply and take samples from it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418653" lims:id="418653"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>order any person to present any pest control product or other thing for inspection in any manner and under any conditions that the inspector considers necessary to conduct an inspection;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418654" lims:id="418654"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>order the owner or person having possession, care or control of a means of transport that the inspector intends to enter, to move it to a place where the inspector can enter it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418655" lims:id="418655"><Label>(d.1)</Label><Text>examine or test, or take samples of, anything that is in the place being inspected;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418656" lims:id="418656"><Label>(d.2)</Label><Text>examine a document that is in the place being inspected, make copies of it or take extracts from it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418657" lims:id="418657"><Label>(d.3)</Label><Text>order the owner or person having possession, care or control of a pest control product or other thing to which this Act or the regulations apply that is in the place being inspected to move it or, for any time that may be necessary, not to move it or to restrict its movement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418658" lims:id="418658"><Label>(d.4)</Label><Text>use or cause to be used a computer or other device that is in the place being inspected to examine data that is contained in or available to a computer system or reproduce it or cause it to be reproduced in the form of a printout or other intelligible output and remove the output for examination or copying;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418659" lims:id="418659"><Label>(d.5)</Label><Text>use or cause to be used copying equipment that is in the place being inspected and remove the copies for examination;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418660" lims:id="418660"><Label>(d.6)</Label><Text>take photographs or make recordings or sketches;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418661" lims:id="418661"><Label>(d.7)</Label><Text>order any person in the place being inspected to establish their identity to the inspector’s satisfaction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418662" lims:id="418662"><Label>(d.8)</Label><Text>prohibit or limit access to all or part of the place being inspected or to anything that is in the place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418663" lims:id="418663"><Label>(d.9)</Label><Text>remove anything from the place being inspected for the purpose of examination, conducting tests or taking samples; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418664" lims:id="418664"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>conduct any tests or analyses or take any measurements.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418665" lims:id="418665"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418666" lims:id="418666">Persons accompanying inspector</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An inspector may be accompanied by any person that they believe is necessary to help them exercise their powers or perform their duties or functions under this section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418667" lims:id="418667"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418668" lims:id="418668">Entering private property</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An inspector and any person accompanying them may enter and pass through private property, other than a dwelling house on that property, in order to gain entry to a place referred to in paragraph (1)(a).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418669" lims:id="418669"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418670" lims:id="418670">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to do anything the person was ordered to do by an inspector under paragraphs (1)(c), (d), (d.3) or (d.7) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418671" lims:id="418671"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418672" lims:id="418672"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418674" lims:id="418674">2002, c. 28, s. 48; 2016, c. 9, s. 45</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418675" lims:id="418675"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418676" lims:id="418676">Warrant required to enter dwelling-place</MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418677" lims:id="418677"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An inspector may not enter a dwelling-place except with the consent of its occupant or under the authority of a warrant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418678" lims:id="418678"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418679" lims:id="418679">Authority to issue warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If on <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> application a justice is satisfied by information on oath that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418680" lims:id="418680"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the conditions for entry described in section 48 exist in relation to a dwelling-place,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418681" lims:id="418681"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>entry to the dwelling-place is necessary for a purpose related to verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with the provisions of this Act and the regulations, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418682" lims:id="418682"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>entry to the dwelling-place has been refused or there are reasonable grounds to believe that entry will be refused,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418683" lims:id="418683"><Text>the justice may at any time sign and issue a warrant authorizing the inspector named in it to enter and inspect the dwelling-place, subject to any conditions that may be specified in the warrant.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418684" lims:id="418684"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418685" lims:id="418685">Use of force</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An inspector who executes a warrant shall not use force unless he or she is accompanied by a peace officer and the use of force is specifically authorized in the warrant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418686" lims:id="418686"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418687" lims:id="418687">Telewarrant</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If an inspector believes that it would be impracticable to appear personally to make an application for a warrant under subsection (2), a warrant may be issued by telephone or other means of telecommunication, on information submitted by telephone or other means of telecommunication, and section 487.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies for that purpose, with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418689" lims:id="418689">2002, c. 28, s. 49; 2016, c. 9, s. 46</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418690" lims:id="418690"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418691" lims:id="418691">Assistance to inspectors</MarginalNote><Label>50</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418692" lims:id="418692"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The owner or the person in charge of a place entered by an inspector under section 48 or 49 and any person found in the place shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418693" lims:id="418693"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>give the inspector all reasonable assistance in their power to enable the inspector to exercise powers or perform duties or functions under the provisions of this Act or the regulations; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418694" lims:id="418694"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provide the inspector with any information relevant to the administration of the provisions of this Act or the regulations that the inspector may reasonably require.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418695" lims:id="418695"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418696" lims:id="418696">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (1) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418697" lims:id="418697"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418698" lims:id="418698"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418700" lims:id="418700">2002, c. 28, s. 50; 2016, c. 9, s. 47</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418701" lims:id="418701"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418702" lims:id="418702">Production of documents, information or samples</MarginalNote><Label>51</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418703" lims:id="418703"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An inspector may, for a purpose related to verifying compliance or preventing non-compliance with the provisions of this Act and the regulations, order a person to provide, on the date, at the time and place and in the manner specified by the inspector, any document, information or sample specified by the inspector.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418704" lims:id="418704"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418705" lims:id="418705">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to do anything the person was ordered to do by an inspector under subsection (1) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418706" lims:id="418706"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418707" lims:id="418707"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418709" lims:id="418709">2002, c. 28, s. 51; 2016, c. 9, s. 48</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418710" lims:id="418710" level="2"><TitleText>Seizures</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418711" lims:id="418711"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418712" lims:id="418712">Inspector may seize</MarginalNote><Label>52</Label><Text>An inspector may seize and detain any pest control product or other thing that the inspector has reasonable grounds to believe</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418713" lims:id="418713"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>was used in a contravention of a provision of this Act or the regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418714" lims:id="418714"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is something in relation to which a provision of this Act or the regulations was contravened; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418715" lims:id="418715"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>was obtained by the contravention of a provision of this Act or the regulations.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418717" lims:id="418717">2002, c. 28, s. 52; 2016, c. 9, s. 49</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418718" lims:id="418718" level="2"><TitleText>Dealing with Seized Things</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418719" lims:id="418719"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418720" lims:id="418720">Storage, movement and disposition</MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418721" lims:id="418721"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An inspector may, in respect of a pest control product or other thing seized under this Act,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418722" lims:id="418722"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on notice to its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure or to the owner or person responsible for the place where it was seized, store it or move it at the expense of the person to whom the notice is given;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418723" lims:id="418723"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>order its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure or the owner or person responsible for the place where it was seized to store it or move it at the expense of the person being so ordered;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418724" lims:id="418724"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>if the pest control product or other thing is perishable, order its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure to dispose of it at the expense of the person being so ordered or, on notice to its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure, dispose of it at the expense of the person to whom the notice is given; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418725" lims:id="418725"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if the inspector is of the opinion that the pest control product or other thing endangers human health or safety or the environment and that its disposition is necessary to respond to the danger, order its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure to dispose of it, despite subsection 6(8), at the expense of the person being so ordered or, on notice to its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure, dispose of it, despite subsection 6(8), at the expense of the person to whom the notice is given.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418726" lims:id="418726"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418727" lims:id="418727">Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order under paragraph (1)(c) or (d) shall be communicated by delivering a written notice to the owner or person and the notice</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418728" lims:id="418728"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>must include a statement of the reasons for the order; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418729" lims:id="418729"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>may specify the period within which and the manner in which the pest control product or other thing is to be disposed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418730" lims:id="418730"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418731" lims:id="418731">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to do anything the person was ordered to do by an inspector under paragraph (1)(b), (c) or (d) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418732" lims:id="418732"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418733" lims:id="418733"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418734" lims:id="418734"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418735" lims:id="418735">Interference with seized things</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Except with the authorization of an inspector, no person shall move, alter or interfere with a pest control product or other thing seized under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418736" lims:id="418736"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418737" lims:id="418737">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (4) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418738" lims:id="418738"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418739" lims:id="418739"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418741" lims:id="418741">2002, c. 28, s. 53; 2016, c. 9, s. 51</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418742" lims:id="418742"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418743" lims:id="418743">Release of seized thing</MarginalNote><Label>53.1</Label><Text>If an inspector is satisfied that the provisions of this Act and the regulations that apply with respect to a pest control product or other thing seized under this Act have been complied with, the product or thing must be released.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418745" lims:id="418745">2016, c. 9, s. 52</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-01-15" lims:fid="418746" lims:id="418746"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418747" lims:id="418747">Application for return</MarginalNote><Label>53.2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-01-15" lims:enacted-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418748" lims:id="1110034"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection 55(1), if proceedings are instituted in relation to a pest control product or other thing seized under this Act, its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure may apply, in the case of a violation, to the Review Tribunal continued by subsection 27(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-8.8">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal> or, in the case of an offence, to the court before which the proceedings are being held, for an order that the thing be returned.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418749" lims:id="418749"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418750" lims:id="418750">Order for return</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Review Tribunal or court, as the case may be, is satisfied that sufficient evidence exists or may reasonably be obtained without the continued detention of the pest control product or other thing, the Tribunal or court may order it to be returned to the applicant, subject to any conditions the Tribunal or court may impose to ensure that it is preserved for any purpose for which it may subsequently be required.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-01-15" lims:enacted-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="1110036" lims:id="1110036" lims:enactId="1036393">2016, c. 9, ss. 52, 72</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418753" lims:id="418753" level="2"><TitleText>Removal, Forfeiture or Destruction of Unlawful Imports</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418754" lims:id="418754"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418755" lims:id="418755">Unlawful imports</MarginalNote><Label>53.3</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418756" lims:id="418756"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An inspector who has reasonable grounds to believe that an imported pest control product does not meet the requirements of the regulations or was imported in contravention of a provision of this Act or the regulations may decide whether to give the owner or importer, or the person having possession, care or control of the product, the opportunity to take a measure in respect of it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418757" lims:id="418757"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418758" lims:id="418758">Factors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In making a decision under subsection (1), the inspector shall consider, among other factors</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418759" lims:id="418759"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>whether the pest control product endangers human health or safety or the environment; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418760" lims:id="418760"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any other prescribed factors.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418761" lims:id="418761"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418762" lims:id="418762">Duty of inspector</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the inspector decides under subsection (1) not to give the owner or importer or the person having possession, care or control of the pest control product the opportunity to take a measure in respect of it, the inspector shall exercise, in respect of the product, any of the powers conferred by the provisions of this Act, other than this section, or of the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418763" lims:id="418763"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418764" lims:id="418764">Measures that may be taken and notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>However, if the inspector decides under subsection (1) to give the owner or importer, or the person having possession, care or control of the pest control product the opportunity to take a measure in respect of it, the inspector, or any other inspector who is informed of the decision, shall decide whether the owner or importer, or the person having possession, care or control of it may remove it from Canada at their expense, consent to its forfeiture or take either of these measures, and shall notify or cause to be notified the owner or importer, or the person having possession, care or control of the product that they may take that measure within the period specified by the inspector or other inspector, as the case may be.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418765" lims:id="418765"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418766" lims:id="418766">Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If a person is notified under subsection (4) that they may consent to the forfeiture of the pest control product and the person consents to its forfeiture, the product is forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada and may be disposed of, as the Minister may direct, at the person’s expense.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418768" lims:id="418768">2016, c. 9, s. 52</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418769" lims:id="418769"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418770" lims:id="418770">Removal or destruction of unlawful imports</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418771" lims:id="418771"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An inspector who has reasonable grounds to believe that an imported pest control product does not meet the requirements of the regulations or was imported in contravention of a provision of this Act or the regulations may, by written notice, whether the pest control product is seized or not, order its owner or importer, or the person having possession, care or control of it, to remove it from Canada at their expense or, if removal is not possible, to destroy it at their expense.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418772" lims:id="418772"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418773" lims:id="418773">Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the pest control product is not removed from Canada, or destroyed, within the period specified in the notice — or, if no period is specified, within 90 days after the day on which the notice was delivered — it is, despite section 53.1, forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada and may be disposed of, as the Minister may direct, at the expense of the person to whom the notice was delivered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418774" lims:id="418774"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418775" lims:id="418775">Suspension of application of subsection (2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An inspector may, for the period specified by the inspector, suspend the application of subsection (2) if the inspector is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418776" lims:id="418776"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the pest control product does not endanger human health or safety or the environment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418777" lims:id="418777"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the pest control product will not be sold within that period;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418778" lims:id="418778"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the measures that should have been taken for the pest control product not to have been imported in contravention of a provision of this Act or the regulations will be taken within that period; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418779" lims:id="418779"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if the pest control product does not meet the requirements of the regulations, it will be brought into compliance with those requirements within that period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418780" lims:id="418780"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418781" lims:id="418781">Cancellation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An inspector may cancel the notice if the inspector is satisfied that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418782" lims:id="418782"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the pest control product does not endanger human health or safety or the environment;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418783" lims:id="418783"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the pest control product has not been sold within the period referred to in subsection (5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418784" lims:id="418784"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the measures referred to in paragraph (3)(c) were taken within that period; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418785" lims:id="418785"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>if the pest control product did not meet the requirements of the regulations when it was imported, it was brought into compliance with those requirements within that period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418786" lims:id="418786"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418787" lims:id="418787">Period</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The period for the purposes of subsection (4) is</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418788" lims:id="418788"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the application of subsection (2) was suspended under subsection (3), the period of the suspension; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418789" lims:id="418789"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if the application of subsection (2) was not suspended, the period specified in the notice or, if no period was specified, the period of 90 days after the day on which the notice was delivered.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418790" lims:id="418790"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418791" lims:id="418791">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with an order in the notice is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418792" lims:id="418792"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418793" lims:id="418793"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418795" lims:id="418795">2002, c. 28, s. 54; 2016, c. 9, s. 52</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418796" lims:id="418796" level="2"><TitleText>Forfeiture</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418797" lims:id="418797"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418798" lims:id="418798">Unclaimed pest control products or other things</MarginalNote><Label>54.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418799" lims:id="418799"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A pest control product or other thing seized under this Act is, at the Minister’s election, forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada if</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418800" lims:id="418800"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>within 60 days after the seizure, no person is identified in accordance with the regulations, if any, as its owner or as the person who is entitled to possess it; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418801" lims:id="418801"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure does not claim it within 60 days after the day on which they are notified that an inspector has released it.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418802" lims:id="418802"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418803" lims:id="418803">Proceedings instituted</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply if proceedings are instituted for a violation or an offence that relates to the seized pest control product or other thing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418804" lims:id="418804"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418805" lims:id="418805">Disposition</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A seized pest control product or other thing that is forfeited under subsection (1) may be disposed of, as the Minister may direct, at the expense of its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418807" lims:id="418807">2016, c. 9, s. 52</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2019-01-15" lims:fid="418808" lims:id="418808"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418809" lims:id="418809">Forfeiture on consent</MarginalNote><Label>55</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418810" lims:id="418810"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the election of Her Majesty in right of Canada, a pest control product or other thing seized under this Act by an inspector is forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada if the owner consents to its forfeiture. The pest control product or other thing that is forfeited may be disposed of, as the Minister directs, at the owner’s expense.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2019-01-15" lims:enacted-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418811" lims:id="1110041"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2019-01-15" lims:enacted-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="1110042" lims:id="1110042">Forfeiture by court order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Review Tribunal, continued by subsection 27(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-8.8">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>, decides that a person has committed a violation, or if an offender is convicted of an offence under this Act, the Tribunal or the court, as the case may be, may, in addition to imposing a penalty or punishment, order that the pest control product or other thing that was involved in the violation or offence be forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada, regardless of whether the product or thing was seized under this Act or not.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418813" lims:id="418813"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418814" lims:id="418814">Directions of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A pest control product or other thing that is forfeited under subsection (2) may be disposed of as the Minister directs, at the expense of,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418815" lims:id="418815"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if it was not seized, its owner; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418816" lims:id="418816"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>if it was seized, its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2019-01-15" lims:enacted-date="2012-11-22" lims:fid="1110044" lims:id="1110044" lims:enactId="1033795">2002, c. 28, s. 55; 2012, c. 24, s. 106; 2016, c. 9, ss. 52, 72</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418819" lims:id="418819"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418820" lims:id="418820">Return of seized things</MarginalNote><Label>56</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418821" lims:id="418821"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A seized pest control product or other thing shall be returned to its owner or the person having possession, care or control of the product or thing at the time of its seizure if it has not been forfeited at the final conclusion of proceedings in respect of a violation or an offence under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418822" lims:id="418822"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418823" lims:id="418823">Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A seized pest control product or other thing may be</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418824" lims:id="418824"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>detained pending the payment of any fine or penalty imposed on its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of seizure; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418825" lims:id="418825"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>sold in satisfaction of the fine or penalty.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418827" lims:id="418827">2002, c. 28, s. 56; 2016, c. 9, s. 52</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418828" lims:id="418828"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418829" lims:id="418829">Forfeiture on application of inspector</MarginalNote><Label>56.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418830" lims:id="418830"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A judge of a superior court of the province in which a pest control product or other thing is seized under this Act may, on the application of an inspector, order that the pest control product or other thing be forfeited to Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418831" lims:id="418831"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418832" lims:id="418832">Notice and inquiry</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The order may be made only if any notice to any persons that the judge directs was given and the judge finds, after making any inquiry that he or she considers necessary, that the pest control product or other thing is one by means of or in relation to which any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations have been contravened.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418833" lims:id="418833"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418834" lims:id="418834">Disposition</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A pest control product or other thing that is forfeited under subsection (1) may be disposed of, as the Minister may direct, at the expense of its owner or the person having possession, care or control of it at the time of its seizure.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418836" lims:id="418836">2016, c. 9, s. 52</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418837" lims:id="418837" level="2"><TitleText>Compliance Measures</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418838" lims:id="418838"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418839" lims:id="418839">Inspector may order measures</MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418840" lims:id="418840"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an inspector has reasonable grounds to believe that a person has contravened this Act or the regulations, he or she may order the person</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418841" lims:id="418841"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to stop or shut down any activity or thing involved in the contravention; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418842" lims:id="418842"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to take any other measures that the inspector considers necessary to prevent further contravention, including</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418843" lims:id="418843"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>modifying a pest control product or its labelling or disposing of the product so as to comply with this Act and the regulations, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418844" lims:id="418844"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>manufacturing, handling, storing, transporting, importing, exporting, packaging, labelling, distributing or using a registered pest control product in accordance with the conditions of registration.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418845" lims:id="418845"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418846" lims:id="418846">Validity period</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) may apply for a specified period or until the inspector is satisfied that no further contravention is likely to take place.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418847" lims:id="418847"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418848" lims:id="418848">Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) shall be communicated by delivering a written notice to the registrant or, as the case may be, to the owner or person having possession, care or control of the pest control product, activity or thing that was involved in the contravention and the notice must be accompanied by a statement of the reasons for the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418849" lims:id="418849"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418850" lims:id="418850">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with an order in a notice delivered under subsection (3) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418851" lims:id="418851"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418852" lims:id="418852"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418853" lims:id="418853"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418854" lims:id="418854">Prosecutions</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order under subsection (1) may be given whether or not the person has been charged with an offence relating to the contravention, but if the person is charged, the order may be confirmed, varied or rescinded by the court that tries the offence.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418856" lims:id="418856">2002, c. 28, s. 57; 2016, c. 9, ss. 54, 62(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418857" lims:id="418857" level="2"><TitleText>Disposal and Risk-control Measures</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418858" lims:id="418858"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418859" lims:id="418859">Disposal of samples</MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Text>A sample taken under this Act or the regulations may be disposed of as an inspector or analyst may direct.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418860" lims:id="418860"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418861" lims:id="418861">Inspectors may take measures to control risks</MarginalNote><Label>59</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418862" lims:id="418862"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 6(8), an inspector may take any measures described in subsection (2) if he or she has reasonable grounds to believe that there has been a contravention of this Act or the regulations and that a pest control product, or any other thing that has been treated or contaminated by a pest control product, poses a health or environmental risk that the Minister considers is unacceptable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418863" lims:id="418863"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418864" lims:id="418864">Measures</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The inspector may</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418865" lims:id="418865"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>order an owner or a person having possession, care or control of the pest control product or other thing to dispose of it or do anything else that the inspector considers necessary to reduce or eliminate the risks it poses;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418866" lims:id="418866"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>dispose of the product or other thing or do anything else that the inspector considers necessary to reduce or eliminate the risks it poses, at the expense of its owner or the person having possession, care or control of the product or thing; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418867" lims:id="418867"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>authorize any other person to exercise the powers described in paragraph (b).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418868" lims:id="418868"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418869" lims:id="418869">Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An order under paragraph (2)(a) shall be communicated by delivering a written notice to the owner or person having possession, care or control of the product or thing and the notice</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418870" lims:id="418870"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>must include a statement of the reasons for the order; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418871" lims:id="418871"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>may specify the period within which and the manner in which the required action must be taken.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418872" lims:id="418872"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418873" lims:id="418873">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who fails to comply with an order in a notice delivered under subsection (3) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418874" lims:id="418874"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418875" lims:id="418875"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418877" lims:id="418877">2002, c. 28, s. 59; 2016, c. 9, ss. 55, 62(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418878" lims:id="418878" level="2"><TitleText>Review of Inspectors’ Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418879" lims:id="418879"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418880" lims:id="418880">Request for review</MarginalNote><Label>60</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418881" lims:id="418881"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, an order in respect of which notice has been delivered under subsection 53(2), 57(3) or 59(3) shall be reviewed on the written request of the person to whom the notice was delivered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418882" lims:id="418882"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418883" lims:id="418883">Contents of and time for making request</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A request under subsection (1) shall state the grounds for the request and the decision that is requested and must be delivered to the Minister within 10 days after the date on which the notice referred to in that subsection was delivered to the person who made the request.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418884" lims:id="418884"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418885" lims:id="418885">Reviewer</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A review requested under subsection (1) may be conducted by the inspector who delivered the notice or by any other inspector or official to whom the review is assigned.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418886" lims:id="418886"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418887" lims:id="418887">Refusal when grounds already considered</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A review requested under subsection (1) may be refused if the request does not comply with subsection (2) or if the grounds stated in the request were presented to and considered by the inspector before the notice was delivered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418888" lims:id="418888"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418889" lims:id="418889">Refusal in case of emergency</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the reasons in a notice referred to in subsection (1) include the existence of an emergency concerning risks to human health or safety or the environment, the reviewer may refuse to undertake the review until he or she is satisfied that there has been sufficient compliance with the order in the notice to address the emergency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418890" lims:id="418890"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418891" lims:id="418891">Refusal not affected by inspector’s prior knowledge of emergency</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (5), the reviewer may refuse to undertake the review no matter how long before delivery of the notice the inspector had known of the circumstances concerning the emergency.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418892" lims:id="418892"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418893" lims:id="418893">Reasons for refusal</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>A refusal under subsection (4) or (5) shall be communicated in writing to the person who made the request, with reasons for the refusal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418894" lims:id="418894"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418895" lims:id="418895">Review initiated by inspector</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>An inspector who delivers a notice referred to in subsection (1), or any other inspector or official assigned to do so, may review the order included in the notice regardless of whether a request has been made under that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418896" lims:id="418896"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418897" lims:id="418897">Conduct of review</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>A review referred to in subsection (1) or (8) shall be conducted in accordance with the regulations, if any.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418898" lims:id="418898"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418899" lims:id="418899">Decision on completion of review</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>On completion of a review, the reviewer shall make a decision to confirm, amend, terminate or cancel the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418900" lims:id="418900"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418901" lims:id="418901">Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Written notice of the reviewer’s decision under subsection (10), with reasons, shall be delivered to the person who made the request or, if there was no request, to the person to whom the notice referred to in subsection (1) was, or could have been, delivered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418902" lims:id="418902"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418903" lims:id="418903">Delay in proceedings under section 61</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>An application shall not be made under section 61 in relation to an order until</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418904" lims:id="418904"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the expiry of the 10-day period referred to in subsection (2) without a review having been requested under subsection (1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418905" lims:id="418905"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a request for a review has been refused under subsection (4) or (5); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418906" lims:id="418906"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a review that has been requested under subsection (1) and has not been refused under subsection (4) or (5), or a review that has been undertaken under subsection (8), has been completed and action has been taken under subsection (10).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418907" lims:id="418907"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418908" lims:id="418908">Effect of amendment</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>When the decision under subsection (10) is to amend an order, the notice of that decision under subsection (11) is deemed, for the purpose of section 61, to have been delivered under subsection 53(2), 57(3) or 59(3), as the case may be, and the amended order is subject to review under this section.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418910" lims:id="418910">2002, c. 28, s. 60; 2016, c. 9, s. 62(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418911" lims:id="418911" level="2"><TitleText>Court Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418912" lims:id="418912"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418913" lims:id="418913">Application for court order</MarginalNote><Label>61</Label><Text>If a person fails to comply with an order in respect of which notice has been delivered under subsection 53(2), 57(3) or 59(3), the Minister may apply to the Federal Court or any other court of competent jurisdiction for an order requiring the person to comply with the notice or authorizing an inspector to take any measures the court considers necessary to ensure compliance with the notice.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418915" lims:id="418915">2002, c. 28, s. 61; 2016, c. 9, s. 62(E)</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418916" lims:id="418916" level="1"><TitleText>Delivery of Documents</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418917" lims:id="418917"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418918" lims:id="418918">Method of delivery</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418919" lims:id="418919"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Notices or other documents required or authorized to be delivered under this Act may be delivered by any method that provides proof of delivery or by any prescribed method.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418920" lims:id="418920"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418921" lims:id="418921">Representative in Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An applicant for registration of a pest control product or a registrant, who does not reside in Canada, shall</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418922" lims:id="418922"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>designate a representative who resides in Canada to whom correspondence and any notices or documents referred to in subsection (1) can be sent; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418923" lims:id="418923"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>inform the Minister in writing of the designation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418924" lims:id="418924"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418925" lims:id="418925">Presumption</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any correspondence, notices or documents received by the representative designated under subsection (2) are deemed to have been received by the applicant or registrant who designated the representative.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418926" lims:id="418926"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418927" lims:id="418927">Requirement to communicate through designated representative</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may require an applicant or registrant referred to in subsection (2) to conduct any communications with the Minister through the designated representative of the applicant or registrant.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418928" lims:id="418928"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418929" lims:id="418929">Refusal of communications</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, the Minister may refuse to receive or act on any communication that is not made in compliance with a requirement made by the Minister under subsection (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418930" lims:id="418930"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418931" lims:id="418931"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-22">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-22">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply in respect of notices or other documents delivered under this Act.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418933" lims:id="418933">2002, c. 28, s. 62; 2016, c. 9, s. 57</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418934" lims:id="418934" level="1"><TitleText>Fees, Charges and Costs</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418935" lims:id="418935"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418936" lims:id="418936">Recovery of fees</MarginalNote><Label>63</Label><Text>Her Majesty in right of Canada may recover, as a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada, any fee or charge that applies in relation to the administration of the provisions of this Act or the regulations.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418938" lims:id="418938">2002, c. 28, s. 63; 2016, c. 9, s. 58</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418939" lims:id="418939"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418940" lims:id="418940">Recovery of costs</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Text>Her Majesty in right of Canada may recover, as a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada, any costs incurred by Her Majesty in right of Canada in relation to anything required or authorized under this Act, including</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418941" lims:id="418941"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the inspection, treatment, testing or analysis of a place, pest control product or other thing or the storage, movement, seizure, detention, forfeiture, disposition or return of a pest control product or other thing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418942" lims:id="418942"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>any enforcement or risk-control measures taken by the Minister or an inspector under this Act.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418944" lims:id="418944">2002, c. 28, s. 64; 2016, c. 9, s. 58</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418945" lims:id="418945"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418946" lims:id="418946">Time limit</MarginalNote><Label>64.1</Label><Text>Proceedings to recover a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada under this Act shall not be commenced later than five years after the debt became payable.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418948" lims:id="418948">2016, c. 9, s. 58</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418949" lims:id="418949"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418950" lims:id="418950">Certificate of default</MarginalNote><Label>64.2</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418951" lims:id="418951"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any debt that may be recovered under section 63 or 64 in respect of which there is a default of payment, or the part of any such debt that has not been paid, may be certified by the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418952" lims:id="418952"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418953" lims:id="418953">Judgment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On production to the Federal Court, a certificate made under subsection (1) shall be registered in that Court and, when registered, has the same force and effect, and all proceedings may be taken on the certificate, as if it were a judgment obtained in that Court for a debt of the amount specified in the certificate and all reasonable costs and charges attendant in the registration of the certificate.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418955" lims:id="418955">2016, c. 9, s. 58</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418956" lims:id="418956" level="1"><TitleText>Limitation on Liability</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418957" lims:id="418957"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="418958" lims:id="418958">Her Majesty not liable</MarginalNote><Label>65</Label><Text>If a person must, by or under this Act or the regulations, do anything or permit an inspector to do anything, Her Majesty in right of Canada is not liable for any costs, loss or damage resulting from the compliance or to pay any fee, rent or other charge for what is done, provided, maintained or permitted.</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418959" lims:id="418959" level="1"><TitleText>Compensation for Use of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418960" lims:id="418960"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418961" lims:id="418961">Agreements to determine compensation</MarginalNote><Label>66</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418962" lims:id="418962"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall determine the terms and conditions of agreements to be entered into by applicants and registrants for the purposes of determining compensation payable for the right to use or rely on information provided by registrants to the Minister under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418963" lims:id="418963"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418964" lims:id="418964">Negotiation and arbitration</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An agreement referred to in subsection (1) shall be entered into, and provide for the determination of compensation payable through negotiation and binding arbitration, in accordance with the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418965" lims:id="418965"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418966" lims:id="418966"><XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-34.6">Commercial Arbitration Act</XRefExternal> applies</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-34.6">Commercial Arbitration Act</XRefExternal> applies to an arbitration for the purposes of this section and the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418967" lims:id="418967"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418968" lims:id="418968">Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-34.6">Commercial Arbitration Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to an arbitration referred to in subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418969" lims:id="418969"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418970" lims:id="418970">Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Regulations made by the Minister of Justice under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-34.6">Commercial Arbitration Act</XRefExternal> apply to an arbitration referred to in subsection (3) unless the parties otherwise agree.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418972" lims:id="418972">2002, c. 28, s. 66; 2017, c. 6, s. 112</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="418973" lims:id="418973" level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:lastAmendedDate="2020-07-01" lims:fid="418974" lims:id="418974"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418975" lims:id="418975">Regulations — Governor in Council</MarginalNote><Label>67</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418976" lims:id="418976"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418977" lims:id="418977"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prescribing policies of the Government of Canada that are consistent with the objectives of this Act for the purposes of the definition <DefinitionRef>government policy</DefinitionRef> in section 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418978" lims:id="418978"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prescribing the nomenclature of pests and pest control products for the purposes of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418979" lims:id="418979"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting the information and other things that must accompany an application made under section 7 or 10;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418980" lims:id="418980"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>respecting standards of laboratory practice to be used in conducting tests to obtain information about pest control products, certification of compliance with those standards, inspection and audit of compliance and the consequences of a failure to comply;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418981" lims:id="418981"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>respecting the evaluation of the health or environmental risks or the value of pest control products;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418982" lims:id="418982"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>respecting the registration of pest control products, including the types of registration for classes of products, and, for each type,</Text><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418983" lims:id="418983"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the criteria and characteristics, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418984" lims:id="418984"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the period or maximum period for which the registration is valid, which periods may be either finite or indefinite;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418985" lims:id="418985"><Label>(f.1)</Label><Text>respecting minor uses of a pest control product and defining <DefinitionRef>minor use</DefinitionRef> for the purposes of this Act and the regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418986" lims:id="418986"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>stating which requirements of the regulations are conditions of registration;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418987" lims:id="418987"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>respecting the circumstances and conditions under which information provided to the Minister by registrants may be used or relied upon in relation to applications or registrations of other persons, including distinctions among the rights of registrants based on the purposes for which the information was provided to the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418988" lims:id="418988"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>respecting the Pest Control Products Export Control List, authorizations to export pest control products and the amendment, suspension and cancellation of authorizations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418989" lims:id="418989"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>respecting review panels, including their establishment, the selection and remuneration of panel members and the travel and living expenses to which they are entitled;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418990" lims:id="418990"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>respecting authorizations to use unregistered pest control products for specific purposes and the amendment, suspension and cancellation of authorizations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418991" lims:id="418991"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>respecting the Register, including information that is to be included in the Register and public access to the information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418992" lims:id="418992"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>respecting the public disclosure of confidential test data;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418993" lims:id="418993"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>prescribing information that is to be excluded in whole or in part from the application of subsection 43(5);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418994" lims:id="418994"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>respecting the manufacture, possession, handling, storage, transport, import, export, distribution, use or disposition of pest control products;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418995" lims:id="418995"><Label>(p)</Label><Text>prescribing standards for pest control products, including standards relating to their form and composition;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418996" lims:id="418996"><Label>(q)</Label><Text>respecting the measures to be taken to facilitate the recognition of pest control products by a change in colouration or other means;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418997" lims:id="418997"><Label>(r)</Label><Text>respecting the packaging, labelling and advertising of pest control products;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418998" lims:id="418998"><Label>(s)</Label><Text>respecting pest control product safety information, including information related to product safety data sheets;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="418999" lims:id="418999"><Label>(t)</Label><Text>respecting the keeping of records by registrants, manufacturers, importers, exporters, distributors and users of pest control products in relation to the products that they manufacture, store, import, export, distribute, use or dispose of and the requirements for making those records available to the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419000" lims:id="419000"><Label>(u)</Label><Text>respecting the recording by registrants of information on sales of pest control products, the retention and reporting to the Minister of such information by registrants and former registrants and the use of such information by the Minister;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419001" lims:id="419001"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>respecting the taking of samples and the conduct of analyses for the purposes of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419002" lims:id="419002"><Label>(w)</Label><Text>respecting the inspection and operation of establishments in which registered pest control products are manufactured;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419003" lims:id="419003"><Label>(x)</Label><Text>respecting the preservation, detention and forfeiture of pest control products and any other things seized by an inspector;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419004" lims:id="419004"><Label>(y)</Label><Text>respecting the destruction or disposition of pest control products or any other thing forfeited or authorized to be disposed of under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419005" lims:id="419005"><Label>(z)</Label><Text>respecting reviews under section 60;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419006" lims:id="419006"><Label>(z.01)</Label><Text>respecting the entering into of agreements and the determination of compensation payable through negotiations and binding arbitration, under section 66;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419007" lims:id="419007"><Label>(z.1)</Label><Text>respecting the delivery or transmission of documents under this Act, including the transmission of documents in electronic form;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419008" lims:id="419008"><Label>(z.2)</Label><Text>respecting fees and charges in relation to the administration of this Act or the regulations;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419009" lims:id="419009"><Label>(z.21)</Label><Text>establishing classes of pest control products and any categories and subcategories of those classes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419010" lims:id="419010"><Label>(z.3)</Label><Text>respecting the implementation, in relation to pest control products, of international agreements that affect those products;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419011" lims:id="419011"><Label>(z.4)</Label><Text>exempting persons, activities or pest control products, including products that are imported solely for the purpose of export, from the application of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations, and prescribing the conditions under which they are exempt; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419012" lims:id="419012"><Label>(z.5)</Label><Text>prescribing anything that by this Act is to be prescribed and generally for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419013" lims:id="419013"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419014" lims:id="419014">Incorporation by reference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, regulations made under paragraph (1)(d) or (p) that incorporate a standard by reference may incorporate the standard as amended to a certain date or from time to time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419015" lims:id="419015"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419016" lims:id="419016">Jointly produced documents</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>A regulation made under this Act may incorporate by reference documents that the Minister produces jointly with another government for the purpose of harmonizing the regulation with other laws.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419017" lims:id="419017"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419018" lims:id="419018">Internally produced standards</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>A regulation made under this Act may incorporate by reference technical or explanatory documents that the Minister produces, including</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419019" lims:id="419019"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>specifications, classifications, illustrations, graphs or other information of a technical nature; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419020" lims:id="419020"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>test methods, procedures, operational standards, safety standards or performance standards of a technical nature.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419021" lims:id="419021"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419022" lims:id="419022">Scope of incorporation</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Documents may be incorporated by reference as they exist on a particular date or as they are amended from time to time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2020-07-01" lims:enacted-date="2020-03-13" lims:fid="419023" lims:id="1253151"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2020-07-01" lims:enacted-date="2020-03-13" lims:fid="1253152" lims:id="1253152">Regulations re WTO Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Without limiting the authority conferred by subsection (1), the Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary for the purpose of implementing, in relation to pest control products, Article 39(3) of the Agreement on Trade-related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights set out in Annex 1C to the WTO Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2020-07-01" lims:enacted-date="2020-03-13" lims:fid="419025" lims:id="1253153"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2020-07-01" lims:enacted-date="2020-03-13" lims:fid="1253154" lims:id="1253154">Definition of <DefinitionRef>WTO Agreement</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In subsection (3), <DefinedTermEn>WTO Agreement</DefinedTermEn> has the meaning assigned by the definition <DefinitionRef>Agreement</DefinitionRef> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="W-11.8">World Trade Organization Agreement Implementation Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2017-09-21" lims:fid="419030" lims:id="419030">2002, c. 28, s. 67; 2016, c. 9, s. 59; 2017, c. 6, s. 113</HistoricalNoteSubItem><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2020-07-01" lims:enacted-date="2020-03-13" lims:fid="1253155" lims:id="1253155" lims:enactId="1238410">2020, c. 1, s. 206</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419031" lims:id="419031" level="1"><TitleText>Interim Orders</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419032" lims:id="419032"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419033" lims:id="419033">Interim orders</MarginalNote><Label>67.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419034" lims:id="419034"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may make an interim order that contains any provision that may be contained in a regulation made under this Act if the Minister believes that immediate action is required to deal with a significant risk, direct or indirect, to health, safety or the environment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419035" lims:id="419035"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419036" lims:id="419036">Cessation of effect</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An interim order has effect from the time that it is made but ceases to have effect on the earliest of</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419037" lims:id="419037"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>14 days after it is made, unless it is approved by the Governor in Council,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419038" lims:id="419038"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the day on which it is repealed,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419039" lims:id="419039"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the day on which a regulation made under this Act, that has the same effect as the interim order, comes into force, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419040" lims:id="419040"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>one year after the interim order is made or any shorter period that may be specified in the interim order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419041" lims:id="419041"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419042" lims:id="419042">Contravention of unpublished order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall be convicted of an offence consisting of a contravention of an interim order that, at the time of the alleged contravention, had not been published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> unless it is proved that, at the time of the alleged contravention, the person had been notified of the interim order or reasonable steps had been taken to bring the purport of the interim order to the notice of those persons likely to be affected by it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419043" lims:id="419043"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419044" lims:id="419044">Exemption form <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-22">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An interim order</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419045" lims:id="419045"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is exempt from the application of sections 3, 5 and 11 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="S-22">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419046" lims:id="419046"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shall be published in the <XRefExternal reference-type="other" link="gazette">Canada Gazette</XRefExternal> within 23 days after it is made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419047" lims:id="419047"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419048" lims:id="419048">Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>For the purpose of any provision of this Act other than this section, any reference to regulations made under this Act is deemed to include interim orders, and any reference to a regulation made under a specified provision of the Act is deemed to include a reference to the portion of an interim order containing any provision that may be contained in a regulation made under the specified provision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419049" lims:id="419049"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419050" lims:id="419050">Tabling of order</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A copy of each interim order must be tabled in each House of Parliament within 15 days after it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419051" lims:id="419051"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419052" lims:id="419052">House not sitting</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>In order to comply with subsection (6), the interim order may be sent to the Clerk of the House if the House is not sitting.</Text></Subsection><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419054" lims:id="419054">2004, c. 15, s. 111.1</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419055" lims:id="419055" level="1"><TitleText>Offences and Punishment</TitleText></Heading><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419056" lims:id="419056" level="2"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419057" lims:id="419057"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419058" lims:id="419058">Contravention causing risk or harm</MarginalNote><Label>68</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419059" lims:id="419059"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence if, in contravening this Act or the regulations, they cause</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419060" lims:id="419060"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a risk of imminent death or serious bodily harm to another person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419061" lims:id="419061"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a risk of substantial harm to the environment; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419062" lims:id="419062"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>harm to the environment.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419063" lims:id="419063"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419064" lims:id="419064">Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (1) is liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419065" lims:id="419065"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419066" lims:id="419066"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419067" lims:id="419067"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419068" lims:id="419068">Offence committed wilfully or recklessly</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person is guilty of an offence if, while contravening this Act or the regulations, they wilfully or recklessly cause</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419069" lims:id="419069"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a risk of imminent death or serious bodily harm to another person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419070" lims:id="419070"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a risk of substantial harm to the environment; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419071" lims:id="419071"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>harm to the environment.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419072" lims:id="419072"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419073" lims:id="419073">Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection (3) is liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419074" lims:id="419074"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $300,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419075" lims:id="419075"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $1,000,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419076" lims:id="419076"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419077" lims:id="419077">Contravention of regulations</MarginalNote><Label>69</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes a provision of the regulations is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419078" lims:id="419078"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419079" lims:id="419079"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419080" lims:id="419080"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419081" lims:id="419081">Due diligence</MarginalNote><Label>69.1</Label><Text>A person is not to be found guilty of an offence under this Act — other than an offence under section 30 or subsection 33(8), 40(1) or 44(7), an offence under subsection 47(4) as it relates to a contravention of subsection 47(3) or an offence under subsection 68(3) or 70(3) — if they establish that they exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of the offence.</Text><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419083" lims:id="419083">2016, c. 9, s. 60</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419084" lims:id="419084" level="2"><TitleText>Related Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419085" lims:id="419085"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419086" lims:id="419086">Officers, etc., of corporations</MarginalNote><Label>70</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419087" lims:id="419087"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a corporation commits an offence under this Act, any officer, director or agent of the corporation who directed, authorized, assented to, acquiesced in or participated in the commission of the offence is a party to and guilty of the offence and liable on conviction to the punishment provided for the offence, whether or not the corporation has been prosecuted or convicted.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419088" lims:id="419088"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419089" lims:id="419089">Duty to ensure compliance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every director and officer of a corporation shall take all reasonable care to ensure that the corporation complies with this Act and the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419090" lims:id="419090"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419091" lims:id="419091">Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection (2) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419092" lims:id="419092"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $200,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419093" lims:id="419093"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $500,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:lastAmendedDate="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419094" lims:id="419094"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419095" lims:id="419095">Offence by employee or agent or mandatary</MarginalNote><Label>71</Label><Text>In a prosecution for an offence under this Act — other than an offence under section 30 or subsection 33(8), 40(1) or 44(7), an offence under subsection 47(4) as it relates to a contravention of subsection 47(3) or an offence under subsection 68(3) or 70(3) — it is sufficient proof of the offence to establish that it was committed by an employee or agent or mandatary of the accused, whether or not the employee or agent or mandatary is identified or has been prosecuted for the offence, unless the accused establishes that</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419096" lims:id="419096"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the offence was committed without the knowledge or consent of the accused; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419097" lims:id="419097"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the accused exercised all due diligence to prevent its commission.</Text></Paragraph><HistoricalNote><HistoricalNoteSubItem lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419099" lims:id="419099">2002, c. 28, s. 71; 2016, c. 9, s. 61</HistoricalNoteSubItem></HistoricalNote></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419100" lims:id="419100"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419101" lims:id="419101">Continuing offence</MarginalNote><Label>72</Label><Text>If an offence under this Act is continued on more than one day, the person who committed it is liable to be convicted for a separate offence for each day on which it is continued.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419102" lims:id="419102"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419103" lims:id="419103">Limitation period</MarginalNote><Label>73</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419104" lims:id="419104"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A proceeding by way of summary conviction in respect of an offence under this Act may be commenced at any time within two years after the day on which the Minister became aware of the subject-matter of the proceedings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419105" lims:id="419105"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419106" lims:id="419106">Minister’s certificate</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A document purporting to have been issued by the Minister, certifying the day on which the Minister became aware of the subject-matter of the proceedings, is evidence of that fact without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed it and without further proof.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419107" lims:id="419107"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419108" lims:id="419108">Venue</MarginalNote><Label>74</Label><Text>An information in respect of an offence under this Act may be tried, determined or adjudged by a summary conviction court if the defendant is resident or carrying on business within the territorial division of the court, even though the matter of the information did not arise in that territorial division.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419109" lims:id="419109"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419110" lims:id="419110">Analysis and examination</MarginalNote><Label>75</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419111" lims:id="419111"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An inspector may submit to an analyst for analysis or examination any pest control product or other thing seized by the inspector, any sample taken from that product or thing, or any other sample taken by the inspector.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419112" lims:id="419112"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419113" lims:id="419113">Certificate of analyst</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A certificate of an analyst stating that the analyst has analysed or examined a pest control product or other thing or a sample and stating the result of the analysis or examination is evidence of the statements contained in the certificate without proof of the signature or the official character of the person appearing to have signed it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419114" lims:id="419114"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419115" lims:id="419115">Attendance of analyst</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The party against whom the certificate is produced may, with leave of the court, require the attendance of the analyst for the purpose of cross-examination.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419116" lims:id="419116"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419117" lims:id="419117">Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The certificate shall not be received in evidence unless the party who intends to produce it has given the party against whom it is intended to be produced reasonable notice of that intention, together with a copy of the certificate.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419118" lims:id="419118"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419119" lims:id="419119">Suspended sentence</MarginalNote><Label>76</Label><Text>When an offender is convicted of an offence under this Act, the court may suspend the passing of sentence and may make an order that the offender comply with any condition that has any or all of the effects described in section 77.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419120" lims:id="419120"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419121" lims:id="419121">Orders of court</MarginalNote><Label>77</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419122" lims:id="419122"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When an offender is convicted of an offence under this Act, the court may, having regard to the nature of the offence and the circumstances surrounding its commission, in addition to any other punishment that may be imposed under this Act, make an order that has any or all of the following effects:</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419123" lims:id="419123"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>prohibiting the offender from committing an act or engaging in an activity that may, in the opinion of the court, result in the continuation or repetition of the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419124" lims:id="419124"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>directing the offender to take any measures that the court considers appropriate to avoid harm to human health or the environment that results from or may result from the act or omission that constituted the offence, or to remedy that harm;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419125" lims:id="419125"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>directing the offender to pay the victim, within the period that the court considers reasonable, an amount of money to cover the loss or damage that resulted from the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419126" lims:id="419126"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>directing the offender to publish, in any manner that the court directs, at the offender’s own expense, the facts relating to the offence and an apology for any harm caused by the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419127" lims:id="419127"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>directing the offender, at the offender’s own expense, to notify any person who is aggrieved or affected by the offender’s conduct of the facts relating to the conviction;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419128" lims:id="419128"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>directing the offender to post a bond or pay an amount of money into court that the court considers appropriate to ensure compliance with any condition required under this section;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419129" lims:id="419129"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>directing the offender to submit to the Minister, on application by the Attorney General of Canada made within three years after the conviction, any information with respect to the offender’s activities that the court considers appropriate in the circumstances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419130" lims:id="419130"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>directing the offender to compensate the Minister, in whole or in part, for the cost of any remedial or preventive measure taken by the Minister as a result of the act or omission that constituted the offence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419131" lims:id="419131"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>directing the offender to perform community service, subject to any reasonable conditions that may be imposed by the court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419132" lims:id="419132"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>directing the offender to pay an amount that the court considers appropriate for the purpose of conducting research; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419133" lims:id="419133"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>requiring the offender to comply with any other conditions that the court considers appropriate in the circumstances for securing the offender’s good conduct and for preventing the offender from repeating the same offence or committing another offence under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419134" lims:id="419134"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419135" lims:id="419135">Coming into force and duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made under section 76 or subsection (1) comes into force on the day on which the order is made or on any other day that the court may determine, but shall not continue in force for more than three years after that day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419136" lims:id="419136"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419137" lims:id="419137">Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an offender does not comply with an order requiring the publication of facts relating to the offence, the Minister may publish the facts and recover the costs of publication from the offender.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419138" lims:id="419138"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419139" lims:id="419139">Debt due to Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the court orders the offender to compensate the Minister or if the Minister incurs publication costs under paragraph (1)(h) or subsection (3), the costs incurred by the Minister constitute a debt due to Her Majesty in right of Canada and may be recovered in a court of competent jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419140" lims:id="419140"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419141" lims:id="419141">Additional fine</MarginalNote><Label>78</Label><Text>When an offender has been convicted of an offence under this Act, the court may order the offender to pay, in addition to any fine that may otherwise be imposed under this Act, a fine equal to three times the court’s estimation of any monetary benefits that the court is satisfied the offender gained as a result of the commission of the offence.</Text></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419142" lims:id="419142"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419143" lims:id="419143">Publication of information about contraventions</MarginalNote><Label>79</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419144" lims:id="419144"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may publish information about any contravention of this Act or the regulations, including a contravention designated as a violation under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="A-8.8">Agriculture and Agri-Food Administrative Monetary Penalties Act</XRefExternal>, for the purpose of encouraging voluntary compliance with this Act and the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419145" lims:id="419145"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419146" lims:id="419146">Publication of personal information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The information published under subsection (1) may include personal information as defined in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-21">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419147" lims:id="419147" level="1"><TitleText>Report to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419148" lims:id="419148"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419149" lims:id="419149">Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>80</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419150" lims:id="419150"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall, as soon as possible after the end of each fiscal year, prepare and cause to be laid before each House of Parliament a report on the administration and enforcement of this Act for that year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419151" lims:id="419151"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419152" lims:id="419152">Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall include in the annual report, for the fiscal year covered by the report,</Text><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419153" lims:id="419153"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a status report respecting registrations, including the registration of pest control products that pose lower risks, re-evaluations and special reviews under this Act or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>, chapter P-9 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419154" lims:id="419154"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a report on significant scientific developments relating to the evaluation of the health and environmental risks and the value of pest control products and the integration of those developments into decision-making under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419155" lims:id="419155"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419156" lims:id="419156">Permanent review of Act</MarginalNote><Label>80.1</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419157" lims:id="419157"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The administration of this Act shall, every 7 years after the day on which section 1 comes into force, stand referred to such committee of the House of Commons, of the Senate or of both Houses of Parliament as may be designated or established for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419158" lims:id="419158"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419159" lims:id="419159">Review and report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee designated or established for the purposes of subsection (1) shall, as soon as practicable, undertake a comprehensive review of the provisions and operation of this Act and shall, within one year after the review is undertaken or within such further time as the House of Commons, the Senate or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, may authorize, submit a report thereon, including a statement of any changes to this Act or its administration that the committee would recommend.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419160" lims:id="419160" level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419161" lims:id="419161"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419162" lims:id="419162">Applications under repealed Act</MarginalNote><Label>81</Label><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419163" lims:id="419163"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>This Act and the regulations apply to an application for the registration of a pest control product or for an amendment to its registration made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>, chapter P-9 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, before the day on which section 1 comes into force if no decision to grant or deny the application has been made in respect of that application on or before that day. In any case, paragraph 28(1)(a) and subsection 35(1) do not apply to applications made before April 1, 1995.</Text></Subsection><Subsection lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419164" lims:id="419164"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419165" lims:id="419165">Pest control products registered under repealed Act</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This Act and the regulations apply to all registrations under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>, chapter P-9 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, that are in effect on the day on which section 1 comes into force, except that paragraphs 42(2)(c) to (f) apply only to registrations in respect of which the public has been consulted under this Act in accordance with paragraph 28(1)(a) or (b).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419166" lims:id="419166" level="1"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419167" lims:id="419167"><Label>82 to 88</Label><Text>[Amendments]</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419168" lims:id="419168" level="1"><TitleText>Repeal</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2002-12-31" lims:lastAmendedDate="2002-12-31" lims:fid="419169" lims:id="419169"><Label>89</Label><Text>[Repeal]</Text></Section><Heading lims:inforce-start-date="2016-12-12" lims:fid="419170" lims:id="419170" level="1"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:lastAmendedDate="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419171" lims:id="419171" type="transitional"><MarginalNote lims:inforce-start-date="2006-06-28" lims:fid="419172" lims:id="419172">Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label><FootnoteRef idref="P-9.01_en_1">*</FootnoteRef>90</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, and the provisions of any Act as enacted by this Act, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text><Footnote id="P-9.01_en_1" placement="section" status="editorial" xml:space="default"><Label>*</Label><Text>[Note: Act in force June 28, 2006, <Emphasis style="italic">see</Emphasis> SI/2006-93.]</Text></Footnote></Section></Body><Schedule id="RelatedProvs"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><TitleText>RELATED PROVISIONS</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BillPiece><RelatedOrNotInForce><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
          — 2016, c. 9, s. 68</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Section 54 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>68</Label><Text>Section 54 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>52</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force, continues to apply to a pest control product seized under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal> before that day.</Text></Section></RelatedOrNotInForce><RelatedOrNotInForce><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
          — 2016, c. 9, s. 69</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Sections 60 and 61 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>69</Label><Text>Sections 60 and 61 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>, as they read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>62</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force, continue to apply to a requirement in respect of which a notice has been delivered under subsection 53(2), 57(3) or 59(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before that day.</Text></Section></RelatedOrNotInForce></BillPiece></Schedule><Schedule id="NifProvs"><ScheduleFormHeading type="amending"><TitleText>AMENDMENTS NOT IN FORCE</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><BillPiece><RelatedOrNotInForce><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
          — 2016, c. 9, ss. 36(2), (3)</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>36</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(3) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 8 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Product safety information</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations and as a condition of registration, the registrant of a pest control product shall,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>provide, in accordance with the regulations, to workplaces where the pest control product is manufactured, handled, stored or used, product safety information that complies with the prescribed requirements; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>make available, in accordance with the regulations, to persons who manufacture, handle, store or use the pest control product, product safety information that complies with the prescribed requirements.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section></RelatedOrNotInForce><RelatedOrNotInForce><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
          — 2022, c. 17, s. 69</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2016, c. 9, s. 46(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>69</Label><Text>Subsection 49(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Means of telecommunication</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An application for a warrant under subsection (2) may be submitted, and the warrant may be issued, by a means of telecommunication and section 487.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="C-46">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> applies for those purposes with any necessary modifications.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section></RelatedOrNotInForce><RelatedOrNotInForce><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
          — 2022, c. 17, s. 76</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Clarification — immediate application</MarginalNote><Label>76</Label><Text>For greater certainty, but subject to sections <XRefInternal>77</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>78</XRefInternal>, the amendments made by this Act also apply with respect to proceedings that are ongoing on the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Section></RelatedOrNotInForce><RelatedOrNotInForce><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
          — 2022, c. 17, par. 77(2)(f)</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>77</Label><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain applications for warrants</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Each of the following provisions, as it read immediately before the day on which this Act comes into force, continues to apply with respect to an application made for a warrant under the provision if the application is submitted, and no decision has been made in respect of the application, before that day:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subsection 49(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" link="P-9">Pest Control Products Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></RelatedOrNotInForce><RelatedOrNotInForce><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
          — 2022, c. 17, s. 78.1</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Impact of remote proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>78.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Justice must, no later than three years after the day on which this Act receives royal assent, initiate one or more independent reviews on the use of remote proceedings in criminal justice matters that must include an assessment of whether remote proceedings</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>enhance, preserve or adversely affect access to justice;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>maintain fundamental principles of the administration of justice; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>adequately address the rights and obligations of participants in the criminal justice system, including accused persons.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Justice must, no later than five years after the day on which a review is initiated, cause a report on the review — including any findings or recommendations resulting from it — to be laid before each House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></RelatedOrNotInForce><RelatedOrNotInForce><Heading level="5" style="nifrp"><TitleText>
          — 2022, c. 17, s. 78.2</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review by committee</MarginalNote><Label>78.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the start of the fifth year after the day on which this Act receives royal assent, the provisions enacted or amended by this Act are to be referred to a committee of the Senate and a committee of the House of Commons that may be designated or established for the purpose of reviewing the provisions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committees to which the provisions are referred are to review them and the use of remote proceedings in criminal justice matters and submit reports to the Houses of Parliament of which they are committees, including statements setting out any changes to the provisions that they recommend.</Text></Subsection></Section></RelatedOrNotInForce></BillPiece></Schedule><RecentAmendments><Amendment><AmendmentCitation link="2020_1">2020, c. 1</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2020-07-01</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation link="2019_29">2019, c. 29</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2019-06-21</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation link="2012_24">2012, c. 24, s. 106</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2019-01-15</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation link="2016_9">2016, c. 9, s. 72</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2019-01-15</AmendmentDate></Amendment><Amendment><AmendmentCitation link="2016_9">2016, c. 9, ss. 72(1) to (3)</AmendmentCitation><AmendmentDate>2019-01-15</AmendmentDate></Amendment></RecentAmendments></Statute>