<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-7</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>60-61-62</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2011-2012-2013</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code, the Canada Evidence Act and the Security of Information Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Combating Terrorism Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code, Canada Evidence and Security of Information</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2013</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>9</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2013</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2012-2-7">90645</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment replaces sections 83.28 to 83.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to provide for an investigative hearing for the purpose of gathering information for an investigation of a terrorism offence and to allow for the imposition of a recognizance with conditions on a person to prevent them from carrying out a terrorist activity. In addition, the enactment provides for those sections to cease to have effect or for the possible extension of their operation. The enactment also provides that the Attorney General of Canada and the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness include in their respective annual reports their opinion on whether those sections should be extended. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to create offences of leaving or attempting to leave Canada to commit certain terrorism offences.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> to allow the Federal Court to order that applications to it with respect to the disclosure of sensitive or potentially injurious information be made public and to allow it to order that hearings related to those applications be heard in private. In addition, the enactment provides for the annual reporting on the operation of the provisions of that Act that relate to the issuance of certificates and fiats.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> to increase, in certain cases, the maximum penalty for harbouring a person who committed an offence under that Act.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Lastly, it makes technical amendments in response to a parliamentary review of these Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Combating Terrorism Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 7(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in relation to an aircraft in service, commits an act or omission outside Canada that if committed in Canada would be an offence against any of paragraphs 77(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>),</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in relation to an air navigation facility used in international air navigation, commits an act or omission outside Canada that if committed in Canada would be an offence against paragraph 77(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>),</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 83.08(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>de conclure ou de faciliter sciemment, directement ou non, une opération relativement à des biens visés à l’alinéa <Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>de fournir sciemment à un groupe terroriste, pour son profit ou sur son ordre, des services financiers ou tout autre service connexe liés à des biens visés à l’alinéa <Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 83.08(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>No civil liability</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who acts reasonably in taking, or omitting to take, measures to comply with subsection (1) shall not be liable in any civil action arising from having taken or omitted to take the measures, if they took all reasonable steps to satisfy themselves that the relevant property was owned or controlled by or on behalf of a terrorist group.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 83.1(1) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>83.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person in Canada and every Canadian outside Canada shall disclose without delay to the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or to the Director of the Canadian Security Intelligence Service</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>Subsection 83.12(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 83.18:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Leaving Canada to participate in activity of terrorist group</MarginalNote><Label>83.181</Label><Text>Everyone who leaves or attempts to leave Canada, or goes or attempts to go on board a conveyance with the intent to leave Canada, for the purpose of committing an act or omission outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would be an offence under subsection 83.18(1) is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 83.19:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Leaving Canada to facilitate terrorist activity</MarginalNote><Label>83.191</Label><Text>Everyone who leaves or attempts to leave Canada, or goes or attempts to go on board a conveyance with the intent to leave Canada, for the purpose of committing an act or omission outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would be an offence under subsection 83.19(1) is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 14 years.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 83.2:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Leaving Canada to commit offence for terrorist group</MarginalNote><Label>83.201</Label><Text>Everyone who leaves or attempts to leave Canada, or goes or attempts to go on board a conveyance with the intent to leave Canada, for the purpose of committing an act or omission outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would be an indictable offence under this or any other Act of Parliament for the benefit of, at the direction of or in association with a terrorist group is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 14 years.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Leaving Canada to commit offence that is terrorist activity</MarginalNote><Label>83.202</Label><Text>Everyone who leaves or attempts to leave Canada, or goes or attempts to go on board a conveyance with the intent to leave Canada, for the purpose of committing an act or omission outside Canada that, if committed in Canada, would be an indictable offence under this or any other Act of Parliament if the act or omission constituting the offence also constitutes a terrorist activity is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 14 years.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>Section 83.23 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Concealing person who carried out terrorist activity</MarginalNote><Label>83.23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Everyone who knowingly harbours or conceals any person whom they know to be a person who has carried out a terrorist activity, for the purpose of enabling the person to facilitate or carry out any terrorist activity, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for a term of not more than 14 years, if the person who is harboured or concealed carried out a terrorist activity that is a terrorism offence for which that person is liable to imprisonment for life; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for a term of not more than 10 years, if the person who is harboured or concealed carried out a terrorist activity that is a terrorism offence for which that person is liable to any other punishment.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Concealing person who is likely to carry out terrorist activity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Everyone who knowingly harbours or conceals any person whom they know to be a person who is likely to carry out a terrorist activity, for the purpose of enabling the person to facilitate or carry out any terrorist activity, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>The heading before section 83.28 and sections 83.28 to 83.3 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Investigative Hearing</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>83.28</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section and section 83.29, <DefinedTermEn>judge</DefinedTermEn> means a provincial court judge or a judge of a superior court of criminal jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order for gathering information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), a peace officer may, for the purposes of an investigation of a terrorism offence, apply <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> to a judge for an order for the gathering of information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Attorney General’s consent</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A peace officer may make an application under subsection (2) only if the Attorney General’s prior consent was obtained.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Making of order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The judge to whom the application is made may make an order for the gathering of information if they are satisfied that the Attorney General’s consent was obtained as required by subsection (3), and</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that there are reasonable grounds to believe that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a terrorism offence has been committed,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>information concerning the offence, or information that may reveal the whereabouts of a person suspected by the peace officer of having committed the offence, is likely to be obtained as a result of the order, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>reasonable attempts have been made to obtain the information referred to in subparagraph (ii) by other means; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>there are reasonable grounds to believe that a terrorism offence will be committed,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>there are reasonable grounds to believe that a person has direct and material information that relates to the offence referred to in subparagraph (i), or that may reveal the whereabouts of an individual who the peace officer suspects may commit the offence referred to in that subparagraph, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>reasonable attempts have been made to obtain the information referred to in subparagraph (ii) by other means.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents of order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection (4) shall order the examination, on oath or not, of the person named in the order and require the person to attend at the place fixed by the judge, or by the judge designated under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), as the case may be, for the examination and to remain in attendance until excused by the presiding judge, and may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>order the person to bring to the examination any thing in their possession or control, and produce it to the presiding judge;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designate another judge as the judge before whom the examination is to take place; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>include any other terms or conditions that the judge considers desirable, including terms or conditions for the protection of the interests of the person named in the order and of third parties or for the protection of any ongoing investigation.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Execution of order</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The order may be executed anywhere in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Variation of order</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>The judge who made the order, or another judge of the same court, may vary its terms and conditions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Obligation to answer questions and produce things</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>A person named in an order made under subsection (4) shall answer questions put to them by the Attorney General or the Attorney General’s agent, and shall produce to the presiding judge things that the person was ordered to bring, but may refuse if answering a question or producing a thing would disclose information that is protected by any law relating to privilege or to disclosure of information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Judge to rule</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The presiding judge shall rule on any objection or other issue relating to a refusal to answer a question or to produce a thing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No person excused from complying with subsection (8)</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>No person shall be excused from answering a question or producing a thing under subsection (8) on the ground that the answer or thing may tend to incriminate them or subject them to any proceeding or penalty, but</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no answer given or thing produced under subsection (8) shall be used or received against the person in any criminal proceedings against them, other than a prosecution under section 132 or 136; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no evidence derived from the evidence obtained from the person shall be used or received against the person in any criminal proceedings against them, other than a prosecution under section 132 or 136.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right to counsel</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>A person has the right to retain and instruct counsel at any stage of the proceedings.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order for custody of thing</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>The presiding judge, if satisfied that any thing produced during the course of the examination will likely be relevant to the investigation of any terrorism offence, may order that the thing be given into the custody of the peace officer or someone acting on the peace officer’s behalf.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Arrest warrant</MarginalNote><Label>83.29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The judge who made the order under subsection 83.28(4), or another judge of the same court, may issue a warrant for the arrest of the person named in the order if the judge is satisfied, on an information in writing and under oath, that the person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is evading service of the order;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is about to abscond; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>did not attend the examination, or did not remain in attendance, as required by the order.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Execution of warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The warrant may be executed at any place in Canada by any peace officer having jurisdiction in that place.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person to be brought before judge</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A peace officer who arrests a person in the execution of the warrant shall, without delay, bring the person, or cause them to be brought, before the judge who issued the warrant or another judge of the same court. The judge in question may, to ensure compliance with the order, order that the person be detained in custody or released on recognizance, with or without sureties.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application of section 707</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 707 applies, with any necessary modifications, to persons detained in custody under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Recognizance with Conditions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Attorney General’s consent</MarginalNote><Label>83.3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General’s consent is required before a peace officer may lay an information under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Terrorist activity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1), a peace officer may lay an information before a provincial court judge if the peace officer</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>believes on reasonable grounds that a terrorist activity will be carried out; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>suspects on reasonable grounds that the imposition of a recognizance with conditions on a person, or the arrest of a person, is necessary to prevent the carrying out of the terrorist activity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appearance</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The judge who receives the information may cause the person to appear before any provincial court judge.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Arrest without warrant</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsections (2) and (3), a peace officer may arrest a person without a warrant and cause the person to be detained in custody, in order to bring them before a provincial court judge in accordance with subsection (6), if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>either</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the grounds for laying an information referred to in paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) exist but, by reason of exigent circumstances, it would be impracticable to lay an information under subsection (2), or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>an information has been laid under subsection (2) and a summons has been issued; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the peace officer suspects on reasonable grounds that the detention of the person in custody is necessary in order to prevent a terrorist activity.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duty of peace officer</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If a peace officer arrests a person without a warrant in the circumstance described in subparagraph (4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i), the peace officer shall, within the time prescribed by paragraph (6)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>lay an information in accordance with subsection (2); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>release the person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>When person to be taken before judge</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Unless a peace officer, or an officer in charge as defined in Part XVI, is satisfied that a person should be released from custody unconditionally before their appearance before a provincial court judge in accordance with the rules in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), and so releases the person, the person detained in custody shall be taken before a provincial court judge in accordance with the following rules:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if a provincial court judge is available within 24 hours after the person has been arrested, the person shall be taken before a provincial court judge without unreasonable delay and in any event within that period; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if a provincial court judge is not available within 24 hours after the person has been arrested, the person shall be taken before a provincial court judge as soon as feasible.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>How person dealt with</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>When a person is taken before a provincial court judge under subsection (6),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if an information has not been laid under subsection (2), the judge shall order that the person be released; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if an information has been laid under subsection (2),</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the judge shall order that the person be released unless the peace officer who laid the information shows cause why the person’s detention in custody is justified on one or more of the following grounds:</Text><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>the detention is necessary to ensure the person’s appearance before a provincial court judge in order to be dealt with in accordance with subsection (8),</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(B)</Label><Text>the detention is necessary for the protection or safety of the public, including any witness, having regard to all the circumstances including</Text><Subclause><Label>(I)</Label><Text>the likelihood that, if the person is released from custody, a terrorist activity will be carried out, and</Text></Subclause><Subclause><Label>(II)</Label><Text>any substantial likelihood that the person will, if released from custody, interfere with the administration of justice, and</Text></Subclause></Clause><Clause><Label>(C)</Label><Text>the detention is necessary to maintain confidence in the administration of justice, having regard to all the circumstances, including the apparent strength of the peace officer’s grounds under subsection (2), and the gravity of any terrorist activity that may be carried out, and</Text></Clause></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the judge may adjourn the matter for a hearing under subsection (8) but, if the person is not released under subparagraph (i), the adjournment may not exceed 48 hours.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Hearing before judge</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>The judge before whom the person appears in accordance with subsection (3)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may, if satisfied by the evidence adduced that the peace officer has reasonable grounds for the suspicion, order that the person enter into a recognizance to keep the peace and be of good behaviour for any period that does not exceed 12 months and to comply with any other reasonable conditions prescribed in the recognizance, including the conditions set out in subsection (10), that the judge considers desirable for preventing the carrying out of a terrorist activity; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the person was not released under subparagraph (7)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i), shall order that the person be released, subject to the recognizance, if any, ordered under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Refusal to enter into recognizance</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The judge may commit the person to prison for a term not exceeding 12 months if the person fails or refuses to enter into the recognizance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions — firearms</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Before making an order under paragraph (8)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), the judge shall consider whether it is desirable, in the interests of the safety of the person or of any other person, to include as a condition of the recognizance that the person be prohibited from possessing any firearm, cross-bow, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device, ammunition, prohibited ammunition or explosive substance, or all of those things, for any period specified in the recognizance, and if the judge decides that it is so desirable, they shall add the condition to the recognizance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Surrender, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>If the judge adds the condition described in subsection (10) to a recognizance, they shall specify in it the manner and method by which</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the things referred to in that subsection that are in the person’s possession shall be surrendered, disposed of, detained, stored or dealt with; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the authorizations, licences and registration certificates that are held by the person shall be surrendered.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>If the judge does not add the condition to a recognizance, they shall include in the record a statement of the reasons for not adding it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Variance of conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>The judge, or any other judge of the same court, may, on application of the peace officer, the Attorney General or the person, vary the conditions fixed in the recognizance.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other provisions to apply</MarginalNote><Label>(14)</Label><Text>Subsections 810(4) and (5) apply, with any necessary modifications, to proceedings under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 83.31 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Attorney General’s opinion</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada shall include in the annual report under subsection (1) his or her opinion, supported by reasons, on whether the operation of sections 83.28 and 83.29 should be extended.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 83.31 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Opinions</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of Canada and the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness shall include in their annual reports under subsections (2) and (3), respectively, their opinion, supported by reasons, on whether the operation of section 83.3 should be extended.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 83.32(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Sunset provision</MarginalNote><Label>83.32</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 83.28, 83.29 and 83.3 cease to have effect at the end of the 15th sitting day of Parliament after the fifth anniversary of the coming into force of this subsection unless, before the end of that day, the operation of those sections is extended by resolution — whose text is established under subsection (2) — passed by both Houses of Parliament in accordance with the rules set out in subsection (3).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A comprehensive review of sections 83.28, 83.29 and 83.3 and their operation shall be undertaken by any committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established by the Senate or the House of Commons, or by both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>The committee referred to in subsection (1.1) shall, within a year after a review is undertaken under that subsection or within any further time that may be authorized by the Senate, the House of Commons or both Houses of Parliament, as the case may be, submit a report on the review to Parliament, including its recommendation with respect to extending the operation of section 83.28, 83.29 or 83.3.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, establish the text of a resolution that provides for the extension of the operation of section 83.28, 83.29 or 83.3 and that specifies the period of the extension, which may not exceed five years from the first day on which the resolution has been passed by both Houses of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 83.32(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsequent extensions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The operation of section 83.28, 83.29 or 83.3 may be further extended in accordance with the procedure set out in this section, but the reference to “the fifth anniversary of the coming into force of this subsection” in subsection (1) is to be read as a reference to “the expiry of the most recent extension under this section”.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>Section 83.33 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Transitional provision — sections 83.28 and 83.29</MarginalNote><Label>83.33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In the event that sections 83.28 and 83.29 cease to have effect in accordance with section 83.32, proceedings commenced under those sections shall be completed if the hearing before the judge of the application made under subsection 83.28(2) began before those sections ceased to have effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transitional provision — section 83.3</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the event that section 83.3 ceases to have effect in accordance with section 83.32, a person detained in custody under section 83.3 shall be released when that section ceases to have effect, except that subsections 83.3(7) to (14) continue to apply to a person who was taken before a judge under subsection 83.3(6) before section 83.3 ceased to have effect.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xii.4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xii.41)</Label><Text>section 83.181 (leaving Canada to participate in activity of terrorist group),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xii.5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xii.51)</Label><Text>section 83.191 (leaving Canada to facilitate terrorist activity),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xii.6):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xii.61)</Label><Text>section 83.201 (leaving Canada to commit offence for terrorist group),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii.62)</Label><Text>section 83.202 (leaving Canada to commit offence that is terrorist activity),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 32, s. 26(3)</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>Paragraph 462.48(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the facts relied on to justify the belief, on reasonable grounds, that the person referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) has committed or benefited from the commission of any of the offences referred to in subsection (1.1) and that the information or documents referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) are likely to be of substantial value, whether alone or together with other material, to the investigation for the purposes of which the application is made.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>primary designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 487.04 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i.05):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.051)</Label><Text>section 83.181 (leaving Canada to participate in activity of terrorist group),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>primary designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 487.04 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i.06):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.061)</Label><Text>section 83.191 (leaving Canada to facilitate terrorist activity),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>primary designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 487.04 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i.07):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.071)</Label><Text>section 83.201 (leaving Canada to commit offence for terrorist group,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.072)</Label><Text>section 83.202 (leaving Canada to commit offence that is terrorist activity),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-5</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA EVIDENCE ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 43</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Text>Subsection 37(7) of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>When determination takes effect</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>An order of the court that authorizes disclosure does not take effect until the time provided or granted to appeal the order has expired or, if the order is appealed, the time provided or granted to appeal a judgment of an appeal court that confirms the order has expired and no further appeal from a judgment that confirms the order is available.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 43</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermFr>renseignements sensibles</DefinedTermFr> in section 38 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>renseignements sensibles</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>sensitive information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermFr>renseignements sensibles</DefinedTermFr> Les renseignements, en provenance du Canada ou de l’étranger, qui concernent les relations internationales ou la défense ou la sécurité nationales, qui se trouvent en la possession du gouvernement du Canada et qui sont du type des renseignements à l’égard desquels celui-ci prend des mesures de protection.</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 141(7)</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 38.04(2) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application to Federal Court — general</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If, with respect to information about which notice was given under any of subsections 38.01(1) to (4), the Attorney General of Canada does not provide notice of a decision in accordance with subsection 38.03(3) or, other than by an agreement under section 38.031, does not authorize the disclosure of the information or authorizes the disclosure of only part of the information or authorizes the disclosure subject to any conditions,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 141(7)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 38.04(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court records</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph (5)(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>), an application under this section is confidential. During the period when an application is confidential, the Chief Administrator of the Courts Administration Service may, subject to section 38.12, take any measure that he or she considers appropriate to protect the confidentiality of the application and the information to which it relates.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 141(7)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 38.04(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall hear the representations of the Attorney General of Canada and, in the case of a proceeding under Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister of National Defence, with respect to making the application public;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.1</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall, if he or she decides that the application should be made public, make an order to that effect;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a.2</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall hear the representations of the Attorney General of Canada and, in the case of a proceeding under Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister of National Defence, concerning the identity of all parties or witnesses whose interests may be affected by either the prohibition of disclosure or the conditions to which disclosure is subject, and concerning the persons who should be given notice of any hearing of the matter;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 43</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 38.06(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure order</MarginalNote><Label>38.06</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Unless the judge concludes that the disclosure of the information or facts referred to in subsection 38.02(1) would be injurious to international relations or national defence or national security, the judge may, by order, authorize the disclosure of the information or facts.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure — conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the judge concludes that the disclosure of the information or facts would be injurious to international relations or national defence or national security but that the public interest in disclosure outweighs in importance the public interest in non-disclosure, the judge may by order, after considering both the public interest in disclosure and the form of and conditions to disclosure that are most likely to limit any injury to international relations or national defence or national security resulting from disclosure, authorize the disclosure, subject to any conditions that the judge considers appropriate, of all or part of the information or facts, a summary of the information or a written admission of facts relating to the information.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 38.06 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>When determination takes effect</MarginalNote><Label>(3.01)</Label><Text>An order of the judge that authorizes disclosure does not take effect until the time provided or granted to appeal the order has expired or, if the order is appealed, the time provided or granted to appeal a judgment of an appeal court that confirms the order has expired and no further appeal from a judgment that confirms the order is available.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 43</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 38.06(4) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Admissibilité en preuve</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>La personne qui veut faire admettre en preuve ce qui a fait l’objet d’une autorisation de divulgation prévue au paragraphe (2), mais qui ne pourra peut-être pas le faire à cause des règles d’admissibilité applicables à l’instance, peut demander à un juge de rendre une ordonnance autorisant la production en preuve du fait, des renseignements, du résumé ou de l’aveu dans la forme ou aux conditions que celui-ci détermine, dans la mesure où telle forme ou telles conditions sont conformes à l’ordonnance rendue au titre du paragraphe (2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 43</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 38.11(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Special rules — hearing in private</MarginalNote><Label>38.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The judge conducting a hearing under subsection 38.04(5) or the court hearing an appeal or review of an order made under any of subsections 38.06(1) to (3) may make an order that the hearing be held, or the appeal or review be heard, in private.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special rules — hearing in National Capital Region</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>A hearing under subsection 38.04(5) or an appeal or review of an order made under any of subsections 38.06(1) to (3) shall, at the request of either the Attorney General of Canada or, in the case of a proceeding under Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister of National Defence, be held or heard, as the case may be, in the National Capital Region, as described in the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Capital Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 38.11 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote><Language xml:lang="la">Ex parte</Language> representations — public hearing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a hearing under subsection 38.04(5) is held, or an appeal or review of an order made under any of subsections 38.06(1) to (3) is heard, in public, any <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> representations made in that hearing, appeal or review shall be made in private.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 43</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>Section 38.12 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Protective order</MarginalNote><Label>38.12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The judge conducting a hearing under subsection 38.04(5) or the court hearing an appeal or review of an order made under any of subsections 38.06(1) to (3) may make any order that the judge or the court considers appropriate in the circumstances to protect the confidentiality of any information to which the hearing, appeal or review relates.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court records</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court records relating to a hearing that is held, or an appeal or review that is heard, in private or to any <Language xml:lang="la">ex parte</Language> representations are confidential. The judge or the court may order that the court records, or any part of them, relating to a private or public hearing, appeal or review be sealed and kept in a location to which the public has no access.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 43</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>Subsection 38.13(9) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Expiry</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The certificate expires 10 years after the day on which it is issued and may be reissued.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 38.16:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>38.17</Label><Text>Each year the Attorney General of Canada shall prepare and cause to be laid before each House of Parliament a report for the previous year on the operation of sections 38.13 and 38.15 that includes the number of certificates and fiats issued under sections 38.13 and 38.15, respectively.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. O-5; 2001, c. 41, s. 25</MarginalNote><TitleText>SECURITY OF INFORMATION ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Text>The heading before section 2 of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Security of Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>DÉFINITIONS ET INTERPRÉTATION</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Text>The heading before section 3 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 3:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><?Pub Caret?><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OFFENCES</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 29; 2004, c. 12, s. 21(E)</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>special operational information</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 8(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the identity of a person, agency, group, body or entity that was, is or is intended to be, has been approached to be, or has offered or agreed to be, a confidential source of information, intelligence or assistance to the Government of Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 29</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>Section 21 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Concealing person who carried out offence</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who, for the purpose of enabling or facilitating an offence under this Act, knowingly harbours or conceals a person whom they know to be a person who has committed an offence under this Act, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for a term of not more than 14 years, if the person who is harboured or concealed committed an offence under this Act for which that person is liable to imprisonment for life; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for a term of not more than 10 years, if the person who is harboured or concealed committed an offence under this Act for which that person is liable to any other punishment.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Concealing person who is likely to carry out offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who, for the purpose of enabling or facilitating an offence under this Act, knowingly harbours or conceals any person whom he or she knows to be a person who is likely to carry out an offence under this Act, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 10 years.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 1 to 9 and 14 to 29 come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 10 to 13 come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>