<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-32</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>60-61-62</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2011-2012-2013</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Civil Marriage Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Civil Marriage of Non-residents Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Civil Marriage</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2013</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><?Pub Caret1?><AnnualStatuteNumber>30</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2013</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2012-2-16">90647</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Civil Marriage Act</XRefExternal> in order to provide that all marriages performed in Canada between non-residents, whether they are of the same sex or of the opposite sex, that would be valid in Canada if the spouses were domiciled in Canada are valid for the purposes of Canadian law even if one or both of the non-residents do not, at the time of the marriage, have the capacity to enter into it under the law of their respective state of domicile. It also establishes a new divorce process that allows a Canadian court to grant a divorce to non-resident spouses who reside in a state where a divorce cannot be granted to them because that state does not recognize the validity of their marriage.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Civil Marriage of Non-residents Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2005, c. 33</MarginalNote><TitleText>CIVIL MARRIAGE ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Civil Marriage Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>MARRIAGE</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act and the headings before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Marriage of non-resident persons</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A marriage that is performed in Canada and that would be valid in Canada if the spouses were domiciled in Canada is valid for the purposes of Canadian law even though either or both of the spouses do not, at the time of the marriage, have the capacity to enter into it under the law of their respective state of domicile.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retroactivity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies retroactively to a marriage that would have been valid under the law that was applicable in the province where the marriage was performed but for the lack of capacity of either or both of the spouses to enter into it under the law of their respective state of domicile.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order dissolving marriage</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Any court order, made in Canada or elsewhere before the coming into force of this subsection, that declares the marriage to be null and void or that grants a divorce to the spouses dissolves the marriage, for the purposes of Canadian law, as of the day on which the order takes effect.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The heading before section 6 and sections 6 to 15 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><TitleText>DISSOLUTION OF MARRIAGE FOR NON-RESIDENT SPOUSES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>court</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>In this Part, <DefinedTermEn>court</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a province, means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for Ontario, the Superior Court of Justice;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for Quebec, the Superior Court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for Nova Scotia and British Columbia, the Supreme Court of the province;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for New Brunswick, Manitoba, Saskatchewan and Alberta, the Court of Queen’s Bench for the province;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland and Labrador, the trial division of the Supreme Court of the province; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>for Yukon and the Northwest Territories, the Supreme Court, and in Nunavut, the Nunavut Court of Justice.</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>It also means any other court in the province whose judges are appointed by the Governor General and that is designated by the Lieutenant Governor in Council of the province as a court for the purposes of this Part.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Divorce — non-resident spouses</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court of the province where the marriage was performed may, on application, grant the spouses a divorce if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>there has been a breakdown of the marriage as established by the spouses having lived separate and apart for at least one year before the making of the application;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>neither spouse resides in Canada at the time the application is made; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>each of the spouses is residing — and for at least one year immediately before the application is made, has resided — in a state where a divorce cannot be granted because that state does not recognize the validity of the marriage.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The application may be made by both spouses jointly or by one of the spouses with the other spouse’s consent or, in the absence of that consent, on presentation of an order from the court or a court located in the state where one of the spouses resides that declares that the other spouse</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is incapable of making decisions about his or her civil status because of a mental disability;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is unreasonably withholding consent; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>cannot be found.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception if spouse is found</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), the other spouse’s consent is required if that spouse is found in connection with the service of the application.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No corollary relief</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Divorce Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to a divorce granted under this Act.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Effective date generally</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A divorce takes effect on the day on which the judgment granting the divorce is rendered.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certificate of divorce</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After a divorce takes effect, the court must, on request, issue to any person a certificate that a divorce granted under this Act dissolved the marriage of the specified persons effective as of a specified date.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conclusive proof</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The certificate, or a certified copy of it, is conclusive proof of the facts so certified without proof of the signature or authority of the person appearing to have signed the certificate.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Legal effect throughout Canada</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>On taking effect, a divorce granted under this Act has legal effect throughout Canada.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Marriage dissolved</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>On taking effect, a divorce granted under this Act dissolves the marriage of the spouses.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>competent authority</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a court in a province, means the body, person or group of persons ordinarily competent under the laws of that province to make rules regulating the practice and procedure in that court.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rules</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), the competent authority may make rules applicable to any applications made under this Part in a court in a province, including rules</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>regulating the practice and procedure in the court;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the conduct and disposition of any applications that are made under this Part without an oral hearing;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing and regulating the duties of the officers of the court; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing and regulating any other matter considered expedient to attain the ends of justice and carry into effect the purposes and provisions of this Part.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exercise of power</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The power of a competent authority to make rules for a court must be exercised in the like manner and subject to the like terms and conditions, if any, as the power to make rules for that court that are conferred on that authority by the laws of the province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not statutory instruments</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Rules that are made under this section by a competent authority that is not a judicial or quasi-judicial body are deemed not to be statutory instruments within the meaning and for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Part, including regulations providing for uniformity in the rules made under section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations prevail</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any regulations that are made to provide for uniformity in the rules prevail over those rules.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>Section 4 comes into force in a province on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council or throughout Canada on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>