<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>S-9</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>41</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>60-61-62</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2011-2012-2013</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Nuclear Terrorism Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Criminal Code</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2013</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>13</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2013</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2012-3-9">90649</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to create four new offences relating to nuclear terrorism in order to implement the Amendment to the Convention on the Physical Protection of Nuclear Material and the International Convention for the Suppression of Acts of Nuclear Terrorism.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nuclear Terrorism Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 2(1)</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>Attorney General</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>with respect to proceedings in relation to an offence referred to in subsection 7(3.71), or in relation to an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition “terrorist activity” in subsection 83.01(1) if the act or omission was committed outside Canada but is deemed under any of subsections 7(2), (2.1) to (2.21), (3), (3.1), (3.72) and (3.73) to have been committed in Canada, means either the Attorney General of Canada or the Attorney General or Solicitor General of the province in which those proceedings are taken and includes his or her lawful deputy,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>environment</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>environnement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>environment</DefinedTermEn> means the components of the Earth and includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>air, land and water,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>all layers of the atmosphere,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>all organic and inorganic matter and living organisms, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the interacting natural systems that include components referred to in paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>nuclear facility</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>installation nucléaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>nuclear facility</DefinedTermEn> means </Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any nuclear reactor, including a reactor installed on a vessel, vehicle, aircraft or space object for use as an energy source in order to propel the vessel, vehicle, aircraft or space object or for any other purpose, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any plant or conveyance used for the production, storage, processing or transport of nuclear material or radioactive material;</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>nuclear material</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>matière nucléaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>nuclear material</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>plutonium, except plutonium with an isotopic concentration of plutonium-238 that is greater than 80%,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>uranium-233,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>uranium containing uranium-233 or uranium-235 or both in an amount such that the abundance ratio of the sum of those isotopes to the isotope uranium-238 is greater than 0.72%,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>uranium with an isotopic concentration equal to that occurring in nature, except uranium in the form of ore or ore-residue, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any substance containing any material described in paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>radioactive material</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>matière radioactive</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>radioactive material</DefinedTermEn> means any material that emits one or more types of ionizing radiation, such as alpha or beta particles, neutrons and gamma rays, and that is capable of, owing to its radiological or fissile properties, causing death, serious bodily harm or substantial damage to property or the environment;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 7 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2.2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Nuclear terrorism offence committed outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2.21)</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Act or any other Act, everyone who commits an act or omission outside Canada that if committed in Canada would constitute an offence under any of sections 82.3 to 82.6, or a conspiracy or attempt to commit such an offence, or being an accessory after the fact or counselling in relation to such an offence, is deemed to have committed that act or omission in Canada if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the act or omission is committed on a ship that is registered or licensed, or for which an identification number has been issued, under any Act of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the act or omission is committed on an aircraft that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is registered in Canada under regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is leased without crew and operated by a person who is qualified under regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> to be registered as owner of an aircraft in Canada under those regulations;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who commits the act or omission is a Canadian citizen; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who commits the act or omission is, after the commission of the act or omission, present in Canada.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 27 (1st Supp.), s. 5(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 7(3.2) to (3.6) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>The heading before section 79 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Dangerous Materials and Devices</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 82.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>device</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>82.2</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 82.3 to 82.5, <DefinedTermEn>device</DefinedTermEn> means any of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a nuclear explosive device;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a device that disperses radioactive material;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a device that emits ionizing radiation and that is capable of causing death, serious bodily harm or substantial damage to property or the environment.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Possession, etc., of nuclear material, radioactive material or device</MarginalNote><Label>82.3</Label><Text>Everyone who, with intent to cause death, serious bodily harm or substantial damage to property or the environment, makes a device or possesses, uses, transfers, exports, imports, alters or disposes of nuclear material, radioactive material or a device or commits an act against a nuclear facility or an act that causes serious interference with or serious disruption of its operations, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Use or alteration of nuclear material, radioactive material or device</MarginalNote><Label>82.4</Label><Text>Everyone who, with intent to compel a person, government or international organization to do or refrain from doing any act, uses or alters nuclear material, radioactive material or a device or commits an act against a nuclear facility or an act that causes serious interference with or serious disruption of its operations, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Commission of indictable offence to obtain nuclear material, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>82.5</Label><Text>Everyone who commits an indictable offence under this or any other Act of Parliament, with intent to obtain nuclear material, radioactive material or a device or to obtain access to a nuclear facility, is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for life.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Threats</MarginalNote><Label>82.6</Label><Text>Everyone who threatens to commit an offence under any of sections 82.3 to 82.5 is guilty of an indictable offence and is liable to imprisonment for a term of not more than 14 years.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Armed forces</MarginalNote><Label>82.7</Label><Text>For greater certainty, sections 82.3 to 82.6 do not apply to an act that is committed during an armed conflict and that, at the time and in the place of its commission, is in accordance with customary international law or conventional international law applicable to the conflict, or to activities undertaken by military forces of a state in the exercise of their official duties, to the extent that those activities are governed by other rules of international law.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 41, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(v) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>terrorist activity</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 83.01(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>the offences referred to in subsection 7(2.21) that implement the Convention on the Physical Protection of Nuclear Material, done at Vienna and New York on March 3, 1980, as amended by the Amendment to the Convention on the Physical Protection of Nuclear Material, done at Vienna on July 8, 2005 and the International Convention for the Suppression of Acts of Nuclear Terrorism, done at New York on September 14, 2005,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 183 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (xii):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(xii.01)</Label><Text>section 82.3 (possession, etc., of nuclear material, radioactive material or device),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii.02)</Label><Text>section 82.4 (use or alteration of nuclear material, radioactive material or device),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii.03)</Label><Text>section 82.5 (commission of indictable offence to obtain nuclear material, etc.),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii.04)</Label><Text>section 82.6 (threats),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Text>Paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>.<Emphasis style="italic">1</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>primary designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in section 487.04 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i.04):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.041)</Label><Text>section 82.3 (possession, etc., of nuclear material, radioactive material or device),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.042)</Label><Text>section 82.4 (use or alteration of nuclear material, radioactive material or device),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.043)</Label><Text>section 82.5 (commission of indictable offence to obtain nuclear material, etc.),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.044)</Label><Text>section 82.6 (threats),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 24, s. 45</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 607(6) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — foreign trials <Language xml:lang="la">in absentia</Language></MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A person who is alleged to have committed an act or omission outside Canada that is an offence in Canada by virtue of any of subsections 7(2) to (3.1) or (3.7), or an offence under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Crimes Against Humanity and War Crimes Act</XRefExternal>, and in respect of which the person has been tried and convicted outside Canada, may not plead <Language xml:lang="fr"><Emphasis style="italic">autrefois convict</Emphasis></Language> with respect to a count that charges that offence if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>