<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C–16</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>52-53</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the registration of information relating to sex offenders, to amend the Criminal Code and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Sex Offender Information Registration</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2004</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>01</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><?Pub Caret1?><AnnualStatuteNumber>10</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2004</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>The enactment requires that certain information about sex offenders be registered in a national database. This database is part of the automated criminal conviction records retrieval system maintained by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police. It is intended to serve as a tool that will help police investigate crimes of a sexual nature by providing them with access to current and reliable information relating to sex offenders.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>The enactment amends the Criminal Code to enable the Crown to apply for an order to require an offender who is convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of a mental disorder for, certain offences to report regularly to a designated registration centre and provide information. It creates a new Criminal Code offence for failure to comply with the order, as well as an offence for providing false or misleading information.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>The enactment regulates access to, and the use and disclosure of, the information contained in the database and includes an offence for contravention of those provisions.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PURPOSE AND PRINCIPLES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to help police services investigate crimes of a sexual nature by requiring the registration of certain information relating to sex offenders.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Principles</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This Act shall be carried out in recognition of, and in accordance with, the following principles:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the interest of protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, police services must have rapid access to certain information relating to sex offenders;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the collection and registration of accurate information on an ongoing basis is the most effective way of ensuring that such information is current and reliable; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the privacy interests of sex offenders and the public interest in their rehabilitation and reintegration into the community as law-abiding citizens require that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the information be collected only to enable police services to investigate crimes that there are reasonable grounds to suspect are of a sexual nature, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>access to the information, and use and disclosure of it, be restricted.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>database</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote> <DefinedTermFr>banque de données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>database</DefinedTermEn> means the database that contains the information that is registered under this Act.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>renseignement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>information</DefinedTermEn> includes characteristics recorded and photographs taken under subsection 5(3) and fingerprints taken under subsection 9(2).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>résidence principale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>main residence</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>main residence</DefinedTermEn> means the place in Canada where a person lives most often or, if there is no such place, the place in Canada where they may be found most often.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>membre d’un service de police</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>member of a police service</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>member of a police service</DefinedTermEn> includes</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an officer or non-commissioned member of the Canadian Forces who is appointed for the purposes of section 156 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in an area in which an aboriginal police service is responsible for policing, a member of that police service.</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>loi ontarienne</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Ontario Act</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Ontario Act</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>.order</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ordonnance</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>.order</DefinedTermEn> means an order under section 490.012 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>person who collects information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>préposé à la collecte</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>person who collects information</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is authorized under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1) to collect information.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>person who registers information</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>préposé à l’enregistrement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>person who registers information</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is authorized under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1) to register information.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>bureau d’inscription</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn> means a place that is designated as a registration centre under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>retained</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>agent contractuel</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>retained</DefinedTermEn> means retained under a contract for services, whether the contract is entered into with an individual, or with their employer or another person to whom the individual provides services.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>secondary residence</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>résidence secondaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>secondary residence</DefinedTermEn> means a place in Canada, other than a main residence, where a person regularly lives.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>sex offender</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>délinquant sexuel</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>sex offender</DefinedTermEn> means a person who is subject to one or more orders or to an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, a crime is of a sexual nature if it consists of one or more acts that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>are either sexual in nature or committed with the intent to commit an act or acts that are sexual in nature; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>constitute an offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OBLIGATIONS OF SEX OFFENDERS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>First obligation to report</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A sex offender shall report, for the first time under this Act, in person to the registration centre that serves the area in which their main residence is located.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reporting date</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an order shall report within 15 days after</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the order is made, if they are convicted of the offence in connection with which the order is made but are not given a custodial sentence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they receive an absolute or conditional discharge under Part XX.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, if they are found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for the offence in connection with which the order is made;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they are released from custody pending the determination of an appeal relating to the offence in connection with which the order is made; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>they are released from custody after serving the custodial portion of a sentence for the offence in connection with which the order is made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reporting date</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> shall report,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if they are not in custody on the day on which they become subject to the obligation, within 15 days after that day; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in any other case, within 15 days after</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>they receive an absolute or conditional discharge under Part XX.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>they are released from custody pending the determination of an appeal, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>they are released from custody after serving the custodial portion of a sentence.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compliance before leaving Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A sex offender shall not leave Canada before they report under this section.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Subsequent obligation to report</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Text>A sex offender shall subsequently report to the registration centre that serves the area in which their main residence is located in person or in accordance with regulations made under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1),</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within 15 days after they change their main residence or any secondary residence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within 15 days after they change their given name or surname; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at any time between 11 months and one year after they last reported to a registration centre under this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation and order</MarginalNote><Label>4.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a person who is subject to an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> becomes subject to an order, they shall report on the reporting dates established under the order only.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>More than one order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to more than one order shall report on the reporting dates established under the most recent order only.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Compliance if temporarily outside Canada</MarginalNote><Label>4.3</Label><Text>A sex offender who is outside Canada when they are required to report under section 4.1 shall report not later than 15 days after they return to Canada.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to provide information</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a sex offender reports to a registration centre, they shall provide the following information to a person who collects information at the registration centre:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>their given name and surname, and every alias that they use;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>their date of birth and gender;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the address of their main residence and every secondary residence or, if there is no such address, the location of that place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the address of every place at which they are employed or retained, or are engaged on a volunteer basis or, if there is no such address, the location of that place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the address of every educational institution at which they are enrolled or, if there is no such address, the location of that place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a telephone number at which they may be reached, if any, for every place referred to in paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), and the number of every mobile telephone or pager in their possession; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>their height and weight and a description of every physical distinguishing mark that they have.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When a sex offender provides the information referred to in subsection (1), the person who collects the information may ask them when and where they were convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, an offence in connection with which an order was made or, if they are subject to an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a designated offence within the meaning of subsection 490.011(1) of that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Additional information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>When a sex offender reports to a registration centre in person, the person who collects the information referred to in subsection (1) may record any observable characteristic that may assist in identification of the sex offender, including their eye colour and hair colour, and may require that their photograph be taken.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice about absence</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A sex offender shall notify a person who collects information at the registration centre that serves the area in which their main residence is located</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>of every address or location at which they stay or intend to stay, and of their actual or estimated dates of departure from, and return to, their main residence or a secondary residence, not later than 15 days after departure if they are in Canada but are absent from their main residence and every secondary residence for a period of at least 15 consecutive days;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>of their actual or estimated date of departure from their main residence or a secondary residence, not later than 15 days after departure if they are outside Canada for a period of at least 15 consecutive days; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>of their actual return to their main residence or a secondary residence after a departure referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), not later than 15 days after they return, unless they are required to report under section 4.1 or 4.3 within that period.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Means of notification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notification shall be by registered mail or in accordance with regulations made under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1), but a sex offender may not be required to provide notification in person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Young sex offender</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>A sex offender who is under 18 years of age has the right to have an appropriate adult chosen by them in attendance when they report to a registration centre and when information is collected.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>RESPONSIBILITIES OF PERSONS WHO COLLECT AND REGISTER INFORMATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Registration of information</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a police service receives a copy of an order sent in accordance with subparagraph 490.018(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)(iii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a person who registers information for the police service shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>register without delay in the database only the name of the police service and the following information relating to the person who is subject to the order:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>their given name and surname,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the number that identifies a record of fingerprints collected from them under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>, if such a record exists,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>every offence to which the order relates,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>when and where the offence or offences were committed,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>when and where the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, the offence or offences,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>the age and gender of every victim of the offence or offences, and the victim’s relationship to the person,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>the date and duration of the order, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>the court that made the order; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ensure that the registration of the information is done in a manner and in circumstances that ensure its confidentiality.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registration of information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>When the Attorney General of a province or minister of justice of a territory receives a copy of an affidavit of service and notice sent in accordance with subsection 490.021(6) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the Attorney General or minister of justice shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>register without delay in the database only the following information relating to the person who was served with the notice:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>their given name and surname,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the number that identifies a record of fingerprints collected from them under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>, if such a record exists,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the date on which the notice was served,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>every offence referred to in the notice,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>when and where the offence or offences were committed,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>when and where the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, the offence or offences,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>the age and gender of every victim of the offence or offences, and the victim’s relationship to the person,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>the expected duration of the person’s obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>in the case of a person referred to in paragraph 490.02(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the date, if any, on which the person last reported under the Ontario Act and the duration of their obligation to comply with section 3 of that Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ensure that the registration of the information is done in a manner and in circumstances that ensure its confidentiality; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>send the person a copy of all of the information relating to them that is registered in the database, by registered mail, free of charge and without delay.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Information to be given to sex offender</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a sex offender reports to a registration centre and provides satisfactory proof of their identity to a person who collects information, that person shall immediately inform them of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the nature of their obligations under sections 4 to 6 and of the information that may be collected under sections 5 and 6; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the purpose for which the information is being collected.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Fingerprints</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person who collects information has reasonable grounds to suspect that a person who is reporting to the registration centre as a sex offender under this Act is not the sex offender and no other proof of identity is satisfactory in the circumstances, they may take fingerprints from the person in order to confirm their identity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of fingerprints</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, if the fingerprints provided under subsection (2) confirm that the person who is reporting is the sex offender, they shall not be disclosed, or used for any other purpose, and shall be destroyed without delay.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Privacy and confidentiality</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The person who collects information shall ensure that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the sex offender’s privacy is respected in a manner that is reasonable in the circumstances; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the information is provided and collected in a manner and in circumstances that ensure its confidentiality.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Registration of information</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>A person who registers information collected at a registration centre</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall, subject to paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and any regulations made under paragraph 19(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), register without delay, in the database, only the information collected under sections 5 and 6;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may register at any time, in the database, the number that identifies a record of fingerprints collected from a sex offender under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Identification of Criminals Act</XRefExternal>, if such a record exists; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall ensure that the registration of the information is done in a manner and in circumstances that ensure its confidentiality.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Copy of information</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>A person who collects information at a registration centre shall, free of charge,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>either give a copy of the information collected under section 5, dated and signed by the person who collected it, to the sex offender when they report to the registration centre in person and provide information under this Act, or send it to the sex offender by mail or another means agreed to by the sex offender, without delay after it is collected, if they report in accordance with regulations made under paragraph 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or subsection 19(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>send the sex offender a copy of the information collected under section 6, dated and signed by the person who collected it, by mail or another means agreed to by the sex offender, without delay after it is collected;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>send the sex offender a copy of all of the information relating to them that is registered in the database, by mail or another means agreed to by the sex offender, without delay once the information referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is registered; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at the request of the sex offender, send them a copy of all of the information relating to them that is registered in the database, by mail or another means agreed to by the sex offender, without delay once the information referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is registered.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request for correction of information</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A sex offender or a person served with a notice under section 490.021 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> may, at any time, ask a person who collects information at the registration centre that serves the area in which their main residence is located to correct any information relating to them that is registered in the database that they believe contains an error or omission.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Correction or notation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The person who collects information shall, without delay, ensure that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>information in the database is corrected if they are satisfied that the information contains an error or omission; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a notation is attached to the information in the database that reflects any correction that is requested but not made.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>MANAGEMENT OF INFORMATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization for research</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>The Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police may authorize a person to consult information that is registered in the database for research or statistical purposes if the Commissioner</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is satisfied that those purposes cannot reasonably be accomplished without consulting that information; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>obtains from the person a written undertaking that no subsequent disclosure of that information will be made, or be allowed to be made, in a form that could reasonably be expected to identify any individual to whom it relates.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Maintenance of database</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>The database is to be maintained by the Royal Canadian Mounted Police.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Retention of information</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3) and regulations made under paragraphs 19(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), information that is registered in the database in accordance with this Act shall be kept in the database indefinitely.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permanent removal and destruction of information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, if a person who is subject to an order is finally acquitted of every offence in connection with which the order was made, or receives a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or section 748 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> for every such offence, all information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database in connection with that order shall be destroyed, or permanently removed from the database, in accordance with regulations made under paragraph 19(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Permanent removal and destruction of information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite any other Act of Parliament, all information that is collected under this Act, or registered in the database, in connection with an obligation under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> shall be destroyed, or permanently removed from the database, in accordance with regulations made under paragraph 19(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) and with any court order made under subsection 490.023(4) or 490.024(2) of that Act, if the person who is subject to the obligation</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is finally acquitted of every offence to which the obligation relates or receives a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or section 748 of that Act for every such offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is granted an exemption order under subsection 490.023(2) of that Act or on an appeal from a decision made under that subsection.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PROHIBITIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Unauthorized persons</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No person shall exercise any function or perform any duty under this Act that they are not authorized under this Act to exercise or perform.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unauthorized consultation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No person shall consult any information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database, unless they are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a member or employee of, or a person retained by, a police service who consults the information for the purpose of investigating a specific crime that there are reasonable grounds to suspect is of a sexual nature;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who collects information at the registration centre at which a sex offender last reported who consults the information in order to ensure compliance by the sex offender with an order or orders or with section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who collects or registers information and who consults the information in order to exercise the functions or perform the duties assigned to them under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who is authorized under section 13 to consult information that is registered in the database for research or statistical purposes and who does so for those purposes;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police or a person authorized by the Commissioner who consults information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database in order to perform the duties of the Commissioner under this Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a member or employee of, or a person retained by, the Royal Canadian Mounted Police who is authorized to consult the information in order to maintain the database and who does so for that purpose.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limited data matching</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>No person shall match any information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database with any other data unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person is a member or employee of, or a person retained by, a police service who matches the data for the purpose of investigating a specific crime that there are reasonable grounds to suspect is of a sexual nature, and the resulting matched data is used for the purpose of that investigation only; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person is authorized under section 13 to consult information that is registered in the database, and the resulting matched data is made anonymous.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unauthorized disclosure</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No person shall disclose any information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database or the fact that information relating to a person is collected under this Act or registered in the database, or allow it to be disclosed,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>except to the sex offender, or the person who was served with a notice under section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, to whom the information relates;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>except to a person referred to in any of paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>), if the disclosure to them is necessary to enable them to fulfil the purposes, perform the duties or exercise the functions referred to in that paragraph;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>except to a member or employee of, or a person retained by, a police service, if the disclosure to them is necessary to ensure compliance by a sex offender with an order or orders or with section 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>except to a person or court referred to in any of paragraphs 490.03(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, in accordance with that paragraph;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>except to a person to whom the disclosure is necessary for a prosecution for an offence under section 17 or under section 490.031 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or an appeal from a decision made in such a proceeding, and to a court in connection with the prosecution or appeal, if the information is relevant to that proceeding;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>except to a person to whom the disclosure is necessary to assist an investigation of any act or omission referred to in subsection 7(4.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> by a police service in the state where the act or omission was committed; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the person is authorized under section 13 to consult information that is registered in the database, the information is disclosed for research or statistical purposes, and the disclosure is not made, or allowed to be made, in a form that could reasonably be expected to identify any individual to whom it relates.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Unauthorized use</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No person shall use any information that is collected under this Act or registered in the database, or allow it to be used, for a purpose other than those referred to in paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) and (4)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OFFENCES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who knowingly provides false or misleading information under subsection 5(1) or 6(1) is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a first offence, on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a second or subsequent offence,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years, or to both, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every person who knowingly contravenes any of subsections 16(1) to (5) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>AUTHORIZATIONS, DESIGNATIONS AND REGULATIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The lieutenant governor in council of a province may, for the purposes of this Act, make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the means by which classes of persons designated by the lieutenant governor in council of the province are required to report under section 4.1 or 4.3 or provide notification under section 6;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorizing persons or classes of persons in the province to collect information;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>authorizing persons or classes of persons in the province to register information; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>designating places or classes of places in the province as registration centres, and the area of the province served by each registration centre.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), the lieutenant governor in council of a province may, by regulation, exercise the power of the Governor in Council with respect to any matter referred to in paragraph 19(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) if the Governor in Council does not make a regulation with respect to that matter that applies in the province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations cease to apply</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A regulation made with respect to a matter by the lieutenant governor in council of a province under subsection (2) ceases to apply if the Governor in Council makes a regulation with respect to that matter that applies in the province.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the Governor in Council may, by regulation, exercise any power of the lieutenant governor in council of a province under any of paragraphs 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) if the lieutenant governor in council of the province does not make a regulation under that paragraph.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations cease to apply</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A regulation made by the Governor in Council under subsection (1) in the exercise of a power under any of paragraphs 18(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) ceases to apply in a province if the lieutenant governor in council of the province makes a regulation under that paragraph.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the recording, the retention and maintenance, and the protection of information collected under this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the retention and maintenance, and the protection of information that is registered in the database;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the registration of photographs taken under subsection 5(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the destruction of information under subsections 9(3) and 15(2) and (3) and the permanent removal of information from the database; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>generally for carrying out the purposes and provisions of this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><TitleText>RELATED AMENDMENTS TO THE CRIMINAL CODE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 490.01:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Sex Offender Information</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3" type="normal"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>490.011</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and in sections 490.012 to 490.032.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>crime of a sexual nature</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>crimes de nature sexuelle</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>crime of a sexual nature</DefinedTermEn> means a crime referred to in subsection 3(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>database</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>banque de données</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>database</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>infraction désignée</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under any of the following provisions:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 7(4.1) (offence in relation to sexual offences against children),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 151 (sexual interference),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 152 (invitation to sexual touching),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>section 153 (sexual exploitation),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>section 153.1 (sexual exploitation of person with disability),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>section 155 (incest),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>subsection 160(3) (bestiality in presence of or by a child),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>section 163.1 (child pornography),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>section 170 (parent or guardian procuring sexual activity),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>section 172.1 (luring a child by means of a computer system),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>subsection 173(2) (exposure),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii)</Label><Text>paragraph 212(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) (stupefying or overpowering for the purpose of sexual intercourse),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiii)</Label><Text>subsection 212(2) (living on the avails of prostitution of a person under age of eighteen),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiv)</Label><Text>subsection 212(2.1) (aggravated offence — living on the avails of prostitution of a person under age of eighteen),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xv)</Label><Text>subsection 212(4) (obtaining prostitution of person under age of eighteen),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xvi)</Label><Text>section 271 (sexual assault),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xvii)</Label><Text>section 272 (sexual assault with a weapon, threats to a third party or causing bodily harm),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xviii)</Label><Text>paragraph 273(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) (aggravated sexual assault — use of a firearm),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xix)</Label><Text>paragraph 273(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) (aggravated sexual assault), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xx)</Label><Text>subsection 273.3(2) (removal of a child from Canada);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under any of the following provisions:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 173(1) (indecent acts),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 177 (trespassing at night),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 230 (murder in commission of offences),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>section 234 (manslaughter),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>paragraph 246(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) (overcoming resistance to commission of offence),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>section 264 (criminal harassment),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>section 279 (kidnapping),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>section 280 (abduction of a person under age of sixteen),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>section 281 (abduction of a person under age of fourteen),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>paragraph 348(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) (breaking and entering a dwelling house with intent to commit an indictable offence),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>paragraph 348(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) (breaking and entering a dwelling house and committing an indictable offence),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii)</Label><Text>paragraph 348(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) (breaking and entering a place other than a dwelling house with intent to commit an indictable offence), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiii)</Label><Text>paragraph 348(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) (breaking and entering a place other than a dwelling house and committing an indictable offence);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under any of the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as they read from time to time before January 4, 1983:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 144 (rape),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>section 145 (attempt to commit rape),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 149 (indecent assault on female),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>section 156 (indecent assault on male), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsection 246(1) (assault with intent);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an offence under any of the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, chapter C-34 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, as they read from time to time before January 1, 1988:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 146(1) (sexual intercourse with a female under age of fourteen),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 146(2) (sexual intercourse with a female between ages of fourteen and sixteen),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>section 153 (sexual intercourse with step-daughter),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>section 157 (gross indecency),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>section 166 (parent or guardian procuring defilement), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>section 167 (householder permitting defilement);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in any of paragraphs (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an attempt or conspiracy to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Ontario Act</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>loi ontarienne</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Ontario Act</DefinedTermEn> means <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Christopher’s Law (Sex Offender Registry), 2000</XRefExternal>, S.O. 2000, c. 1.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>pardon</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>réhabilitation</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>pardon</DefinedTermEn> means a pardon granted by any authority under law, other than a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or under section 748, that has not ceased to have effect or been revoked.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>bureau d’inscription</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>registration centre</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal></Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Review Board</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>commission d’examen</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Review Board</DefinedTermEn> means the Review Board established or designated for a province under subsection 672.38(1).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>verdict de non-responsabilité</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 672.1.</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of this section and sections 490.012 to 490.032, a person who is convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, a designated offence does not include a young person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> unless they are given an adult sentence within the meaning of that subsection for the offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Young Offenders Act</XRefExternal>, chapter Y-1 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, unless they are convicted of the offence in ordinary court within the meaning of that subsection.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Order to Comply with Registration Requirements</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>490.012</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A court shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in Form 52 requiring a person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in subsection 490.013(2), (3) or (4) as soon as possible after it imposes a sentence on the person for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1), or renders a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for such an offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A court shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in Form 52 requiring a person to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in subsection 490.013(2), (3) or (4) as soon as possible after it imposes a sentence on the person for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1), if the prosecutor establishes beyond a reasonable doubt that the person committed the offence with the intent to commit an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of that definition.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A court shall, on application of the prosecutor, make an order in Form 52 requiring a person in respect of whom an order may be made under subsection (1) or (2) to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in subsection 490.013(5), as soon as possible after it imposes a sentence on the person for a designated offence or renders a verdict of not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for such an offence, if the prosecutor establishes that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person was, before or after the coming into force of that Act, previously convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person is not, and was not at any time, subject to an obligation under section 490.019; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>no order was made under subsection (1) in connection with the previous offence.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The court is not required to make an order under this section if it is satisfied that the person has established that, if the order were made, the impact on them, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The court shall give reasons for its decision.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Date order begins</MarginalNote><Label>490.013</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An order made under section 490.012 begins on the day on which it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 490.012(1) or (2)</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 10 years after it was made if the offence in connection with which it was made was prosecuted summarily or is an offence for which the maximum term of imprisonment is two or five years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 20 years after it was made if the offence in connection with which it was made is one for which the maximum term of imprisonment is 10 or 14 years; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies to the person for life if the offence in connection with which it was made is one for which the maximum term of imprisonment is life.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 490.012(1) or (2) applies to a person for life if they are, or were at any time, subject to an obligation under section 490.019.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 490.012(1) or (2) applies to a person for life if they are, or were at any time, subject to an order made previously under either of those subsections.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of order</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An order made under subsection 490.012(3) applies to a person for life.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>490.014</Label><Text>The prosecutor, or a person who is subject to an order under section 490.012, may appeal from a decision of the court under that section on any ground of appeal that raises a question of law or of mixed law and fact. The appeal court may dismiss the appeal, or allow it and order a new hearing, quash the order or make an order that may be made under that section.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for termination order</MarginalNote><Label>490.015</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an order may apply for a termination order</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>not earlier than five years after the order was made, in the case of an order that is applicable for 10 years under paragraph 490.013(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>not earlier than 10 years after the order was made, in the case of an order that is applicable for 20 years under paragraph 490.013(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>not earlier than 20 years after the order was made, in the case of an order that is applicable for life under paragraph 490.013(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) or subsection 490.013(3) or (5); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on or after the day on which they receive a pardon.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application for termination of multiple orders</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If more than one order is made in respect of a person, the person may apply for a termination order not earlier than 20 years after the most recent order was made under section 490.012, or on or after the day on which they receive a pardon. The application must be in relation to every order that is in effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Person subject to obligation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an applicant is also subject to an obligation under section 490.019, the application must be in relation to that obligation as well as to every order that is in effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Re-application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person whose application is refused may re-apply not earlier than five years after they made the previous application. However, they may not re-apply under this subsection if an order is made with respect to them under section 490.012 after the previous application was made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Court to which application is made</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person must apply to a superior court of criminal jurisdiction under this section if such a court made an order to which the application relates. In any other case, they must apply to a court of criminal jurisdiction.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Termination order</MarginalNote><Label>490.016</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court shall make a termination order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact on them of continuing the order or orders, and any obligation, to which the application relates, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in the protection of society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court shall give reasons for its decision.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>490.017</Label><Text>The prosecutor or the person who applied for a termination order may appeal from a decision made under subsection 490.016(1) on any ground of appeal that raises a question of law or of mixed law and fact. The appeal court may dismiss the appeal, or allow it and order a new hearing, quash the termination order or make an order that may be made under that subsection.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>490.018</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When a court or appeal court makes an order under section 490.012, it shall cause</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the order to be read by or to the person who is subject to it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a copy of the order to be given to that person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that person to be informed of sections 4 to 7 and subsection 17(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> and section 490.031; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a copy of the order to be sent to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the Review Board that is responsible for making a disposition with respect to that person, if applicable,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the person in charge of the place in which that person is to serve the custodial portion of a sentence or is to be detained in custody as part of a disposition under Part XX.1, if applicable, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the police service whose member charged that person with the offence in connection with which the order is made.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Endorsement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After paragraphs (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) have been complied with, the person who is subject to the order shall endorse the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice on disposition by Review Board</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A Review Board shall cause a copy of the order to be given to the person who is subject to it when it directs</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under paragraph 672.54(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), that the person be discharged absolutely; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>under paragraph 672.54(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), that the person be discharged subject to conditions, unless the conditions restrict the person’s liberty in a manner and to an extent that prevent them from complying with section 4, 4.1, 4.3 or 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice before release</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The person in charge of the place in which the person is serving the custodial portion of a sentence, or is detained in custody, before their release or discharge shall give the person a copy of the order not earlier than 10 days before their release or discharge.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Obligation to Comply with Registration Requirements</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Obligation to comply</MarginalNote><Label>490.019</Label><Text>A person who is served with a notice in Form 53 shall comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for the applicable period specified in section 490.022 unless a court makes an exemption order under subsection 490.023(2).</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Persons who may be served</MarginalNote><Label>490.02</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General of a province or minister of justice of a territory may serve a person with a notice only if the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) and</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on the day on which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> comes into force, they are subject to a sentence for, or have not received an absolute discharge under Part XX.1 from, the offence; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in any other case,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>their name appears in connection with the offence, immediately before the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> comes into force, in the sex offender registry established under the Ontario Act, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>they either were a resident of Ontario at any time between April 23, 2001 and the day on which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> comes into force or committed the offence in Ontario.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A notice shall not be served on a person</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) if they have been finally acquitted of, or have received a free pardon granted under Her Majesty’s royal prerogative of mercy or section 748 for, every offence in connection with which notice may be served on them under that paragraph;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) if an application has been made for an order under subsection 490.012(3) in relation to any offence in connection with which notice may be served on them under that paragraph; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) if they have provided proof of a pardon in accordance with subsection 9(1) of the Ontario Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Period for and method of service</MarginalNote><Label>490.021</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The notice shall be personally served within one year after the day on which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a person referred to in paragraph 490.02(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is unlawfully at large or is in breach of any terms of their sentence or discharge, or conditions set under this Act, that relate to residence, the notice may be served by registered mail at their last known address.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a person referred to in paragraph 490.02(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is not in compliance with section 3 of the Ontario Act on the day on which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> comes into force, the notice may be served by registered mail at their last known address.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If a person referred to in paragraph 490.02(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) is in compliance with section 3 and subsection 7(2) of the Ontario Act on the day on which the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> comes into force but fails to comply with subsection 3(1) or 7(2) of the Ontario Act within one year after that day, the notice shall be served within one year after the day on which they failed to comply and may be served by registered mail at their last known address.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof of service</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>An affidavit of the person who served the notice, sworn before a commissioner or other person authorized to take affidavits, is evidence of the service and the notice if it sets out that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who served the notice has charge of the appropriate records and has knowledge of the facts in the particular case;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the notice was personally served on, or mailed to, the person to whom it was directed on a named day; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who served the notice identifies a true copy of the notice as an exhibit attached to the affidavit.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The person who served the notice shall, without delay, send a copy of the affidavit and the notice to the Attorney General of the province, or the minister of justice of the territory, in which the person was served.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Date obligation begins</MarginalNote><Label>490.022</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The obligation under section 490.019 begins</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>either one year after the day on which a person is served with a notice under section 490.021 or when a court decides not to make an exemption order under subsection 490.023(2), whichever is later; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>when an exemption order made under this Act is quashed.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Date obligation ends</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The obligation ends on the earliest of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which an exemption order is made on an appeal from a decision made under subsection 490.023(2),</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which the obligation of a person referred to in paragraph 490.02(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) to comply with section 3 of the Ontario Act ends under paragraph 7(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of that Act, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which a person referred to in paragraph 490.02(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) provides satisfactory proof of a pardon to a person who collects information, within the meaning of subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act"><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal></XRefExternal>, at a registration centre.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of obligation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If none of paragraphs (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) applies earlier, the obligation</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 10 years after the day on which the person was sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for an offence to which the obligation relates that was prosecuted summarily or for which the maximum term of imprisonment is two or five years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>ends 20 years after the day on which the person was sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for an offence to which the obligation relates and for which the maximum term of imprisonment is 10 or 14 years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies for life if the maximum term of imprisonment for an offence to which the obligation relates is life; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>applies for life if the person was convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, more than one offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>490.023</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is not subject to an order under section 490.012 may, within one year after the day on which they are served with a notice under section 490.021, apply to any court of criminal jurisdiction for an order exempting them from the obligation under section 490.019.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court shall make an exemption order if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact of the obligation on them, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in protecting society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The court shall give reasons for its decision.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the court makes an exemption order, it shall also make an order requiring the permanent removal from the database of all information that relates to the person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>490.024</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Attorney General or the person who applied for an exemption order may appeal from a decision of the court under subsection 490.023(2) on any ground of appeal that raises a question of law or of mixed law and fact. The appeal court may dismiss the appeal, or allow it and order a new hearing, quash the exemption order or make an order that may be made under that subsection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Effect of exemption order</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an appeal court makes an exemption order, it shall also make an order requiring the permanent removal from the database of all information that relates to the person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Requirements relating to notice</MarginalNote><Label>490.025</Label><Text>When a court decides not to make an exemption order under subsection 490.023(2) or an appeal court dismisses an appeal from such a decision or quashes an exemption order made under that subsection, it shall notify the Attorney General of the decision and cause the person who applied for the exemption order to be informed of sections 4 to 7 and subsection 17(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> and section 490.031.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application for termination order</MarginalNote><Label>490.026</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person who is subject to an obligation under section 490.019 and is not subject to an order under section 490.012 may apply to a court of criminal jurisdiction for a termination order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Time for application</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person may apply for a termination order under subsection (1) if the following period has elapsed since the day on which they were sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for an offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1):</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>five years if the offence was prosecuted summarily or is an offence for which the maximum term of imprisonment is two or five years;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>10 years if the offence is one for which the maximum term of imprisonment is 10 or 14 years; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>20 years if the offence is one for which the maximum term of imprisonment is life.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>More than one offence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who committed more than one offence referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) may apply for a termination order under subsection (1) if 20 years have elapsed since the day on which they were sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for the most recent offence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Re-application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A person whose application is refused may re-apply if five years have elapsed since the day on which they made the previous application. However, they may not re-apply under this subsection if an order is made with respect to them under section 490.012 after the previous application was made.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Termination order</MarginalNote><Label>490.027</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The court shall make an order terminating the obligation if it is satisfied that the person has established that the impact on them of continuing the obligation, including on their privacy or liberty, would be grossly disproportionate to the public interest in the protection of society through the effective investigation of crimes of a sexual nature, to be achieved by the registration of information relating to sex offenders under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reasons for decision</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The court shall give reasons for its decision.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deemed application</MarginalNote><Label>490.028</Label><Text>If a person is eligible to apply for both an exemption order under section 490.023 and a termination order under section 490.026 within one year after they are served with a notice under section 490.021, an application within that period for one order is deemed to be an application for both.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appeal</MarginalNote><Label>490.029</Label><Text>The Attorney General or the person who applied for a termination order may appeal from a decision of the court made under section 490.027 on any ground of appeal that raises a question of law or of mixed law and fact. The appeal court may dismiss the appeal, or allow it and order a new hearing, quash the termination order or make an order that may be made under that section.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Disclosure of Information</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Disclosure by Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>490.03</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>At the request of a prosecutor or the Attorney General, as the case may be, the Commissioner of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police shall disclose information that is registered in the database or the fact that such information is registered in the database</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the prosecutor, if the Commissioner is satisfied that the disclosure is necessary for the purposes of a proceeding for an order under section 490.012; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the Attorney General, if the Commissioner is satisfied that the disclosure is necessary for the purposes of a proceeding under section 490.015, 490.023 or 490.026, or an appeal from a decision made in a proceeding under any of those sections or in a proceeding for an order under section 490.012.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure by Commissioner</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>At the request of the Attorney General, the Commissioner shall disclose to the Attorney General all information relating to a person that is registered in the database if the person, in connection with a proceeding, discloses any such information or the fact that any such information is registered in the database.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in legal proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The prosecutor or the Attorney General may disclose the information to a court in connection with a proceeding referred to in subsection (1) or (2), or to an appeal court in connection with an appeal from a decision made in the proceeding, if the information is relevant to the proceeding or appeal.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disclosure in legal proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Information that is collected under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> or registered in the database and that is relevant to the proceeding may be disclosed to a judge or justice in a proceeding relating to an application for a search warrant in connection with the investigation of a crime that there are reasonable grounds to suspect is of a sexual nature.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Offences</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>490.031</Label><Text>Every person who, without reasonable excuse, fails to comply with an order made under section 490.012 or with an obligation under section 490.019, is guilty of an offence and liable</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a first offence, on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a second or subsequent offence,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>on conviction on indictment, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than two years, or to both, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>on summary conviction, to a fine of not more than $10,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than six months, or to both.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>490.032</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>requiring that additional information be contained in a notice under Form 53; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing, for one or more provinces, the form and content of that information.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Part XXVIII of the Act is amended by adding the following at the end of that Part:</Text><AmendedText><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 52</Label><OriginatingRef>(Section 490.012)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>ORDER TO COMPLY WITH SEX OFFENDER INFORMATION REGISTRATION ACT</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><FormGroup><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Province of ....................</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>To A.B., of ................, (<Emphasis style="italic">occupation</Emphasis>):</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>You have been convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, ............. (<Emphasis style="italic">insert description of offence(s)</Emphasis>), a designated offence (<Emphasis style="italic">or if more than one offence</Emphasis>, designated offences) within the meaning of subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, under ......... (<Emphasis style="italic">insert the applicable designated offence provision(s) of the Criminal Code</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>1.</Label><Text>You must report for the first time, in person, to the registration centre that serves the area in which your main residence is located, whenever required under subsection 4(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>2.</Label><Text>You must subsequently report to the registration centre that serves the area in which your main residence is located whenever required under section 4.1 or 4.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, for a period of ...... years after this order is made (<Emphasis style="italic">or if paragraph 490.013(2)(c) or any of subsections 490.013(3) to (5) of the Criminal Code applies</Emphasis>, for life).</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Information relating to you will be collected under sections 5 and 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> by a person who collects information at the registration centre.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Information relating to you will be registered in a database, and may be consulted, disclosed and used in the circumstances set out in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>5.</Label><Text>If you believe that the information registered in the database contains an error or omission, you may ask a person who collects information at the registration centre that serves the area in which your main residence is located to correct the information.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>6.</Label><Text>You have the right to appeal this order.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>7.</Label><Text>You have the right to apply to a court to terminate this order, and the right to appeal any decision of that court.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>8.</Label><Text>If you are found to have contravened this order, you may be subject to a fine or imprisonment, or to both.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>9.</Label><Text>If you are found to have provided false or misleading information, you may be subject to a fine or imprisonment, or to both.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Dated this ................ day of ................, at ................. .</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="center"><Text>.........................................</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="center"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of judge and name of court</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="center"><Text>.........................................</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" justification="center"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">Signature of person subject to order</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision></FormGroup><FormGroup><ScheduleFormHeading><Label>FORM 53</Label><OriginatingRef>(Sections 490.019 and 490.032)</OriginatingRef><TitleText>NOTICE OF OBLIGATION TO COMPLY WITH SEX OFFENDER INFORMATION REGISTRATION ACT</TitleText></ScheduleFormHeading><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Canada,</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Province of ....................</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" topmarginspacing="0"><Text>(<Emphasis style="italic">territorial division</Emphasis>)</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>To A.B., of ............, (<Emphasis style="italic">occupation</Emphasis>), a person referred to in subsection 490.02(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Because, on ....... (<Emphasis style="italic">insert date(s)</Emphasis>), you were convicted of, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder for, ......... (<Emphasis style="italic">insert description of offence(s)</Emphasis>), one or more offences referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) or (<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, under ....... (<Emphasis style="italic">insert the applicable offence provision(s) of the Criminal Code</Emphasis>), this is provided to give you notice that you are required to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>1.</Label><Text>You must report for the first time, in person, to the registration centre that serves the area in which your main residence is located, whenever required under subsection 4(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>2.</Label><Text>You must subsequently report to the registration centre that serves the area in which your main residence is located whenever required under section 4.1 or 4.3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> for a period of ....... years after the day on which you were sentenced, or found not criminally responsible on account of mental disorder, for the offence (<Emphasis style="italic">or if paragraph 490.022(3)(c) of the Criminal Code applies</Emphasis>, for life) or for any shorter period set out in subsection 490.022(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>3.</Label><Text>Information relating to you will be collected under sections 5 and 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal> by a person who collects information at the registration centre.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Information relating to you will be registered in a database, and may be consulted, disclosed and used in the circumstances set out in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>5.</Label><Text>If you believe that the information registered in the database contains an error or omission, you may ask a person who collects information at the registration centre that serves the area in which your main residence is located to correct the information.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>6.</Label><Text>You have the right to apply to a court to exempt you from the obligation to comply with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Sex Offender Information Registration Act</XRefExternal>, and the right to appeal any decision of that court.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>7.</Label><Text>You have the right to apply to a court to terminate the obligation, and the right to appeal any decision of that court.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>8.</Label><Text>If you are found to have contravened the obligation, you may be subject to a fine or imprisonment, or to both.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>9.</Label><Text>9. If you are found to have provided false or misleading information, you may be subject to a fine or imprisonment, or to both.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>Dated this ................ day of ................, at ................. .</Text></Provision></FormGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>REVIEW AND REPORT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Review by committee</MarginalNote><Label>21.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The administration of this Act shall, two years after the coming into force of this Act, be reviewed by the parliamentary committee that may be designated or established by Parliament for that purpose.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee designated or established by Parliament for the purpose of subsection (1) shall undertake a review of the provisions and operation of this Act and shall, within six months after the review is undertaken or within any further time that may be authorized, submit a report to Parliament thereon including a statement of any changes to this Act or its administration that the committee would recommend.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Schedule II to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding, in alphabetical order, a reference to</Text><AmendedText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-1"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Sex Offender Information Registration Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’enregistrement de renseignements sur les délinquants sexuels</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></Provision></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>and a corresponding reference in respect of that Act to “subsections 9(3) and 16(4)”.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-47</MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 1, s. 4</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Records Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>unless the pardon is subsequently revoked or ceases to have effect, requires the judicial record of the conviction to be kept separate and apart from other criminal records and removes any disqualification or obligation to which the person so convicted is, by reason of the conviction, subject by virtue of the provisions of any Act of Parliament, other than section 109, 110, 161, 259, 490.012 or 490.019 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> or subsection 147.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Defence Act</XRefExternal>, or of a regulation made under an Act of Parliament.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING PROVISION</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-20</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>If Bill C-20, introduced in the 2nd Session of the 37th Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (protection of children and other vulnerable persons) and the Canada Evidence Act</XRefExternal> (the “other Act”), receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of section 6 of the other Act and the coming into force of this Act, subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>designated offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 490.011(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>section 162 (voyeurism),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>subsection 173(1) (indecent acts),</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>