<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C–8</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>52-53</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish the Library and Archives of Canada, to amend the Copyright Act and to amend certain Acts in consequence</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Library and Archives of Canada Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Library and Archives of Canada</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2004</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>1</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2004</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment creates the Library and Archives of Canada as the successor to the National Library and the National Archives of Canada and provides for the appointment of its head, the Librarian and Archivist of Canada.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment provides for functions and powers of the Librarian and Archivist that are a modernization of the present functions and powers of the National Librarian and National Archivist of Canada and integrates their formerly distinct missions. The regime for legal deposit of publications has also been updated to provide for the deposit of electronic publications. A new power to preserve the documentary heritage of Canada as found on the Internet has also been introduced.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the Copyright Act by providing for a longer term of protection for unpublished or posthumously published works of authors who died before 1949. The new terms of protection are extended for varying periods, depending on the date of the author's death and whether or not the work is published during the particular periods in question. Furthermore, requirements for archives holding unpublished works in their collections that were deposited before 1999 to obtain consents from copyright holders for the making of certain copies of those works and related recordkeeping or owner tracing requirements have been removed.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Text>This enactment makes several consequential amendments to relevant legislation and contains transitional provisions and coordinating amendments.</Text></Provision></Summary><?Pub Caret?><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>WHEREAS it is necessary that</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the documentary heritage of Canada be preserved for the benefit of present and future generations;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Canada be served by an institution that is a source of enduring knowledge accessible to all, contributing to the cultural, social and economic advancement of Canada as a free and democratic society;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that institution facilitate in Canada cooperation among the communities involved in the acquisition, preservation and diffusion of knowledge; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that institution serve as the continuing memory of the government of Canada and its institutions;</Text></Provision></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION AND APPLICATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>The definitions in this section apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>documentary heritage</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>patrimoine documentaire</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>documentary heritage</DefinedTermEn> means publications and records of interest to Canada.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>government institution</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>institution fédérale</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>government institution</DefinedTermEn> means a government institution listed in Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> or the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> or any institution designated by the Governor in Council.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>government record</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>document fédéral</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>government record</DefinedTermEn> means a record that is under the control of a government institution.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Librarian and Archivist</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Version anglaise seulement</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Librarian and Archivist</DefinedTermEn> means the Librarian and Archivist of Canada appointed under subsection 5(1).</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the member of the Queen's Privy Council for Canada who is designated by the Governor in Council as the Minister for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>ministerial record</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>document ministériel</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>ministerial record</DefinedTermEn> means a record of a member of the Queen's Privy Council for Canada who holds the office of a minister and that pertains to that office, other than a record that is of a personal or political nature or that is a government record.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>publication</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>publication</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>publication</DefinedTermEn> means any library matter that is made available in multiple copies or at multiple locations, whether without charge or otherwise, to the public generally or to qualifying members of the public by subscription or otherwise. Publications may be made available through any medium and may be in any form, including printed material, on-line items or recordings.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>document</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn> means any documentary material other than a publication, regardless of medium or form.</Text></Definition></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>This Act binds Her Majesty in right of Canada.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>ESTABLISHMENT AND ORGANIZATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>There is hereby established a branch of the public service of Canada to be known as the Library and Archives of Canada presided over by the Minister and under the direction of the Librarian and Archivist.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment of Librarian and Archivist</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall appoint an officer, to be called the Librarian and Archivist of Canada, to hold office during pleasure and to have the rank and powers of a deputy head of a department.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Acting Librarian and Archivist</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Librarian and Archivist is absent or incapacitated or if the office of Librarian and Archivist is vacant, the Minister may appoint a person to act as Librarian and Archivist, but the term of such an appointment shall not exceed six months except with the approval of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of Advisory Council</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>The Minister may establish an Advisory Council to advise the Librarian and Archivist with regard to making the documentary heritage known to Canadians and to anyone with an interest in Canada and facilitating access to it.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OBJECTS AND POWERS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Objects</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>The objects of the Library and Archives of Canada are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to acquire and preserve the documentary heritage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to make that heritage known to Canadians and to anyone with an interest in Canada and to facilitate access to it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to be the permanent repository of publications of the Government of Canada and of government and ministerial records that are of historical or archival value;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to facilitate the management of information by government institutions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to coordinate the library services of government institutions; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to support the development of the library and archival communities.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers of Librarian and Archivist</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Librarian and Archivist may do anything that is conducive to the attainment of the objects of the Library and Archives of Canada, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>acquire publications and records or obtain the care, custody or control of them;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>take measures to catalogue, classify, identify, preserve and restore publications and records;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>compile and maintain information resources such as a national bibliography and a national union catalogue;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide information, consultation, research or lending services, as well as any other services for the purpose of facilitating access to the documentary heritage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establish programs and encourage or organize any activities, including exhibitions, publications and performances, to make known and interpret the documentary heritage;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enter into agreements with other libraries, archives or institutions in and outside Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>advise government institutions concerning the management of information produced or used by them and provide services for that purpose;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide leadership and direction for library services of government institutions;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide professional, technical and financial support to those involved in the preservation and promotion of the documentary heritage and in providing access to it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>carry out such other functions as the Governor in Council may specify.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sampling from Internet</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In exercising the powers referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and for the purpose of preservation, the Librarian and Archivist may take, at the times and in the manner that he or she considers appropriate, a representative sample of the documentary material of interest to Canada that is accessible to the public without restriction through the Internet or any similar medium.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Destruction or disposal</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Librarian and Archivist may dispose of any publication or record under his or her control, including by destruction, if he or she considers that it is no longer necessary to retain it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any such disposition is subject to the terms and conditions under which the publication or record has been acquired or obtained.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>LEGAL DEPOSIT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Deposit of publications</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, the publisher who makes a publication available in Canada shall, at the publisher's own expense, provide two copies of the publication to the Librarian and Archivist - who shall acknowledge their receipt - within</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in any case other than one referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), seven days after the day it is made available; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a publication that is in a class prescribed under paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>), seven days after receiving a written request from the Librarian and Archivist or any longer period specified in the request.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may make regulations for the purposes of this section, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>defining <DefinedTermEn>publisher</DefinedTermEn>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting any measures that must be taken to make the publications that use a medium other than paper and their contents accessible to the Librarian and Archivist;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the classes of publications in respect of which only one copy is required to be provided; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the classes of publications in respect of which the obligation under subsection (1) applies only on a written request from the Librarian and Archivist.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Property</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Publications provided to the Librarian and Archivist under this section belong to Her Majesty and form part of the collection of the Library and Archives of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Each version, edition or form of a publication</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, every version, edition or form of a publication shall be considered a distinct publication.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OBTAINING ARCHIVAL QUALITY RECORDINGS FOR PRESERVATION PURPOSES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Providing archival quality copy</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the Librarian and Archivist determines that a recording that was made available to the public in Canada has historical or archival value, he or she may by a written request require any other person who is legally entitled to provide such a copy to provide to the Librarian and Archivist, in accordance with the terms specified, a copy of that recording in the form and quality that the Librarian and Archivist determines is suitable for archival purposes and specifies in the request.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>recording</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>recording</DefinedTermEn> means anything that requires a machine in order to use its content, whether sounds, images or other information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment for copy</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Librarian and Archivist shall reimburse the person, other than Her Majesty in right of Canada or one of Her agents, who provides a copy under subsection (1) for the actual cost of making that copy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Binding on Crown in right of a province</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>This section binds Her Majesty in right of a province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Property</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Copies provided to the Librarian and Archivist under this section belong to Her Majesty and form part of the collection of the Library and Archives of Canada.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>GOVERNMENT AND MINISTERIAL RECORDS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Destruction and disposal</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No government or ministerial record, whether or not it is surplus property of a government institution, shall be disposed of, including by being destroyed, without the written consent of the Librarian and Archivist or of a person to whom the Librarian and Archivist has, in writing, delegated the power to give such consents.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right of access to records</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite anything in any other Act of Parliament, the Librarian and Archivist has a right of access to any record to whose disposition he or she has been asked to consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section, the Librarian and Archivist may have access to a record to which subsection 69(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> applies, only with the consent of the Clerk of the Privy Council and to a government record that contains information the disclosure of which is restricted by or pursuant to any provision set out in Schedule II to that Act, only with the consent of the head of the government institution in question.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right to give access</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite anything in any other Act of Parliament, any officer or employee of a government institution may grant to the Librarian and Archivist access to any record to whose disposition the Librarian and Archivist has been asked to consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Security requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Librarian and Archivist and every person acting on behalf or under the direction of the Librarian and Archivist shall, with respect to access to records, satisfy any security requirements applicable to, and take any oath of secrecy required to be taken by, persons who normally have access to those records.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Transfer of records</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The transfer to the care and control of the Librarian and Archivist of government or ministerial records that he or she considers to have historical or archival value shall be effected in accordance with any agreements for the transfer of records that may be made between the Librarian and Archivist and the government institution or person responsible for the records.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by regulation, prescribe terms and conditions governing the transfer of records under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Government records at risk</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If government records referred to in subsection (1) are, in the opinion of the Librarian and Archivist, at risk of serious damage or destruction, the Librarian and Archivist may require their transfer in the manner and at the time that the Librarian and Archivist specifies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Records of former government institutions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Except as otherwise directed by the Governor in Council, the Librarian and Archivist shall have the care and control of all records of a government institution whose functions have ceased.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>Sections 12 and 13 do not apply in respect of records that are library or museum materials kept by a government institution for reference or exhibition purposes.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Restricted access to Privy Council confidences</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>The Librarian and Archivist shall not provide access to confidences of the Queen's Privy Council for Canada to which subsection 69(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> applies without the consent of the Clerk of the Privy Council.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SURPLUS CROWN ASSETS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Surplus publications</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Text>Despite the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Surplus Crown Assets Act</XRefExternal>, all publications that have become surplus to the requirements of any government institution shall be placed in the care or control of the Librarian and Archivist.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Surplus Crown Assets Act</XRefExternal> not to apply</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Surplus Crown Assets Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to any record or publication that is in the care or control of the Librarian and Archivist.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>FINANCIAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Account</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There shall be an account in the accounts of Canada called the Library and Archives of Canada Account to which shall be credited all amounts received for the Library and Archives of Canada including by way of gift.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amounts payable out of Account</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Any amounts required for the purposes of this Act may be paid out of the Library and Archives of Canada Account.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Use of funds</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Amounts referred to in subsection (1) shall be used in accordance with any terms and conditions attached to them.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>GENERAL</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Production of certified copy</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), if the Librarian and Archivist is compelled to produce a record or publication that is under his or her control, the Librarian and Archivist may certify a copy of it and produce that copy, which is receivable in evidence in the same manner as the original without proof of the signature or official character of the person or persons appearing to have certified it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Production of original</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the court, tribunal or other entity under whose authority the Librarian and Archivist may be compelled to produce a record or publication is satisfied that it is necessary, taking into account the risks implicit in the production of the original and the importance of its preservation and of continued access to it, to order that the original of the record or publication be produced, the court, tribunal or other entity shall ensure that any measures that are required to protect and preserve it are taken and that it is returned to the care and control of the Librarian and Archivist as soon as it is no longer needed for the purposes of the matter in question.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OFFENCES AND PENALTIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Offence and punishment</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes subsection 10(1) or the regulations or fails to comply with a request of the Librarian and Archivist under subsection 11(1) is guilty of an offence and liable on summary conviction</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of an individual, to the fine referred to in subsection 787(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a corporation, to the fine referred to in paragraph 735(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No imprisonment in default of fine payment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 787(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a term of imprisonment may not be imposed for default of payment of a fine imposed under subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recovery of fines</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A fine imposed under subsection (1) is a debt payable to Her Majesty in right of Canada and may be recovered as such in any court of competent jurisdiction or by any manner provided for in any Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-42</MarginalNote><TitleText>AMENDMENTS TO THE COPYRIGHT ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 24, s. 18(1)</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 30.21(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Copyright Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Copying works deposited in archive</MarginalNote><Label>30.21.</Label><Text>It is not an infringement of copyright for an archive to make a copy, in accordance with subsection (3), of an unpublished work that is deposited in the archive.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 31, s. 60(E)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 30.21(3)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the person who deposited the work, if a copyright owner, did not, at the time the work was deposited, prohibit its copying;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 24, s. 18(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 30.21(5) to (7) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) applies in respect of unpublished works deposited in an archive on or before September 1, 1999 or at any time after that date.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. A-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Access to Information Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 3, s. 32 (Sch., s. 1(1))</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>Paragraph 68(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>material placed in the Library and Archives of Canada, the National Gallery of Canada, the Canadian Museum of Civilization, the Canadian Museum of Nature or the National Museum of Science and Technology by or on behalf of persons or organizations other than government institutions.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (3rd Supp.), s. 12(5) (Sch., s. 1(3))</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by striking out the following under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Archives nationales du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Library</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque nationale</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Library and Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque et Archives du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-42</MarginalNote><TitleText>Copyright Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 24, s. 18(1)</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>Section 30.5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Copyright Act</XRefExternal> and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><?Pub Dtl?><TitleText>Library and Archives of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Section><?Pub Dtl?><MarginalNote>Permitted acts</MarginalNote><Label>30.5</Label><Text>It is not an infringement of copyright for the Librarian and Archivist of Canada under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make a copy of a work or other subject-matter in taking a representative sample for the purpose of preservation under subsection 8(2) of that Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>effect the fixation of a copy of a publication, as defined in section 2 of that Act, that is provided by telecommunication in accordance with subsection 10(1) of that Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make a copy of a recording, as defined in subsection 11(2) of that Act, for the purposes of section 11 of that Act; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at the time that a broadcasting undertaking, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal>, communicates a work or other subject-matter to the public by telecommunication, make a copy of the work or other subject-matter that is included in that communication.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 24, s. 18(1)</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Text>Subsection 30.8(7) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>official archive</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>In subsection (6), <DefinedTermEn>official archive</DefinedTermEn> means the Library and Archives of Canada or any archive established under the law of a province for the preservation of the official archives of the province.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. V-1; 2000, c. 34, par. 94(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)(F)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Veterans Affairs Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 34, s. 16</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>Paragraph 6.6(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Veterans Affairs Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>personal information collected or obtained by the Library and Archives of Canada in the administration of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, or any predecessor enactment relating to the same subject-matter.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. E-15</MarginalNote><TitleText>Excise Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 27, s. 128(3)</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>Paragraph 295(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide access to records of confidential information to the Librarian and Archivist of Canada or a person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Librarian and Archivist, solely for the purposes of section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, and transfer such records to the care and control of such persons solely for the purposes of section 13 of that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>Financial Administration Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 11, s. 46</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the references in column I to</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Archives nationales du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Library</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque nationale</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>and the corresponding references in column II to the “Minister of Canadian Heritage”.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30.</Label><Text>Schedule I.1 to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order in column I:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Library and Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque et Archives du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>and a corresponding reference in column II to the “Minister of Canadian Heritage”.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. H-4</MarginalNote><TitleText>Historic Sites and Monuments Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (3rd Supp.), s. 12(5) (Sch., s. 2)</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Historic Sites and Monuments Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Librarian and Archivist of Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (5th Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>Income Tax Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>32.</Label><Text>Paragraph 241(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide access to records of taxpayer information to the Librarian and Archivist of Canada or a person acting on behalf of or under the direction of the Librarian and Archivist, solely for the purposes of section 12 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, and transfer such records to the care and control of such persons solely for the purposes of section 13 of that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2003, c. 14</MarginalNote><TitleText>Injured Military Members Compensation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>33.</Label><Text>Paragraph 13(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Injured Military Members Compensation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>personal information collected or obtained by the Library and Archives of Canada in the administration of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canda Act</XRefExternal>, or any predecessor enactment relating to the same subject-matter.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 29</MarginalNote><TitleText>Nunavut Land Claims Agreement Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>34.</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Nunavut Land Claims Agreement Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Library and Archives of Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Parliament of Canada Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 36, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>Subsection 75.1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Selection</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Speaker of the Senate and the Speaker of the House of Commons, acting together, shall select the Parliamentary Poet Laureate from a list of three names submitted in confidence by a committee chaired by the Parliamentary Librarian and also composed of the Librarian and Archivist of Canada, the Commissioner of Official Languages for Canada and the Chair of the Canada Council.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-6</MarginalNote><TitleText>Pension Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 34, s. 41</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>Paragraph 109.1(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pension Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>personal information collected or obtained by the Library and Archives of Canada in the administration of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, or any predecessor enactment relating to the same subject-matter.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-21</MarginalNote><TitleText>Privacy Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (3rd Supp.), s. 12(5) (Sch., s. 4(1))</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 8(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to the Library and Archives of Canada for archival purposes;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (3rd Supp.), s. 12(5) (Sch., s. 4(2))</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Personal information disclosed by Library and Archives of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to any other Act of Parliament, personal information under the custody or control of the Library and Archives of Canada that has been transferred there by a government institution for historical or archival purposes may be disclosed in accordance with the regulations to any person or body for research or statistical purposes.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (3rd Supp.), s. 12(5) (Sch., s. 4(3))</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>Subsection 10(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception for Library and Archives of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply in respect of personal information under the custody or control of the Library and Archives of Canada that has been transferred there by a government institution for historical or archival purposes.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1990, c. 3, s. 32 (Sch., s. 6(1))</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>Paragraph 69(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>material placed in the Library and Archives of Canada, the National Gallery of Canada, the Canadian Museum of Civilization, the Canadian Museum of Nature or the National Museum of Science and Technology by or on behalf of persons or organizations other than government institutions.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (3rd Supp.), s. 12(5) (Sch., s. 4(6))</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is amended by striking out the following under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Archives nationales du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Library</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque nationale</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41.</Label><Text>The schedule to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Government Institutions</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Library and Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque et Archives du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 17; 2001, c. 41, s. 48</MarginalNote><TitleText>Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 12, s. 1</MarginalNote><Label>42.</Label><Text>Paragraph 54(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>notwithstanding the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, shall destroy each report received and all information received or collected on the expiry of the applicable period referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 30</MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Sector Compensation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>43.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Sector Compensation Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Portions of the Public Service</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Archives nationales du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Library</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque nationale</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44.</Label><Text>Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order under the heading “<Emphasis style="italic">Other Portions of the Public Service</Emphasis>”:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Library and Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque et Archives du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-35</MarginalNote><TitleText>Public Service Staff Relations Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>SOR/87-297</MarginalNote><Label>45.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Archives nationales du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Library</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque nationale</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>46.</Label><Text>Part I of Schedule I to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Library and Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque et Archives du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. W-3</MarginalNote><TitleText>War Veterans Allowance Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 34, s. 84</MarginalNote><Label>47.</Label><Text>Paragraph 30(1.1)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">War Veterans Allowance Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>personal information collected or obtained by the Library and Archives of Canada in the administration of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, or any predecessor enactment relating to the same subject-matter.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 1</MarginalNote><TitleText>Youth Criminal Justice Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>48.</Label><Text>The portion of section 126 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Records in the custody, etc., of archivists</MarginalNote><Label>126.</Label><Text>When records originally kept under sections 114 to 116 are under the custody or control of the Librarian and Archivist of Canada or the archivist for any province, that person may disclose any information contained in the records to any other person if</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>49.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 128(2) and (3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposal of records</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to paragraph 125(7)(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>), any record kept under sections 114 to 116, other than a record kept under subsection 115(3), may, in the discretion of the person or body keeping the record, be destroyed or transmitted to the Librarian and Archivist of Canada or the archivist for any province, at any time before or after the end of the applicable period set out in section 119.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposal of R.C.M.P. records</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>All records kept under subsection 115(3) shall be destroyed or, if the Librarian and Archivist of Canada requires it, transmitted to the Librarian and Archivist, at the end of the applicable period set out in section 119 or 120.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 128(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Authority to inspect</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Librarian and Archivist of Canada may, at any time, inspect records kept under sections 114 to 116 that are under the control of a government institution as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, and the archivist for a province may at any time inspect any records kept under those sections that the archivist is authorized to inspect under any Act of the legislature of the province.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 34</MarginalNote><TitleText>Yukon First Nations Land Claims Settlement Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>50.</Label><Text>Paragraph 15(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon First Nations Land Claims Settlement Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Library and Archives of Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1994, c. 35</MarginalNote><TitleText>Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>51.</Label><Text>Paragraph 25(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Yukon First Nations Self-Government Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Library and Archives of Canada;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>No continuation in office</MarginalNote><Label>52.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The persons who were the National Archivist of Canada and the National Librarian immediately before the coming into force of section 55 cease to hold those offices on the coming into force of subsection 5(1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Transfer of existing holdings</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The records and publications that constituted the collections of the National Archives of Canada and the National Library immediately before the coming into force of section 55 are transferred to the Librarian and Archivist subject to any terms and conditions that were applicable to those records and publications.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Continuation of personnel</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who was, immediately before the coming into force of section 55, an employee employed in the National Archives of Canada or the National Library is an employee of the Library and Archives of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Transfer of funds</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>All amounts that were in the accounts of Canada called the National Archives of Canada Account and the National Library Special Operating Account immediately before the coming into force of section 55 are transferred to the Library and Archives of Canada Account.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, “National Archives of Canada” and “National Library” are replaced by “Library and Archives of Canada” in</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any regulation, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other instrument made</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the execution of a power conferred by or under an Act of Parliament, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>by or under the authority of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, “National Archivist of Canada” and “National Librarian” are replaced by “Librarian and Archivist of Canada” in</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any regulation, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>any other instrument made</Text><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the execution of a power conferred by or under an Act of Parliament, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph type="amending"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>by or under the authority of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>References</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, a reference in any contract or other document to</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the “National Archives of Canada” or the “National Library” shall be read as a reference to the “Library and Archives of Canada”; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the “National Archivist of Canada” or the “National Librarian” shall be read as a reference to the Librarian and Archivist of Canada”.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-6</MarginalNote><Label>53.</Label><Text>If Bill C-6, introduced in the 3rd session of the 37th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Assisted Human Reproduction Act</XRefExternal> (the “other Act”), receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of section 1 of this Act and section 16 of the other Act, paragraph 16(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the other Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>government institutions subject to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Library and Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-25</MarginalNote><Label>54.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (5) apply if Bill C-25, introduced in the 2nd session of the 37th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal> (the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 1 of this Act and subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Labour Relations Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 2 of the other Act, section 4 of the English version of this Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>There is hereby established a branch of the federal public administration to be known as the Library and Archives of Canada presided over by the Minister and under the direction of the Librarian and Archivist.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of section 4 of this Act and section 11 of the other Act, Schedule IV to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 11 of the other Act, is amended</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>by striking out the following:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Archives nationales du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>National Library</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque nationale</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Library and Archives of Canada</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Bibliothèque et Archives du Canada</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 55 of this Act comes into force before, or on the same day as, section 224 of the other Act, then, on the coming into force of section 55 of this Act, paragraph 224(<Emphasis style="italic">z</Emphasis>.52) of the other Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the repeal of Part I of Schedule I to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal> takes effect by virtue of an order made under section 285 of the other Act before the coming into force of section 45 of this Act, then, on the day on which that Part I is repealed, section 45 of this Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>REPEALS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>55.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Archives of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 1 of the 3rd Supplement to the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1985, is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal of R.S., c. N-12</MarginalNote><Label>56.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Library Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order</MarginalNote><Label>57.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, other than sections 21, 53 and 54, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>