<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C–17</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>52-53</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend certain Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Amendments and Corrections Act, 2003</ShortTitle><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2004</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><ConsolidatedNumber /><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>16</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2004</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends and makes corrections to certain laws of Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><?Pub Caret?><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-46</MarginalNote><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Amendments and Corrections Act, 2003</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA CUSTOMS AND REVENUE AGENCY ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Section 21 of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Customs and Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Indemnisation</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>Les administrateurs et le commissaire délégué nommé en vertu du paragraphe 26(1) sont réputés être des agents de l'État pour l'application de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur l'indemnisation des agents de l'État</XRefExternal> et appartenir à l'administration publique fédérale pour l'application des règlements pris en vertu de l'article 9 de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur l'aéronautique</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The heading before section 25 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading><TitleText>Commissaire et commissaire délégué</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Text>Sections 26 to 29 of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Nomination et mandat du commissaire délégué</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le gouverneur en conseil peut nommer un commissaire délégué des douanes et du revenu à titre amovible pour un mandat maximal de cinq ans. Celui-ci peut recevoir un ou plusieurs nouveaux mandats d'au plus cinq ans chacun.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Attributions du commissaire délégué</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Le commissaire délégué exerce les attributions que lui confie le commissaire.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence ou empêchement du commissaire</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>En cas d'absence ou d'empêchement du commissaire ou de vacance de son poste, sa charge est assumée par le commissaire délégué.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Absence ou empêchement</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>En cas d'absence ou d'empêchement du commissaire et du commissaire délégué ou de vacance de leur poste, le ministre peut confier à un employé de l'Agence les attributions du commissaire; cependant, l'intérim ne peut dépasser soixante jours sans l'approbation du gouverneur en conseil.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Temps plein</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le commissaire et le commissaire délégué assument leur charge à temps plein.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rémunération</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>L'Agence verse au commissaire et au commissaire délégué la rémunération que fixe le gouverneur en conseil.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Frais de déplacement et de séjour</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>Le commissaire et le commissaire délégué sont indemnisés des frais de déplacement et de séjour entraînés par l'accomplissement de leurs fonctions hors de leur lieu habituel de travail.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5.</Label><Text>Section 57 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Activités politiques</MarginalNote><Label>57.</Label><Text>Les articles 32 à 34 de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur l'emploi dans la fonction publique</XRefExternal> s'appliquent aux commissaire, commissaire délégué et employés de l'Agence. À ces fins, les commissaire et commissaire délégué sont réputés être des administrateurs généraux, et les employés, des fonctionnaires, au sens de l'article 2 de cette loi.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 1 (2nd Supp.)</MarginalNote><TitleText>CUSTOMS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2001, c. 25, s. 36</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Paragraph 43.1(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Customs Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>s'agissant de marchandises exportées d'un pays ALÉNA, du Chili ou du Costa Rica, sur toute autre question portant sur l'application à celles-ci du paragraphe 1 de l'article 509 de l'ALÉNA, du paragraphe 1 de l'article E-09 de l'ALÉCC ou du paragraphe 1 de l'article V.9 ou du paragraphe 10 de l'article IX.2 de l'ALÉCCR, selon le cas;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. F-11</MarginalNote><TitleText>FINANCIAL ADMINISTRATION ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 24, s. 29</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>Section 104.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>officer-director</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>104.1</Label><Text>In this Division, <DefinedTermEn>officer-director</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a parent Crown corporation, means the chairperson and the chief executive officer of the corporation, by whatever name called.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 105(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Continuation in office</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), if a director of a parent Crown corporation is not appointed to take office on the expiration of the term of an incumbent director, other than an officer-director, the incumbent director continues in office until his or her successor is appointed.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 105(8) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Qualifications preserved</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Nothing in this section is to be construed as empowering the appointment or re-appointment as a director or officer-director of a parent Crown corporation, or the continuation in office as a director of a parent Crown corporation, of any person who does not meet any qualifications for the appointment, re-appointment or continuation established by any other Act of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. I-3</MarginalNote><TitleText>IMPORTATION OF INTOXICATING LIQUORS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>2002, c. 22</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>Subparagraph 3(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)(i) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Importation of Intoxicating Liquors Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsection 411(7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>, is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>are entitled to the benefit of the Costa Rica Tariff in the List of Tariff Provisions set out in the schedule to the <Emphasis style="italic">Customs Tariff</Emphasis>, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. L-8</MarginalNote><TitleText>LIEUTENANT GOVERNORS SUPERANNUATION ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>disabled</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>contributor</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>contributor</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>contributeur</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>contributor</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a Lieutenant Governor who is required by subsection 4(1) to contribute to the Consolidated Revenue Fund and includes</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a Lieutenant Governor who has ceased to be required to so contribute by reason of subsection 4(2), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a Lieutenant Governor who has ceased to hold office as the lieutenant governor of a province and who has become entitled to an immediate pension or a deferred pension under this Act,</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who is required by subsection 4.1(3) to contribute to the Consolidated Revenue Fund, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a person who is no longer required by subsection 4.1(3) to contribute to the Consolidated Revenue Fund by reason of the expiry of the period referred to in that subsection and who has, on the expiry of that period, become entitled to an immediate pension or a deferred pension under this Act;</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 12, s. 170</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(ii) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>survivor</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a former Lieutenant Governor, to him or her immediately before the later of the day on which he or she ceased to be a Lieutenant Governor and the day on which he or she ceased to contribute under subsection 4.1(3), or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 12, s. 170</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(ii) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>survivor</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of a former Lieutenant Governor, with him or her immediately before the later of the day on which he or she ceased to be a Lieutenant Governor and the day on which he or she ceased to contribute under subsection 4.1(3).</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 3(1) of the Act before subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)(i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Pension to Lieutenant Governor</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every contributor who has contributed under this Act for five consecutive years is, subject to this Act,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>entitled on the later of the day on which he or she ceases to hold office as the lieutenant governor of a province and the day on which he or she ceases to contribute under subsection 4.1(3),</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 3(2) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amount of pension</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to this Act, the pension to which a contributor is entitled under this section is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>three-tenths of the average salary received by him or her during the last five years of his or her service as the lieutenant governor of a province; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>in the case of a contributor to whom section 4.1 applies, three-tenths of the average salary on which his or her contributions under this Act were based.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Option deemed to be exercised</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If under subsection (1) a contributor is entitled to a deferred pension or a return of contributions at his or her option and he or she fails to exercise the option within six months after the later of the day on which he or she ceases to hold office as the lieutenant governor of a province and the day on which he or she ceased to contribute under subsection 4.1(3), he or she is deemed to have exercised the option in favour of a deferred pension.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Return of contributions</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every contributor who, on the later of the day on which he or she ceases to hold office as the lieutenant governor of a province and the day on which he or she ceases to contribute under subsection 4.1(3), is not entitled to a pension under subsection (1) is, on that later date, entitled to a return of the total contributions made by him or her under this Part, together with interest, if any, calculated under subsection (5).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 3(5)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>calculate interest at the rate of four per cent compounded annually on the aggregate amount in respect of each contribution year from December 31 of that year to December 31 of the year immediately preceding the later of the year in which the contributor ceased to hold office as the lieutenant governor of a province and the year in which the contributor ceased to contribute under subsection 4.1(3).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 3 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of <DefinedTermEn>disabled</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>disabled</DefinedTermEn> means afflicted with a permanent infirmity that renders the contributor incapable of performing the duties and functions of his or her office or incapable of pursuing regularly any substantially gainful occupation commensurate with his or her qualifications.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1991, c. 31, s. 242</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>Subsection 4(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal>, the amount contributed under subsection (1) or 4.1(3) is deemed to be contributed to or under a registered pension plan.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 4:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Contributor deemed to be lieutenant governor</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A contributor who ceases to hold office as the lieutenant governor of a province by reason of having become disabled is deemed, for the purposes of this Act, to remain a lieutenant governor of a province for the period referred to in subsection (2) if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>at the time of ceasing to hold office, he or she had not contributed under this Act in respect of five years of service as the lieutenant governor of a province; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>he or she becomes entitled to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>long-term disability insurance benefits under the terms of the Public Service Management Insurance Plan, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a disability allowance under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The contributor is deemed to remain a lieutenant governor of a province during the period that commences on the day on which he or she ceased to hold office by reason of having become disabled and ends on the earliest of the day</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on which he or she dies,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on which he or she ceases to be entitled to long-term disability insurance benefits under the terms of the Public Service Management Insurance Plan unless he or she immediately becomes entitled to a disability allowance under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on which he or she ceases to be entitled to a disability allowance under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>that is five years after the day on which he or she commenced to hold office as the lieutenant governor of a province.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contribution</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>During the period referred to in subsection (2), the contributor shall contribute to the Consolidated Revenue Fund six per cent of the salary that he or she would have been paid if he or she had remained a lieutenant governor of a province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Manner of payment</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The contributions that the contributor is required to make under subsection (3) are to be</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>remitted directly by the contributor on a monthly, quarterly, semi-annual or annual basis if he or she becomes entitled to long-term disability insurance benefits under the Public Service Management Insurance Plan; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>made by reservation from the disability allowance payable to him or her under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(1) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Choix de ne pas contribuer sous le régime de l'article 4</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Un lieutenant-gouverneur peut choisir, par écrit, dans les six mois qui suivent sa nomination à la charge de lieutenant-gouverneur d'une province, de ne pas contribuer sous le régime de l'article 4 et, s'il fait ce choix, il n'est pas tenu, malgré l'article 4, de contribuer sous le régime de cet article.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 12, s. 172</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sections do not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Sections 3 to 4.1 do not apply to a Lieutenant Governor who has made an election under this section and sections 7 and 8 do not apply to the survivor of a Lieutenant Governor who has made an election under this section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>The heading before section 7 and sections 7 to 9 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Survivors</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Pension of survivor</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a contributor who has ceased to hold office as the lieutenant governor of a province, or who has ceased to contribute under subsection 4.1(3), but who is entitled to be paid an immediate pension or a deferred pension under section 3 dies, his or her survivor is to be paid a pension equal to one half of the immediate pension or deferred pension to which the contributor was entitled under that section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Pension of survivor</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a contributor who has ceased to be required to contribute under subsection 4(1) by reason of subsection 4(2) dies while holding office as the lieutenant governor of a province, his or her survivor is to be paid a pension equal to one half of the immediate pension or deferred pension to which the contributor would have become entitled under section 3 had he or she, immediately prior to his or her death, ceased, for any reason other than death, to hold office as the lieutenant governor of the province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Apportionment when two survivors</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a pension is payable under subsection (1) or (2) and there are two survivors of the contributor, the total amount of the pension is to be apportioned so that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the survivor referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>survivor</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 receives an amount, if any, equal to the total amount less any amount determined under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of this subsection; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the survivor referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of that definition receives an amount equal to that proportion of the total amount that the number of years that the survivor cohabited with the contributor while the contributor was a lieutenant governor of a province is of the number of years that the contributor was a lieutenant governor of a province.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inclusion</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the period during which a contributor contributed under subsection 4.1(3) is to be included in determining the number of years that he or she was a lieutenant governor of a province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Years</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In determining a number of years for the purpose of paragraph (3)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), a part of a year is to be counted as a full year if the part is six or more months and ignored if it is less.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Commencement of pension to survivor</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>A pension that is payable under this section to a survivor of a contributor commences to be payable immediately after the death of the contributor.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Return of contributions to survivor</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a contributor dies while holding office as the lieutenant governor of a province or while being required to contribute under subsection 4.1(3) and his or her survivor is not entitled to a pension under section 7, his or her survivor is to be paid the total amount of the contributions made by the contributor under this Part, together with interest, if any, calculated under subsection 3(5).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Apportionment when two survivors</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a return of contributions is payable under subsection (1) and there are two survivors of the contributor, the total amount of the return of contributions is to be apportioned so that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the survivor referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>survivor</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 receives an amount, if any, equal to the total amount less any amount determined under paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of this subsection; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the survivor referred to in paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of that definition receives an amount equal to that proportion of the total amount that the number of years that the survivor cohabited with the contributor while the contributor was a lieutenant governor of a province is of the number of years that the contributor was a lieutenant governor of a province.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Inclusion</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For the purposes of paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), the period during which a contributor contributed under subsection 4.1(3) is to be included in determining the number of years that he or she was a lieutenant governor of a province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Years</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In determining a number of years for the purpose of paragraph (2)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), a part of a year is to be counted as a full year if the part is six or more months and ignored if it is less.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Death Benefit</TitleText></Heading><Section><Label>9.</Label><Text>If, on the death of a contributor, there is no survivor to whom a pension or return of contributions under this Act may be paid, or if the contributor's survivor dies, any amount by which the total amount of the contributions made by the contributor under this Part, together with interest, if any, calculated under subsection 3(5), exceeds the total amount paid to the contributor and his or her survivor under this Part is to be paid, as a death benefit, to the contributor's estate or succession or, if less than $1,000, as the President of the Treasury Board may direct.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Text>Paragraph 11(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prescribing the medical examination to be required to determine whether a contributor is disabled for the purposes of section 3; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>Section 13 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 13(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), a person to whom subsection 4.1(1) applies is required, in respect of the period referred to in subsection 4.1(2), to contribute to the Supplementary Retirement Benefits Account one per cent of the salary that he or she would have been paid during that period if the person had continued to hold office as a lieutenant governor of a province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Manner of payment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The contributions that the contributor is required to make under subsection (2) are to be</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>remitted directly by the contributor on a monthly, quarterly, semi-annual or annual basis if he or she becomes entitled to long-term disability insurance benefits under the Public Service Management Insurance Plan; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>made by reservation from the disability allowance payable to him or her under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 12</MarginalNote><TitleText>MODERNIZATION OF BENEFITS AND OBLIGATIONS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Text>Section 174 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Modernization of Benefits and Obligations Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section type="amending"><Label>174.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 8:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Election for former Lieutenant Governor</MarginalNote><Label>8.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If the person to whom a former Lieutenant Governor is married or with whom he or she is cohabiting in a relationship of a conjugal nature, having so cohabited for a period of at least one year, would not be entitled to a pension under section 7 in the event of the former Lieutenant Governor's death, the former Lieutenant Governor may make an election, in accordance with the regulations, to reduce the amount of the pension to which he or she is entitled in order that the person could become entitled to a pension under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person referred to in subsection (1) is entitled to a pension in an amount determined in accordance with the election and the regulations if the former Lieutenant Governor dies and the election is not revoked or deemed to have been revoked, and the person was married to the former Lieutenant Governor at the time of his or her death, or was cohabiting with the former Lieutenant Governor in a relationship of a conjugal nature for a period of at least one year immediately before his or her death.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No entitlement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A person who is entitled to receive a pension under section 7 after the former Lieutenant Governor's death is not entitled to a pension under subsection (2) in respect of that former Lieutenant Governor.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 31</MarginalNote><TitleText>NATIONAL ROUND TABLE ON THE ENVIRONMENT AND THE ECONOMY ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Executive Director</DefinedTermEn> in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Round Table on the Environment and the Economy Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>président-directeur général</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>President</DefinedTermEn> means the President of the Round Table appointed under section 10;</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20.</Label><Text>Subsections 9(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Executive committee</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There shall be an executive committee of the Round Table consisting of the Chairperson and the President and not fewer than five or more than seven other members of the Round Table to be appointed by the members for any term of office that they consider appropriate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Functions of executive committee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The executive committee shall assist the President in supervising the work of the Round Table and shall perform the duties and functions that are imposed, or exercise the powers that are conferred, on the executive committee by or under the by-laws or resolutions of the Round Table.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21.</Label><Text>Section 10 of the Act and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>PRESIDENT</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>President</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There shall be a President of the Round Table, who shall be appointed by the Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Minister, to hold office during pleasure for a term of not more than five years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chief executive officer</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President is the chief executive officer of the Round Table and has supervision over and direction of the work and staff of the Round Table and shall perform the duties and functions that are imposed, or exercise the powers that are conferred, on the President by or under the by-laws or resolutions of the Round Table.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reappointment</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The President is eligible for reappointment.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If the President is absent or unable to act or the office of President is vacant, the executive committee may authorize an employee of the Round Table to act as President.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22.</Label><Text>Subsection 12(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>President's salary</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President is to be paid the salary or other remuneration that the Governor in Council may fix.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23.</Label><Text>Subsection 13(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>President's expenses</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The President is entitled to be paid reasonable travel and living expenses incurred by him or her in performing duties under this Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24.</Label><Text>Section 21 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Compensation</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>The President and employees of the Round Table are deemed to be employees for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and to be employed in the public service of Canada for the purposes of any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. P-1</MarginalNote><TitleText>PARLIAMENT OF CANADA ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Retroactive coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>24.1</Label><Text>Despite Order in Council P.C. 2003-1118 of July 24, 2003 and registered as SI/2003-142, paragraphs 60(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsection 10(2) of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Members of Parliament Retiring Allowances Act and the Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, being chapter 16 of the Statutes of Canada, 2003, are deemed to have come into force on January 1, 2001.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-3</MarginalNote><TitleText>SALARIES ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>25.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Salaries Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 4:</Text><AmendedText><Heading level="1"><TitleText>DISABILITY ALLOWANCE AND OTHER BENEFITS FOR FORMER LIEUTENANT GOVERNORS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Entitlement to disability allowance</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A lieutenant governor who resigns by reason of disability, and who has not contributed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> in respect of five years of service, may elect to receive an annual disability allowance equal to 70% of his or her annual salary on the date of resignation if, at the time of resignation, he or she is</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>65 years of age or over; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>incapable, because of the disability, of performing his or her duties.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Entitlement to disability allowance</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A former lieutenant governor who is in receipt of long-term disability insurance benefits under the Public Service Management Insurance Plan immediately before reaching the age of 65 years, and who has not contributed under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> in respect of five years of service, is entitled, on becoming 65 years of age, to receive an annual disability allowance equal to 70% of his or her annual salary at the time he or she resigned as lieutenant governor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Adjustments</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The disability allowance is to be adjusted to take into account changes in the annual salary on which it was based.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duration of allowance</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The disability allowance is to be paid until the earlier of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day on which the recipient of the allowance dies, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the day that is five years after the day on which he or she commenced to hold office as lieutenant governor.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>This section does not apply to a lieutenant governor who has elected under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> not to contribute pursuant to section 4 of that Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting disability allowances, including regulations respecting</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the determination of eligibility for disability allowances and medical examinations that are required;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>elections to receive disability allowances and the revocation of elections; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the administration and payment of disability allowances.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Retroactive regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Regulations made under subsection (1) may, if they so provide, be retroactive.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. S-24</MarginalNote><TitleText>SUPPLEMENTARY RETIREMENT BENEFITS ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>26.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Supplementary Retirement Benefits Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception in relation to retirement year or month</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (5), the retirement year or retirement month of a person who is required to contribute under subsection 4.1(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is, for the purposes of this section, the year or month, as the case may be, in which that person ceased to contribute under that Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (8):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (8)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>), a person who is required to contribute under subsection 4.1(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is, for the purposes of that paragraph, deemed to have ceased to hold office on the day on which he or she ceased to contribute under that Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27.</Label><Text>Section 6 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deeming</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (2), a person who is required to contribute under subsection 4.1(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is, for the purposes of subsection (2), deemed to have ceased to contribute in respect of current service on the day on which he or she ceased to contribute under that Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>SOR/2003-30</MarginalNote><TitleText>CONSULAR FEES (SPECIALIZED SERVICES) REGULATIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Retroactive coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>The <Emphasis style="italic">Consular Fees (Specialized Services) Regulations</Emphasis>, made by Order in Council P.C. 2003-4 of January 23, 2003 and registered as SOR/2003-30, are deemed for all purposes to have been made on April 1, 1998, and everything done under, and all consequences flowing from, those Regulations since April 1, 1998 are deemed effective as if those Regulations had been made on that date.</Text></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. L-8</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>On the later of the coming into force of subsection 5(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by subsection 14(2) of this Act, and section 174 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Modernization of Benefits and Obligations Act</XRefExternal>, as enacted by section 18 of this Act, subsection 5(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Lieutenant Governors Superannuation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sections do not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Sections 3 to 4.1 do not apply to a Lieutenant Governor who has made an election under this section and sections 7 to 8.1 do not apply to the survivor of a Lieutenant Governor who has made an election under this section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="amending"><TitleText>Bill C-25</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1999, c. 17</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Text>If Bill C-25, introduced in the 2nd Session of the 37th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of section 230 of that Act and the coming into force of section 5 of this Act, section 57 of the French version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Customs and Revenue Agency Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Activités politiques</MarginalNote><Label>57.</Label><Text>La partie 7 de la <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Loi sur l'emploi dans la fonction publique</XRefExternal> s'applique aux commissaire, commissaire délégué et employés de l'Agence. Pour l'application de cette partie, les commissaire et commissaire délégué sont réputés être des administrateurs généraux, au sens du paragraphe 2(1) de cette loi, et les employés, des fonctionnaires, au sens du paragraphe 2(1) de cette loi.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1993, c. 31</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>If Bill C-25, introduced in the 2nd Session of the 37th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Modernization Act</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of paragraph 224(<Emphasis style="italic">z</Emphasis>.58) of that Act and the coming into force of section 24 of this Act, section 21 of the English version of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Round Table on the Environment and the Economy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Compensation</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>The President and employees of the Round Table are deemed to be employees for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Government Employees Compensation Act</XRefExternal> and to be employed in the federal public administration for the purposes of any regulations made under section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 6 is deemed to have come into force on April 1, 2003.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 9 comes into force or is deemed to have come into force on the coming into force of subsection 395(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Excise Act, 2001</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Sections 10 to 17 and 25 to 27 come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>