<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-20</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>3</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>52-53</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2004</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to change the names of certain electoral districts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to change the names of certain electoral districts</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Electoral districts</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2004</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>14</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>19</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2004</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment changes the names of 38 electoral districts as follows:</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Bonavista — Exploits to Bonavista — Gander — Grand Falls — Windsor</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>St. John's North to St. John's East</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>St. John's South to St. John's South — Mount Pearl</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>North Nova to Cumberland — Colchester — Musquodoboit Valley</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Fundy to Fundy Royal;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>St. Croix — Belleisle to New Brunswick Southwest</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Argenteuil — Mirabel to Argenteuil — Papineau — Mirabel</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Beauport to Beauport — Limoilou</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Charlesbourg to Charlesbourg — Haute Saint Charles</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Charlevoix — Montmorency to Montmorency — Charlevoix — Haute Côte Nord</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Laurier to Laurier — Sainte Marie</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Longueuil to Longueuil — Pierre Boucher</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Matapédia — Matane to Haute Gaspésie — La Mitis — Matane — Matapédia</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Nunavik — Eeyou to Abitibi — Baie James — Nunavik — Eeyou</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Portneuf to Portneuf — Jacques Cartier</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Richelieu to Bas Richelieu — Nicolet — Bécancour</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Rimouski — Témiscouata to Rimouski Neigette — Témiscouata — Les Basques</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Rivière du Loup — Montmagny to Montmagny — L'Islet — Kamouraska — Rivière du Loup</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Roberval to Roberval — Lac Saint Jean</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Carleton — Lanark to Carleton — Mississippi Mills</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Clarington — Scugog — Uxbridge to Durham</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Grey — Bruce — Owen Sound to Bruce — Grey — Owen Sound</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Kitchener — Conestoga to Kitchener — Wilmot — Wellesley — Woolwich</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Middlesex — Kent — Lambton to Lambton — Kent — Middlesex</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Charleswood — St. James to Charleswood — St. James — Assiniboia</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Dauphin — Swan River to Dauphin — Swan River — Marquette</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Churchill River to Desnethé — Missinippi — Churchill River</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Athabasca to Fort McMurray — Athabasca</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Calgary North Centre to Calgary Centre North</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Calgary South Centre to Calgary Centre</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Edmonton — Beaumont to Edmonton — Mill Woods — Beaumont</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Westlock — St. Paul to Battle River</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Dewdney — Alouette to Pitt Meadows — Maple Ridge — Mission</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Kamloops — Thompson to Kamloops — Thompson — Cariboo</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Kelowna to Kelowna — Lake Country</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>North Okanagan — Shuswap to Okanagan — Shuswap</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Southern Interior to British Columbia Southern Interior</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>West Vancouver — Sunshine Coast to West Vancouver — Sunshine Coast — Sea to Sky Country</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Bonavista — Gander — Grand Falls — Windsor”</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 2 of that part relating to the Province of Newfoundland and Labrador is amended by substituting the name “Bonavista — Gander — Grand Falls — Windsor” for the name “Bonavista — Exploits”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “St. John's East”</MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 6 of that part relating to the Province of Newfoundland and Labrador is amended by substituting the name “St. John's East” for the name “St. John's North”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “St. John's South — Mount Pearl”</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 7 of that part relating to the Province of Newfoundland and Labrador is amended by substituting the name “St. John's South — Mount Pearl” for the name “St. John's South”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Cumberland — Colchester — Musquodoboit Valley”</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 7 of that part relating to the Province of Nova Scotia is amended by substituting the name “Cumberland — Colchester — Musquodoboit Valley” for the name “North Nova”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Fundy Royal”</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 4 of that part relating to the Province of New Brunswick is amended by substituting the name “Fundy Royal” for the name “Fundy”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “New Brunswick Southwest”</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 8 of that part relating to the Province of New Brunswick is amended by substituting the name “New Brunswick Southwest” for the name “St. Croix — Belleisle”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Argenteuil — Papineau — Mirabel”</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 4 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Argenteuil — Papineau — Mirabel” for the name “Argenteuil — Mirabel”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Beauport — Limoilou”</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 7 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Beauport — Limoilou” for the name “Beauport”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Charlesbourg — Haute-Saint-Charles”</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 13 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Charlesbourg — Haute-Saint-Charles” for the name “Charlesbourg”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Montmorency — Charlevoix — Haute-Côte-Nord”</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 14 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Montmorency — Charlevoix — Haute-Côte-Nord” for the name “Charlevoix — Montmorency”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Laurier — Sainte-Marie”</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 31 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Laurier — Sainte-Marie” for the name <DefinedTermEn>Laurier</DefinedTermEn>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Longueuil — Pierre-Boucher”</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 35 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Longueuil — Pierre-Boucher” for the name “Longueuil”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Haute- Gaspésie — La Mitis — Matane — Matapédia”</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 41 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Haute-Gaspésie — La Mitis — Matane — Matapédia” for the name “Matapédia — Matane”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Abitibi — Baie-James — Nunavik — Eeyou”</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 46 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Abitibi — Baie-James — Nunavik — Eeyou” for the name “Nunavik — Eeyou”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Portneuf — Jacques-Cartier’</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 51 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Portneuf — Jacques-Cartier” for the name “Portneuf”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Bas-Richelieu — Nicolet — Bécancour”</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 54 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Bas-Richelieu — Nicolet — Bécancour” for the name “Richelieu”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Rimouski- Neigette — Témiscouata — Les Basques”</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 56 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Rimouski-Neigette — Témiscouata — Les Basques” for the name “Rimouski — Témiscouata”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Montmagny — L'Islet — Kamouraska — Rivière-du-Loup”</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 58 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Montmagny — L'Islet — Kamouraska — Rivière-du-Loup” for the name “Rivière-du-Loup — Montmagny”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Roberval — Lac-Saint-Jean”</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 60 of that part relating to the Province of Quebec is amended by substituting the name “Roberval — Lac-Saint-Jean” for the name “Roberval”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Carleton — Mississippi Mills”</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 12 of that part relating to the Province of Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Carleton — Mississippi Mills” for the name “Carleton — Lanark”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Durham”</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 14 of that part relating to the Province of Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Durham” for the name “Clarington — Scugog — Uxbridge”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Bruce — Grey — Owen Sound”</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 26 of that part relating to the Province of Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Bruce — Grey — Owen Sound” for the name “Grey — Bruce — Owen Sound”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Kitchener — Wilmot — Wellesley — Woolwich”</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 38 of that part relating to the Province of Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Kitchener — Wilmot — Wellesley — Woolwich” for the name “Kitchener — Conestoga”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Lambton — Kent — Middlesex”</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 46 of that part relating to the Province of Ontario is amended by substituting the name “Lambton — Kent — Middlesex” for the name “Middlesex — Kent — Lambton”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “<DefinedTermEn>Charleswood — St. James — Assiniboia</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 2 of that part relating to the Province of Manitoba is amended by substituting the name <DefinedTermEn>Charleswood — St. James — Assiniboia</DefinedTermEn> for the name <DefinedTermEn>Charleswood — St. James</DefinedTermEn>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to <DefinedTermEn>Dauphin — Swan River — Marquette</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 4 of that part relating to the Province of Manitoba is amended by substituting the name <DefinedTermEn>Dauphin — Swan River — Marquette</DefinedTermEn> for the name <DefinedTermEn>Dauphin — Swan River</DefinedTermEn>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to <DefinedTermEn>Desnethé — Missinippi — Churchill River</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 3 of that part relating to the Province of Saskatchewan is amended by substituting the name <DefinedTermEn>Desnethé — Missinippi — Churchill River</DefinedTermEn> for the name <DefinedTermEn>Churchill River</DefinedTermEn>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to Fort McMurray — Athabasca”</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 1 of that part relating to the Province of Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Fort McMurray — Athabasca” for the name “Athabasca”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Calgary Centre-North”</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 3 of the English version of that part relating to the Province of Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Calgary Centre-North” for the name “Calgary North Centre”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Calgary Centre”</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 6 of that part relating to the Province of Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Calgary Centre” for the name “Calgary South Centre”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Edmonton — Mill Woods — Beaumont”</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 11 of that part relating to the Province of Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Edmonton — Mill Woods — Beaumont” for the name “Edmonton — Beaumont”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Battle River”</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 25 of that part relating to the Province of Alberta is amended by substituting the name “Battle River” for the name “Westlock — St. Paul”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Pitt Meadows — Maple Ridge — Mission”</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 7 of that part relating to the Province of British Columbia is amended by substituting the name “Pitt Meadows — Maple Ridge — Mission” for the name “Dewdney — Alouette”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Kamloops — Thompson — Cariboo”</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 10 of that part relating to the Province of British Columbia is amended by substituting the name “Kamloops — Thompson — Cariboo” for the name “Kamloops — Thompson”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Kelowna — Lake Country”</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 11 of that part relating to the Province of British Columbia is amended by substituting the name “Kelowna — Lake Country” for the name “Kelowna”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “Okanagan — Shuswap”</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 18 of that part relating to the Province of British Columbia is amended by substituting the name “Okanagan — Shuswap” for the name “North Okanagan — Shuswap:.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “British Columbia Southern Interior”</MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 26 of that part relating to the Province of British Columbia is amended by substituting the name “British Columbia Southern Interior” for the name “Southern Interior”.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Name changed to “West Vancouver — Sunshine Coast — Sea to Sky Country”</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>In the representation order declared in force by proclamation of August 25, 2003 under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Electoral Boundaries Readjustment Act</XRefExternal>, paragraph 36 of that part relating to the Province of British Columbia is amended by substituting the name “West Vancouver — Sunshine Coast — Sea to Sky Country” for the name “West Vancouver — Sunshine Coast”.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><?Pub Caret1?><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on September 1, 2004.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>