<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-48</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1-2 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (bail reform)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Criminal Code (bail reform)</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code (bail reform)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>12</MM><DD>5</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>30</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2023</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2023-05-15">91154</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>create a reverse onus provision for any person charged with a serious offence involving violence and the use of a weapon who has been convicted, within the last five years, of a serious offence involving violence and the use of a weapon;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>add certain firearms offences to the existing reverse onus provisions;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>expand the reverse onus provision for offences involving intimate partner violence to ensure that it applies to an accused person who has been previously discharged for such an offence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>require the court to consider if an accused person has any previous convictions involving violence and to include in the record a statement that the safety and security of the community was considered; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>require the court to include in the record a statement setting out how the court determined whether the accused is Aboriginal or belongs to a vulnerable population and, if so, how the particular circumstances of the accused were considered.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment also makes further clarifications and provides for a parliamentary review of the provisions it enacts or amends to commence on the fifth anniversary of the day on which it receives royal assent, or as soon as feasible after that anniversary.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Canada’s criminal justice system contributes to a safe, peaceful and prosperous society and the bail system plays a critical role in achieving this objective;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas the criminal justice system, including the bail system, is a shared responsibility between the federal, provincial and territorial governments;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas repeated acts of violence, serious offences committed with firearms or other weapons and random acts of violence all have a harmful impact on victims and communities and undermine public safety and confidence in the criminal justice system;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas a proper functioning bail system is necessary to maintain confidence in the criminal justice system, including in the administration of justice;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas a proper functioning bail system respects and upholds the rights guaranteed by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</XRefExternal>, including the presumption of innocence, the right to liberty and the right not to be denied reasonable bail without just cause;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas detention is justified when it is necessary according to the grounds for detention set out in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, including for the protection of public safety and to maintain confidence in the administration of justice;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>Whereas bail decisions are informed by other important considerations, such as the need to consider the particular circumstances of accused persons, including those from populations that face disadvantages at the bail stage and are overrepresented in the criminal justice system;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>And whereas confidence in the administration of justice is eroded in cases when accused persons are released on bail while their detention is justified, including because of risks to public safety, or when accused persons are unnecessarily detained;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Criminal Code</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 25, s. 225(3)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(3)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>whether the accused has been previously convicted of a criminal offence, including any offence in the commission of which violence was used, threatened or attempted against any person.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 37(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 515(6)(a)(vi) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>that is an offence under section 95, 98, 98.1, 99, 100, 102 or 103,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2008, c. 6, s. 37(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 515(6)(a)(viii) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>that is alleged to involve, or whose subject-matter is alleged to be, a firearm, a cross-bow, a prohibited weapon, a restricted weapon, a prohibited device, any ammunition or prohibited ammunition or an explosive substance, and that is alleged to have been committed while the accused was under a prohibition order within the meaning of subsection 84(1), including a release order made under this section, that prohibited the accused from possessing any of those things;</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2019, c. 25, s. 225(6)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 515(6)(b.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>with an offence in the commission of which violence was allegedly used, threatened or attempted against their intimate partner, and the accused has been previously convicted or discharged under section 730 of an offence in the commission of which violence was used, threatened or attempted against any intimate partner of theirs;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b.2)</Label><Text>with an offence in the commission of which violence was allegedly used, threatened or attempted against a person with the use of a weapon, and the accused has been previously convicted, within five years of the day on which they were charged for that offence, of another offence in the commission of which violence was also used, threatened or attempted against any person with the use of a weapon, if the maximum term of imprisonment for each of those offences is 10 years or more;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 13, s. 20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 515(13) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Victim’s and community’s safety and security</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>A justice who makes an order under this section shall include in the record of the proceedings a statement that the justice considered the safety and security of every victim of the offence and the safety and security of the community when making the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Aboriginal accused or vulnerable populations</MarginalNote><Label>(13.1)</Label><Text>A justice who makes an order under this section shall include in the record of proceedings a statement that sets out both how they determined whether the accused is an accused referred to in section 493.2 and their determination. If the justice determines that the accused is an accused referred to in section 493.2, they shall also include a statement indicating how they considered their particular circumstances, as required under that section.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Review by Committee</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Fifth anniversary of royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>On the fifth anniversary of the day on which this Act receives royal assent, or as soon as feasible after that anniversary, the provisions enacted or amended by this Act are to be referred to the standing committee of the Senate and the standing committee of the House of Commons that normally consider matters relating to justice.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the amendments made by this Act also apply with respect to proceedings that are ongoing on the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill S-205</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) and (3) apply if Bill S-205, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Criminal Code and to make consequential amendments to another Act (interim release and domestic violence recognizance orders)</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If subsection <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal>(4) of this Act comes into force before subsection 1(3) of the other Act, then that subsection 1(3) is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If subsection 1(3) of the other Act comes into force on the same day as subsection <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal>(4) of this Act, then that subsection 1(3) is deemed to have come into force before that subsection <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal>(4).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="CIF"><MarginalNote>30th day after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the 30th day after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>