<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-9</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Judges Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Judges Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Judges Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>18</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2023</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-12-9">91064</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend the Judges Act</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal> to replace the process through which the conduct of federally appointed judges is reviewed by the Canadian Judicial Council. It establishes a new process for reviewing allegations of misconduct that are not serious enough to warrant a judge’s removal from office and makes changes to the process by which recommendations regarding removal from office can be made to the Minister of Justice. As with the provisions it replaces, this new process also applies to persons, other than judges, who are appointed under an Act of Parliament to hold office during good behaviour.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. J-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Judges Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Commissioner</DefinedTermEn> means the Commissioner for Federal Judicial Affairs referred to in section 73; (<DefinedTermFr>commissaire</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Justice of Canada; (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2014, c. 39, s. 317</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 2.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application to prothonotaries</MarginalNote><Label>2.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), sections 26 to 26.3, 34 and 39, paragraphs 40(1)(a) and (b), subsection 40(2), sections 41, 41.2 to 42, 43.1 to 56 and 57, paragraph 60(2)(b) and Part IV also apply to a prothonotary of the Federal Court.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 11, s. 15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>Minister</DefinitionRef> in section 52.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2006, c. 11, s. 16</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 53(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Amounts payable out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The salaries, allowances and annuities payable under Parts I to III and the amounts payable under sections 46.1, 51 and 52.15 shall be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 53(2) and (3) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prorating</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For any period less than a year, the salaries and annuities payable shall be paid pro rata.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Monthly instalments</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The salaries and annuities payable shall be paid by monthly instalments.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 58 of the Act and the heading “Interpretation” before it are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Paragraph 59(1)(a) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Chief Justice of Canada, who shall be the chairperson of the Council;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Subsection 60(2) of the Act is amended by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (a) and by repealing paragraphs (c) and (d).</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Paragraph 61(3)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting the processes and proceedings under Part IV.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 62 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Employment of counsel and assistants</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Text>The Council may engage the services of any persons that it considers necessary for carrying out its objects and duties, and also the services of counsel to assist the Council in the processes and proceedings under Part IV.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 27 (2nd Supp.), ss. 5 and 6; R.S., c. 16 (3rd Supp.), ss. 5 and 6; 1992, c. 1, s. 144(1) (Sch. VII, s. 37(F)); 1993, c. 34, s. 89; 2002, c. 8, ss. 106(1) and (2)(E) and par. 111(d)(E) and (e)(E); 2014, c. 39, ss. 326 and 327; 2021, c. 23, s. 252</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The heading before section 63 and sections 63 to 71 of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Section 72 of the Act and the heading “Interpretation” before it are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 78:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART IV</Label><TitleText>Conduct Review Process</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 1</Label><TitleText>Complaints Concerning Judges</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Definition</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>judicial office</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>79</Label><Text>In this Division, <DefinedTermEn>judicial office</DefinedTermEn> includes the office of a prothonotary of the Federal Court.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Removal from Office</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Justification</MarginalNote><Label>80</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Division, the removal from office of a judge is justified only if, for any of the following reasons, the judge’s continuation in office would undermine public confidence in the impartiality, integrity or independence of the judge or of their office to such an extent that it would render the judge incapable of executing the functions of judicial office:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>infirmity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>misconduct;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>failure in the due execution of judicial office;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the judge is in a position that a reasonable, fair-minded and informed observer would consider to be incompatible with the due execution of judicial office.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Rosters</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of roster of judges</MarginalNote><Label>81</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Council shall establish a roster of superior court judges who may be designated as members of a panel established under this Division. The judges on the roster must not be members of the Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Number</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The number of judges on the roster is set at the discretion of the Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Recommendation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The naming of a judge to the roster must be made on the recommendation of the Canadian Superior Courts Judges Association.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Term</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A judge named to the roster remains on it for four years unless they cease to hold judicial office or request to be removed from the roster. When the four-year term ends, the judge may be renamed to the roster on the recommendation of the Canadian Superior Courts Judges Association.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment of lay persons</MarginalNote><Label>82</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Council shall establish a roster of lay persons who may be designated as members of a review panel or full hearing panel established under this Division.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Number</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The number of persons on the roster is set at the discretion of the Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>To be named to the roster, a person must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>never have been admitted to the bar of any province or to the Chambre des notaires du Québec;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>never have worked as a paralegal in Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>meet the other selection criteria established by the Council.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Selection criteria made public</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Council shall make public the selection criteria that it has established for the purpose of paragraph (3)(c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Term</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person named to the roster of lay persons remains on it for four years unless they request to be removed from the roster or, in the opinion of the Council, they cease to meet the conditions set out in subsection (3). When the four-year term ends, the person may be renamed to the roster.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Official languages</MarginalNote><Label>83</Label><Text>In naming persons to the roster of judges and to the roster of lay persons, the Council shall take into account the fact that the proceedings of panels established under this Division will be in either or both official languages.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Diversity</MarginalNote><Label>84</Label><Text>The Council shall name persons who reflect the diversity of the Canadian population to the roster of judges and to the roster of lay persons.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rosters available to public</MarginalNote><Label>85</Label><Text>The Council shall make the roster of judges and the roster of lay persons available to the public.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Complaints</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Complaints</MarginalNote><Label>86</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Complaints may be made to the Council, in the form specified by the Council, in respect of a judge of a superior court for any reason referred to in paragraphs 80(a) to (d).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Complaint by Council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Council may make a complaint only if two of its members have reasonable grounds to believe that the public’s confidence in the impartiality, integrity or independence of the judge or of the judicial office of the judge could be undermined for any reason referred to in paragraphs <XRefInternal>80</XRefInternal>(a) to (d).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Anonymous complaints</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A complaint may be made anonymously, but such a complaint may be dealt with only if two members of the Council have reasonable grounds to believe that the public’s confidence in the impartiality, integrity or independence of the judge or of the judicial office of the judge could be undermined for any reason referred to in paragraphs <XRefInternal>80</XRefInternal>(a) to (d).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to complainant</MarginalNote><Label>87</Label><Text>The Council shall establish policies respecting the notifying of complainants of any decisions made under this Division.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Screening Officer</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>88</Label><Text>The Council may designate as a screening officer one or more persons, including a judge, who meets the criteria specified by the Council.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Referral to screening officer</MarginalNote><Label>89</Label><Text>The Council shall refer every complaint to a screening officer, other than a complaint made by the Council itself or an anonymous complaint.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Dismissal of complaint</MarginalNote><Label>90</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), a screening officer may dismiss a complaint if they are of the opinion that it</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is frivolous, vexatious or made for an improper purpose or is an abuse of process;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>was not made for a reason referred to in paragraphs <XRefInternal>80</XRefInternal>(a) to (d); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>does not meet the other screening criteria specified by the Council.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Screening criteria to be made public</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Council shall make public the screening criteria that it has established for the purpose of paragraph (1)(c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A screening officer shall not dismiss a complaint that alleges sexual misconduct or sexual harassment or that alleges discrimination on a prohibited ground of discrimination within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Referral to Council</MarginalNote><Label>91</Label><Text>If a screening officer does not dismiss a complaint, they shall refer it to the Council for the designation of a reviewing member.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Reviewing Member</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>92</Label><Text>In the case of a complaint made by the Council itself or an anonymous complaint, or on receipt of a complaint referred to it under section <XRefInternal>91</XRefInternal>, the Council shall designate one of its members to review the complaint.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Written submissions</MarginalNote><Label>93</Label><Text>The reviewing member shall give the judge who is the subject of the complaint an opportunity to make written submissions about the complaint within the time limit established by the Council for the purpose of this section.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Dismissal of complaint</MarginalNote><Label>94</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The reviewing member shall dismiss the complaint if they are of the opinion that it should be dismissed for any reason set out in paragraphs <XRefInternal>90</XRefInternal>(1)(a) to (c) or that it is wholly without merit.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Communication of dismissal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the reviewing member dismisses the complaint, they shall inform the complainant in writing of their decision and the reasons for it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exclusion</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The reasons shall not include information that is confidential or personal, or that is not in the public interest to disclose.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Referral to Council</MarginalNote><Label>95</Label><Text>If the reviewing member does not dismiss the complaint, they shall refer it to the Council for the establishment of a review panel.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of decision</MarginalNote><Label>96</Label><Text>The reviewing member shall give notice of their decision to the judge who is the subject of the complaint and to the chief justice of the court of which the judge is a member.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provision of information</MarginalNote><Label>97</Label><Text>After the review panel is established, the reviewing member shall provide it with every document in their possession that relates to the complaint. The reviewing member may also provide the review panel with their observations about the complaint and their recommendations about how it should be resolved.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Review Panel</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>98</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), on receipt of a complaint referred to it under section <XRefInternal>95</XRefInternal>, the Council shall establish a review panel consisting of the following persons designated by the Council to review the complaint:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a member of the Council;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a judge named in the roster of judges; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person named in the roster of lay persons.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Direction to review new complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a complaint is referred to the Council under section 95 and a review panel established to review a previous complaint involving the same judge has not yet made a decision in respect of that complaint, the Council may direct the review panel to also review the new complaint.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Written submissions</MarginalNote><Label>99</Label><Text>The review panel shall give the judge who is the subject of the complaint and chief justice of the court of which the judge is a member an opportunity to provide written submissions within the time limit established by the Council for the purpose of this section.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Basis of decisions</MarginalNote><Label>100</Label><Text>The review panel shall make its decision only on the basis of the substance of the complaint, any information provided under section <XRefInternal>97</XRefInternal>, any written submissions provided under section <XRefInternal>99</XRefInternal> and any other document that it considers relevant.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Referral to Council</MarginalNote><Label>101</Label><Text>The review panel shall refer the complaint to the Council for the establishment of a full hearing panel if it determines that the judge’s removal from office could be justified.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Dismissal of complaint or action</MarginalNote><Label>102</Label><Text>If the review panel does not refer the complaint to the Council under section <XRefInternal>101</XRefInternal>, it may dismiss the complaint or take one or more of the following actions if it considers it appropriate to do so in the circumstances:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>issue a private or public expression of concern;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>issue a private or public warning;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>issue a private or public reprimand;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>order the judge to apologize, either privately or publicly, by whatever means the panel considers appropriate in the circumstances;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>order the judge to take specific measures, including attending counselling or a continuing education course;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>take any action that the panel considers to be equivalent to any of the actions referred to in paragraphs (a) to (e);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>with the consent of the judge, take any other action that the panel considers appropriate in the circumstances.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of decision and reasons</MarginalNote><Label>103</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The review panel shall give notice of its decision and the reasons for it to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge who is the subject of the complaint;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the chief justice of the court of which that judge is a member; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Council.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Communication of dismissal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the review panel dismisses the complaint, it shall inform the complainant in writing of its decision and the reasons for it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exclusion</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The reasons shall not include information that is confidential or personal, or that is not in the public interest to disclose.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request to establish panel</MarginalNote><Label>104</Label><Text>If the review panel takes any action under section <XRefInternal>102</XRefInternal>, the judge who is the subject of the complaint may, within 30 days after the day on which the review panel sends the judge a notice informing the judge of its decision, request that the Council establish a reduced hearing panel to review the complaint.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provision of information</MarginalNote><Label>105</Label><Text>If a reduced hearing panel or a full hearing panel is established in respect of a complaint that was before a review panel, the review panel shall provide to the presenting counsel in respect of the hearing panel all the information that was before it and the decision and reasons it provided under section <XRefInternal>103</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Hearing Panels</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Presenting Counsel</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>106</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>When it establishes a reduced hearing panel or a full hearing panel, the Council shall designate one of its members to designate a lawyer of at least 10 years’ standing at the bar of any province to act as presenting counsel in respect of the hearing panel.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The member of the Council who designates the presenting counsel shall not be designated as any of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a member of the reduced hearing panel or the full hearing panel;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a member of any appeal panel established in respect of any decision of the reduced hearing panel or the full hearing panel.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Replacement</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The presenting counsel may at any time be replaced by another presenting counsel designated in accordance with subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Role</MarginalNote><Label>107</Label><Text>The role of the presenting counsel consists of preparing a statement of allegations against a judge who is the subject of a complaint before a reduced hearing panel or full hearing panel, as the case may be, and presenting evidence. The presenting counsel is also responsible for bringing an appeal and presenting arguments in an appeal.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Instructions</MarginalNote><Label>108</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The presenting council shall take instructions from the Council member who designated them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of the Council member who designated the presenting counsel, the Council may designate another Council member to give instructions to the presenting counsel.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Standards of conduct</MarginalNote><Label>109</Label><Text>In fulfilling their responsibilities, the presenting counsel shall conduct themselves in accordance with the standards and principles that govern the conduct of Crown prosecutors, with any modifications that may be necessary.</Text></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Reduced Hearing Panel</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>110</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), on receipt of a request made under section <XRefInternal>104</XRefInternal>, the Council shall establish a reduced hearing panel consisting of the following persons designated by it to review the complaint to which the request relates:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a member of the Council;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a judge named in the roster of judges; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a lawyer of at least 10 years’ standing at the bar of any province.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Direction to review new complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a request is made under section <XRefInternal>104</XRefInternal> by a judge who has previously made a request under that section and the reduced hearing panel established in respect of the previous request has not yet made a decision in respect of the complaint to which the previous request relates, the Council may direct the reduced hearing panel to also review the new complaint.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision and reasons not considered</MarginalNote><Label>111</Label><Text>In considering the complaint, the reduced hearing panel shall not consider the decision of the review panel that caused the judge who is the subject of the complaint to make the request under section <XRefInternal>104</XRefInternal> or the reasons for that decision.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Referral of complaint to Council</MarginalNote><Label>112</Label><Text>The reduced hearing panel shall refer the complaint to the Council for the establishment of a full hearing panel if it determines that the removal from office of the judge who is the subject of the complaint could be justified.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Dismissal or actions</MarginalNote><Label>113</Label><Text>If the reduced hearing panel does not refer the complaint to the Council under section <XRefInternal>112</XRefInternal>, it may dismiss the complaint or take one or more of the actions referred to in paragraphs <XRefInternal>102</XRefInternal>(a) to (g) if it considers it appropriate to do so in the circumstances.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of decision and reasons</MarginalNote><Label>114</Label><Text>The reduced hearing panel shall give notice of its decision and the reasons for it to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge who is the subject of the complaint;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the chief justice of the court of which that judge is a member;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Council; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the presenting counsel.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision and reasons made public</MarginalNote><Label>115</Label><Text>The Council shall make public the reduced hearing panel’s decision and the reasons for it, as soon as feasible after receiving them, if the reduced hearing panel’s hearings were public. If they were not public, the Council shall make public as much of the decision and reasons as possible having regard to the reasons for holding the hearings, or part of them, in private.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>116</Label><Text>The judge to whom the complaint relates and the presenting counsel may respectively, within 30 days after the day on which the reduced hearing panel sends them a notice of its decision, file with the Council a notice appealing the decision.</Text></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Full Hearing Panel</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>117</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), on receipt of a referral of a complaint made under section <XRefInternal>101</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>112</XRefInternal>, the Council shall establish a full hearing panel consisting of the following persons to review the complaint:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>two members of the Council who are designated by it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a judge named in the roster of judges who is designated by it;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person named in the roster of lay persons who is designated by it; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a lawyer who is a member of the bar of a province and who is designated in accordance with subsection (2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Designation of lawyer</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The lawyer referred to in paragraph (1)(d) is to be designated by the Minister. However, if the full hearing panel is being established as the result of a request by the Minister under section <XRefInternal>148</XRefInternal> or the Minister does not designate a lawyer within 30 days after the day on which the Minister receives written notice from the Council that a full hearing panel is to be established, the lawyer is to be designated by the Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Direction to review new complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a complaint is referred to the Council under section 101 or 112, and a full hearing panel established to review a previous complaint or to consider a request made under section <XRefInternal>148</XRefInternal> involving the same judge has not yet made a decision in respect of the previous complaint or the request, the Council may direct the full hearing panel to also review the new complaint.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision and reasons not considered</MarginalNote><Label>118</Label><Text>In considering the complaint, the full hearing panel shall not consider the decision of the review panel or reduced hearing panel, as the case may be, that led to the establishment of the full hearing panel, or the reasons for that decision.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Removal justified</MarginalNote><Label>119</Label><Text>If the full hearing panel determines, on a balance of probabilities, that the judge’s removal from office is justified, it shall make a decision to that effect.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Dismissal or action</MarginalNote><Label>120</Label><Text>If the full hearing panel determines, on a balance of probabilities, that the judge’s removal is not justified, it may dismiss the complaint or take one or more of the actions referred to in paragraphs <XRefInternal>102</XRefInternal>(a) to (g) if the full hearing panel considers that it is appropriate to do so in the circumstances.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of decision and reasons</MarginalNote><Label>121</Label><Text>The full hearing panel shall give notice of its decision and the reasons for it to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge who is the subject of the complaint;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the chief justice of the court of which that judge is a member;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Council; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the presenting counsel.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision and reasons made public</MarginalNote><Label>122</Label><Text>The Council shall make public the full hearing panel’s decision and the reasons for it, as soon as feasible after receiving the decision, if the full hearing panel’s hearings were public. If they were not public, the Council shall make public as much of the decision and reasons as possible having regard to the reasons for holding the hearings, or part of them, in private.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>123</Label><Text>The judge who is the subject of the complaint and the presenting counsel may respectively, within 30 days after the day on which the full hearing panel sends them a notice of its decision, file with the Council a notice appealing the decision.</Text></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Rights of Judge</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Rights</MarginalNote><Label>124</Label><Text>The judge who is the subject of a complaint that is before a hearing panel has the right to be heard, to cross-examine witnesses and to adduce evidence, in person or by counsel.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Statement of allegation and notice</MarginalNote><Label>125</Label><Text>The judge who is the subject of a complaint that is before a hearing panel is to be provided with a copy of the statement of allegations prepared by the presenting counsel and given reasonable notice of the subject matter and the date, time and place of the hearings.</Text></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Salaries and Annuities</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Time in judicial office and salary</MarginalNote><Label>126</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of calculating an annuity under Part I, if a full hearing panel decides that the removal from office of a judge who is the subject of a complaint is justified, the day after the day on which the judge is given notice of the full hearing panel’s decision is the day to be used to determine the number of years the judge has been in judicial office and the salary annexed to the office held by the judge at the time of his or her resignation, removal or attaining the age of retirement unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the decision is set aside by a decision of the Supreme Court of Canada, or by the decision of an appeal panel if the appeal panel’s decision is final;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Minister’s response under subsection <XRefInternal>140</XRefInternal>(1) provides that no action is to be taken to remove the judge from office; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the matter of removal of the judge from office is put to one or both Houses of Parliament and is rejected by either of them.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contributions toward annuities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No reservations are to be made under section 50 from the judge’s salary in respect of the period that begins on the day after the day on which the judge is given notice of the full hearing panel’s decision, unless one of paragraphs (1)(a) to (c) applies, in which case the judge shall contribute an amount equal to the amount that would have been reserved from the judge’s salary had subsection (1) not applied.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Salary increases</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in subsection (1) is to be construed as removing from the judge any entitlement to a salary increase that takes effect on or after the day on which the judge is given notice of the full hearing panel’s decision.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>127</Label><Text>A hearing panel has all the powers vested in a superior court of the province in which the judge who is the subject of the complaint resides, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the power to summon before it any witness and require them to give evidence on oath, orally or in writing or on solemn affirmation if they are entitled to affirm in civil matters, and to produce any documents and evidence that it considers necessary; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the power to enforce the attendance of any witness and compel them to give evidence.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Rules of evidence</MarginalNote><Label>128</Label><Text>A hearing panel is not bound by any legal or technical rules of evidence and may receive and base a decision on evidence presented in its hearings that it considers credible or trustworthy in the circumstances of the case.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Hearings public</MarginalNote><Label>129</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A hearing panel’s hearings are to be public, but it may hold all or any part of its hearings in private if it considers doing so to be in the public interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition of publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A hearing panel may prohibit the publication of any information or documents placed before it, if it is of the opinion that such a publication is not in the public interest.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Appeals</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Appeal Panel</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>130</Label><Text>On receipt of a notice of appeal filed under section 116 or 123, the Council shall establish an appeal panel consisting of the following persons designated by it:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>three members of the Council; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>two judges named in the roster of judges.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Power</MarginalNote><Label>131</Label><Text>The appeal panel has all the powers vested in the court of appeal of the province in which the judge who is the subject of the complaint resides. It may, among other things, reverse, vary or affirm any decision of the reduced hearing panel or full hearing panel, as the case may be, and make any decision the hearing panel could have made.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Hearings public</MarginalNote><Label>132</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The appeal panel’s hearings are to be public, but it may conduct all or any part of its hearings in private if it considers doing so to be in the public interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Prohibition of publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The appeal panel may prohibit the publication of any information or documents placed before it if it is of the opinion that such a publication is not in the public interest.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right to make submissions</MarginalNote><Label>133</Label><Text>The judge who is the subject of the appeal and the presenting counsel are each entitled to make oral and written submissions to the appeal panel.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Nature of appeal</MarginalNote><Label>134</Label><Text>The appeal is to be heard on the basis of the record of the hearing panel whose decision was appealed and on any submissions made by the judge who is the subject of the appeal and the presenting counsel. The appeal panel may, in exceptional circumstances, admit additional evidence or testimony if, in its opinion, it is essential in the interests of justice to do so.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of decision and reasons</MarginalNote><Label>135</Label><Text>The appeal panel shall give notice of its decision and the reasons for it to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge who is the subject of the appeal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the chief justice of the court of which that judge is a member;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Council; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the presenting counsel.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision and reasons made public</MarginalNote><Label>136</Label><Text>The Council shall make public the appeal panel’s decision and the reasons for it, as soon as feasible after receiving them, if the appeal panel’s hearings were public. If they were not public, the Council shall make public as much of the decision and reasons as possible having regard to the reasons for holding the hearings, or part of them, in private.</Text></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Supreme Court of Canada</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Notice of application for leave to appeal</MarginalNote><Label>137</Label><Text>The judge who is the subject of a decision of an appeal panel and the presenting counsel may respectively, within 30 days after the day on which the appeal panel sends them a notice of its decision, file a notice of application for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court of Canada.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Right of attorneys general</MarginalNote><Label>138</Label><Text>If leave to appeal is granted by the Supreme Court of Canada, the Attorney General of Canada and the attorney general of a province may intervene in the appeal.</Text></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>Report to Minister</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report with recommendation</MarginalNote><Label>139</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If a full hearing panel is established in respect of a complaint, the full hearing panel shall, as soon as feasible after the earliest of the following, provide to the Minister a report setting out a recommendation, consistent with the final decision in respect of the complaint, as to whether or not the judge who is the subject of the complaint should be removed from office:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the judge and the presenting counsel have both waived their rights under section <XRefInternal>123</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>137</XRefInternal>,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the time limit for exercising those rights has expired, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Supreme Court of Canada has not granted leave to appeal or, if it has, it has made a decision in respect of the appeal panel’s decision.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Decisions and reasons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The report must also set out the full hearing panel’s decision and any decision of the appeal panel and the Supreme Court of Canada, as well as the reasons, if any, for those decisions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Copy of report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The full hearing panel shall as soon as feasible give a copy of the report to the judge, the presenting counsel and the Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report made public</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Council shall make public as much of the report as it considers appropriate taking into account the extent to which the decisions and reasons set out in the report were made public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of all three judges of the full hearing panel, the Council shall designate one of its members to assist the other members of the full hearing panel in preparing the report or, if the others are also absent or incapacitated, to provide the report.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Minister’s response</MarginalNote><Label>140</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall respond publicly to the report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of responding publicly, the Minister may seek information from the full hearing panel on any matter that the Minister considers necessary.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Obligation to provide information</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The full hearing panel shall provide the judge who is the subject of the report and the presenting counsel with any information that it provides to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence or incapacity</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of all three judges of the full hearing panel, the Council shall designate one of its members to assist the other members of the full hearing panel in providing the information to the Minister or, if the others are also absent or incapacitated, to provide the information.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Ineligibility</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Ineligibility</MarginalNote><Label>141</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A member of the Council and a judge named in the roster of judges is not eligible to be designated</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>as a reviewing member under section <XRefInternal>92</XRefInternal>, or as a member of any panel established under this Division, in respect of any complaint involving a judge of the court of which they are a member; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>more than once under this Division in respect of the same complaint or the same judge.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Subsections <XRefInternal>86</XRefInternal>(2) and (3)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A member of the Council who is referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>86</XRefInternal>(2) or (3) whose belief led to the Council making a complaint in respect of a judge or to an anonymous complaint being dealt with is not eligible to be designated, in their capacity as a member of the Council or in any other capacity, as a reviewing member under section <XRefInternal>92</XRefInternal> or as a member of any panel established under this Division, in respect of the complaint.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Designation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation from roster of judges</MarginalNote><Label>142</Label><Text>The Council may designate a judge named in the roster of judges to be a member of a panel established under section <XRefInternal>98</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>110</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>117</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>130</XRefInternal> instead of designating a member of the Council as the section in question requires.</Text></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Immunity</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Immunity</MarginalNote><Label>143</Label><Text>A screening officer, a reviewing member or a member of a panel established under this Division shall have the same immunity as a judge of a superior court.</Text></Section><Heading level="4"><TitleText>Financial Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>144</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the fees, allowances and expenses to be paid or reimbursed under section <XRefInternal>146</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Guidelines</MarginalNote><Label>145</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations, the Commissioner shall make guidelines respecting the fees, allowances and expenses to be paid or reimbursed under section <XRefInternal>146</XRefInternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The guidelines may incorporate by reference any policy, guideline or directive of the Treasury Board or any federal department regarding fees, allowances or expenses, as it is amended from time to time.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Obligation to justify differences</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an amount provided for in the guidelines made under subsection (1) differs from the amount provided for in Treasury Board directives regarding fees, allowances and expenses, the Commissioner shall make the reasons for the difference available to the public unless the difference is attributable solely to compliance with the regulations.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Amounts payable out of C.R.F.</MarginalNote><Label>146</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to the regulations made under section 144 and the guidelines made under subsection <XRefInternal>145</XRefInternal>(1), there shall be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund all amounts payable in respect of the following:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the expenses incurred by members of the Council and judges named in the roster of judges in the course of carrying out their duties under this Division or Division 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the expenses incurred by and the allowances payable to panel members, other than judges, in the course of carrying out their duties under this Division or Division 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the fees of and the expenses incurred by presenting counsel in the course of carrying out their duties under this Division or Division 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (2), the fees of and the expenses incurred by lawyers representing judges who are the subject of a complaint under this Division or Division 2;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the fees and expenses of lawyers and experts engaged by panels established under this Division or Division 2; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the expenses incidental to the conduct of meetings and hearings under this Division or Division 2, including the renting of rooms, the recording and transcription of proceedings, translation services and security.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restriction</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Fees and expenses of lawyers representing judges may be paid only in respect of proceedings under this Division or Division 2 or in respect of appeals to the Supreme Court of Canada relating to those proceedings. For greater certainty, no payments to lawyers representing judges are to be made in respect of any judicial review of any decision made under this Division or Division 2.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Independent review of financial provisions</MarginalNote><Label>147</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which the first report is submitted under section <XRefInternal>160</XRefInternal> and on every fifth anniversary of that day, the Council shall cause an independent review of the application of sections <XRefInternal>144</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>146</XRefInternal> to be conducted. The review is to be conducted by a person or body designated by the Commissioner in consultation with the Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The person or body conducting the review shall provide a report of their findings and recommendations to the Minister, the chairperson of the Council and the Commissioner. The report shall include a finding on whether sections <XRefInternal>144</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>146</XRefInternal> have been applied in a manner consistent with best practices regarding financial controls.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to be made public</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Council shall make the report public with any redactions that the Commissioner and chairperson of the Council jointly consider necessary to protect confidential or personal information.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 2</Label><TitleText>Requests Concerning Judges</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Request</MarginalNote><Label>148</Label><Text>The Minister or the attorney general of a province may request that the Council establish a full hearing panel to determine whether the removal from office of a judge of a superior court is justified.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>149</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), on receipt of the request, the Council shall establish a full hearing panel in accordance with section <XRefInternal>117</XRefInternal> to consider the request.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Direction to consider new request</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a full hearing panel established to consider a previous request made under section <XRefInternal>148</XRefInternal> or to review a complaint made under section <XRefInternal>101</XRefInternal> or <XRefInternal>112</XRefInternal> involving the same judge has not yet made a decision in respect of the previous request or the complaint, the Council may direct the full hearing panel to also consider the new request.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application of sections <XRefInternal>119</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>143</XRefInternal></MarginalNote><Label>150</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>119</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>143</XRefInternal> apply, with any necessary modifications, in respect of the request and all proceedings arising from it.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 3</Label><TitleText>Requests Concerning Office Holders</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Removal from office</MarginalNote><Label>151</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Division, the removal from office of a person appointed under an Act of Parliament to hold office during good behaviour, other than a judge, is justified only if, for any of the following reasons, the person’s continuation in office would undermine public confidence in the integrity of the person or of their office to such an extent that it would render the person incapable of executing the functions of their office:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>infirmity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>misconduct;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>failure in the due execution of their office;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the person has been placed in a position that a reasonable, fair-minded and informed observer would consider to be incompatible with the due execution of their office.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Request</MarginalNote><Label>152</Label><Text>The Minister may request that the Council establish a full hearing panel to determine whether the removal from office of a person referred to in section <XRefInternal>151</XRefInternal> is justified.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>153</Label><Text>On receipt of the request, the Council shall establish a full hearing panel in accordance with section <XRefInternal>117</XRefInternal> to consider the request.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Application of sections <XRefInternal>119</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>125</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>127</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>143</XRefInternal></MarginalNote><Label>154</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>119</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>125</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>127</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>143</XRefInternal> apply, with any necessary modifications, in respect of the request and all proceedings arising from it.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Removal from office</MarginalNote><Label>155</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On receipt of a report provided under subsection <XRefInternal>139</XRefInternal>(1) containing a recommendation that a person be removed from office, the Governor in Council, may, on the recommendation of the Minister, by order, remove the person from office if the person is a person who may be removed from office by the Governor in Council other than on address of the Senate or House of Commons or joint address of the Senate and House of Commons.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Orders and reports laid before Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an order is made under subsection (1), a copy of the order and a copy of the report relating to the order must be laid before each House of Parliament within 15 days after the day on which the order is made or, if either House is not then sitting, on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Leave of absence with salary</MarginalNote><Label>156</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, for any period that the Governor in Council considers appropriate, grant leave of absence to any person, other than a judge, whose removal from office is recommended because of infirmity in a report provided under subsection <XRefInternal>139</XRefInternal>(1) and, if leave of absence is granted, the person’s salary is to continue to be paid during the period of leave of absence.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><Label>DIVISION 4</Label><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Powers, rights and duties not affected</MarginalNote><Label>157</Label><Text>Nothing in, or done or omitted to be done under the authority of, this Part affects any power, right or duty of the Senate, the House of Commons or the Governor in Council in relation to the removal from office of a judge or any other person.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Decision final</MarginalNote><Label>158</Label><Text>A decision made by a member of the Council under any of Divisions 1 to 3 or by a member of a panel established under any of those Divisions is final and is not to be questioned or reviewed in any court other than provided for in this Part.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Remote appearance</MarginalNote><Label>159</Label><Text>For greater certainty, any proceedings or hearings under this Part may take place by remote appearance.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>160</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Council shall, within three months after the end of each calendar year, submit a report to the Minister setting out, in respect of the year, the number of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>complaints received;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>complaints dismissed by a screening officer;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>complaints dismissed by a reviewing member;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>complaints reviewed by review panels, hearing panels and appeal panels; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>complaints in respect of which any of the actions referred to in paragraphs <XRefInternal>102</XRefInternal>(a) to (g) were taken.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to be made public</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>After the annual report is submitted to the Minister, the Council shall make it public.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “Minister of Justice of Canada”</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Act is amended by replacing “Minister of Justice of Canada” with “Minister” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsection 26(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraph 26.1(1)(b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsection 28(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>subsection 29(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>subsection 31(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>section 31.1;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>subsection 32(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>subsection 32.1(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 33(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 41(3) after paragraph (b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>section 48; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>subsections 54(1.1) to (3).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “<Language xml:lang="fr">ministre de la Justice du Canada</Language>”</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The French version of the Act is amended by replacing “<Language xml:lang="fr">ministre de la Justice du Canada</Language>” with “<Language xml:lang="fr">ministre</Language>” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 51(3) after paragraph (b); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 51(4) before paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “Minister of Justice”</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The English version of the Act is amended by replacing “Minister of Justice” with “Minister” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subsections 26(3), (4), (6) and (7); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 51(3) after paragraph (b) and the portion of subsection 51(4) before paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Ongoing inquiries and investigations</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which this Act comes into force, continues to apply in respect of any inquiry or investigation commenced under that Act before that day.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Inquiry requested under subsection 63(1)</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an inquiry has been requested under subsection 63(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal> before the day on which this Act comes into force and the inquiry has not commenced before that day, the request is deemed to be a request made on that day under section 148 of that Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal> of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Complaint or allegation referred to in subsection 63(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a complaint or allegation referred to in subsection 63(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal> is made before the day on which this Act comes into force and an investigation into it has not commenced before that day, the complaint or allegation is deemed to be a complaint made on that day under subsection 86(1) of that Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal> of this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Inquiry requested under subsection 69(1)</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If an inquiry has been requested under subsection 69(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal> before the day on which this Act comes into force and the inquiry has not commenced before that day, the request is deemed to be a request made on that day under section 152 of that Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal> of this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Notice of application for leave to appeal</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>If a report made under section 65 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Judges Act</XRefExternal>, as that section read immediately before the day on which this Act comes into force, contains a recommendation that a judge be removed from office, that judge may, within 30 days after that day, file a notice of application for leave to appeal the report to the Supreme Court of Canada and, if leave is granted, section 138 of that Act, as enacted by section <XRefInternal>12</XRefInternal> of this Act, applies with respect to the appeal.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>