<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-8</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act, to make consequential amendments to other Acts and to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act, to make consequential amendments to other Acts and to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act, to make consequential amendments to other Acts and to amend ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>19</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2023</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-5-9">91085</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>reorganize existing inadmissibility provisions relating to sanctions to establish a distinct ground of inadmissibility based on sanctions;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>expand the scope of inadmissibility based on sanctions to include not only sanctions imposed on a country but also those imposed on an entity or a person; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>expand the scope of inadmissibility based on sanctions to include all orders and regulations made under section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also makes consequential amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergencies Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Finally, it amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations</XRefExternal> to, among other things, provide that the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, instead of the Immigration Division, will have the authority to issue a removal order on grounds of inadmissibility based on sanctions under new paragraph 35.1(1)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(2)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the establishment of policies respecting the enforcement of this Act and inadmissibility on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, sanctions or organized criminality; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Subsection 21(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Protected person</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Except in the case of a person described in subsection 112(3) or a person who is a member of a prescribed class of persons, a person whose application for protection has been finally determined by the Board to be a Convention refugee or to be a person in need of protection, or a person whose application for protection has been allowed by the Minister, becomes, subject to any federal-provincial agreement referred to in subsection 9(1), a permanent resident if the officer is satisfied that they have made their application in accordance with the regulations and that they are not inadmissible on any ground referred to in section 34, 35 or 35.1, subsection 36(1) or section 37 or 38.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Subsection 25(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations — request of foreign national</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1.2), the Minister must, on request of a foreign national in Canada who applies for permanent resident status and who is inadmissible — other than under section 34, 35, 35.1 or 37 — or who does not meet the requirements of this Act, and may, on request of a foreign national outside Canada — other than a foreign national who is inadmissible under section 34, 35, 35.1 or 37 — who applies for a permanent resident visa, examine the circumstances concerning the foreign national and may grant the foreign national permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by humanitarian and compassionate considerations relating to the foreign national, taking into account the best interests of a child directly affected.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Subsection 25.1(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Humanitarian and compassionate considerations — Minister’s own initiative</MarginalNote><Label>25.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, on the Minister’s own initiative, examine the circumstances concerning a foreign national who is inadmissible — other than under section 34, 35, 35.1 or 37 — or who does not meet the requirements of this Act and may grant the foreign national permanent resident status or an exemption from any applicable criteria or obligations of this Act if the Minister is of the opinion that it is justified by humanitarian and compassionate considerations relating to the foreign national, taking into account the best interests of a child directly affected.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 35(1)(c) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Subsection 35(1) of the Act is amended by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by repealing paragraphs (d) and (e).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 35(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 35:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Sanctions</MarginalNote><Label>35.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A foreign national is inadmissible on grounds of sanctions if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>their entry into or stay in Canada is restricted under a decision, resolution or measure of an international organization of states or association of states, of which Canada is a member, that imposes sanctions on a person, entity or <DefinitionRef>foreign state</DefinitionRef>, within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>, against which or whom Canada has imposed or has agreed to impose sanctions in concert with that organization or association;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>they are currently the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>they are currently the subject of an order or regulation made under section 4 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Clarification</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, despite section 33, a foreign national whose entry into or stay in Canada is no longer restricted under a decision, resolution or measure referred to in paragraph (1)(a) or who ceases being the subject of an order or regulation referred to in paragraph (1)(b) or (c) is no longer inadmissible under that paragraph.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Paragraphs 42(2)(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the matters referred to in paragraph (1)(a) constitute inadmissibility only if the family member is inadmissible under section 34, 35, 35.1 or 37; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the matters referred to in paragraph (1)(b) constitute inadmissibility only if the foreign national is an accompanying family member of a person who is inadmissible under section 34, 35, 35.1 or 37.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Subsections 42.1(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Exception — application to Minister</MarginalNote><Label>42.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, on application by a foreign national, declare that the matters referred to in section 34, paragraph 35(1)(b) and subsection 37(1) do not constitute inadmissibility in respect of the foreign national if they satisfy the Minister that it is not contrary to the national interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception — Minister’s own initiative</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, on the Minister’s own initiative, declare that the matters referred to in section 34, paragraph 35(1)(b) and subsection 37(1) do not constitute inadmissibility in respect of a foreign national if the Minister is satisfied that it is not contrary to the national interest.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Paragraph 55(3)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has reasonable grounds to suspect that the permanent resident or the foreign national is inadmissible on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, sanctions, serious criminality, criminality or organized criminality.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Paragraph 58(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Minister is taking necessary steps to inquire into a reasonable suspicion that they are inadmissible on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, sanctions, serious criminality, criminality or organized criminality;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Subsection 64(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>No appeal for inadmissibility</MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>No appeal may be made to the Immigration Appeal Division by a foreign national or their sponsor or by a permanent resident if the foreign national or permanent resident has been found to be inadmissible on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, sanctions, serious criminality or organized criminality.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>Paragraph 101(1)(f) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the claimant has been determined to be inadmissible on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, serious criminality or organized criminality.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Sanctions made before coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subsection 35.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> applies in respect of a foreign national whose entry into or stay in Canada is restricted under a decision, resolution or measure referred to in paragraph 35.1(1)(a) of that Act made before the day on which this Act receives royal assent, or who is the subject of an order or regulation referred to in paragraph 35.1(1)(b) or (c) of that Act made before that day, as long as the decision, resolution, measure, order or regulation is in effect on that day.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-29</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Subsection 10.1(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Citizenship Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proof</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), if the Minister seeks a declaration that the person has obtained, retained, renounced or resumed his or her citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances, with respect to a fact described in sections 34, 35, 35.1 or 37 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>, the Minister need prove only that the person has obtained, retained, renounced or resumed his or her citizenship by false representation or fraud or by knowingly concealing material circumstances.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 22 (4th Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergencies Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Clause 30(1)(h)(iii)(A) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Emergencies Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(A)</Label><Text>security, violating human or international rights, sanctions or serious criminality, or</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-21</MarginalNote><Label>15.1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if Bill C-21, introduced in the 1st session of the 44th Parliament and entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to amend certain Acts and to make certain consequential amendments (firearms)</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”), receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 52 of the other Act and section 1 of this Act are in force, paragraph 4(2)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the establishment of policies respecting the enforcement of this Act and inadmissibility on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, sanctions, transborder criminality or organized criminality; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 55 of the other Act and section 9 of this Act are in force, paragraph 55(3)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has reasonable grounds to suspect that the permanent resident or the foreign national is inadmissible on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, sanctions, serious criminality, criminality, transborder criminality or organized criminality.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>On the first day on which both section 56 of the other Act and section 10 of this Act are in force, paragraph 58(1)(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Minister is taking necessary steps to inquire into a reasonable suspicion that they are inadmissible on grounds of security, violating human or international rights, sanctions, serious criminality, criminality, transborder criminality or organized criminality;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>SOR/2002-227</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>Subsection 24.1(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>24.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A foreign national may apply for a declaration of relief under subsection 42.1(1) of the Act if a decision has been made to refuse their application for permanent or temporary resident status, or a removal order has been issued against them, on the basis of a determination of inadmissibility under section 34, paragraph 35(1)(b) or subsection 37(1) of the Act.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>Paragraph 24.2(1)(g) of the Regulations is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the provision of the Act under which they were determined to be inadmissible — section 34, paragraph 35(1)(b) or subsection 37(1) — as well as the date on which and the city and country in which the determination was made and whether the determination resulted in a decision or removal order referred to in subsection 24.1(1).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subparagraph 65(b)(ii) of the Regulations is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>at least five years, if they are inadmissible on any other grounds under the Act, except sections 34 to 35.1 and subsections 36(1) and 37(1) of the Act;</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>Paragraph 228(1)(f) of the Regulations is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>if the foreign national is inadmissible under subsection 35.1(1) of the Act on grounds of sanctions, a deportation order.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Paragraph 229(1)(b) of the Regulations is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a deportation order, if they are inadmissible under subsection 35(1) of the Act on grounds of violating human or international rights;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>Subsection 230(3) of the Regulations is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>is inadmissible under subsection 35.1(1) of the Act on grounds of sanctions;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Report referred to Immigration Division</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Text>Paragraphs 228(1)(f) and 229(1)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations</XRefExternal>, as they read immediately before the day on which this Act receives royal assent, continue to apply in respect of a foreign national for whom, before that day, a report was referred to the Immigration Division for an admissibility hearing under subsection 44(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> and in respect of whom no decision has been made by the Immigration Division before that day.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Referral to committee</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after the third anniversary of the day on which this Act receives royal assent, the provisions enacted or amended by this Act are to be referred to the committee of the Senate, of the House of Commons or of both Houses of Parliament that may be designated or established for the purpose of reviewing those provisions.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The committee to which the provisions are referred is to review them and submit a report to the House or Houses of Parliament of which it is a committee, including a statement setting out any changes to the provisions that the committee recommends.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>