<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-228</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act, the Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act and the Pension Benefits Standards Act, 1985</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Pension Protection Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act, the Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act and the Pension Benefits Standards Act, 1985</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>27</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>6</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2023</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-01-13">441077</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</XRefExternal> to ensure that claims in respect of unfunded liabilities or solvency deficiencies of pension plans and claims relating to the cessation of an employer’s participation in group insurance plans are paid in priority in the event of bankruptcy proceedings.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pension Benefits Standards Act, 1985</XRefExternal> to provide for the tabling of an annual report respecting the solvency of pension plans.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pension Protection Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. B-3; 1992, c. 27, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 60(1.5)(a)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after clause (A):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(A.1)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the sum of all special payments, determined in accordance with section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pension Benefits Standards Regulations, 1985</XRefExternal>, that were required to be paid by the employer to the fund referred to in sections 81.5 and 81.6 to liquidate an unfunded liability or a solvency deficiency,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(A.2)</Label><Text>any amount required to liquidate any other unfunded liability or solvency deficiency of the fund as determined at the time of the filing of the notice of intention or of the proposal, if no notice of intention was filed,</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 60(1.5)(a)(iii) of the Act is amended by adding the following after clause (A):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(A.1)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the sum of all special payments, determined in accordance with section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pension Benefits Standards Regulations, 1985</XRefExternal>, that would have been required to be paid by the employer to the fund referred to in sections 81.5 and 81.6 to liquidate an unfunded liability or a solvency deficiency if the prescribed plan were regulated by an Act of Parliament,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(A.2)</Label><Text>any amount required to liquidate any other unfunded liability or solvency deficiency of the fund as determined at the time of the filing of the notice of intention or of the proposal, if no notice of intention was filed,</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 81.5(1)(b) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the sum of all special payments, determined in accordance with section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pension Benefits Standards Regulations, 1985</XRefExternal>, that were required to be paid by the employer to the fund referred to in this section and section 81.6 to liquidate an unfunded liability or a solvency deficiency,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.2)</Label><Text>any amount required to liquidate any other unfunded liability or solvency deficiency of the fund,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 81.5(1)(c) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the sum of all special payments, determined in accordance with section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pension Benefits Standards Regulations, 1985</XRefExternal>, that would have been required to be paid by the employer to the fund referred to in this section and section 81.6 to liquidate an unfunded liability or a solvency deficiency if the prescribed plan were regulated by an Act of Parliament,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.2)</Label><Text>any amount required to liquidate any other unfunded liability or solvency deficiency of the fund,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 81.6(1)(b) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the sum of all special payments, determined in accordance with section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pension Benefits Standards Regulations, 1985</XRefExternal>, that would be required to be paid by the employer to the fund referred to in section 81.5 and this section to liquidate an unfunded liability or a solvency deficiency,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.2)</Label><Text>any amount required to liquidate any other unfunded liability or solvency deficiency of the fund,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 81.6(1)(c) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the sum of all special payments, determined in accordance with section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pension Benefits Standards Regulations, 1985</XRefExternal>, that would have been required to be paid by the employer to the fund referred to in section 81.5 and this section to liquidate an unfunded liability or a solvency deficiency if the prescribed plan were regulated by an Act of Parliament,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(i.2)</Label><Text>any amount required to liquidate any other unfunded liability or solvency deficiency of the fund,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-36</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 6(6)(a)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Companies’ Creditors Arrangement Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after clause (A):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(A.1)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the sum of all special payments, determined in accordance with section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pension Benefits Standards Regulations, 1985</XRefExternal>, that were required to be paid by the employer to the fund referred to in sections 81.5 and 81.6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> to liquidate an unfunded liability or a solvency deficiency,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(A.2)</Label><Text>any amount required to liquidate any other unfunded liability or solvency deficiency of the fund as determined on the day on which proceedings commence under this Act,</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 6(6)(a)(iii) of the Act is amended by adding the following after clause (A):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Clause><Label>(A.1)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the sum of all special payments, determined in accordance with section 9 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Pension Benefits Standards Regulations, 1985</XRefExternal>, that would have been required to be paid by the employer to the fund referred to in sections 81.5 and 81.6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Bankruptcy and Insolvency Act</XRefExternal> to liquidate an unfunded liability or a solvency deficiency if the prescribed plan were regulated by an Act of Parliament,</Text></Clause><Clause><Label>(A.2)</Label><Text>any amount required to liquidate any other unfunded liability or solvency deficiency of the fund as determined on the day on which proceedings commence under this Act,</Text></Clause></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 32 (2nd Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Pension Benefits Standards Act, 1985</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 40 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Pension Benefits Standards Act, 1985</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>40</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Superintendent shall, after consultation with the Chief Actuary of the Office of the Superintendent of Financial Institutions and as soon as possible after the end of each fiscal year, submit to the Minister a report on</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the operation of this Act during that year; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the success of pension plans in meeting the funding requirements, determined in accordance with section 9, and the corrective measures taken or directed to be taken to deal with any pension plans that are not meeting the funding requirements.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the day the Minister receives it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transmission to provinces</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>As soon as possible after the tabling of the report in Parliament, the Superintendent shall transmit the report to the relevant provincial ministers responsible for finance and provincial securities commissions.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><?Pub Caret -3?><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Exception — employers</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 2 to 4 do not apply in respect of a person who is an employer and who, on the day before the day on which those sections come into force, participated in a prescribed pension plan for the benefit of the person’s employees until the fourth anniversary of the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Exception — companies</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 5(1) and (2) do not apply in respect of a company that, on the day before the day on which those subsections come into force, participated in a prescribed pension plan for the benefit of its employees until the fourth anniversary of the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>