<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" date-time="2022-01-19 15:50:48" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-242</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>44</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>70-71</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II – 1 Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2021-2022-2023</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (temporary resident visas for parents and grandparents)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Reuniting Families Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (temporary resident visas for parents and grandparents)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2023</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>21</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2023</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2022-01-19">441122</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> to allow a parent or grandparent who applies for a temporary resident visa as a visitor to purchase private health insurance outside Canada and to stay in Canada for a period of five years.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>It also requires the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration to prepare and table a report in respect of a reduction to the minimum income requirement that the child or grandchild must meet in order for the visiting parent or grandparent to be able to enter and remain in Canada for an extended period.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Reuniting Families Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2001, c. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 15:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Health insurance policy</MarginalNote><Label>15.1</Label><Text>A health insurance policy purchased from an insurance company outside Canada that is approved by the Minister satisfies any requirement in an instruction given under subsection 15(4) that a foreign national who applies for a temporary resident visa in order to visit their Canadian citizen or permanent resident child or grandchild for an extended period must have private health insurance.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 29 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extended period</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>In the case of a temporary resident who is authorized to enter and remain in Canada for an extended period in order to visit a Canadian citizen or permanent resident who is their child or grandchild, the period referred to in subsection (2) is five years.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Report to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Citizenship and Immigration must prepare a report in respect of a reduction to the minimum income requirement that the child or grandchild of a foreign national must meet in order for the foreign national to be able to enter and remain in Canada for an extended period to visit that child or grandchild, including in respect of any special circumstances to be taken into account in the processing of temporary resident visa applications and a review process for the decisions made in relation to those applications.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Tabling</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament no later than one year after this Act receives royal assent or, if either House is not then sitting, on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the website of the Department of Citizenship and Immigration within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in a House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Explanation</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>If, within two years after this Act receives royal assent, the Minister of Citizenship and Immigration does not provide for a reduction to the minimum income requirement that the child or grandchild of a foreign national must meet in order for the foreign national to be able to enter and remain in Canada for an extended period to visit that child or grandchild or the circumstances or review process referred to in subsection 4(1), the Minister must table in each House of Parliament a statement of the reasons for not doing so.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>