<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>S-203</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and other Acts (ending the captivity of whales and dolphins)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Ending the Captivity of Whales and Dolphins Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Criminal Code and other Acts (ending the captivity of whales and dolphins)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>11</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2019</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2014-10-20">4211336</BillRefNumber></Identification><?Pub Caret -2?><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to create offences respecting cetaceans in captivity. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> to prohibit the taking of a cetacean into captivity and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</XRefExternal> to require a permit for the import of a cetacean into Canada and the export of a cetacean from Canada.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Captivity of Whales and Dolphins Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 445.1:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>cetacean</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>445.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>cetacean</DefinedTermEn> includes any member of the cetacean order, including a whale, dolphin or porpoise.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Offence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (3) and (3.1), every one commits an offence who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>owns, has the custody of or controls a cetacean that is kept in captivity;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>breeds or impregnates a cetacean; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>possesses or seeks to obtain reproductive materials of cetaceans, including sperm or an embryo.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (2)(a) does not apply to a person who</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>owns, has the custody of or controls a cetacean that is kept in captivity at the coming into force of this section and remains continuously in captivity thereafter;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>has the custody of or controls a cetacean that is kept in captivity for the purpose of providing it with assistance or care or to rehabilitate it following an injury or another state of distress; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>is authorized to keep a cetacean in captivity in the best interests of the cetacean’s welfare pursuant to a licence issued by the Lieutenant Governor in Council of a province or by such other person or authority in the province as may be specified by the Lieutenant Governor in Council.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) does not apply to a person who is conducting scientific research pursuant to a licence issued by the Lieutenant Governor in Council of a province or by such other person or authority in the province as may be specified by the Lieutenant Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Every one commits an offence who promotes, arranges, conducts, assists in, receives money for or takes part in any meeting, competition, exhibition, pastime, practice, display or event at or in the course of which captive cetaceans are used for performance for entertainment purposes unless such performance is authorized pursuant to a licence issued by the Lieutenant Governor in Council of a province or by such other person or authority in the province as may be specified by the Lieutenant Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Every one who commits an offence under subsection (2) or (4) is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and liable to a fine not exceeding $200,000.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. F-14</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 28:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Taking cetaceans into captivity</MarginalNote><Label>28.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), no one shall move a live cetacean, including a whale, dolphin or porpoise, from its immediate vicinity with the intent to take it into captivity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person may move a live cetacean from its immediate vicinity when the cetacean is injured or in distress and is in need of assistance.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 52</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 7:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Cetacean: import and export</MarginalNote><Label>7.1</Label><Text>No person shall, except under and in accordance with a permit issued pursuant to subsection 10(1.1), import into Canada or export from Canada a living cetacean, including a whale, dolphin or porpoise, or sperm, a tissue culture or an embryo of a cetacean.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 10 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Issuance</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, on application and on such terms and conditions as the Minister thinks fit, issue a permit authorizing the importation or exportation of a living cetacean, or sperm, a tissue culture or an embryo of a cetacean, if the importation or exportation is for the purpose of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>conducting scientific research; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>keeping the cetacean in captivity if it is in the best interests of the cetacean’s welfare to do so.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Related provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Aboriginal and treaty rights</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the amendments made by this Act to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fisheries Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Wild Animal and Plant Protection and Regulation of International and Interprovincial Trade Act</XRefExternal> shall not be construed so as to abrogate or derogate from the protection provided for existing aboriginal or treaty rights of the aboriginal peoples of Canada by the recognition and affirmation of these rights in section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>