<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-71</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67-68</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018-2019</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend certain Acts and Regulations in relation to firearms</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend certain Acts and Regulations in relation to firearms</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend certain Acts and Regulations in relation to firearms</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2019</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>9</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2019</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-3-16">90859</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 of this Act amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> to, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>remove the reference to the five-year period, set out in subsection 5(2) of that Act, that applies to the mandatory consideration of certain eligibility criteria for holding a licence;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>require, when a non-restricted firearm is transferred, that the transferee’s firearms licence be verified by the Registrar of Firearms and that businesses keep certain information related to the transfer; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>remove certain automatic authorizations to transport prohibited and restricted firearms.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to repeal the authority of the Governor in Council to prescribe by regulation that a prohibited or restricted firearm be a non-restricted firearm or that a prohibited firearm be a restricted firearm and, in consequence, the Part</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>repeals certain provisions of regulations made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> to grandfather certain individuals and firearms, including firearms previously prescribed as restricted or non-restricted firearms in those provisions.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Furthermore, Part 1 amends section 115 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to clarify that firearms and other things seized and detained by, or surrendered to, a peace officer at the time a prohibition order referred to in that section is made are forfeited to the Crown.</Text></Provision></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 2, among other things,</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal>, by repealing the amendments made by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Economic Action Plan 2015 Act, No. 1</XRefExternal>, to retroactively restore the application of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> to the records related to the registration of non-restricted firearms until the day on which this enactment receives royal assent;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>provides that the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> continue to apply to proceedings that were initiated under those Acts before that day until the proceedings are finally disposed of, settled or abandoned; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>directs the Commissioner of Firearms to provide the minister of the Government of Quebec responsible for public security with a copy of such records, at that minister’s request.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText>Amendments to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Regulations Prescribing Certain Firearms and Other Weapons, Components and Parts of Weapons, Accessories, Cartridge Magazines, Ammunition and Projectiles as Prohibited, Restricted or Non-Restricted</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 39</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 27, s. 2(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless otherwise provided, words and expressions used in this Act have the meanings assigned to them by section 2 or 84 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in this Act shall be construed so as to permit or require the registration of non-restricted firearms.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 5(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Criteria</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In determining whether a person is eligible to hold a licence under subsection (1), a chief firearms officer or, on a reference under section <XRefInternal>74</XRefInternal>, a provincial court judge shall have regard to whether the person</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 5(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b) and by replacing paragraph (c) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>has a history of behaviour that includes violence or threatened or attempted violence or threatening conduct on the part of the person against any person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>is or was previously prohibited by an order — made in the interests of the safety and security of any person — from communicating with an identified person or from being at a specified place or within a specified distance of that place, and presently poses a threat or risk to the safety and security of any person;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>in respect of an offence in the commission of which violence was used, threatened or attempted against the person’s intimate partner or former intimate partner, was previously prohibited by a prohibition order from possessing any firearm, cross-bow, prohibited weapon, restricted weapon, prohibited device or prohibited ammunition; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>for any other reason, poses a risk of harm to any person.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, for the purposes of paragraph (2)(c), threatened violence and threatening conduct include threats or conduct communicated by the person to a person by means of the Internet or other digital network.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 12 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (8):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Grandfathered individuals — regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>An individual is eligible to hold a licence authorizing the individual to possess prohibited firearms of a prescribed class if the individual</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>possesses one or more firearms of that class on a day that is prescribed with respect to that class;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>holds a registration certificate for one or more firearms of that class in the circumstances prescribed with respect to that class; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>was continuously the holder of a registration certificate for one or more firearms of that class beginning on the day that is prescribed — or that is determined under the regulations — with respect to that class.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 12 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (9):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Grandfathered individuals — CZ rifle</MarginalNote><Label>(10)</Label><Text>An individual is eligible to hold a licence authorizing the individual to possess one or more firearms referred to in subsection (11) if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the individual possessed one or more such firearms on June 30, 2018;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the individual</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>held on that day a registration certificate for one or more such firearms, in the case where at least one of those firearms was on that day a restricted firearm, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>applies, before the first anniversary of the commencement day, for a registration certificate that is subsequently issued for a firearm referred to in subsection (11), in any other case; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the individual was continuously the holder of a registration certificate for one or more such firearms beginning on</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>June 30, 2018, in the case where at least one of those firearms was on that day a restricted firearm, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the day on which a registration certificate referred to in subparagraph (b)(ii) is issued to the individual, in any other case.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Grandfathered firearms — CZ rifle</MarginalNote><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Subsection (10) applies in respect of a firearm that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is a</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>Ceská Zbrojovka (CZ) Model CZ858 Tactical-2P rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>Ceská Zbrojovka (CZ) Model CZ858 Tactical-2V rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>Ceská Zbrojovka (CZ) Model CZ858 Tactical-4P rifle, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>Ceská Zbrojovka (CZ) Model CZ858 Tactical-4V rifle; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>was registered as a restricted firearm on June 30, 2018 or, in the case of a firearm that was not a restricted firearm on that day, is the subject of an application made before the first anniversary of the commencement day for a registration certificate that is subsequently issued.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the firearms referred to in subparagraphs (11)(a)(i) to (iv) include only firearms that are prohibited firearms on the commencement day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Grandfathered individuals — SAN Swiss Arms</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>An individual is eligible to hold a licence authorizing the individual to possess one or more firearms referred to in subsection (14) if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the individual possessed one or more such firearms on June 30, 2018;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the individual</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>held on that day a registration certificate for one or more such firearms, in the case where at least one of those firearms was on that day a restricted firearm, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>applies, before the first anniversary of the commencement day, for a registration certificate that was subsequently issued for a firearm referred to in subsection (14), in any other case; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the individual was continuously the holder of a registration certificate for one or more such firearms beginning on</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>June 30, 2018, in the case where at least one of the firearms was on that day a restricted firearm, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the day on which a registration certificate referred to in subparagraph (b)(ii) is issued to the individual, in any other case.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Grandfathered firearms — SAN Swiss Arms</MarginalNote><Label>(14)</Label><Text>Subsection (13) applies in respect of a firearm that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is a</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Classic Green rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Classic Green carbine,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Classic Green CQB rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Black Special rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Black Special carbine,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Black Special CQB rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vii)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Black Special Target rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(viii)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Blue Star rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ix)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Heavy Metal rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(x)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Red Devil rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xi)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Swiss Arms Edition rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xii)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Classic Green Sniper rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiii)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Ver rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xiv)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Aestas rifle,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xv)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Autumnus rifle, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(xvi)</Label><Text>SAN Swiss Arms Model Hiemis rifle; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>was registered as a restricted firearm on June 30, 2018 or, in the case of a firearm that was not a restricted firearm on that day, is the subject of an application made before the first anniversary of the commencement day for a registration certificate that is subsequently issued.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 27, s. 6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 19(1.1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Target practice or competition</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>In the case of an authorization to transport issued for a reason referred to in paragraph (1)(a) within the province where the holder of the authorization resides, the specified places must — except in the case of an authorization that is issued for a prohibited firearm referred to in subsection 12(9) — include all shooting clubs and shooting ranges that are approved under section 29 and that are located in that province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception for prohibited firearms other than prohibited handguns</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), an individual must not be authorized to transport a prohibited firearm — other than a handgun referred to in subsection 12(6.1) or a prohibited firearm referred to in subsection 12(9) — between specified places except for the purposes referred to in paragraph (1)(b).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 19(1.1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Target practice or competition</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>In the case of an authorization to transport issued for a reason referred to in paragraph (1)(a) within the province where the holder of the authorization resides, the specified places must — except in the case of an authorization that is issued for a prohibited firearm referred to in subsection 12(9), (11) or (14) — include all shooting clubs and shooting ranges that are approved under section 29 and that are located in that province.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception for prohibited firearms other than prohibited handguns</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), an individual must not be authorized to transport a prohibited firearm — other than a handgun referred to in subsection 12(6.1) or a prohibited firearm referred to in subsection 12(9), (11) or (14) — between specified places except for the purposes referred to in paragraph (1)(b).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 27, s. 6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 19(2.1) to (2.3) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Automatic authorization to transport — licence renewal</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>An individual who holds a licence authorizing the individual to possess restricted firearms or handguns referred to in subsection 12(6.1) must, if the licence is renewed, be authorized to transport them within the individual’s province of residence to and from all shooting clubs and shooting ranges that are approved under section 29. However, the authorization does not apply to a restricted firearm or a handgun referred to in subsection 12(6.1) whose transfer to the individual was approved, in accordance with subparagraph 28(b)(ii), for the purpose of having it form part of a gun collection.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Automatic authorization to transport — transfer</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>If a chief firearms officer has authorized the transfer of a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm to an individual who holds a licence authorizing the individual to possess prohibited firearms or restricted firearms, the individual must be authorized to transport the firearm within the individual’s province of residence from the place where they acquire it to the place where they may possess it under section 17.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Automatic authorization to transport — transfer</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>If a chief firearms officer has authorized the transfer of a restricted firearm or a handgun referred to in subsection 12(6.1) to an individual who holds a licence authorizing the individual to possess a restricted firearm or such a handgun, the individual must be authorized to transport their restricted firearm or handgun within the individual’s province of residence to and from all shooting clubs and shooting ranges that are approved under section 29, unless the transfer of the restricted firearm or handgun was approved, in accordance with subparagraph 28(b)(ii), for the purpose of having it form part of a gun collection.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 6, s. 11; 2015, c. 27, s. 7</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Sections 23 and 23.1 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Authorization to transfer non-restricted firearms</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A person may transfer one or more non-restricted firearms if, at the time of the transfer,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the transferee holds a licence authorizing the transferee to acquire and possess a non-restricted firearm;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Registrar has, at the transferor’s request, issued a reference number for the transfer and provided it to the transferor; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the reference number is still valid.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Information — transferee’s licence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The transferee shall provide to the transferor the prescribed information that relates to the transferee’s licence, for the purpose of enabling the transferor to request that the Registrar issue a reference number for the transfer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reference number</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Registrar shall issue a reference number if he or she is satisfied that the transferee holds and is still eligible to hold a licence authorizing them to acquire and possess a non-restricted firearm.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Period of validity</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A reference number is valid for the prescribed period.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Registrar not satisfied</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the Registrar is not satisfied as set out in subsection (3), he or she may so inform the transferor.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 27, s. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>Subsection 54(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Applications</MarginalNote><Label>54</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A licence, registration certificate or authorization, other than an authorization referred to in subsection 19(2.1), (2.2) or (2.3), may be issued only on application made in the prescribed form — which form may be in writing or electronic — or in the prescribed manner. The application must set out the prescribed information and be accompanied by payment of the prescribed fees.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 58:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Conditions — licence issued to business</MarginalNote><Label>58.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A chief firearms officer who issues a licence to a business must attach the following conditions to the licence:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the business must record and, for the prescribed period, keep the prescribed information that relates to the business’ possession and disposal of non-restricted firearms;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the business must record and — for a period of 20 years from the day on which the business transfers a non-restricted firearm, or for a longer period that may be prescribed — keep the following information in respect of the transfer:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the reference number issued by the Registrar,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the day on which the reference number was issued,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the transferee’s licence number, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the firearm’s make, model and type and, if any, its serial number; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the business must, unless otherwise directed by a chief firearms officer, transmit any records containing the information referred to in paragraph (a) or (b) to a prescribed official if it is determined that the business will cease to be a business.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Destruction of records</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The prescribed official may destroy the records transmitted to them under paragraph (1)(c) at the times and in the circumstances that may be prescribed.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 27, s. 13(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>Subsection 61(3.1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Automatic authorization to transport</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>An authorization to transport referred to in subsection 19(1.1), (2.1), (2.2) or (2.3) must take the form of a condition attached to a licence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote /></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Paragraph 70(1)(a) of the Act is amended by adding the following after subparagraph (i):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i.1)</Label><Text>transfers, as defined in section 21, a non-restricted firearm other than in accordance with section 23,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 85(1) of the French version of the Act before subparagraph (a)(i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Section><MarginalNote>Autres registres du directeur</MarginalNote><Label>85</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Le directeur établit un registre :</Text><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>des armes à feu acquises ou détenues par les personnes précisées ci-après et utilisées par celles-ci dans le cadre de leurs fonctions :</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 85(1)(b) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>b)</Label><Text>des armes à feu acquises ou détenues par des particuliers sous les ordres et pour le compte des forces policières ou d’un ministère fédéral ou provincial;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 85(1) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (a) and by adding the following after paragraph (b):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>every request for a reference number made to the Registrar under section 23 and, if the request is refused, the reasons for refusing the request; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>every reference number that is issued by the Registrar under subsection 23(3) and, with respect to each reference number, the day on which it was issued and the licence numbers of the transferor and transferee.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 85(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reporting of acquisitions and transfers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A person referred to in paragraph (1)(a) or (b) who acquires or transfers a firearm shall have the Registrar informed of the acquisition or transfer.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 6, s. 25</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>Section 90.1 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>The portion of section 109 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Punishment</MarginalNote><Label>109</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under section 106, 107 or 108, who contravenes subsection 29(1) or who contravenes a regulation made under paragraph 117(d), (e), (f), (g), (i), (j), (k.2), (l), (m) or (n) the contravention of which has been made an offence under paragraph 117(o)</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 117 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>regulating, for the purpose of issuing a reference number under section 23, the provision of information by a transferor, a transferee and the Registrar;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 117(m) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>regulating the keeping, transmission and destruction of records in relation to firearms, prohibited weapons, restricted weapons, prohibited devices and prohibited ammunition;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 117 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (n):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(n.1)</Label><Text>regulating the transmission of records under paragraph 58.1(1)(c) by a business to a prescribed official;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 126:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Licence of business — deemed conditions</MarginalNote><Label>126.1</Label><Text>Every licence of a business that is valid on the commencement day is deemed to include the conditions set out in paragraphs 58.1(1)(a) to (c).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 135:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Revocation of authorization to transport</MarginalNote><Label>135.1</Label><Text>All of the following authorizations to transport a prohibited firearm or a restricted firearm are revoked:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>authorizations issued under any of paragraphs 19(2.1)(b) to (e), as those paragraphs read immediately before the commencement day; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>authorizations issued under paragraph 19(2.2)(b), as that paragraph read immediately before the commencement day, in respect of transportation to and from the places referred to in any of the paragraphs that are set out in paragraph (a).</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 27, s. 18</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>non-restricted firearm</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 84(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>non-restricted firearm</DefinedTermEn> means a firearm that is neither a prohibited firearm nor a restricted firearm; (<DefinedTermFr>arme à feu sans restriction</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1995, c. 39, s. 139</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Text>Subsection 115(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>115</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Unless a prohibition order against a person specifies otherwise, every thing the possession of which is prohibited by the order is forfeited to Her Majesty if, on the commencement of the order, the thing is in the person’s possession or has been seized and detained by, or surrendered to, a peace officer.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 27, s. 34</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>Subsections 117.15(3) and (4) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>SOR/98-462; SOR/2015-213, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Regulations Prescribing Certain Firearms and Other Weapons, Components and Parts of Weapons, Accessories, Cartridge Magazines, Ammunition and Projectiles as Prohibited, Restricted or Non-Restricted</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>The title of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Regulations Prescribing Certain Firearms and Other Weapons, Components and Parts of Weapons, Accessories, Cartridge Magazines, Ammunition and Projectiles as Prohibited, Restricted or Non-Restricted</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><LongTitle>Regulations Prescribing Certain Firearms and Other Weapons, Components and Parts of Weapons, Accessories, Cartridge Magazines, Ammunition and Projectiles as Prohibited or Restricted</LongTitle></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Sections 3.1 and 3.2 of the Regulations are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>Part 2.1 of the schedule to the Regulations is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>1</XRefInternal>, subsections <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal>(2) and <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(2) and sections <XRefInternal>16</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>2</XRefInternal> comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection <XRefInternal>4</XRefInternal>(3) and sections <XRefInternal>6</XRefInternal>, <XRefInternal>8</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Sections <XRefInternal>5</XRefInternal> and <XRefInternal>9</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>11</XRefInternal> and subsection <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal>(1) come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal>, subsection <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal>(3) and section <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal> come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council, but that day must not be before the day referred to in subsection (4).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2012, c. 6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 36, s. 230</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 29(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal> is deemed never to have been amended by section 230 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Economic Action Plan 2015 Act, No. 1</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 36, s. 230</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 29(4) to (7) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal> are deemed never to have come into force and are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 36, s. 231</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>Section 30 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal> is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section and in sections <XRefInternal>26</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>commencement day</DefinedTermEn> means the day on which this Act receives royal assent. (<DefinedTermFr>date d’entrée en vigueur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>copy</DefinedTermEn> means a copy referred to in subsection 29(1) or (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>copie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>personal information</DefinedTermEn> means any <DefinitionRef>personal information</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, that is contained in a record or copy. (<DefinedTermFr>renseignements personnels</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>record</DefinedTermEn> means, other than in section <XRefInternal>28</XRefInternal>, a record referred to in subsection 29(1) or (2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>registres</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>specified proceeding</DefinedTermEn> means any request, complaint, investigation, application, judicial review, appeal or other proceeding under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> that is with respect to a record or copy or to personal information and that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>was made or initiated on or before June 22, 2015 and was not concluded, or in respect of which no decision was made, on or before that day; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>was made or initiated after June 22, 2015 but before the commencement day. (<DefinedTermFr>procédure désignée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Non-application — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>26</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to section <XRefInternal>27</XRefInternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> does not apply as of the commencement day with respect to records and copies.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Non-application — <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to section <XRefInternal>27</XRefInternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, other than its subsections 6(1) and (3), does not apply as of the commencement day with respect to personal information.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Non-application — subsections 6(1) and (3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, by reason of subsection 29(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal>, subsections 6(1) and (3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> do not apply as of April 5, 2012 with respect to personal information.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Continued application</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal>, other than its subsections 6(1) and (3), and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> continue to apply with respect to any specified proceeding and to any complaint, investigation, application, judicial review or appeal that results from a specified proceeding.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Period running on June 22, 2015 restarts</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A time limit, or other period of time, under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> or the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> that was running on June 22, 2015 with respect to a specified proceeding described in paragraph (a) of the definition of that expression in section <XRefInternal>25</XRefInternal> is deemed to restart, from the beginning, on the commencement day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Specified proceeding initiated after June 22, 2015</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A specified proceeding described in paragraph (b) of the definition of that expression in section <XRefInternal>25</XRefInternal> is deemed to be made or initiated on the commencement day.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>For greater certainty</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, no destruction of records or copies that are the subject of proceedings referred to in subsection (1) is to occur until all proceedings referred to in that subsection are finally disposed of, settled or abandoned.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Permission to view records</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Text>The Commissioner of Firearms shall permit the Information Commissioner to view — for the purpose of settling the Federal Court proceeding <Emphasis style="italic">Information Commissioner of Canada v. Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness</Emphasis>, bearing court file number T-785-15 — any record that was in the Canadian Firearms Registry on April 3, 2015.</Text></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Copy to Government of Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Commissioner of Firearms shall — for the purpose of the administration and enforcement of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Firearms Registration Act</XRefExternal>, chapter 15 of the Statutes of Quebec, 2016 — provide the Quebec Minister with a copy of all records that were in the Canadian Firearms Registry on April 3, 2015 and that relate to firearms registered, as at that day, as non-restricted firearms, if the Quebec Minister provides the Commissioner with a written request to that effect before the end of the 120th day after the day on which the Commissioner sends written notice under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If no request is provided under subsection (1) before the Commissioner is in a position to proceed with ensuring the destruction of the records referred to in that subsection, the Commissioner shall, as soon as he or she is in that position, send written notice to the Quebec Minister of that fact.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Destruction of records</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 29(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Ending the Long-gun Registry Act</XRefExternal>, the Commissioner shall proceed with ensuring the destruction of the records referred to in subsection (1) only after</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>he or she provides the Quebec Minister with a copy of the records, in the case where that Minister provides a written request in accordance with subsection (1); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the end of the 120th day after the day on which the Commissioner sends written notice under subsection (2), in any other case.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinitionRef>Quebec Minister</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>Quebec Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the minister of the Government of Quebec responsible for public security.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Extension</MarginalNote><Label>30</Label><Text>The Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness may, during the 120-day period referred to in subsection <XRefInternal>29</XRefInternal>(1), make an order extending that period for another 120 days, and in that case the references in subsections <XRefInternal>29</XRefInternal>(1) and (3) to “the 120th day” are to be read as references to “the 240th day”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>