<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>C-70</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to give effect to the Agreement on Cree Nation Governance between the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and the Government of Canada, to amend the Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to give effect to the Agreement on Cree Nation Governance between the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and the Government of Canada, to amend the Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to give effect to the Agreement on Cree Nation Governance between the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and the Government of Canada ...</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>29</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>4</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2018</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2018-2-8">90863</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to give effect to the Agreement on Cree Nation Governance between the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and the Government of Canada, to amend the Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act and to make related and consequential amendments to other Acts</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment gives effect to the Agreement on Cree Nation Governance between the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and the Government of Canada. It amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</XRefExternal> to reduce the administrative burden related to the internal governance of the Naskapi, to ensure that the Act no longer applies to the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and to make changes to certain aspects of the mandate of the Cree-Naskapi Commission to take into account the Agreement. It also makes related and consequential amendments to other Acts.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Enactment of Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Enactment</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal> is enacted as follows:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BillInternal><LongTitle>An Act to give effect to the Agreement on Cree Nation Governance between the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and the Government of Canada</LongTitle><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Grand Council of the Crees (Eeyou Istchee), the Cree Nation Government and the Government of Canada have negotiated the Agreement on Cree Nation Governance between the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and the Government of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>Whereas that agreement was signed by the parties on July 18, 2017;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>And whereas ratification of that agreement requires the coming into force of an Act of Parliament that gives effect to that agreement;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agreement</DefinedTermEn> means the Agreement on Cree Nation Governance between the Crees of Eeyou Istchee and the Government of Canada, entered into on July 18, 2017, between the Government of Canada, the Grand Council of the Crees (Eeyou Istchee) and the Cree Nation Government, including any amendments made to it. (<DefinedTermFr>accord</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cree Constitution</DefinedTermEn> means the constitution developed under section 3.1 of the Agreement and ratified in accordance with sections 31.4, 31.6 and 31.7 of the Agreement. (<DefinedTermFr>constitution crie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cree Nation</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as <DefinitionRef>Cree Nation</DefinitionRef> in section 1.1 of the Agreement. (<DefinedTermFr>nation crie</DefinedTermFr> ou <DefinedTermFr>nation crie d’Eeyou Istchee</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cree Nation Government</DefinedTermEn> means the legal person established under section 2 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the Cree Nation Government</XRefExternal>, CQLR, chapter G-1.031. (<DefinedTermFr>Gouvernement de la nation crie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definitions used in Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Category IA land</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Cree beneficiary</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Cree First Nation</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Cree First Nation law</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Cree law</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Cree Nation Government law</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>federal law</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Inuk of Chisasibi</DefinedTermEn> (in the singular) or <DefinedTermEn>Inuit of Chisasibi</DefinedTermEn> (in the plural) and the <DefinedTermEn>James Bay and Northern Quebec Agreement</DefinedTermEn> have the same meaning as in section 1.1 of the Agreement.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Agreement</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement given effect</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Agreement is approved, given effect and declared valid and has the force of law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement binding</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Agreement is binding on, and may be relied on by, the parties and all other persons and bodies.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>James Bay and Northern Quebec Agreement prevails</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>The James Bay and Northern Quebec Agreement prevails over the Agreement to the extent of any inconsistency or conflict between them.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Agreement prevails</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Agreement prevails over this Act to the extent of any inconsistency or conflict between them.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Act prevails</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), this Act prevails over any other federal law to the extent of any inconsistency or conflict between them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">James Bay and Northern Quebec Native Claims Settlement Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">James Bay and Northern Quebec Native Claims Settlement Act</XRefExternal> prevails over this Act to the extent of any inconsistency or conflict between them.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Constitution and Cree Laws</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Cree Constitution</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Cree Constitution is given effect and has the force of law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Constitution binding</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the Cree Constitution is binding on, and may be relied on by, all persons and bodies. However, the Cree Constitution is not binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Cree law</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A Cree law made in accordance with the Agreement and the Cree Constitution has the force of law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Third parties</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a Cree law is binding on, and may be relied on by, all persons and bodies. However, a Cree law is not binding on Her Majesty in right of Canada or a province.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Cree First Nations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Continuation of Cree bands</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Cree bands constituted as corporations under sections 12 and 12.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</XRefExternal>, as they read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force, are continued as Cree First Nations and continue to be the same legal entities.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>New Cree First Nations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>New Cree First Nations may be constituted in accordance with Chapter 23 of the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Legal capacity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A Cree First Nation has, subject to the Agreement, the capacity, rights, powers and privileges of a natural person.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Application of Other Acts</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to Cree laws or resolutions of Cree First Nations or of the Cree Nation Government made under the Agreement.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Text>Except for the purpose of determining which of the Cree beneficiaries are <DefinitionRef>Indians</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to Cree First Nations, nor does it apply on or in respect of Category IA land.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Non-application of certain Acts</MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Corporations Act</XRefExternal>, chapter C-32 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Not-for-profit Corporations Act</XRefExternal> and any other Acts of Parliament specifically applicable to corporations do not apply to Cree First Nations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>However, the Governor in Council may, by order, at the request of the Cree Nation Government, provide that an Act of Parliament referred to in subsection (1), or any provision of that Act, applies to any Cree First Nation.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Tax and Seizure Exemptions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Continuation of exemptions</MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>Subject to section 9 of the James Bay and Northern Quebec Agreement, the tax and seizure exemptions regimes set out in sections 187 to 193 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</XRefExternal>, as they read immediately before the day on which section <XRefInternal>3</XRefInternal> comes into force, continue to apply as provided in sections <XRefInternal>14</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section and section <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>, <DefinedTermEn>Indian</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in subsection (2), a Cree beneficiary who is an <DefinitionRef>Indian</DefinitionRef> as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in section <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>, an <DefinitionRef>Indian</DefinitionRef> as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this section and section <XRefInternal>15</XRefInternal>, personal property</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that became the property of a Cree First Nation by virtue of section 13 or 13.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</XRefExternal>, as they read immediately before the day on which section 3 comes into force, and had been purchased by Canada with money appropriated by Parliament,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is purchased by Canada, after July 3, 1984, with money appropriated by Parliament for the use and benefit of Indians or Cree First Nations, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that is given, after July 3, 1984, to Indians or to a Cree First Nation under a treaty or agreement between a Cree First Nation and Canada</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>shall be deemed always to be situated on Category IA land.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Property exempt from taxation</MarginalNote><Label>15</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other Act of Parliament or of the legislature of any province, but subject to any Cree First Nation laws made pursuant to paragraph 6.2(1)(k) of the Agreement or any Cree Nation Government laws made pursuant to section 8.15 of the Agreement, the following property is exempt from taxation:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the interest of an Indian or a Cree First Nation in Category IA land; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the personal property of an Indian or a Cree First Nation situated on Category IA land.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Ownership, occupation, etc., of exempt property</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding any other Act of Parliament or of the legislature of any province, but subject to any Cree First Nation laws made pursuant to paragraph 6.2(1)(k) of the Agreement or any Cree Nation Government laws made pursuant to section 8.15 of the Agreement,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>no Indian or Cree First Nation is subject to taxation in respect of the ownership, occupation, possession or use of any property described in paragraph (1)(a) or (b) or is otherwise subject to taxation in respect of any such property; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>no succession duty, inheritance tax or estate duty is payable on the death of any Indian in respect of any such property or the succession thereto if the property passes to an Indian.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>In sections <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>, <DefinedTermEn>Indian</DefinedTermEn> means an <DefinitionRef>Indian</DefinitionRef> as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Property exempt from seizure, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>17</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this section and sections <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>, movable and immovable property situated on Category IA land and belonging to a Cree beneficiary or an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA land, and any right or interest of such a person in Category IA land, is not subject to privilege, hypothec or any other charge, or to attachment, levy, seizure or execution, in favour of or at the instance of any person other than a Cree beneficiary, a Cree First Nation, the Cree Nation Government or an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA land.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Property exempt from seizure, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to this section and sections <XRefInternal>18</XRefInternal> to <XRefInternal>20</XRefInternal>, movable and immovable property situated on Category IA land and belonging to a Cree First Nation is not subject to privilege, hypothec or any other charge, or to attachment, levy, seizure or execution, in favour of or at the instance of any person other than a Cree beneficiary, a Cree First Nation, the Cree Nation Government or an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA land.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The right or interest of a Cree First Nation in its Category IA land is not subject to privilege, hypothec or any other charge, or to attachment, levy, seizure or execution, in favour of or at the instance of any person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A right or interest in Category IA land of a person other than a Cree beneficiary or a Cree First Nation, or the immovable property of such person situated on Category IA land, is not subject to attachment, levy, seizure or execution in favour of or at the instance of any person other than a Cree beneficiary or a Cree First Nation, except where the Cree First Nation has authorized that person to pledge, charge or hypothecate that right or interest or immovable property, in which case creditors may exercise their normal remedies in relation to that pledge, charge or hypothecation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditional sales</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who sells movable property to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Cree beneficiary,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA land, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a Cree First Nation</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>under an agreement whereby the right of property or right of possession thereto remains wholly or in part in the seller may exercise his or her rights under that agreement notwithstanding that the movable property is situated on Category IA land.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Property deemed situated on Category IA land</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>For the purposes of section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>, movable property</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that became the property of a Cree First Nation by virtue of section 13 or 13.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</XRefExternal> as it read immediately before the day on which section 3 comes into force, and had been purchased with money appropriated by Parliament,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is purchased after July 3, 1984 with money appropriated by Parliament or by the legislature of Quebec for the use and benefit of Indians, Cree beneficiaries, or Cree First Nations, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that is, after July 3, 1984, provided to Cree beneficiaries or a Cree First Nation under a treaty or agreement between a Cree First Nation and Canada</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>shall be deemed always to be situated on Category IA land.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Property deemed to be property of a Cree First Nation</MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Text>Where a Cree First Nation has, pursuant to paragraph 11A.0.6 or 11.2.6, as the case may be, of the James Bay and Northern Quebec Agreement, delegated to the Cree Nation Government the power to coordinate and administer a program, movable property that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is necessary for the coordination or administration of that program,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is owned by the Cree Nation Government, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>was purchased with money appropriated by Parliament or by the legislature of Quebec for the use and benefit of Indians, Cree beneficiaries or Cree First Nations</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>shall, for the purposes of section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>, be deemed always to be the property of the Cree First Nation for whose use and benefit it was purchased.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Waiver of exemption</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A Cree beneficiary or an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA land may, in writing, waive the exemption conferred by subsection <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(1) in favour of any person, on such terms and conditions as are agreed to by the parties, but, in the case of a right or interest in Category IA land, the consent of the Cree First Nation must be obtained to the waiver and the terms and conditions thereof in accordance with the Cree Constitution.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver by Cree First Nation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A Cree First Nation may, in writing, waive the exemption conferred by subsection <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal>(2) in favour of any person, on such terms and conditions as are agreed to by the parties, subject to the approval of the waiver and the terms and conditions thereof in accordance with the Cree Constitution.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>General</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice — Agreement</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice must be taken of the Agreement.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Agreement must be published by the Queen’s Printer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A copy of the Agreement published by the Queen’s Printer is evidence of the Agreement and of its contents, and a copy purporting to be published by the Queen’s Printer is presumed to be so published unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Judicial notice — Cree law</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Judicial notice must be taken of any Cree law.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A copy of any Cree law that is certified to be a true copy by a person authorized by the Cree First Nation that made the law or the Cree Nation Government, as the case may be, is evidence of that law and of its contents, without proof of the signature or official character of the person appearing to have signed it, unless the contrary is shown.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Notice to Cree First Nation</MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If an issue arises in any judicial or administrative proceeding in respect of the operability, constitutionality or validity of a provision of a Cree First Nation law, then the issue must not be decided until the party raising the issue has served notice on the Cree First Nation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to Cree Nation Government</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an issue arises in any judicial or administrative proceeding in respect of the operability, constitutionality or validity of the Agreement, the James Bay and Northern Quebec Agreement, this Act or a Cree Nation Government law, then the issue must not be decided until the party raising the issue has served notice on the Cree Nation Government.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Content and timing</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The notice must clearly state the contentions the person intends to assert and the grounds on which they are based and be served at least 30 days before the case is ready for trial. The notice must be accompanied by all pleadings already filed in the record.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Participation in proceedings</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Cree First Nation or the Cree Nation Government, as the case may be, becomes a party to the proceeding without further formality and may submit conclusions to the court or tribunal, in which case the court or tribunal must rule on them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Waiver</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Only the Cree First Nation or the Cree Nation Government, as the case may be, may waive the notice period referred to in subsection (3).</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Inuit of Chisasibi</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For any period during which the council of the Cree Nation of Chisasibi does not include an Inuk of Chisasibi, the Inuit of Chisasibi are entitled to have one Inuk of Chisasibi present as an observer at meetings of that council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations – Inuk observer</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the manner of selection and term and tenure of the Inuk observer referred to in subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights of Inuk observer</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Inuk observer referred to in subsection (1) shall be notified of, and has the right to attend, all council meetings, and has the right to participate in the deliberations of the council, as if he or she were a council member, but he or she does not have the right to vote.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Orders and regulations</MarginalNote><Label>25</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make any orders and regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary for the purpose of carrying out any of the provisions of the Agreement.</Text></Section></Body></BillInternal></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1984, c. 18</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The long title of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><LongTitle>An Act respecting certain provisions of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement relating principally to Naskapi local government and to the land regime governing Category IA-N land and respecting the Cree-Naskapi Commission</LongTitle></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>The preamble to the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas the Government of Canada is obligated, pursuant to section 7 of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement, to recommend to Parliament special legislation to provide for an orderly and efficient system of Naskapi local government, for the administration, management and control of Category IA-N land by the Naskapi band, and for the protection of certain individual and collective rights under the said agreement;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="no"><Text>And whereas this Act is not intended to preclude the Naskapi from benefitting from future legislative or other measures respecting Indian government in Canada that are not incompatible with the said agreement;</Text></Provision></Preamble></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Section 1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Agreements</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Category IA land</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Category II land</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Cree band</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Cree beneficiary</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Cree Regional Authority</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Inuk of Fort George</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>Inuit of Fort George</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>James Bay and Northern Quebec Agreement</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Naskapi band</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>Oujé-Bougoumou Band Complementary Agreement</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 1(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>band</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>Category III land</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>chief</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>council member</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>elector</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>member</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>band</DefinedTermEn> or <DefinedTermEn>Naskapi band</DefinedTermEn> means the Naskapi Nation of Kawawachikamach referred to in section 14; (<DefinedTermFr>bande</DefinedTermFr> ou <DefinedTermFr>bande naskapie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Category III land</DefinedTermEn> means the land established as Category III land pursuant to the Northeastern Quebec Agreement and <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the land regime in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec); (<DefinedTermFr>terre de catégorie III</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>chief</DefinedTermEn> means the person holding the office of chief of the band pursuant to Part II; (<DefinedTermFr>chef</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>council member</DefinedTermEn> means the chief or a councillor of the band; (<DefinedTermFr>membre du conseil</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>elector</DefinedTermEn> means a member of the band who is 18 years of age or over and not under curatorship under the laws of the Province; (<DefinedTermFr>électeur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>member</DefinedTermEn> means a member of the band as provided in section 20; (<DefinedTermFr>membre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph (a) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>Category IA-N land</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>until the transfer to Canada by Quebec by final deed referred to in paragraph (b), the land referred to in sections 4.4 and 5 of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement of which the administration, management and control was transferred to Canada by Quebec by temporary deed by Quebec Order in Council No. 394-81 of February 12, 1981, pursuant to sections 191.3 and 191.5 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the land regime in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec) for the exclusive use and benefit of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Naskapis de Schefferville band, and accepted by Canada by Canada Order in Council P.C. 1981-809 of March 26, 1981,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph (b) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>Category IA-N land</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>after the transfer to Canada by Quebec by final deed for the exclusive use and benefit of the Naskapi band pursuant to sections 4.4 and 5 of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement and section 191.6 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the land regime in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec), the land described in such final deed,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>Naskapi Development Corporation</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Naskapi Development Corporation</DefinedTermEn> means the Naskapi Development Corporation established by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Act respecting the Naskapi Development Corporation</XRefExternal> (Quebec); (<DefinedTermFr>Société de développement des Naskapis</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermFr>assemblée extraordinaire</DefinedTermFr> and <DefinedTermFr>personne morale</DefinedTermFr> or <DefinedTermFr>personalité morale</DefinedTermFr> in subsection 2(1) of the French version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermFr>assemblée extraordinaire</DefinedTermFr> L’assemblée de la bande mentionnée aux articles 83 à 88. (<DefinedTermEn>special band meeting</DefinedTermEn>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermFr>personne morale</DefinedTermFr> ou <DefinedTermFr>personnalité morale</DefinedTermFr> S’entendent au sens de « corporation » dans la Convention du Nord-Est québécois. (<DefinitionFrOnly>French version only</DefinitionFrOnly>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cree Nation Government</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>Gouvernement de la nation crie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Subsection 2(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> band</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A reference in this Act to <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> band is a reference to <DefinitionRef>band</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Except for the purpose of determining which of the Naskapi beneficiaries are <DefinitionRef>Indians</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the band, nor does it apply on or in respect of Category IA-N land.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>The heading before section 6 of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Règlements administratifs et résolutions de la bande</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Sections 6 to 8 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Territorial limits of band by-laws</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Text>A by-law of the band made under this Act may have application within the following territorial limits:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the band’s Category IA-N land; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Category III land situated within the perimeter of the band’s Category IA-N land and the ownership of which was ceded by letters patent or by any other method prior to January 31, 1978.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>By-law may require licence or permit</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>A by-law of the band made under this Act may require the holding of a licence or permit and may provide for the issuance thereof and the fees therefor.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>By-law may prohibit activities</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>A by-law of the band made under this Act may prohibit an activity.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>The heading before section 9.1 and sections 9.1 to 9.3 of the Act are repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 11(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Incorporation by reference of provincial laws</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purpose of applying the portion of paragraph 5.1.13 of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement dealing with the leasing of lands and the granting of real rights to non-Natives, the Governor in Council may make regulations for the purpose of making provincial law in force in the Province applicable to leasehold interests or other real rights in Category IA-N land granted to non-beneficiaries for periods exceeding five years, including any renewal thereof.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 11(2)(a) to (d) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Naskapi beneficiary;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a corporation or other body established pursuant to the Northeastern Quebec Agreement;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a corporation or other body the majority of whose shareholders or members are Naskapi beneficiaries; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a corporation or other body in which Naskapi beneficiaries participate, as shareholders or members or otherwise, and that is prescribed.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>The heading of Part I of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Administration locale</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 3 and 4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>The heading “Incorporation of Bands” before section 12 and sections 12 to 15 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Band Name</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Naskapi Nation of Kawawachikamach</MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Naskapi Band of Quebec (Bande Naskapi du Québec, in French, and Kobac Naskapi-aeyouch, in Naskapi), which was formerly the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Naskapis de Schefferville band and was constituted as a corporation by this subsection, as it read on July 3, 1984, is continued as the same legal entity bearing the following names, subject to section 16:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Naskapi Nation of Kawawachikamach, in English;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Nation naskapie de Kawawachikamach, in French; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>Naskapi Eeyouch Kawawachikamach, in Naskapi.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Name</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The band may be designated by any of its names mentioned in paragraphs (1)(a) to (c).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Subsection 16(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Change of band name</MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The band may, by by-law approved by the electors of the band at a special band meeting or referendum at which at least 5% of the electors voted on the matter, change its English, French or Naskapi name, but no such by-law is valid unless approved by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>14</Label><Text>The heading before section 17 and sections 17 to 20 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Membership of Band</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Membership of band</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Text>The members of the band are the Naskapi beneficiaries.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Paragraphs 20.1(a) to (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>shall be deemed to be a member of the band for the purposes of paragraph 21(f), section 45, subsection 55(1), paragraphs 90(2)(a) and (b) and subsections 94(3) and (4) and 103(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>shall, if 18 years of age or over and not under curatorship under the laws of the Province, be deemed to be an elector of the band for the purposes of section 63, subparagraph 66(1)(a)(i) and sections 68 and 75, but is not eligible to be elected chief of the band; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>shall, if 18 years of age or over and not under curatorship under the laws of the Province, be deemed to be an elector of the band for the purposes of section 81, except where the matter submitted to a vote is a matter referred to in Part VI, VII, VIII or IX.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>The heading before section 21 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Objects and Powers of Band</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 21 of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Objects of band</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Text>The objects of the band are</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 21(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>to act as the local government authority on its Category IA-N land;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 21(b) to (d) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>to use, manage, administer and regulate its Category IA-N land and the natural resources thereof;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>to control the disposition of rights and interests in its Category IA-N land and in the natural resources thereof;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>to regulate the use of buildings on its Category IA-N land;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 21(h) to (j) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>to establish and administer services, programs and projects for members of the band and other residents of Category IA-N land and residents of the Category III land referred to in paragraph 6(b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>to promote and preserve the culture, values and traditions of the Naskapi; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>to exercise the powers and carry out the duties conferred or imposed on the band or on its predecessor <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> band by any Act of Parliament or regulations made thereunder, and by the Northeastern Quebec Agreement.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 22(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Legal capacity of band</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The band has, subject to this Act and the regulations, the capacity, rights, powers and privileges of a natural person.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 22(2)(a)(ii) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>its buildings or other immovable assets on its Category IA-N land; or</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 22(2)(b) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the provision of public services to or in respect of its Category IA-N land or residents thereof.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 23(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Band may not be continued under <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 268 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the band.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 23, s. 352 </HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 23(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Acts not applicable to band</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Corporations Act</XRefExternal>, chapter C-32 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Not-for-profit Corporations Act</XRefExternal> do not apply to the band.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>Section 24 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Head office of band</MarginalNote><Label>24</Label><Text>The head office of the band shall be located at such place on its Category IA-N land as is fixed by the band.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>Sections 27 and 28 of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Resolutions and by-laws</MarginalNote><Label>27</Label><Text>The council shall act by resolution, except where required to act by by-law.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Chief</MarginalNote><Label>28</Label><Text>The chief of the band is the band’s principal representative and chief executive officer and shall perform any duties assigned to him or her by the regulations and the by-laws of the band.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>22</Label><Text>Subsection 29(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Deputy chief</MarginalNote><Label>29</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>One councillor shall hold office as deputy chief in accordance with an election by-law made under section 64 or in accordance with regulations made under paragraph 67(1)(a).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>Sections 31 and 32 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Use of Naskapi language at council meetings</MarginalNote><Label>31</Label><Text>In addition to any other rights relating to the use of the Naskapi language, the band may conduct its council meetings in the Naskapi language.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Language of by-laws and resolutions</MarginalNote><Label>32</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A by-law or resolution of the band shall be enacted or adopted in either the English or the French language, and may also be enacted or adopted in the Naskapi language.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Versions adopted in more than one language</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a by-law is enacted or a resolution is adopted in more than one of the English, French or Naskapi languages, all versions in which it is enacted or adopted are equally authoritative.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Subsection 33(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Quorum of council</MarginalNote><Label>33</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Except as provided in subsection (2), a quorum of the council consists of a majority of the number of positions of council member, subject to subsection 38(5).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>25</Label><Text>Subsection 35(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Voting</MarginalNote><Label>35</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The approval of any matter by the council requires the affirmative votes of the majority of the council members present when the vote is taken, subject to subsection (2) and subsection 38(5).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>26</Label><Text>Section 36 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>27</Label><Text>Subsection 37(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>When council must meet</MarginalNote><Label>37</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The council shall meet at least once in every calendar quarter.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>28</Label><Text>Subsection 38(7) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>29</Label><Text>Section 43 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Duties of band treasurer</MarginalNote><Label>43</Label><Text>The band treasurer is the chief financial officer of the band, and is responsible for the receipt and deposit of band moneys and for all aspects of the financial administration of the band.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>30</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 45(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Power to make by-laws respecting local government</MarginalNote><Label>45</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this section, the band may make by-laws of a local nature for the good government of its Category IA-N land and of the inhabitants of such land, and for the general welfare of the members of the band, and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, may make by-laws respecting</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 45(1)(h)(ii) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>of occupants and tenants of its Category IA-N land, except Canada and Quebec,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>31</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 46(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>By-laws re land and resource use and planning</MarginalNote><Label>46</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The band may make by-laws respecting land and resource use and planning, including, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, by-laws respecting</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 46(1)(a) to (c) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the inventory, use and management of its Category IA-N land and the natural resources thereof;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the adoption of land use plans and resource use plans in relation to its Category IA-N land; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>use permits relating to its Category IA-N land and buildings located thereon, and the conditions relating to the issuance, suspension or revocation of such permits.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>32</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 48(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the exercise of the right to harvest referred to in section 15 of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement and in <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting hunting and fishing rights in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 48(1)(c) and (d) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>residence requirements relating to sport hunting and sport fishing by persons other than Naskapi beneficiaries, as contemplated by section 37 of that Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the right of persons of Naskapi ancestry to harvest for personal use, as contemplated by section 38.1 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 48(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Proposed by-laws to be submitted to Coordinating Committee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), a copy of each by-law described in subsection (1) that a band proposes to make shall, a reasonable period of time before its enactment, be submitted by the band to the Coordinating Committee referred to in section 15 of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement and in <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting hunting and fishing rights in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec), in order to enable that Committee to make representations to the band with respect thereto, but the band is not bound by any such representations.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>33</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 48:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>By-laws — ticketing scheme</MarginalNote><Label>48.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The band may make by-laws respecting the establishment of a ticketing scheme governing proceedings, commenced by means of a ticket, in respect of the contravention of any by-law of the band indicated in those by-laws.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreement with Government of Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>By-laws may be made under subsection (1) only if an agreement is entered into between the band and the Government of Quebec.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>34</Label><Text>Subsection 50(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Original to be signed</MarginalNote><Label>50</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The original copy of any by-law of the band must be signed by the band secretary or such other person as is designated by by-law.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>35</Label><Text>Subsection 52(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Posting of by-laws</MarginalNote><Label>52</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within one week after a by-law has been enacted by the band, or has been enacted by the band and approved by the electors of the band at a special band meeting or referendum (where such approval is required), the band secretary shall post a copy of the by-law on the band’s Category IA-N land at a public place designated by the band.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, ss. 7, 8 and 9</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>36</Label><Text>The heading “Cree Transitional Provisions” before section 58 and sections 58 to 62.3 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Existing council of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Naskapi band</MarginalNote><Label>61</Label><Text>Subject to section 62, the council of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Naskapis de Schefferville band that is in office pursuant to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> immediately before the coming into force of this Part becomes the council of the band on the coming into force of this Part, and continues in office as such until the expiration of its term of office under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> or until a day two years after the coming into force of this Part, whichever occurs first.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provisions of this Act to apply</MarginalNote><Label>62</Label><Text>For the transitional period described in section 61, the council has the powers and duties of a band council elected under this Act, and the provisions of this Act and the regulations apply, with such modifications as the circumstances require, to the council as if it had been elected under this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>37</Label><Text>Subsection 63(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Each elector entitled to vote</MarginalNote><Label>63</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), each elector of the band is entitled to vote in any election of council members held by the band, whether the election is conducted pursuant to an election by-law made under section 64 or pursuant to regulations made under paragraph 67(1)(a).</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>38</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 68 of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Eligibility to be elected council member</MarginalNote><Label>68</Label><Text>Any elector of the band is eligible to be elected to the office of council member of the band unless he or she</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 68(f) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>resides on the Matimekosh Reserve.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>39</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subparagraph 69(b)(vi) of the Act of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>is under curatorship under the laws of the Province;</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 69(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the office-holder resides on the Matimekosh Reserve; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>40</Label><Text>Section 71 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Returning Officers</MarginalNote><Label>71</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The band shall appoint a person who is not a council member as Returning Officer, and shall fix his or her tenure and term of office.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Deputy and Assistant Returning Officers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Returning Officer shall appoint a Deputy Returning Officer and may appoint any Assistant Returning Officers who are necessary to assist him or her in the performance of his or her duties.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence, etc., of Returning Officer</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the Returning Officer is absent or incapacitated or the office of Returning Officer is vacant, the Deputy Returning Officer has and may exercise all the powers and duties of the Returning Officer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Absence, etc., of both Returning Officer and Deputy Returning Officer</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In the event of the absence or incapacity of both the Returning Officer and the Deputy Returning Officer or if both such offices are vacant, the band secretary has and may exercise all the powers and duties of the Returning Officer.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>41</Label><Text>Paragraph 73(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>is under curatorship under the laws of the Province.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>42</Label><Text>Subsection 78(1) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Contestation of election</MarginalNote><Label>78</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any candidate for election as council member or any 15 electors of the band may, within five days of the day of any election held by the band, contest the election of any council member or council members elected thereat by submitting to the Returning Officer a written notice to that effect.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>43</Label><Text>Section 80 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Use of Naskapi language</MarginalNote><Label>80</Label><Text>In addition to any other rights relating to the use of the Naskapi language, the band may conduct ordinary band meetings, special band meetings and referenda in the Naskapi language.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>44</Label><Text>Section 81 of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Each elector may vote</MarginalNote><Label>81</Label><Text>Each elector of the band is entitled to vote in respect of any matter submitted to a vote at an ordinary band meeting, special band meeting or referendum.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>45</Label><Text>The heading of Part IV of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Financial Administration</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>46</Label><Text>Paragraph 90(2)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>send a copy of it to the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>47</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 91(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Access to books and records</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister or a council member or elector of the band, or any person authorized in writing by the Minister or by a council member or elector, may, at any reasonable time, inspect the books of account and financial records of the band, and a person is guilty of an offence who</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 91(2.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 12</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>48</Label><Text>Subsections 93(5) and (5.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>If band fails to act</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>If the band fails to act under subsection (4), the Minister may appoint a new auditor and fix that auditor’s remuneration.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice to the band</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall inform the band in writing of the appointment.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 13</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>49</Label><Text>Subsection 94(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where report delayed</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the auditor has not been able to prepare the report within the period mentioned in subsection (1), the auditor shall notify the band and the Minister of the reasons for the delay.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>50</Label><Text>Subsection 97(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Long-term borrowing</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A by-law made under subsection (1) authorizing long-term borrowing, other than for housing purposes, must be approved by the electors of the band at a special band meeting or referendum at which at least 20% of the electors voted on the matter.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>51</Label><Text>Section 98 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations re long-term borrowing</MarginalNote><Label>98</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting long-term borrowing by the band.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>52</Label><Text>Section 99 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>By-laws re contracts and tenders</MarginalNote><Label>99</Label><Text>The band may make by-laws respecting procedures for the awarding of contracts and the calling of tenders in relation thereto, and such by-laws may take into account the preferential contract and employment benefits for Naskapi beneficiaries contained in the Northeastern Quebec Agreement or established pursuant to that agreement.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 14(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>53</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 100(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>When administrator may be appointed</MarginalNote><Label>100</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>If, as a result of an inspection by the Minister or a person authorized by the Minister under subsection 91(2), the auditor’s report under subsection 94(1), or any non-compliance with the provisions of this Part, the Minister is of the opinion that the financial affairs of the band are in serious disorder, the Minister may give written notice to the band, of his or her intention to appoint an administrator to administer the financial affairs of the band, setting out his or her reasons for so doing.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 14(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 100(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment of administrator</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>At any time between 60 days and one year after giving notice to the band under subsection (1), the Minister may, if the Minister is of the opinion that the situation referred to in the notice has not been adequately remedied, appoint, by order, an administrator to administer the financial affairs of the band, and the order shall set out the duties of the administrator. The Minister shall send a copy of the order without delay to the band.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>54</Label><Text>The heading of Part V of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Residence and Access Rights on Category IA-N Land</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>55</Label><Text>Subsection 102(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>By-laws respecting the exercise of residence and access rights</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The band may make by-laws for the purpose of regulating, on its Category IA-N land, the exercise of residence or access rights conferred by sections 103 to 106, but, except in the case of an authorization to reside under paragraph 103(2)(a) or an authorization of access under paragraph 105(5)(e), such a by-law may not, notwithstanding section 8, unreasonably restrict or, except as provided by subsection 103(3), effectively deny any such residence or access right.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>56</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 103(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Right to reside on Category IA-N land</MarginalNote><Label>103</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following persons have the right to reside on Category IA-N land of the band:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 103(1)(a) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a member of the band;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 103(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special categories of persons who may reside on Category IA-N land</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In addition to persons described in subsection (1), the following persons may reside on Category IA-N land of the band:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 103(2)(a) and (b) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a person so authorized in writing by the band or by a by-law of the band;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a person so authorized by virtue of a grant from the band under Part VIII;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraph 103(2)(d) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (3), a person engaged in administrative or public duties approved by the band or scientific studies approved by the band.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsection 103(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Band’s control over number of outsiders</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The band may prohibit a person described in paragraph (2)(d) from residing on its Category IA-N land where the number of such persons would be such as to significantly alter the demographic composition of the community.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 15</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>57</Label><Text>Section 104 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Pre-Agreement residence and occupation rights not affected</MarginalNote><Label>104</Label><Text>A person who is not a Naskapi beneficiary and was, immediately before January 31, 1978, residing on or occupying, by virtue of a right of residence or occupancy, land that became Category IA-N land by virtue of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement, and continues to reside on or occupy that land by virtue of that right at the coming into force of this Part, may continue to reside on or occupy that land in accordance with that right until the expiry of that right.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 16(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>58</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 105(1) to (3) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 105(4)(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a person deemed by paragraph 20.1(a) to be a member of the band.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 105(5) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special categories of persons who are permitted access to Category IA-N land</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>In addition to persons described in subsection (4), the following persons are permitted access to Category IA-N land of the band to the extent required in order to exercise their rights or functions referred to below, subject to the terms and conditions of the right or function in question:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Paragraph 105(5)(b) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a holder of a right or interest granted under Part VIII in Category IA-N land or in a building situated thereon;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 16(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraph 105(5)(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a holder of a mining right or other subsurface right referred to in section 115 or a person exercising a right under subsection 113(3); and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>59</Label><Text>Sections 106 and 107 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Public’s access to public facilities</MarginalNote><Label>106</Label><Text>Any member of the public is permitted access to the public facilities and installations mentioned in section 191.45 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the land regime in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec), where all or any part of such a facility or installation is located on Category IA-N land.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Matimekosh Reserve</MarginalNote><Label>107</Label><Text>Despite the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>, a Naskapi beneficiary who, immediately before the coming into force of this section, resided on the Matimekosh Reserve has the right to continue to reside on, and enjoy access to and movement about, that reserve, subject to subsection 20.25A of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>60</Label><Text>Section 109 of the Act and the heading of Part VI before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Rights of Band, Quebec and Others in Relation to Category IA-N Land</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Quebec retains bare ownership</MarginalNote><Label>109</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Quebec retains the bare ownership of Category IA-N land.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Band’s rights — land and resources</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to this Act, the band has the exclusive use and benefit of its Category IA-N land and the natural resources thereof, and may administer, manage, control, use and enjoy that land and the natural resources thereof for community, commercial, industrial, residential or other purposes, as if it were the owner thereof.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>61</Label><Text>Section 110 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Band ownership of soapstone deposits</MarginalNote><Label>110</Label><Text>All deposits of soapstone, and any other similar material used for traditional arts and crafts of the Naskapi on Category IA-N land of the band are the property of the band.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>62</Label><Text>Section 111 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Band’s rights subject to provincial control</MarginalNote><Label>111</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The band has the exclusive right to the commercial exploitation of forest resources on its Category IA-N land without the payment of stumpage dues, but it may not exercise the right conferred on it by this subsection, either directly or through persons authorized by the band, unless it obtains cutting rights or a licence to cut timber from the provincial Minister responsible therefor, as required by section 191.40 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the land regime in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where approval required at band meeting</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An authorization from the band to a person for commercial exploitation of forest resources on the band’s Category IA-N land requires the approval of the electors of the band at a special band meeting or referendum at which at least 25% of the electors voted on the matter.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Right of member of band</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subject to any by-law of the band made under section 45 restricting or prohibiting the use of forest resources, a member of the band may use forest resources on Category IA-N land of the band for personal or community purposes.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>63</Label><Text>Section 112 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Gravel</MarginalNote><Label>112</Label><Text>Where it has obtained a permit pursuant to section 191.38 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the land regime in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec), the band may use, in accordance with that permit, gravel and other similar material generally used for personal or community earthworks.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 17</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>64</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 113(1) to (3.1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Mineral and subsurface rights</MarginalNote><Label>113</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this Act, Quebec retains the ownership of all mineral rights and subsurface rights on Category IA-N land.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consent and compensation requirements</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (3), after January 31, 1978, no mineral right or subsurface right on Category IA-N land of the band may be granted or exercised and no mineral or other subsurface material or substance may be mined or extracted from such land without the consent of the band and payment to the band of compensation agreed to by the band.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A holder of a right or title described in section 115 may, without the consent and payment referred to in subsection (2) but subject to subsections 116(1) and (3) and the payment of compensation as set out in subsection 116(4), explore for and exploit minerals on adjacent Category IA-N land if those minerals extend continuously from the minerals that are the object of the permit, right or title.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 113(4)(b) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a grant by the band of a right or interest in its Category IA-N land in connection with the giving of the consent referred to in subsection (2); and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, ss. 18 and 19</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>65</Label><Text>Sections 114 and 115 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Holders of prior rights or titles to minerals</MarginalNote><Label>115</Label><Text>A holder of a right or title (including a mining claim, development licence, exploration permit, mining concession and mining lease) to minerals (“minerals” as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mining Act</XRefExternal> (Quebec) as it read on January 31, 1978) granted before January 31, 1978 on land surrounded by or adjacent to land that subsequently became Category IA-N land pursuant to the Northeastern Quebec Agreement may, subject to subsections 116(3) and (4), use that Category IA-N land to the extent necessary for the exercise of his or her right or title.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>66</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 116(1) to (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Manner in which rights must be exercised</MarginalNote><Label>116</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The rights conferred by subsection 113(3) may not be exercised otherwise than in accordance with Division XXII of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mining Act</XRefExternal> (Quebec) as it read on January 31, 1978, except that the expropriation of servitudes provided for by that Division shall be restricted to temporary servitudes.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 116(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Manner in which rights must be exercised</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The right conferred by section 115 may not be exercised otherwise than in accordance with Division XXII of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Mining Act</XRefExternal> (Quebec) as it read on January 31, 1978, except that the expropriation of servitudes provided for by that Division shall be restricted to temporary servitudes.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 116(4) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compensation to band</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where Category IA-N land is used pursuant to subsection 113(3) or section 115, compensation shall be paid to the band</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 116(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Procedure re replacement land</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Where compensation is payable under paragraph (4)(a), sections 125 and 126 apply, with such modifications as the circumstances require.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>67</Label><Text>The heading before section 117 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Pre-Existing Rights and Interests on Category IA-N Land</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 21(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>68</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 117(1) and (1.1) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 21(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 117(3) to (4) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Previously held rights and interests</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where, immediately before the coming into force of this Part, a person held a right or interest, lawfully granted by the Minister or by the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Naskapis de Schefferville band,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in Category IA-N land,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in land that became Category IA-N land by virtue of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>in a building situated on land described in paragraph (a) or (b),</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>the band shall, if that person so requests within two years after the coming into force of Part VIII, forthwith grant to that person under that Part a right or interest that is equivalent to the person’s former right or interest, whereupon the person’s former right or interest expires; and where the person does not make the request within two years after the coming into force of Part VIII, that person’s former right or interest expires at the end of that period.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, ss. 21(3) and (4)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 117(5) to (7) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Previous possession or occupation</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Where, immediately before the coming into force of this Part, a person was in possession of, or occupied, with the explicit consent of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal> Naskapis de Schefferville band,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>Category IA-N land,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>land that became Category IA-N land by virtue of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a building owned by that band and situated on land described in paragraph (a) or (b),</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>but that person was not a holder of a right or interest in that land or building referred to in subsection (2) or (4), the band shall, if that person so requests within two years after the coming into force of Part VIII, forthwith grant to that person under that Part a right or interest in such land or building that is equitable in the circumstances, taking into account that possession or occupation and all other relevant factors.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Certain restrictions applicable</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsections 132(2) and (4) and section 137 apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, in respect of a grant by the band of a right or interest in land pursuant to subsection (4) or (6).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>69</Label><Text>Subsection 119(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Expropriations</MarginalNote><Label>119</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An expropriating authority may not expropriate any Category IA-N land or any interest therein except as provided by this Part.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>70</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 120(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Expropriation for public services or structures</MarginalNote><Label>120</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this Part, an expropriating authority may expropriate in full ownership any Category IA-N land or any building thereon, or may expropriate a servitude over any Category IA-N land, but only for the purpose of, and to the extent necessary for, the establishment of the following public services or structures:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 120(2)(a) of the French version of the Act before subparagraph (i) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>l’autorité n’a pas réussi, malgré des efforts sérieux, à obtenir, pour un coût inférieur ou sensiblement équivalent à celui de l’implantation de l’ouvrage sur des terres de catégorie IA-N, que celui-ci soit implanté :</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 120(2)(a) of the Act is amended by adding “or” at the end of subparagraph 120(2)(a)(i) and by repealing subparagraph (ii).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of paragraph 120(2)(a) of the English version of the Act after subparagraph (iii) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><ContinuedParagraph><Text>and has been unable to do so at a cost substantially equivalent to or lower than the cost of locating the pipeline or transmission line on Category IA-N land; and</Text></ContinuedParagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Paragraph 120(2)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the pipeline or transmission line is to be located as far as possible from the centre of any residential area located on Category IA-N land.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>71</Label><Text>Subsection 122(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Compensation in money</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Notwithstanding subsections (2) and (4), the expropriating authority may compensate the band exclusively in money in the circumstances described in the third paragraph of section 191.22 of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act respecting the land regime in the James Bay and New Quebec territories</XRefExternal> (Quebec).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>72</Label><Text>Section 123 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Where no compensation payable</MarginalNote><Label>123</Label><Text>The band is not entitled to any compensation where the expropriation is for a purpose mentioned in paragraph 120(1)(a), (b), (c) or (e) and the service or structure in question is of direct benefit to the members of the band as a community or to a significant portion of the band’s Category IA-N land.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>73</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 124(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Statement on expropriation notice</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>An expropriating authority shall indicate on an expropriation notice whether or not the service or structure to be established on the land being expropriated is, in the opinion of the expropriating authority, of direct benefit to the members of the band as a community or to a significant portion of the band’s Category IA-N land.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 124(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where the expropriating authority referred to in subsection (2) fails to indicate its opinion in accordance with that subsection or indicates that, in its opinion, the service or structure referred to in subsection (2) is not of direct benefit to the members of the band as a community or to a significant portion of the band’s Category IA-N land, the service or structure shall be deemed, for the purposes of this Part, not to be of direct benefit to the members of the band as a community or to a significant portion of the band’s Category IA-N land.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 124(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disputes referrable to Administrative Tribunal of Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where the band and an expropriating authority disagree as to whether a service or structure is of direct benefit to the members of the band as a community or to a significant portion of the band’s Category IA-N land, or disagree as to whether a service or structure is one described in paragraphs (1)(a) to (d), the issue shall be determined by the Administrative Tribunal of Quebec, unless the parties have agreed to submit the matter to final and binding arbitration.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 124(6) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Factors to be considered</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In determining whether a service or structure is one described in paragraph (1)(b), (c) or (d) or whether a service or structure not described in subsection (1) is of direct benefit to the members of the band as a community or to a significant portion of the band’s Category IA-N land, regard shall be had to the potential use by the members of the band as a community of the service or structure, the advantages of the service or structure to the members of the band as a community, and the anticipated benefit of the service or structure to the Category IA-N land of the band.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>74</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 125(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Rules governing compensation wholly or partly in land</MarginalNote><Label>125</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where the band is entitled to be compensated with land under paragraph 116(4)(a) or subsection 122(2) or elects to be compensated wholly or partly with land under subsection 122(4), the following rules apply:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraphs 125(1)(b)(i) and (ii) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is Category III land,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is adjacent to Category IA-N land of the band, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 125(1)(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>once replacement land has been accepted by the band, the necessary measures shall forthwith be taken by Quebec and Canada to set aside that replacement land as Category IA-N land of the band, unless other arrangements are agreed to between Quebec and the band and approved at a special band meeting or referendum at which at least 25% of the electors voted on the matter; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 125(2) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>75</Label><Text>Sections 126 and 127 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Reclassification of expropriated land that is no longer required</MarginalNote><Label>126</Label><Text>Where</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the band has been compensated with replacement land pursuant to paragraph 116(4)(a) or subsection 122(2) or (4), or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>no compensation was paid to the band pursuant to section 123,</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>and subsequently the expropriated land is no longer required by the expropriating authority for the purpose for which it was expropriated, Canada and Quebec shall forthwith, if requested by the band by resolution approved by the electors of the band at a special band meeting or referendum at which at least 25% of the electors voted on the matter, take the necessary measures to reclassify the expropriated land as Category IA-N land, and, in the situation described in paragraph (a), shall take the necessary measures to return the replacement land to its former classification.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Determination of amount of money compensation referrable to Administrative Tribunal of Quebec</MarginalNote><Label>127</Label><Text>Where compensation is payable wholly or partly in money pursuant to subsection 122(3) or (4) or paragraph 125(1)(e), and the parties cannot agree on the amount of such compensation, the amount shall be determined by the Administrative Tribunal of Quebec in accordance with the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal> (Quebec), unless the parties submit the matter to final and binding arbitration.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>76</Label><Text>The portion of section 129 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>When expropriated land ceases to be Category IA-N land</MarginalNote><Label>129</Label><Text>Where Category IA-N land has been expropriated in full ownership under this Part, the expropriated land ceases to be Category IA-N land</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>77</Label><Text>The heading of Part VIII of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Dispositions of Rights and Interests in Category IA-N Land and Buildings</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>78</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 135(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Commercial fisheries and outfitting operations</MarginalNote><Label>135</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A grant by the band relating to its Category IA-N land does not permit the grantee to use that land for</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>79</Label><Text>Subsection 137(3) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Approval for deemed transfer of corporation’s right or interest</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where a transfer of a right or interest of a corporation in Category IA-N land of the band is deemed to have occurred by virtue of subsection 130(2) as a result of a change in the effective voting control of the corporation and that change in the effective voting control had not been previously authorized by the band pursuant to subsection (1) or (2), as the case may be, that right or interest of the corporation reverts to the band as of the date of the change in effective voting control of the corporation.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 22</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>80</Label><Text>Section 138 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Consultation requirements before certain projects undertaken</MarginalNote><Label>138</Label><Text>The band shall consult with the department or agency of the Government of Quebec or other person designated by Quebec and the Minister before permitting a person other than a Naskapi beneficiary, a body composed of a majority of Naskapi beneficiaries, or a party to the Northeastern Quebec Agreement to develop a project of a regional or provincial nature on the band’s Category IA-N land.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>81</Label><Text>Subsections 139(1.1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Mode of allocation and fee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The allocation of land by the band pursuant to subsection (1) shall be effected by way of servitude, lease or similar contract, and for a fee not exceeding one dollar.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>82</Label><Text>The heading of Part IX of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Cessions by Band</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>83</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinedTermEn>cession</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 141(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>cession</DefinedTermEn> means the ceding of the whole of the rights and interests of the band in or on any of its Category IA-N land; (<DefinedTermFr>abandon</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 141(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Granting of rights or interests under other Parts of Act</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, the granting of rights or interests by the band in its Category IA-N land pursuant to any other Part of this Act does not constitute a cession within the meaning of this Part.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>84</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 144(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Cession must be approved by referendum</MarginalNote><Label>144</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A cession requires the approval of the electors of the band in a referendum in which more than 50% of the electors of the band vote in favour of the cession.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 144(2)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>must be posted on the band’s Category IA-N land at a public place designated by the band.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>85</Label><Text>Paragraph 150(1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a right conferred by section 115, and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>86</Label><Text>The portion of section 151 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations for establishment and maintenance of land registry system</MarginalNote><Label>151</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations for establishing and maintaining a land registry system, under the control and supervision of the Minister, for the registration of rights and interests in Category IA-N land and in buildings situated thereon, and, without restricting the generality of the foregoing, may make regulations respecting</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>87</Label><Text>The heading of Part XI of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Expropriation by Band</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>88</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of section 153 of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Rights and interests that the band may expropriate</MarginalNote><Label>153</Label><Text>Where regulations made under section 156 are in force, the band may, subject to and in accordance with those regulations, for community purposes or community works, expropriate any right or interest in its Category IA-N land or in any building situated thereon, except for</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 153(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a right conferred by section 115; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>89</Label><Text>The heading of Part XII of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Commission crie-naskapie</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>90</Label><Text>Section 157 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cree First Nation</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; (<DefinedTermFr>première nation crie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>91</Label><Text>Subsection 158(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Cree-Naskapi Commission established</MarginalNote><Label>158</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>There shall be a commission, to be known as the Cree-Naskapi Commission, consisting of a maximum of three individuals appointed by the Governor in Council on the recommendation of the Cree Nation Government and the Naskapi band.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>92</Label><Text>Section 159 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Eligibility</MarginalNote><Label>159</Label><Text>A council member, officer, employee or agent of a Cree First Nation or the Naskapi band is not eligible to be appointed or to continue to serve as a member of the Commission.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>93</Label><Text>Subsection 160(5) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Temporary substitute member</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Where a member is absent or incapacitated, the Governor in Council may, on the recommendation of the Cree Nation Government and the Naskapi band, appoint a temporary substitute member on such terms as are fixed by the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>94</Label><Text>Section 161 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Head office</MarginalNote><Label>161</Label><Text>The head office of the Commission shall be in the City of Val d’Or, Quebec or at such other place as the Governor in Council, on the recommendation of the Cree Nation Government and the Naskapi band, may designate.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>95</Label><Text>Section 164 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Commission may delegate its powers</MarginalNote><Label>164</Label><Text>The Commission may, by unanimous decision of its members, delegate its powers or duties, except the power referred to in subsection 163(3), to one or more of its members.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>96</Label><Text>Subsection 165(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Duties of Commission</MarginalNote><Label>165</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsections (2) and (3), the Commission shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>with respect to Naskapi beneficiaries, investigate any representation submitted to it relating to the implementation of this Act, including representations relating to the exercise or non-exercise of a power under this Act and the performance or non-performance of a duty under this Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>with respect to <DefinitionRef>Cree beneficiaries</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, investigate any representation submitted to it relating to the implementation of the <DefinitionRef>Agreement</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of that Act and the <DefinitionRef>Cree Constitution</DefinitionRef>, as defined in that subsection, including representations relating to the exercise or non-exercise of a power and the performance or non-performance of a duty under that Agreement or the Cree Constitution.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>97</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 166(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Naskapi band or each Cree First Nation referred to in the representation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 24</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 166(1)(d) and (e) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case of a representation referred to in paragraph 165(1)(a), the Minister; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the Cree Nation Government, if it is referred to in the representation.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 166(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Identity of person who made representation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where a person making a representation to the Commission under this Part so requests, the Commission shall not identify that person in any proceeding under this Part or in any report under section 170.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>98</Label><Text>Section 171 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>99</Label><Text>Section 173 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Application of Part</MarginalNote><Label>173</Label><Text>This Part applies only in respect of the succession of a Naskapi beneficiary who dies after the coming into force of this Part and who, at the time of his or her death, was domiciled on Category IA-N land.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 12, ss. 90(1) and (2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>100</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>consorts</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>family council</DefinedTermEn> in section 174 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>consorts</DefinedTermEn> means two persons</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>who are married and whose marriage was solemnized in accordance with, or is recognized under, the laws of the Province,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>who are cohabiting in a conjugal relationship, taking into account Naskapi custom, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>who are cohabiting in a conjugal relationship, having so cohabited for a period of at least one year; (<DefinedTermFr>conjoints</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>family council</DefinedTermEn> means the family council of a deceased Naskapi beneficiary, composed in accordance with section 182; (<DefinedTermFr>conseil de famille</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph (b) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>child</DefinedTermEn> in section 174 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>was done in accordance with Naskapi custom; (<DefinedTermFr>enfant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>101</Label><Text>Section 175 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Lawful heirs on intestate succession</MarginalNote><Label>175</Label><Text>For purposes of intestate succession, a surviving consort and a surviving child are included in the class of lawful heirs of a deceased Naskapi beneficiary.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>102</Label><Text>Subsection 176(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Wills accepted by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may accept as a will any written instrument signed by a Naskapi beneficiary, or bearing his or her mark, in which he or she indicates his or her wishes or intention with respect to the disposition of his or her property on his or her death.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>103</Label><Text>Subsection 178(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Representation of minor heirs</MarginalNote><Label>178</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a Naskapi beneficiary who is a minor under the laws of the Province and ordinarily resident on Category IA-N land, inherits movable or immovable property by virtue of a testamentary or an intestate succession, the parents of that beneficiary are the legal guardians of that property.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>104</Label><Text>Sections 179 and 180 of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Vacant succession</MarginalNote><Label>179</Label><Text>Where a Naskapi beneficiary dies leaving no lawful heirs or where all the heirs renounce the succession, the deceased’s movable and immovable property become the property of the band, unless the band renounces such succession, in which case it shall be dealt with as a vacant succession.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Intestacy</MarginalNote><Label>180</Label><Text>On an intestacy of a Naskapi beneficiary, a majority of the lawful heirs may appoint the band to administer or provide for the administration of the succession (except as regards traditional property), in which case the band may charge a fee for its services.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>105</Label><Text>Subsection 181(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Disposition of traditional property on intestacy</MarginalNote><Label>181</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where a Naskapi beneficiary dies intestate leaving traditional property, the family council of the deceased shall meet within one year of his or her death to decide on the disposition of his or her traditional property.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>106</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 182(1) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Composition of family council</MarginalNote><Label>182</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The family council of a deceased Naskapi beneficiary shall consist of the following person or persons:</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 182(2) of the English version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Where no survivors in immediate family</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where a deceased Naskapi beneficiary leaves no survivors described in subsection (1), the family council of the deceased shall consist of the three closest surviving relatives of the age of majority, as determined in accordance with the law of the Province, who are ordinarily resident in the <DefinitionRef>Territory</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">James Bay and Northern Quebec Native Claims Settlement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>107</Label><Text>Section 183 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Where family council deadlocked</MarginalNote><Label>183</Label><Text>Where the family council is unable to reach a decision on the disposition of any part of the deceased’s traditional property, it may request the council of the band to appoint one or more willing persons to act as the deceased’s family council in respect of that part of the deceased’s traditional property on whose disposition the family council had been unable to reach a decision.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>108</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 184(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Circumstances in which band council acts as the family council</MarginalNote><Label>184</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Where the family council has not reached a decision on the disposition of any part of the deceased’s traditional property within two years after the deceased’s death, the council of the band shall act as the deceased’s family council in respect of that part of the deceased’s traditional property on whose disposition the family council had not reached a decision.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 184(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where, on the death of a Naskapi beneficiary,</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 184(2) of the English version of the Act after paragraph (c) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>the council of the band shall act as the deceased’s family council.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>109</Label><Text>Sections 185 and 186 of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Effect of disposition</MarginalNote><Label>185</Label><Text>A disposition of any traditional property of a deceased Naskapi beneficiary by the deceased’s family council pursuant to this Part passes the property in question to the recipient as of the moment when the recipient takes possession of the property, and any debt in respect of that property thenceforth becomes the responsibility of the recipient.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Where a recipient renounces traditional property</MarginalNote><Label>186</Label><Text>Where any person designated by the family council of a deceased Naskapi beneficiary to receive the deceased’s traditional property pursuant to this Part renounces the property in question before taking possession of it, and no other person is designated by the family council within six months of such renunciation, the disposition of that property shall thenceforth be governed by the laws of the Province relating to intestate succession.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>110</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 187(1)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>in subsection (2), a Naskapi beneficiary who is an <DefinitionRef>Indian</DefinitionRef> as defined in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Indian Act</XRefExternal>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 187(2) of the French version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Pour l’application de la présente partie, sont considérés comme situés en permanence sur les terres de catégorie IA-N les biens personnels :</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 90(2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 187(2)(a) to (c) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that became the property of the band by virtue of section 15, as it read on July 3, 1984, and had been purchased by Canada with money appropriated by Parliament,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is purchased by Canada after the coming into force of this Part with money appropriated by Parliament for the use and benefit of Indians or the band, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that is given, after the coming into force of this Part, to Indians or to the band under a treaty or agreement between the band and Canada</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 187(2) of the English version of the Act after paragraph (c) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>shall be deemed always to be situated on Category IA-N land.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>111</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 188(1)(a) and (b) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the interest of an Indian or the band in Category IA-N land; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the personal property of an Indian or the band situated on Category IA-N land.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 188(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>neither an Indian nor the band is subject to taxation in respect of the ownership, occupation, possession or use of any property described in paragraph (1)(a) or (b) or is otherwise subject to taxation in respect of any such property; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 26</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>112</Label><Text>Section 190 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Property exempt from seizure, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>190</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to this Part, movable and immovable property situated on Category IA-N land and belonging to a Naskapi beneficiary or an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA-N land, and any right or interest of such a person in Category IA-N land, is not subject to privilege, hypothec or any other charge, or to attachment, levy, seizure or execution, in favour of or at the instance of any person other than a Naskapi beneficiary, the band or an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA-N land.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Property exempt from seizure, etc.</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subject to this Part, movable and immovable property situated on Category IA-N land and belonging to the band is not subject to privilege, hypothec or any other charge, or to attachment, levy, seizure or execution, in favour of or at the instance of any person other than a Naskapi beneficiary, the band or an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA-N land.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The right or interest of the band in its Category IA-N land is not subject to privilege, hypothec or any other charge, or to attachment, levy, seizure or execution, in favour of or at the instance of any person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Idem</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>A right or interest in Category IA-N land of a person other than a Naskapi beneficiary or the band, or the immovable property of such person situated on Category IA-N land, is not subject to attachment, levy, seizure or execution in favour of or at the instance of any person other than a Naskapi beneficiary or the band, except where the band has authorized that person to pledge, charge or hypothecate that right or interest or immovable property, in which case creditors may exercise their normal remedies in relation to that pledge, charge or hypothecation.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Conditional sales</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>A person who sells movable property to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Naskapi beneficiary,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA-N land, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the band</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>under an agreement whereby the right of property or right of possession thereto remains wholly or in part in the seller may exercise his or her rights under that agreement notwithstanding that the movable property is situated on Category IA-N land.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 27</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>113</Label><Text>Section 191 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Property deemed situated on Category IA-N land</MarginalNote><Label>191</Label><Text>For the purposes of section 190, movable property</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that became the property of the band by virtue of section 15, as it read on July 3, 1984, and had been purchased with money appropriated by Parliament,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>that is purchased after the coming into force of this Part with money appropriated by Parliament or by the legislature of Quebec for the use and benefit of Indians, Naskapi beneficiaries, or the band, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>that is, after the coming into force of this Part, provided to Naskapi beneficiaries or the band under a treaty or agreement between the band and Canada</Text></Paragraph><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>shall be deemed always to be situated on Category IA-N land.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>114</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 192(1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 192(2) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Property deemed to be property of the Naskapi band</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Where the band has the authority to delegate the power to coordinate and administer a program to the Naskapi Development Corporation and has so delegated, movable property that</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 192(2)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>was purchased with money appropriated by Parliament or by the legislature of Quebec for the use and benefit of Indians, Naskapi beneficiaries or the band</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 192(2) of the English version of the Act after paragraph (c) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>shall, for the purposes of section 190, be deemed always to be the property of the band.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>115</Label><Text>Subsection 193(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Waiver of exemption</MarginalNote><Label>193</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A Naskapi beneficiary or an Indian ordinarily resident on Category IA-N land may, in writing, waive the exemption conferred by subsection 190(1) in favour of any person, on such terms and conditions as are agreed to by the parties, but, in the case of a right or interest in Category IA-N land, the consent of the band must be obtained to the waiver and the terms and conditions thereof, and the band’s consent must be confirmed by the electors of the band at a special band meeting or referendum.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 28</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>116</Label><Text>Section 194 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>117</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 196(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements for policing services</MarginalNote><Label>196</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The band may, with the approval of the Attorney General of Quebec and the provincial Minister responsible for municipal affairs, enter into an agreement with</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 196(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Cree Nation Government,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 196(1) of the Act is amended by adding “or” after paragraph (c) and by repealing paragraph 196(1)(d).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 196(1) of the English version of the Act after paragraph (e) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><ContinuedSectionSubsection><Text>for the provision of policing services on its Category IA-N land.</Text></ContinuedSectionSubsection></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 29</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 196(1.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 30</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>118</Label><Text>Section 197 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Offences under Act</MarginalNote><Label>197</Label><Text>Every person who commits an offence under subsection 38(6), section 44, subsection 91(2), section 95, subsection 100(4) or section 108 is liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding $2,000 or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or to both.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 12, s. 31</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>119</Label><Text>Subsection 199(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>By-law may fix maximum punishment</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A by-law made under this Act may stipulate a maximum fine or a maximum term of imprisonment, or both, for contravention of the by-law, but the maximum fine or maximum term of imprisonment may not exceed $5,000 or six months, respectively.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>120</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 199:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Alternative procedure — ticketing scheme</MarginalNote><Label>199.1</Label><Text>In addition to the summary conviction procedures of Part XXVII of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>, a proceeding in respect of a contravention indicated in the by-laws made under section 48.1 of this Act may be commenced in accordance with the ticketing scheme established by those by-laws.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>121</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 200(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Jurisdiction of justices of the peace</MarginalNote><Label>200</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In addition to the courts and persons having jurisdiction in respect of the offences listed in paragraphs (a) and (b), justices of the peace appointed pursuant to section 12.4.1 of the Northeastern Quebec Agreement have jurisdiction in respect of</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 200(1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>offences under the following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>: section 266 (assault), section 445 (injuring or endangering animals) and section 445.1 (cruelty to animals).</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 200(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Summary conviction court</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purpose of exercising their jurisdiction in respect of offences listed in paragraphs (1)(a) and (b), the justices of the peace referred to in subsection (1) are a summary conviction court within the meaning of Part XXVII of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Terminology</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “a band” with “the band”</MarginalNote><Label>122</Label><Text>The English version of the Act is amended by replacing “a band” with “the band” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the definitions <DefinedTermEn>councillor</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>referendum</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>section 9;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 22(2) before paragraph (a) and subsection (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>subsection 23(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>sections 25 and 26;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>section 39;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 40(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 41(1) before paragraph (a) and subsection (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 44(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 45(2) before paragraph (a), the portion of subsection (4) before paragraph (a) and subsection (6);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 47(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 48(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 50(2) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>subsection 51(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>subsection 52(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(p)</Label><Text>section 54;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(q)</Label><Text>subsection 55(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(r)</Label><Text>section 64;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(s)</Label><Text>subsections 74(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(t)</Label><Text>subsection 75(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(u)</Label><Text>subsection 76(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(v)</Label><Text>subsections 77(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(w)</Label><Text>subsections 82(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(x)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 83(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(y)</Label><Text>section 84;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z)</Label><Text>subsections 86(1), (2) and (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.1)</Label><Text>subsection 89(1) and the portion of subsection (2) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.2)</Label><Text>subsection 90(1), the portion of subsection (2) before paragraph (a) and subsections (3) to (6);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.3)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 91(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.4)</Label><Text>the portion of section 92 before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.5)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 93(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.6)</Label><Text>subsections 94(3) and (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.7)</Label><Text>subsection 96(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.8)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 97(1) before paragraph (a) and subsection (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.9)</Label><Text>subsection 100(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.10)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 113(4) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.11)</Label><Text>subsections 122(1) to (4);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.12)</Label><Text>paragraphs 124(1)(a) and (b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.13)</Label><Text>the portion of subection 132(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.14)</Label><Text>subsections 136(5) and (7) to (9);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.15)</Label><Text>subsections 137(1) and (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.16)</Label><Text>subsection 139(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.17)</Label><Text>subsection 142(1);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.18)</Label><Text>the portion of section 146 before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.19)</Label><Text>section 149;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.20)</Label><Text>paragraphs 150(1)(a) and (b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.21)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 152(1) before paragraph (a) and subsection (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.22)</Label><Text>sections 154 and 155;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.23)</Label><Text>subparagraph 156(c)(i);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.24)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 188(1) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.25)</Label><Text>subsection 193(3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.26)</Label><Text>subsection 202(1); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(z.27)</Label><Text>subsections 203(1) and (2).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “IA or IA-N” with “IA-N”</MarginalNote><Label>123</Label><Text>The Act is amended by replacing “IA or IA-N” with “IA-N” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>subparagraph 22(2)(a)(i);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>subparagraph 45(1)(h)(i);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>paragraph 47(1)(a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>section 101;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>paragraph 108(1)(b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the heading of Part VII;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>subsection 121(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>subparagraphs 129(c)(i) and (d)(i);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 130(2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(j)</Label><Text>section 131;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(k)</Label><Text>paragraphs 132(1)(a) and (b);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(l)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 135(2) before paragraph (a);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(m)</Label><Text>section 140;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(n)</Label><Text>subsections 145(1) to (3);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(o)</Label><Text>section 148;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(p)</Label><Text>the portion of subsection 150(1) before paragraph (a) and subsection (2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(q)</Label><Text>paragraphs 151(f) and (h);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(r)</Label><Text>paragraph 177(a); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(s)</Label><Text>subsection 196(2).</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><TitleText>Transitional Provisions, Related and Consequential Amendments and Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Cree-Naskapi Commission’s report to Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>124</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Cree-Naskapi Commission may prepare and submit to the Minister of Indian Affairs and Northern Development a last report in English, French, Cree and Naskapi, for the period beginning on the day that follows the end of the period for which the 2016 Report of the Cree-Naskapi Commission was completed and ending on the day on which section <XRefInternal>98</XRefInternal> comes into force, on the implementation of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</XRefExternal>, and the Minister shall cause the report to be laid before each House of Parliament on any of the first 10 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the Minister receives it.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Circulation of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>As soon as feasable after the report is laid before each House of Parliament, the Minister shall send a copy of the report to the Cree Nation Government, the Naskapi Development Corporation, the council of each Cree First Nation and the council of the Naskapi band.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this section.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cree First Nation</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>première nation crie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cree-Naskapi Commission</DefinedTermEn> means the Commission established by section 158 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Commission crie-naskapie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Cree Nation Government</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Gouvernement de la nation crie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Naskapi band</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>bande naskapie</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Naskapi Development Corporation</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>. (<DefinedTermFr>Société de développement des Naskapis</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 12</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Related Amendment to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Modernization of Benefits and Obligations Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>125</Label><Text>Sections 89 and 90 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Modernization of Benefits and Obligations Act</XRefExternal> are repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Consequential Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S.C., c. 1970, c. V-4</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Veterans’ Land Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>126</Label><Text>Subsection 46(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Veterans’ Land Act</XRefExternal> is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (a) and by replacing paragraph (b) with the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA-N land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>127</Label><Text>Subsection 13(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Access to Information Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (f):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f.1)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>Cree Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal> or a <DefinitionRef>Cree First Nation</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. E-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>128</Label><Text>Subsection 4(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No interest in land that is <DefinitionRef>Category IA-N land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>, may be expropriated under this Part without the consent of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>No interest in land that is <DefinitionRef>Category IA land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>, may be expropriated under this Part without the consent of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-6</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Lands Surveys Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>129</Label><Text>Subparagraph 24(1)(a)(ii) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Lands Surveys Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA-N land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii.1)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. M-13; 2000, c. 8, s. 2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>130</Label><Text>Paragraph (c) of the definition <DefinedTermEn>taxing authority</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Payments in Lieu of Taxes Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>band,</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>, if it levies and collects a tax on interests in <DefinitionRef>Category IA-N land</DefinitionRef> as defined in that subsection,</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>any <DefinitionRef>Cree First Nation</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal> that levies and collects a tax on interests in <DefinitionRef>Category IA land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in that subsection,</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. N-7</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Energy Board Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>131</Label><Text>Paragraph 78(3)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">National Energy Board Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA-N land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. P-21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>132</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 8(6)(b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Privacy Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the band, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 8(7) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (f):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f.1)</Label><Text>the <DefinitionRef>Cree Nation Government</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal> or a <DefinitionRef>Cree First Nation</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of that Act;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="3"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2008, c. 22</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>133</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The reference to</Text><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Cree-Naskapi (of Quebec) Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les Cris et les Naskapis du Québec</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup><ContinuedSectionSubsection type="amending"><Text>in Part 1 of the schedule to the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Specific Claims Tribunal Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur les Naskapis et la Commission crie-naskapie</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></ContinuedSectionSubsection></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Part 1 of the schedule to the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><BilingualGroup><BilingualItemEn>Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</BilingualItemEn><BilingualItemFr>Loi sur l’accord concernant la gouvernance de la nation crie d’Eeyou Istchee</BilingualItemFr></BilingualGroup></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2009, c. 23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>134</Label><Text>On the first day on which both subsection <XRefInternal>19</XRefInternal>(2) of this Act is in force and section 352 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Not-for-profit Corporations Act</XRefExternal> has produced its effects, subsection 23(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Not-for-profit Corporations Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Not-for-profit Corporations Act</XRefExternal> does not apply to the band.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill — Impact Assessment, Canadian Energy Regulator and Navigation Protection</MarginalNote><Label>135</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections (2) to (4) apply if a Bill entitled <XRefExternal reference-type="act">An Act to enact the Impact Assessment Act and the Canadian Energy Regulator Act, to amend the Navigation Protection Act and to make consequential amendments to other Acts</XRefExternal> (in this section referred to as the “other Act”) is introduced in the 1st session of the 42nd Parliament and receives royal assent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 10 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>131</XRefInternal> of this Act, then</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that section <XRefInternal>131</XRefInternal> is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraph 317(3)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA-N land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>131</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 10 of the other Act, then, on the day on which that section 10 comes into force, paragraph 317(3)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA-N land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>131</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force on the same day as section 10 of the other Act, then</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>that section <XRefInternal>131</XRefInternal> is deemed never to have come into force and is repealed; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>paragraph 317(3)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Energy Regulator Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA-N land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Naskapi and the Cree-Naskapi Commission Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text><DefinitionRef>Category IA land</DefinitionRef>, as defined in subsection 2(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cree Nation of Eeyou Istchee Governance Agreement Act</XRefExternal>; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>