<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-65</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (harassment and violence), the Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act and the Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (harassment and violence), the Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act and the Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</ShortTitle><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Canada Labour Code (harassment and violence), the Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act and the Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>10</MM><DD>25</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>22</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2018</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2017-11-6">90860</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 1 of this enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to strengthen the existing framework for the prevention of harassment and violence, including sexual harassment and sexual violence, in the work place.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 2 amends Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal> with respect to the application of Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to parliamentary employers and employees, without limiting in any way the powers, privileges and immunities of the Senate and the House of Commons and their members.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Part 3 amends a transitional provision in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 1</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>0.1</Label><Text>Subsection 122(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>harassment and violence</DefinedTermEn> means any action, conduct or comment, including of a sexual nature, that can reasonably be expected to cause offence, humiliation or other physical or psychological injury or illness to an employee, including any prescribed action, conduct or comment; (<DefinedTermFr>harcèlement et violence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 9 (1st Supp.), s. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 122.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Prevention of accidents, injuries and illnesses</MarginalNote><Label>122.1</Label><Text>The purpose of this Part is to prevent accidents, occurrences of harassment and violence and physical or psychological injuries and illnesses arising out of, linked with or occurring in the course of employment to which this Part applies.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 123 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Persons appointed and their employer</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>This Part applies to persons appointed under subsection 128(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Employment Act</XRefExternal>, other than persons appointed by a person holding the recognized position of Leader of the Opposition in the Senate or Leader of the Opposition in the House of Commons, and to their employer.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.1</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 123:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>123.1</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in this Part shall be construed so as to abrogate or derogate from the rights provided for under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 20, s. 5; 2013, c. 40, ss. 177(1) and (2)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraphs 125(1)(c) to (e) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>except as provided for in the regulations, investigate, record and report, in accordance with the regulations, all accidents, occurrences of harassment and violence, occupational illnesses and other hazardous occurrences known to the employer;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>make readily available to employees, in printed and electronic form,</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>a copy of this Part and a copy of the regulations made under this Part that apply to the work place,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a statement of the employer’s general policy concerning the health and safety at work of employees, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>any other information related to health and safety that is prescribed or that may be specified by the Minister;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 20, s. 5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 125(1)(f) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>if the information referred to in any of subparagraphs (d)(i) to (iii) is made available in electronic form, ensure that employees receive appropriate training to enable them to have access to the information and, on the request of an employee, make a printed copy of the information available;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 20, s. 5</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Paragraph 125(1)(z.16) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(z.16)</Label><Text>take the prescribed measures to prevent and protect against harassment and violence in the work place, respond to occurrences of harassment and violence in the work place and offer support to employees affected by harassment and violence in the work place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.161)</Label><Text>ensure that employees, including those who have supervisory or managerial responsibilities, receive training in the prevention of harassment and violence in the work place and are informed of their rights and obligations under this Part in relation to harassment and violence;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.162)</Label><Text>undergo training in the prevention of harassment and violence in the work place;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(z.163)</Label><Text>ensure that the person designated by the employer to receive complaints relating to occurrences of harassment and violence has knowledge, training and experience in issues relating to harassment and violence and has knowledge of relevant legislation;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 125 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the investigations, records and reports referred to in paragraph (1)(c).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Former emloyees</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Except as provided for in the regulations, the obligations set out in paragraphs (1)(c) and (z.16) apply to an employer in respect of a former employee in relation to an occurrence of harassment and violence in the work place if the occurrence becomes known to the employer within three months after the day on which the former employee ceases to be employed by the employer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>On application by a former employee, the Minister may, in the prescribed circumstances, extend the time period referred to in subsection (4).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations — former employees</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>For the purpose of subsection (4), the Governor in Council may make regulations respecting an employer’s obligations in respect of former employees.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 20, s. 8</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph 126(1)(h) of the French version of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no" xml:lang="fr"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>h)</Label><Text>de signaler, selon les modalités réglementaires, tout accident ou autre incident ayant causé, dans le cadre de son travail, une blessure à lui-même ou à une autre personne;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 20, s. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 127.1(1) and (2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Complaint to supervisor</MarginalNote><Label>127.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>An employee who believes on reasonable grounds that there has been a contravention of this Part or that there is likely to be an accident, injury or illness arising out of, linked with or occurring in the course of employment shall, before exercising any other recourse available under this Part, except the rights conferred by sections 128, 129 and 132, make a complaint to the employee’s supervisor.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Supervisor or designated person</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>However, in the case of a complaint relating to an occurrence of harassment and violence, the employee may make the complaint to the employee’s supervisor or to the person designated in the employer’s work place harassment and violence prevention policy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Oral or written complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>The complaint may be made orally or in writing.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Resolve complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The employee and the supervisor or designated person, as the case may be, shall try to resolve the complaint between themselves as soon as possible.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 20, s. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 127.1(3) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Investigation of complaint</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The employee or the supervisor may refer an unresolved complaint, other than a complaint relating to an occurrence of harassment and violence, to a chairperson of the work place committee or to the health and safety representative to be investigated jointly</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 127.1(8) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (b), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>in the case of a complaint relating to an occurrence of harassment and violence, the employee and the supervisor or designated person, as the case may be, failed to resolve the complaint between themselves.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 40, s. 180(3)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 127.1(9) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Investigation</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The Minister shall investigate the complaint referred to in subsection (8) unless it relates to an occurrence of harassment and violence and the Minister is of the opinion that</Text><Paragraph><Label>a)</Label><Text>the complaint has been adequately dealt with according to a procedure provided for under this Act, any other Act of Parliament or a collective agreement; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the matter is otherwise an abuse of process.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice</MarginalNote><Label>(9.1)</Label><Text>If the Minister is of the opinion that the conditions described in paragraph (9)(a) or (b) are met, the Minister shall inform the employer and the employee in writing, as soon as feasible, that the Minister will not investigate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Combining investigations — harassment and violence</MarginalNote><Label>(9.2)</Label><Text>The Minister may combine an investigation into a complaint relating to an occurrence of harassment and violence with an ongoing investigation relating to the same employer and involving substantially the same issues and, in that case, the Minister may issue a single decision.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Section 127.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (11):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Former employees</MarginalNote><Label>(12)</Label><Text>A former employee may, within the prescribed time, make a complaint under subsection (1) relating to an occurrence of harassment and violence in the work place, in which case this Part applies to the former employee and to the employer as if the former employee were an employee, to the extent necessary to finally dispose of the complaint.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Extension</MarginalNote><Label>(13)</Label><Text>On application by a former employee, the Minister may, in the prescribed circumstances, extend the time period referred to in subsection (12).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 134.1 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (4):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Investigation — harassment and violence</MarginalNote><Label>(4.1)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (4)(d), a policy committee shall not participate in an investigation, other than an investigation under section 128 or 129, relating to an occurrence of harassment and violence in the work place.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 20, s. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsections 135(3) to (5) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 40, s. 185(1)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 135(6)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>at an employer’s request, the Minister may, in writing, exempt the employer from the requirements of subsection (1) in respect of that work place;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 135 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (6):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Posting of request</MarginalNote><Label>(6.1)</Label><Text>A request for an exemption must be posted in a conspicuous place or places where it is likely to come to the attention of employees, and be kept posted until the employees are informed of the Minister’s decision in respect of the request.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Section 135 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (7):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Investigation — harassment and violence</MarginalNote><Label>(7.1)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (7)(e), a work place committee shall not participate in an investigation, other than an investigation under section 128 or 129, relating to an occurrence of harassment and violence in the work place.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 135.1:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Information likely to reveal identity</MarginalNote><Label>135.11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Neither the Minister nor an employer shall, without the person’s consent, provide, under this Part, a policy committee or a work place committee with any information that is likely to reveal the identity of a person who was involved in an occurrence of harassment and violence in the work place. Neither a policy committee nor a work place committee shall have access to that information without the person’s consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply with respect to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>information provided under section 128 or 129 or a direction or report relating to the application of those sections; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a decision, reasons or a direction referred to in subsection 146.1(2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2000, c. 20, s. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Paragraph 135.2(1)(g) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>requiring a committee to submit an annual report of its activities, containing the prescribed information, to a specified person in the prescribed manner and within the prescribed time; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>Section 136 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (5):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Investigation — harassment and violence</MarginalNote><Label>(5.1)</Label><Text>Despite paragraph (5)(g), a health and safety representative shall not participate in an investigation, other than an investigation under section 128 or 129, relating to an occurrence of harassment and violence in the work place.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 136:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Information likely to reveal identity</MarginalNote><Label>136.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Neither the Minister nor an employer shall, without the person’s consent, provide, under this Part, a health and safety representative with any information that is likely to reveal the identity of a person who was involved in an occurrence of harassment and violence in the work place. A health and safety representative shall not have access to that information without the person’s consent.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection (1) does not apply with respect to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>information provided under section 128 or 129 or a direction or report relating to the application of those sections; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a decision, reasons or a direction referred to in subsection 146.1(2).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.1</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 139:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>139.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister shall prepare and publish an annual report that contains statistical data relating to harassment and violence in work places to which this Part applies. The report shall not contain any information that is likely to reveal the identity of a person who was involved in an occurrence of harassment and violence.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Statistical data</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The statistical data contained in the report shall include information that is categorized according to prohibited grounds of discrimination under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Five-year review</MarginalNote><Label>139.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Five years after the day on which this section comes into force and every five years after that, the Minister shall commence a review of the provisions of this Part relating to harassment and violence. At the conclusion of the review, the Minister shall prepare a report on the review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to be tabled</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the report is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 40, s. 190</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>12</Label><Text>Subsection 140(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The powers, duties or functions of the Minister provided for in section 130, subsections 137.1(1) to (2.1) and (7) to (9), 137.2(4), 138(1) to (2) and (4) to (6), 140(1), (2) and (4), 144(1) and 149(1), sections 152 and 155 and subsections 156.1(1), 157(3) and 159(2) shall not be the subject of an agreement under subsection (2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 40, s. 196</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>13</Label><Text>Subsection 145.1(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Status</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 146 to 146.5, an appeals officer has all of the powers, duties and functions of the Minister under this Part, except for those referred to in subsection (1), section 130, subsections 137.1(1) to (2.1) and (7) to (9), 137.2(4), 138(1) to (2) and (4) to (6), 140(1), (2) and (4), 144(1) and 149(1), sections 152 and 155 and subsections 156.1(1), 157(3) and 159(2).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Subsection 157(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (a):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a.01)</Label><Text>defining the expressions “harassment” and “violence” for the purposes of this Part;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 160:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Pilot projects</MarginalNote><Label>161</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Part, the Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary respecting the establishment and operation of one or more pilot projects for testing which possible amendments to this Part or the regulations made under this Part would improve the prevention of accidents, injuries and illnesses arising out of, linked with or occurring in the course of employment to which this Part applies, including regulations respecting the manner in which and the extent to which any provision of this Part or the regulations made under this Part applies to a pilot project, and adapting any such provision for the purposes of that application.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Repeal of regulations</MarginalNote><Label>162</Label><Text>Unless they are repealed earlier, regulations made under section 161 are repealed on the fifth anniversary of the day on which they come into force.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 9 (1st Supp.), s. 17</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>16</Label><Text>Division XV.1 of Part III of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 295:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Pilot Projects</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>296</Label><Text>Despite anything in this Part, the Governor in Council may make any regulations that the Governor in Council considers necessary respecting the establishment and operation of one or more pilot projects for testing which possible amendments to this Part or the regulations made under this Part would improve compliance with Parts II and III of this Act, including regulations respecting the manner in which and the extent to which any provision of this Part or the regulations made under this Part applies to a pilot project, and adapting any such provision for the purposes of that application.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Repeal of regulations</MarginalNote><Label>297</Label><Text>Unless they are repealed earlier, regulations made under section 296 are repealed on the fifth anniversary of the day on which they come into force.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Transitional Provision</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Requests received before coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>18</Label><Text>A request for an exemption under subsection 135(3) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, as it read on the day before the day on which section <XRefInternal>7</XRefInternal> comes into force, that is received by the Minister before the day on which that section comes into force is to be dealt with in accordance with subsections 135(3) to (5) of that Act as they read on the day before the day on which that section comes into force. If the request is approved on or after the day on which that section comes into force, the exemption may be granted for a period of not more than one year.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendments</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>19</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>other Act</DefinedTermEn> means the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If section 347 of the other Act comes into force before section <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Section 145.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions</MarginalNote><Label>145.1</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 146 to 146.5, the Board has all of the powers, duties and functions of the Minister under this Part, except for those referred to in section 130, subsections 135(6), 137.1(1) to (2.1) and (7) to (9), 137.2(4), 138(1) to (2) and (4) to (6), section 139, subsections 140(1), (2) and (4) and 144(1), section 146.01, subsection 149(1), sections 152 and 155 and subsections 156.1(1), 157(3) and 159(2).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If section <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal> of this Act comes into force before section 347 of the other Act, then, on the day on which that section 347 comes into force, section 145.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Powers, duties and functions</MarginalNote><Label>145.1</Label><Text>For the purposes of sections 146 to 146.5, the Board has all of the powers, duties and functions of the Minister under this Part, except for those referred to in section 130, subsections 135(6), 137.1(1) to (2.1) and (7) to (9), 137.2(4), 138(1) to (2) and (4) to (6), section 139, subsections 140(1), (2) and (4) and 144(1), section 146.01, subsection 149(1), sections 152 and 155 and subsections 156.1(1), 157(3) and 159(2).</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>If section 347 of the other Act comes into force on the same day as section <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal> of this Act, then that section <XRefInternal>13</XRefInternal> is deemed to have come into force before that section 347 and subsection (3) applies as a consequence.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>20</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Sections 0.1 to 16 and 18 come into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Order in council</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>17</XRefInternal> comes into force on a day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council but that day must not be earlier than the day on which section 377 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</XRefExternal> comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 2</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. 33 (2nd Supp.)</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>21</Label><Text>Part III of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliamentary Employment and Staff Relations Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><Label>PART III</Label><TitleText>Occupational Health and Safety</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>87</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Part.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Board</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in section 3. (<DefinedTermFr>Commission</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>employee</DefinedTermEn> means a person employed by an employer and includes the person occupying the recognized position of Clerk of the Senate, Clerk of the House of Commons, Gentleman Usher of the Black Rod, Sergeant-at-Arms or Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel of the House of Commons. (<DefinedTermFr>employé</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>employer</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Senate as represented by any committee or person that the Senate by its rules or orders designates for the purposes of this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the House of Commons as represented by any committee or person that the House of Commons by its orders designates for the purposes of this Part;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the Library of Parliament as represented by the Parliamentary Librarian acting, subject to subsection 74(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal>, on behalf of both Houses of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the office of the Senate Ethics Officer as represented by the Senate Ethics Officer;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the office of the Conflict of Interest and Ethics Commissioner as represented by the Conflict of Interest and Ethics Commissioner;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the Parliamentary Protective Service as represented by the Director of the Parliamentary Protective Service on behalf of the Speakers of the two Houses of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>the office of the Parliamentary Budget Officer as represented by the Parliamentary Budget Officer;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a member of the House of Commons who employs one or more persons or who has the direction or control of staff employed to provide research or associated services to the caucus members of a political party represented in the House of Commons;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of a person occupying the recognized position of Clerk of the Senate, Clerk of the House of Commons, Gentleman Usher of the Black Rod, Sergeant-at-Arms or Law Clerk and Parliamentary Counsel of the House of Commons, the Senate or the House of Commons, as the case may be, as represented by the committee or person described in paragraph (a) or (b); or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>any other person who is recognized as an employer in regulations made under subsection 19.5(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Parliament of Canada Act</XRefExternal> or by-laws made under section 52.5 of that Act. (<DefinedTermFr>employeur</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meaning of <DefinitionRef>employer</DefinitionRef></MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>employer</DefinitionRef> in subsection (1) includes any person who acts on behalf of an employer.</Text></Subsection></Section><?Pub Caret?><Heading level="2"><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> (Part II)</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Application</MarginalNote><Label>88</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, other than subsections 134(2) and (3) and sections 152 and 153, applies to and in respect of an employer and employees, in the same manner and to the same extent as if the employer were a federal work, undertaking or business and the employees were employees to and in respect of which that Part applies except that, for the purpose of that application,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>any reference in that Part to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>“arbitration” is to be read as a reference to adjudication within the meaning of Part I of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>“Board” and “collective agreement” are to be read as references to those expressions as defined in section 3 of this Act,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>“employee” and “employer” are to be read as references to those expressions as defined in subsection 87(1) of this Act, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>“trade union” is to be read as a reference to an <DefinitionRef>employee organization</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 3 of this Act;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>Part I of this Act applies, with any modifications that the circumstances require, in respect of matters brought before the Board under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to the extent necessary to give effect to that purpose; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>matters brought before the Board under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> may be heard and determined only by a <DefinitionRef>member</DefinitionRef> as defined in section 3 of this Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Application to other persons</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This Part also applies to any person who is not an employee but who performs for an employer activities whose primary purpose is to enable the person to acquire knowledge or experience, and to the employer, as if that person were an employee of the employer.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, subject to section 2, nothing in this Part shall be construed so as to abrogate or derogate from the rights provided for under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canadian Human Rights Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Deputy Minister of Labour</MarginalNote><Label>88.01</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Part, the Deputy Minister of Labour shall exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions of the Minister of Labour under this Part and under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> involving a member of the Senate or their staff or a member of the House of Commons or their employees.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of directions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Deputy Minister of Labour exercises the powers or performs the duties and functions set out in section 88.3 or paragraph 88.4(b), he or she shall provide the direction referred to in that section or that paragraph to the Speaker of the Senate or the Speaker of the House of Commons, or both, who shall each table the direction in the House over which he or she presides.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Minister to notify Speakers</MarginalNote><Label>88.1</Label><Text>The Minister of Labour shall notify the Speaker of the Senate or the Speaker of the House of Commons, or both, of the Minister’s intention to enter, under subsection 141(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, a work place controlled by an employer. The Minister shall also notify the Speaker of the Senate or the Speaker of the House of Commons, or both, as soon as possible after the Minister</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>commences an investigation under Part II of that Act in relation to an employer or an employee; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>issues a direction to an employer or an employee under that Part.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Board to notify Speakers</MarginalNote><Label>88.2</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board shall notify the Speaker of the Senate or the Speaker of the House of Commons, or both, as soon as possible after</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Board receives a complaint under subsection 133(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> in relation to an employer; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>an appeal of a direction issued to an employer or an employee is brought under subsection 146(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Power of Speakers</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If the Speaker of the Senate or the Speaker of the House of Commons is notified that an appeal has been brought,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Board shall, at the Speaker’s request, provide to the Speaker a copy of any document that is filed with the Board in the appeal and that is necessary to enable the Speaker to present evidence and make representations under paragraph (b); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the Speaker may present evidence and make representations to the Board in the appeal.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Direction of Minister not complied with</MarginalNote><Label>88.3</Label><Text>The Minister of Labour shall cause to be tabled in the Senate or the House of Commons, or both, a direction that is issued to an employer or an employee under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> if the direction is not complied with within the period provided for in the direction and it is not appealed within the period provided for in that Part. The Minister shall cause the direction to be tabled within a reasonable time after the later of the expiry of the period for compliance and the expiry of the appeal period.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exceptional circumstances</MarginalNote><Label>88.4</Label><Text>If the Minister of Labour considers that exceptional circumstances require that immediate action be taken to prevent a contravention of Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> by an employer or an employee,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Minister shall provide a copy of any direction issued to an employer or an employee under that Part to the Speaker of the Senate or the Speaker of the House of Commons, or both; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>despite section 88.3, the Minister may, before the expiry of the appeal period, cause to be tabled a direction referred to in paragraph (a) in the Senate or the House of Commons, or both, if that direction is not complied with within the period provided for in the direction.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Order, decision or direction of Board not complied with</MarginalNote><Label>88.5</Label><Text>The Board shall, at the request of the Minister of Labour or any person affected by an order or decision made or a direction issued with respect to an employer or an employee by the Board under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, cause the order, decision or direction to be tabled in the Senate or the House of Commons, or both, if it is not complied with within the period provided for in the order, decision or direction. The Board shall cause the order, decision or direction to be tabled within a reasonable time after receiving the request.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers, privileges and immunities</MarginalNote><Label>88.6</Label><Text>For greater certainty, nothing in this Part shall be construed as limiting in any way the powers, privileges and immunities of the Senate and the House of Commons and their members or as authorizing the exercise of a power or the performance of a function or duty by virtue of this Part if the exercise of that power or the performance of that function or duty would interfere, directly or indirectly, with the business of the Senate or the House of Commons.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report — Board</MarginalNote><Label>88.7</Label><Text>The Board shall, as soon as possible after the end of each year, submit a report for that year on its activities under this Part and under Part II of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, as it applies to employers and employees, to the Minister designated as the Minister for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Public Sector Labour Relations and Employment Board Act</XRefExternal>. The Minister shall cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the Minister receives it.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Five-year review</MarginalNote><Label>88.8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Five years after the day on which this Part comes into force and every five years after that, the Minister designated as the Minister for the purposes of this Act shall commence a review of the application, in relation to harassment and violence, of the provisions of this Part. At the conclusion of the review, the Minister shall prepare a report on the review.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Report to be tabled</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the day on which the report is completed.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Text>On the day on which section <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal> of this Act and section 394 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</XRefExternal> come into force, that section 394 is deemed to have come into force before that section <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><Label>23</Label><Text>Section <XRefInternal>21</XRefInternal> comes into force on the later of the day on which this Act receives royal assent and the day fixed under subsection 402(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><Label>PART 3</Label><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 20</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>Section 382 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Budget Implementation Act, 2017, No. 1</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Appeals — subsection 129(7) or 146(1)</MarginalNote><Label>382</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, as it read immediately before the day on which this section comes into force, applies with respect to any appeal made before that day under subsection 129(7) or 146(1) of that Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>