<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en"><?Pub Caret?><Identification><BillNumber>C-211</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>42</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>64-65-66-67</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2015-2016-2017-2018</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting a federal framework on post-traumatic stress disorder</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Federal Framework on Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Federal Framework on Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2018</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId><AnnualStatuteNumber>13</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2018</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-01-14">421100</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>This enactment requires the Minister of Health to convene a conference with the Minister of National Defence, the Minister of Veterans Affairs, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, provincial and territorial government representatives responsible for health and representatives of the medical community and patients’ groups for the purpose of developing a comprehensive federal framework to address the challenges of recognizing the symptoms and providing timely diagnosis and treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is a condition that is characterized by persistent emotional distress occurring as a result of physical injury or severe psychological shock and typically involves disturbance of sleep and constant vivid recall of the traumatic experience, with dulled responses to others and to the outside world;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas there is a clear need for persons who have served as first responders, firefighters, military personnel, corrections officers and members of the RCMP to receive direct and timely access to PTSD support;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>Whereas, while not-for-profit organizations and governmental resources to address mental health issues, including PTSD, exist at the federal and provincial levels, there is no coordinated national strategy that would expand the scope of support to ensure long-term solutions;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0"><Text>And whereas many Canadians, in particular persons who have served as first responders, firefighters, military personnel, corrections officers and members of the RCMP, suffer from PTSD and would greatly benefit from the development and implementation of a federal framework on PTSD that provides for best practices, research, education, awareness and treatment;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Framework on Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Agency</DefinedTermEn> means the Public Health Agency of Canada. (<DefinedTermFr>Agence</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>federal framework</DefinedTermEn> means a framework to address the challenges of recognizing the symptoms and providing timely diagnosis and treatment of post-traumatic stress disorder. (<DefinedTermFr>cadre fédéral</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Health. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Federal Framework on Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Conference</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Minister must, no later than 12 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, convene a conference with the Minister of National Defence, the Minister of Veterans Affairs, the Minister of Public Safety and Emergency Preparedness, provincial and territorial government representatives responsible for health and stakeholders, including representatives of the medical community and patients’ groups, for the purpose of developing a comprehensive federal framework in relation to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>improved tracking of the incidence rate and associated economic and social costs of post-traumatic stress disorder;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the establishment of guidelines regarding</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the diagnosis, treatment and management of post-traumatic stress disorder, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the sharing throughout Canada of best practices related to the treatment and management of post-traumatic stress disorder; and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>the creation and distribution of standardized educational materials related to post-traumatic stress disorder, for use by Canadian public health care providers, that are designed to increase national awareness about the disorder and enhance its diagnosis, treatment and management.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Preparation and tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must prepare a report setting out the federal framework and cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of Parliament within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the Agency’s website within 30 days after the day on which it is laid before a House of Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Review and Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Review</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Agency must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>complete a review of the effectiveness of the federal framework no later than five years after the day on which the report referred to in section 4 is published; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>cause a report on its findings to be laid before each House of Parliament within the next 10 sitting days after the review is completed.</Text></Paragraph></Section></Body></Bill>