<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-12</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>51-52</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2003</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to promote physical activity and sport</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">Physical Activity and Sport Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Physical Activity and Sport</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2003</YYYY><MM>3</MM><DD>19</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="no"><?Pub Caret1?><AnnualStatuteNumber>2</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2003</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment replaces the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fitness and Amateur Sport Act</XRefExternal>, which was enacted in 1961, with modernized legislation that is better adapted to contemporary realities.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment sets out the Government of Canada’s policies regarding physical activity and sport. It also sets out the mandate of the Minister in respect of physical activity and sport.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>The enactment establishes the Sport Dispute Resolution Centre of Canada, an independent organization whose mission is to provide to the sport community a national alternative dispute resolution service for sport disputes, and expertise and assistance in that regard.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble salutation="no"><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>WHEREAS the Government of Canada recognizes that physical activity and sport are integral parts of Canadian culture and society and produce benefits in terms of health, social cohesion, linguistic duality, economic activity, cultural diversity and quality of life;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS the Government of Canada wishes to increase awareness among Canadians of the significant benefits of physical activity and the practice of sport;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS the Government of Canada wishes to encourage and assist Canadians in increasing their level of physical activity and their participation in sport;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>WHEREAS the Government of Canada is committed to promoting physical activity and sport, having regard to the principles set out in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Text>AND WHEREAS the Government of Canada wishes to encourage cooperation among the various governments, the physical activity and sport communities and the private sector in the promotion of physical activity and sport;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>NOW, THEREFORE, Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SHORT TITLE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Physical Activity and Sport Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>INTERPRETATION</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>2.</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the member or members of the Queen’s Privy Council for Canada designated by the Governor in Council for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>POLICIES</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Physical activity policy</MarginalNote><Label>3.</Label><Text>The objectives of the Government of Canada’s policy regarding physical activity are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to promote physical activity as a fundamental element of health and well-being;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to encourage all Canadians to improve their health by integrating physical activity into their daily lives; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to assist in reducing barriers faced by all Canadians that prevent them from being active.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Sport policy — principles</MarginalNote><Label>4.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Government of Canada’s policy regarding sport is founded on the highest ethical standards and values, including doping-free sport, the treatment of all persons with fairness and respect, the full and fair participation of all persons in sport and the fair, equitable, transparent and timely resolution of disputes in sport.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Sport policy — objectives</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The objectives of the Government of Canada’s policy regarding sport are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to increase participation in the practice of sport and support the pursuit of excellence in sport; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to build capacity in the Canadian sport system.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>OBJECTS AND MANDATE</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Objects of Act and mandate of Minister</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The objects of this Act are to encourage, promote and develop physical activity and sport in Canada. The Minister may take any measures that the Minister considers appropriate to further those objects, and in particular may</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>undertake or assist in research or studies in respect of physical activity and sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>arrange for national and regional conferences in respect of physical activity and sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the recognition of achievement in respect of physical activity and sport by the grant or issue of certificates, citations or awards of merit;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>prepare and distribute information relating to physical activity and sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>assist, cooperate with and enlist the aid of any group interested in furthering the objects of this Act;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>coordinate federal initiatives related to the encouragement, promotion and development of physical activity and sport, particularly those initiatives related to the implementation of the Government of Canada’s policy regarding sport, the hosting of major sporting events and the implementation of anti-doping measures, in cooperation with other departments or agencies of the Government of Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>undertake or support any projects or programs related to physical activity or sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide assistance for the promotion and development of Canadian participation in national and international sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide for the training of coaches and any other resource persons to further the objects of this Act in relation to sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide bursaries or fellowships to assist individuals in pursuing excellence in sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>encourage the promotion of sport as a tool of individual and social development in Canada and, in cooperation with other countries, abroad;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>encourage the private sector to contribute financially to the development of sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>facilitate the participation of under-represented groups in the Canadian sport system;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>encourage provincial and territorial governments to promote and develop sport;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>coordinate the Government of Canada’s initiatives and efforts with respect to the staging and hosting of the Canada Games; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>encourage and support alternative dispute resolution for sport.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Financial assistance</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>For the purposes of this Act, the Minister may provide financial assistance in the form of grants and contributions to any person, in accordance with Parts IV and VII of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Official Languages Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>AGREEMENTS AND ARRANGEMENTS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Contribution agreements</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister, with the approval of the Governor in Council, may enter into an agreement with any province or territory providing for the payment of contributions in respect of costs that they incur in undertaking programs designed to encourage, promote and develop physical activity or sport.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Agreements to implement Canada’s policy regarding sport</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement or arrangement with any province or territory respecting the implementation of the Government of Canada’s policy regarding sport.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>International agreements</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>The Minister, with the approval of the Governor in Council, may enter into an agreement or arrangement with the government of any foreign state in order to encourage, promote and develop physical activity and sport.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>SPORT DISPUTE RESOLUTION CENTRE OF CANADA</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Establishment of Centre</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Centre established</MarginalNote><Label>9.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A not-for-profit corporation is hereby established to be called the Sport Dispute Resolution Centre of Canada, in this Act referred to as “the Centre”, which shall include a dispute resolution secretariat and a resource centre.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not an agent of Her Majesty</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Centre is not an agent of Her Majesty.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Not a departmental or Crown corporation</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Centre is not a departmental corporation or a Crown corporation within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Financial Administration Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Status of arbitrator or mediator</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Court Act</XRefExternal>, the Centre or an arbitrator or mediator who provides services under the auspices of the Centre is not a federal board, commission or other tribunal within the meaning of that Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Both official languages to be used</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Centre shall offer its services to, and communicate with, the public in both official languages of Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Head office</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The head office of the Centre shall be at the place in Canada that is designated in the by-laws of the Centre.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Mission and Powers</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Mission</MarginalNote><Label>10.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The mission of the Centre is to provide to the sport community</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a national alternative dispute resolution service for sport disputes; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>expertise and assistance regarding alternative dispute resolution.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interpretation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), a sport dispute includes disputes among sport organizations and disputes between a sport organization and persons affiliated with it, including its members.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Powers</MarginalNote><Label>11.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In carrying out its mission, the Centre has the capacity and powers of a natural person, including the power to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>use any funds that may be provided to it, subject to any terms on which the funds are provided;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>enter into contracts or agreements in its own name;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>conduct studies with respect to the exercise of its powers; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>do any other things that are conducive to the fulfilment of its mission and the exercise of its powers.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restrictions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection (1), the Centre</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may not acquire or construct real property or immovables for valuable consideration, other than those required for its head office;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>shall expressly state in its contracts and agreements that it is entering into the contract or agreement on its own behalf;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may not procure the incorporation of a corporation any shares of which, on incorporation, would be held by, on behalf of or in trust for the Centre; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>may not acquire shares of a corporation that, on acquisition, would be held by, on behalf of or in trust for the Centre.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Board of Directors</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Role</MarginalNote><Label>12.</Label><Text>The affairs and business of the Centre shall be managed by a board of directors, and for that purpose the board may exercise all the powers of the Centre.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Composition</MarginalNote><Label>13.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The board of directors consists of not more than 12 directors, including the chairperson, and the executive director of the Centre who does not have a right to vote.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Non-application of provisions</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Sections 14, 16 and 18 do not apply to the executive director.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>14.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The directors shall be appointed by the Minister to hold office during good behaviour for any term of not more than three years that will ensure, as far as possible, the expiry in any one year of the terms of office of not more than one half of the directors. A director may be appointed to not more than two consecutive terms and may be removed by the Minister for cause.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Appointment criteria</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The directors shall be chosen in accordance with guidelines that are established by the Minister in consultation with the sport community.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Guidelines</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The guidelines shall provide for a board of directors that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is composed of men and women committed to the promotion and development of sport who have the experience or capacity to enable the Centre to achieve its mission; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>is representative of the sport community and of the diversity and bilingual character of Canadian society.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Guidelines referred to in subsection (3) are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Exclusion</MarginalNote><Label>15.</Label><Text>A director may not be appointed as an officer of the Centre.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>No remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>16.</Label><Text>The directors are not entitled to be paid any remuneration, but are entitled to be paid such reasonable travel and other expenses incurred by them in connection with their duties or functions under this Act as may be fixed by the by-laws of the Centre.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>By-laws</MarginalNote><Label>17.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The board of directors may make by-laws with respect to the conduct and management of the affairs of the Centre and the carrying out of the duties and functions of the board under this Act, including by-laws providing for</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the establishment of committees of the board of directors, including an executive committee, and the duties, functions and powers of the committees;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the duties, functions and powers of the chairperson and the officers of the Centre, including the executive director;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the appointment and remuneration of the officers of the Centre;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the delegation of any functions of the board of directors to an executive committee and the manner in which those functions are to be performed;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the mandate, duties and functions of the dispute resolution secretariat, the resource centre and any other part of the Centre;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the terms and conditions of eligibility for services provided by the Centre;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the establishment of a policy respecting the official languages of Canada that includes</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>principles governing the use of English and French by the staff of the Centre in their communications, provision of services and daily work, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>a mechanism for resolving disputes related to the application of the policy;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the fixing of fees and charges to be paid for the services and facilities provided by the Centre or the determination of a manner for calculating those fees and charges;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the establishment of mediation and arbitration procedures for resolving sport disputes, including a mechanism for determining the manner in which the parties may select an arbitrator or mediator and the language, according to the needs of the parties, in which the parties may be heard and the decision rendered;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the qualifications for arbitrators or mediators;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the establishment of a code of ethics for directors, officers and employees of the Centre, as well as for arbitrators and mediators who provide dispute resolution services under the auspices of the Centre; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>personnel management, including terms and conditions of employment of persons employed by the Centre.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>By-laws available to the public</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>A copy of every by-law shall be kept at the head office of the Centre. Anyone is entitled, during the usual business hours of the Centre, to examine the by-laws and, on payment of a reasonable fee, to photocopy them in whole or in part.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal> does not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>By-laws made under subsection (1) are not statutory instruments for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Chairperson</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Designation</MarginalNote><Label>18.</Label><Text>The Minister, after consulting with the directors, shall designate one of them as chairperson to hold office during good behaviour for any term of not more than three years. The chairperson may be designated for not more than two consecutive terms and may be removed by the Minister for cause.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duties</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Text>The chairperson shall determine the times and places of the meetings of the board of directors and presides at those meetings. The chairperson may perform any other duties or functions that are assigned to the chairperson by the board of directors.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Absence, etc., of chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Text>If the chairperson is absent or incapacitated or if the office of chairperson is vacant, the board of directors may designate a director to exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions of the chairperson during the absence, incapacity or vacancy, but no person may be so designated for a period exceeding 90 days without the approval of the Minister.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Executive Director</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment</MarginalNote><Label>21.</Label><Text>The board of directors shall appoint an executive director of the Centre.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duties</MarginalNote><Label>22.</Label><Text>The executive director is the chief executive officer of the Centre and has, on behalf of the board of directors, responsibility for the direction and management of the business and day-to-day operations of the Centre.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Absence, etc., of executive director</MarginalNote><Label>23.</Label><Text>If the executive director is absent or incapacitated or if the office of executive director is vacant, the chairperson may designate any person to exercise the powers and perform the duties and functions of the executive director during the absence, incapacity or vacancy, but no person may be so designated for a period exceeding 90 days without the approval of the board of directors.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Delegation</MarginalNote><Label>24.</Label><Text>The executive director may delegate to any person any power, duty or function conferred on the executive director under this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Personnel</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Personnel</MarginalNote><Label>25.</Label><Text>The Centre may engage any employees and any technical and professional advisers that it considers necessary for the proper conduct of its activities.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Status</MarginalNote><Label>26.</Label><Text>Directors, officers and employees of the Centre are deemed not to be employees of the public service of Canada and, for the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Public Service Superannuation Act</XRefExternal>, are deemed not to be employed in the Public Service.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Audit</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Audit committee</MarginalNote><Label>27.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The board of directors shall establish an audit committee consisting of at least three directors.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Duties of audit committee</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The audit committee shall</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>require the Centre to implement and maintain appropriate internal control procedures;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>review, evaluate and approve those internal control procedures;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>review the Centre’s annual financial statements and report to the Centre before those statements are approved by the board of directors;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>meet with the Centre’s auditor to discuss the Centre’s annual financial statements and the auditor’s report; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>meet with the Centre’s auditor and the Centre’s management to discuss the effectiveness of the internal control procedures.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Special report</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the audit committee is of the opinion that there is any information that should be brought to the attention of the Minister, it shall make a report of that information to the Minister and furnish the board with a copy of the report.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meeting of directors</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The audit committee may call a meeting of the board of directors to consider any matter of concern to the committee.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Technical assistance</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The audit committee may engage, on a temporary basis, the services of persons having technical or specialized knowledge to assist the committee in carrying out its duties under this Act.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Independent audit</MarginalNote><Label>28.</Label><Text>The accounts and financial transactions of the Centre shall be audited annually by an independent auditor designated by the board of directors, and a written report of the audit shall be made to that board.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Arbitrators and Mediators</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Responsibilities of the Centre</MarginalNote><Label>29.</Label><Text>The Centre shall ensure that arbitrators and mediators who provide dispute resolution services under the auspices of the Centre</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>meet the qualifications established by its by-laws;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>are independent of the Centre; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>are, as a group, able to provide services in one or the other of the official languages of Canada or in both, according to the needs of the parties.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>General Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Duty of care</MarginalNote><Label>30.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every director and officer of the Centre, in exercising their powers and performing their duties and functions, must</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>act honestly and in good faith with a view to the best interests of the Centre;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>exercise the care, diligence and skill that a reasonably prudent person would exercise in comparable circumstances; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>comply with this Act and the by-laws of the Centre.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No exculpation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>No provision in a contract or resolution relieves a director or officer from the duty to act in accordance with this Act, the regulations or the by-laws or relieves a director or officer from liability for a breach of any of them.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Reliance on statements</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>A director or officer is not liable for a breach of duty under subsection (1) if the director or officer relies in good faith on</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>financial statements of the Centre represented to the director or officer by an officer of the Centre or in a written report of the auditor of the Centre as fairly reflecting the financial condition of the Centre; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a report of a lawyer, notary, accountant, engineer, appraiser or other person whose position or profession lends credibility to a statement made by that person.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Provisions of <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> apply</MarginalNote><Label>31.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> apply, with any modifications that the circumstances require, to the Centre and its directors, officers and employees as if the Centre were a corporation incorporated under that Act and the provisions of this Act were its articles of incorporation:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 16 (by-law not required to confer powers on Centre, restriction on powers of Centre and validity of acts of Centre);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 20(1), (2) and (4) (records, minutes and place of records);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 22(1) (form of corporate records);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 23 (corporate seal not needed to validate instrument);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsection 108(2) (resignation of director);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 114(1), (2), (5) to (7) and (9) (meeting of directors);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 116 (validity of acts of directors and officers);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">h</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 117 (validity of directors’ resolutions in lieu of meetings);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 120 (conflict of interest of directors and officers);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">j</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 123 (directors’ dissents);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 124(1) to (6) (indemnification of directors and officers and insurance for directors’ and officers’ liability);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">l</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 158 (approval of financial statements by directors);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">m</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 161 (qualifications of auditor);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">n</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 170 (right of auditor to information);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">o</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 171(4) to (7) and paragraph 171(8)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) (duties and administration of audit committee);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">p</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 172 (qualified privilege in defamation for auditor’s statements);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">q</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 253(1) and (3) (notice to directors);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">r</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 255 (waiver of notice); and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">s</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 257(1) and (2) (certificates of Centre as evidence).</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Description with cross-references</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The descriptive words in parentheses that follow the reference to a provision of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Business Corporations Act</XRefExternal> in subsection (1) form no part of that subsection but are inserted for convenience of reference only.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Corporations Act</XRefExternal> does not apply</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Corporations Act</XRefExternal>, chapter C-32 of the Revised Statutes of Canada, 1970, does not apply to the Centre.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Corporate Plan and Annual Report</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Corporate plan</MarginalNote><Label>32.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Centre shall prepare a corporate plan for each fiscal year, and deliver a copy of that plan to the Minister at least 30 days before the start of that fiscal year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Scope and content of corporate plan</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The corporate plan shall encompass all the business and activities of the Centre and shall include a statement of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Centre’s objectives;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the strategies that the Centre intends to use to achieve its objectives, including its operational and financial strategies and its human resource strategies; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Centre’s operating and capital budgets for the next fiscal year.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Corporate plan to be made public</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>After the corporate plan is delivered to the Minister, the Centre shall make the plan public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Corporate plan to be tabled</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause a copy of the corporate plan to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first fifteen days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the plan.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>33.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The chairperson of the board of directors shall, within four months after the end of each fiscal year, deliver a report on the operations of the Centre in that fiscal year to the Minister.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The report shall include</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the financial statements of the Centre and the report of the auditor respecting those statements;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a summary of the Centre’s corporate plan; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>information about the Centre’s performance with respect to the objectives established in the corporate plan.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The total remuneration that each officer receives in a fiscal year from the Centre, including any reimbursements or monetary benefits, and the amount of any reimbursements or monetary benefits that each director receives in a fiscal year from the Centre, shall be set out in the annual financial statements for that year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Distribution of report</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>After its annual report is delivered to the Minister, the Centre shall make the report public.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Annual report to be tabled</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister shall cause a copy of the annual report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first fifteen days on which that House is sitting after the Minister receives the report.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Public meeting</MarginalNote><Label>34.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 60 days after the delivery of its annual report to the Minister, the Centre shall convene a public meeting at a city in Canada selected by the Centre to consider the report and other matters relating to the Centre’s activities during the current fiscal year.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Notice of meeting</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>At least 30 days before the date of a meeting convened under subsection (1), the Centre shall give notice of the time and place of the meeting in accordance with its by-laws.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Dissolution</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Minister may order dissolution</MarginalNote><Label>35.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by order, dissolve the Centre</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the Centre has failed to make by-laws in accordance with paragraphs 17(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>), (<Emphasis style="italic">g</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">i</Emphasis>) to (<Emphasis style="italic">k</Emphasis>) within one year after section 9 comes into force;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the Minister is satisfied that the Centre has failed, for a period of one year, to carry on its affairs and business;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the Minister, on the expiry of any period of five years after the coming into force of section 9, after having made an evaluation of the Centre, is satisfied that the Centre is not fulfilling its mission or is no longer necessary; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on petition by the Centre supported by a resolution passed by at least two thirds of the directors.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Debts and liabilities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>In the event of the dissolution of the Centre, any property of the Centre that remains after the payment of its debts and liabilities, or after the making of adequate provision for the payment of its debts and liabilities, may be transferred to any person or institution having a mission similar to that of the Centre that the Minister specifies in the order.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Dissolution</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If the Minister dissolves the Centre, the affairs of the Centre shall be wound up in accordance with this section and any regulations made under paragraph 36(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>).</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>REGULATIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>36.</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>defining, for the purposes of this Act, the expressions <DefinedTermEn>physical activity</DefinedTermEn>, <DefinedTermEn>sport</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>sport organization</DefinedTermEn>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>respecting the winding up of the Centre; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>generally for carrying into effect the purposes and provisions of sections 3 to 8.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>CONSEQUENTIAL AMENDMENT</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote>1995, c. 11</MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Canadian Heritage Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>37.</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(2)(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Canadian Heritage Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">f</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the encouragement, promotion and development of sport;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>COORDINATING AMENDMENT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-30</MarginalNote><Label>38.</Label><Text>If Bill C-30, introduced in the 1st session of the 37th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Courts Administration Service Act</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then, on the later of the coming into force of section 14 of that Act and subsection 9(4) of this Act, subsection 9(4) of this Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Status of arbitrator or mediator</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>For the purposes of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Federal Courts Act</XRefExternal>, the Centre or an arbitrator or mediator who provides services under the auspices of the Centre is not a federal board, commission or other tribunal within the meaning of that Act.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>REPEAL</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Repeal of R.S., c. F-25</MarginalNote><Label>39.</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Fitness and Amateur Sport Act</XRefExternal> is repealed.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>40.</Label><Text>The provisions of this Act, other than section 38, come into force on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>