<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><!DOCTYPE Bill PUBLIC "-//Justice Canada//DTD Bill Exchange v2.5.0//EN" "BillExchange.dtd"><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><Identification><BillNumber>C-3 </BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>37</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>51-52</Year-s><Monarch>Elizabeth II</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2003</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Canada Pension Plan and the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="official">An Act to amend the Canada Pension Plan and the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canada Pension Plan</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="assented-to"><Date><YYYY>2003</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><Chapter><AnnualStatuteId revised-statute="no"><AnnualStatuteNumber>5</AnnualStatuteNumber><YYYY>2003</YYYY></AnnualStatuteId></Chapter></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</XRefExternal> to</Text><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>permit all amounts held to the credit of the Canada Pension Plan Account to be transferred to the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board, by repealing the requirement to maintain in the Account a three-month operating balance;</Text></Provision></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>establish a means by which the Investment Board may be required to transfer funds to the government, to the credit of the Canada Pension Plan Account, so that the immediate obligations of the Account can be met;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>transfer to the Investment Board, over a three-year period, the right, title or interest in each security held by the Minister of Finance, and establish the conditions on which the securities may be redeemed or replaced;</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">d</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>provide that the foreign property limit in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> applies to the Investment Board and its subsidiaries on a consolidated basis and to provide that the Investment Board will be considered to hold the property of its subsidiaries for the purpose of applying the foreign property limit; and</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-1-1" language-align="no" list-item="no"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>make housekeeping amendments to the Investment Board’s reporting requirements.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-1-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>Her Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. C-8</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA PENSION PLAN</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1996, c. 11, par. 95(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</MarginalNote><Label>1.</Label><Text>Section 91 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> and the heading before it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>91.</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Part.</Text><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Investment Board</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>Office</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Investment Board</DefinedTermEn> means t<?Pub Caret?>he Canada Pension Plan Investment Board established by section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Definition><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Human Resources Development.</Text></Definition></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2.</Label><Text>Subsection 108(4) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Limitation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>No payment shall be made out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund under this section in excess of the total of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the amount of the balance to the credit of the Canada Pension Plan Account, and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the fair market value of the assets of the Investment Board less its liabilities.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 108:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Management of Account</MarginalNote><Label>108.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Any amounts standing to the credit of the Canada Pension Plan Account that exceed the immediate obligations of that Account shall be transferred to the Investment Board, unless any agreement entered into under section 111.1 provides otherwise. The amounts shall be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund and charged to the Canada Pension Plan Account.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment by Investment Board</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister may, by notice, and in accordance with any agreement entered into under section 111.1, require the Investment Board to pay into the Consolidated Revenue Fund any amount necessary to offset amounts charged or required to be charged to the Canada Pension Plan Account under subsection 108(3) and any interest charged under subsection 110(2).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance shall credit interest to the Canada Pension Plan Account at market rates, as determined by that Minister, on any amount standing to the credit of that Account. The interest shall be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 109(1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 109(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Amounts to be charged and credited to Account</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>There shall be paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund and charged to the Canada Pension Plan Account the cost of all securities purchased by the Minister of Finance under section 110, and there shall be paid into the Consolidated Revenue Fund and credited to the Canada Pension Plan Account the proceeds of redemption in whole or in part of any securities purchased by that Minister under that section.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Matured securities — amounts to be charged to Fund</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Where, on the maturity of a security of a province held to the credit of the Canada Pension Plan Investment Fund that was issued before January 1, 1998, the Minister of Finance does not purchase another security under subsection 110(3) or uses only a portion of the principal amount of the matured security to purchase another security, the principal amount of the matured security or the unused portion, as the case may be, shall be charged to the Canada Pension Plan Investment Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Redemption before maturity — amounts to be charged to Fund</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Where the Minister of Finance, under subsection 110(6.4), redeems a security in whole or in part before maturity, the principal amount of the redeemed security, or the amount of the part that is redeemed, shall be charged to the Canada Pension Plan Investment Fund.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 109(2) to (4) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40, s. 90(1)</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 110(1) of the Act before the definition <DefinedTermEn>appropriate provincial Minister</DefinedTermEn> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>110.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>In this section and sections 113 and 117,</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40, s. 90(3)</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinedTermEn>Investment Board</DefinedTermEn> and <DefinedTermEn>operating balance</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 110(1) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection 110(1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(4)</Label><Text>Subsection 110(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest shall be charged to Account</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance shall charge interest to the Canada Pension Plan Account at market rates, as determined by that Minister, on any amount paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund under subsection 108(3) that exceeds the balance to the credit of the Canada Pension Plan Account. Interest shall be charged for the period beginning on the day on which the amount is paid out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund under subsection 108(3) and ending on the day on which the Investment Board pays that amount into the Consolidated Revenue Fund under section 56 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>R.S., c. 30 (2nd Supp.), s. 55(2)</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>Subsection 110(2.1) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40, s. 90(4)</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Subsection 110(3) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Replacement security</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>On the maturity of a security of a province held to the credit of the Canada Pension Plan Investment Fund that was issued before January 1, 1998, the Minister of Finance shall purchase another security issued by the province if requested to do so, in writing, by the appropriate provincial Minister of that province at least 30 days before the date of maturity.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(7)</Label><Text>Subsections 110(3) to (6.1) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40, s. 90(4)</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>Subsections 110(6.2) and (6.3) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><MarginalNote>2000, c. 14, s. 45</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 110(6.4) of the Act before paragraph (<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Redemption at request of province</MarginalNote><Label>(6.4)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance shall redeem a security in whole or in part before maturity if</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(10)</Label><Text>Subsections 110(6.4) to (7) of the Act are repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(11)</Label><Text>Subsection 110(8) of the Act is repealed.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40, s. 91</MarginalNote><Label>6.</Label><Text>Section 111 of the Act is repealed.</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40, s. 91</MarginalNote><Label>7.</Label><Text>Section 111.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Administration agreement</MarginalNote><Label>111.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance may, on terms and conditions satisfactory to the Minister, enter into an agreement with the Investment Board with respect to the administration of any matter referred to in sections 107.1 to 110, including the payment of amounts out of the Consolidated Revenue Fund to the Investment Board, and the payment of amounts by the Investment Board into the Consolidated Revenue Fund.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Administration agreement</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance may enter into an agreement with the Investment Board with respect to the administration of any matter referred to in section 113.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40, s. 91</MarginalNote><Label>8.</Label><Text>Paragraphs 112(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>) and (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a statement of the amounts credited to or charged to the Canada Pension Plan Account during the year;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>a statement consolidating the accounts of the Canada Pension Plan Account and the Investment Board for the year; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 113(1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Minister of Finance shall pay an amount calculated as provided in subsection (2) to the government of that province, by the transfer to that government in the first instance and to the extent necessary for that purpose, of securities of that province that are designated securities as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</XRefExternal>, and in the second instance and to the extent necessary for that purpose, of securities of Canada that are designated securities as defined in section 2 of that Act, and by the payment to that government of any balance then remaining in any manner that may be prescribed.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 113 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Payment by Investment Board</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance may, by notice, and in accordance with any agreement entered into under section 111.1, require the Investment Board to pay to that Minister any amount that the Minister considers necessary for the purposes of subsection (1).</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Rights in securities extinguished</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, where the Minister of Finance transfers to the government of a province a security of that province or of Canada, any right, title or interest of the Investment Board in the security is extinguished.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections 113(1.1) and (1.2) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfer by Investment Board</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Finance may, by notice, and in accordance with any agreement entered into under section 111.1, require the Investment Board to pay to that Minister any amount, and to transfer to that Minister any securities of the province or of Canada referred to in paragraph (1)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>), that are necessary for the purposes of subsection (1).</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10.</Label><Text>Paragraph 114(4)(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">e</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the management or operation of the Canada Pension Plan Account, or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11.</Label><Text>Section 117 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>appropriate provincial Minister</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>appropriate provincial Minister</DefinedTermEn>, in respect of a province, means the province’s minister of the Crown who has primary responsibility for that province’s finances.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" type="amending"><MarginalNote>1997, c. 40</MarginalNote><TitleText>CANADA PENSION PLAN INVESTMENT BOARD ACT</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>12.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><MarginalNote><DefinedTermEn>designated security</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><MarginalNote><DefinedTermFr>titre désigné</DefinedTermFr></MarginalNote><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated security</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an obligation</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>that, before April 1, 1998, was held to the credit of the Canada Pension Plan Investment Fund, as established under subsection 109(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>that, as applied to Canada, is an obligation of the Government of Canada and, as applied to a province, is an obligation of the government of the province or an obligation of any agent of Her Majesty in right of the province that is guaranteed as to principal and interest by that government, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>that complies with the conditions that were set out in section 111 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> as that section read immediately before April 1, 1998; or</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>an obligation that</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>is, on or after April 1, 1998, purchased by the Minister of Finance under section 110 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>is an obligation of the government of a province or an obligation of any agent of Her Majesty in right of a province that is guaranteed as to principal and interest by that government.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subparagraph (<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(i) of the definition “designated security” in section 2 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>on or after April 1, 1998, was purchased by the Minister of Finance under section 110 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> or is purchased by the Board under section 6.1, and</Text></Subparagraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13.</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Objects</MarginalNote><Label>5.</Label><Text>The objects of the Board are</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to assist the Canada Pension Plan in meeting its obligations to contributors and beneficiaries under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to manage any amounts transferred to it under section 108.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, and its right, title or interest in any designated securities, in the best interests of the contributors and beneficiaries under that Act; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">c</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>to invest its assets with a view to achieving a maximum rate of return, without undue risk of loss, having regard to the factors that may affect the funding of the Canada Pension Plan and the ability of the Canada Pension Plan to meet its financial obligations on any given business day.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14.</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 6:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Designated Securities</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Replacement security</MarginalNote><Label>6.1</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the maturity of a designated security of a province that was issued before January 1, 1998, the Board shall purchase another security issued by that province if the Board is requested to do so, in writing, by the appropriate provincial Minister of that province at least 30 days before the date of maturity.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Principal amount</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The principal amount of the replacement security shall be not more than the principal outstanding under the maturing designated security.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Term to maturity</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The replacement security shall be for a term of 20 years.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Interest</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The replacement security shall bear interest at a rate fixed by the Board, in accordance with any agreement entered into between the Board and the Minister. The rate shall be substantially the same as the interest rate that the province would be required to pay if it were to borrow the same amount for the same term through the issuance of a security on the public capital market.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Features of replacement security</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The replacement security shall be issued to or payable to the Board and shall be expressed to be not negotiable and not transferable or assignable.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Redemption at request of province</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>The Board shall redeem a designated security in whole or in part before maturity if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Board is requested to do so, in writing, by the appropriate provincial Minister of a province at least 30 days before the proposed redemption date; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the appropriate provincial Minister has agreed to pay on the proposed redemption date</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>any payments of principal or interest due on or before the proposed redemption date but not yet paid,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>interest on the principal amount being redeemed accrued to the proposed redemption date, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>an amount equal to the present value of the remaining instalments of principal being redeemed and interest on that principal.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Calculation of present value</MarginalNote><Label>(7)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subparagraph (6)(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)(iii), the present value shall be calculated by discounting the instalments of principal being redeemed and interest on that principal using an interest rate fixed by the Board, in accordance with any agreement entered into between the Board and the Minister of Finance. In fixing that rate, the Board shall choose a rate that</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the designated security to be redeemed was issued before January 1, 1998, is substantially the same as the rate that the Government of Canada would be required to pay if it were to borrow the principal amount being redeemed for a term equal to the remaining term of that designated security through the issuance of a security on the public capital market; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>if the designated security to be redeemed was issued on or after January 1, 1998, is substantially the same as the rate that the province would be required to pay if it were to borrow the principal amount being redeemed for a term equal to the remaining term of that designated security through the issuance of a security on the public capital market.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Consolidation of securities</MarginalNote><Label>(8)</Label><Text>At the request of the provincial treasurer or other similar officer of a province, the Board may accept in the place of any series of designated securities of that province acquired during any consecutive period of not more than twelve months, on payment of any interest then accrued on the securities, another security of that province that is in an amount equal to the aggregate amount then outstanding of the designated securities of that series, and that bears interest at a rate determined by the Board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Obligation guaranteed by the provincial government</MarginalNote><Label>(9)</Label><Text>Any security purchased by the Board under this section must be an obligation of the government of a province or an obligation of an agent of Her Majesty in right of a province that is guaranteed as to principal and interest by that government.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15.</Label><Text>Section 37 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>37.</Label><Text>The Board and its subsidiaries shall invest their assets in such a way that tax would not be payable by the Board under subsection 206(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Income Tax Act</XRefExternal> if</Text><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>Part XI of that Act applied to the Board; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>each subsidiary were a corporation that had made a valid election under section 259 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16.</Label><Text>Section 50 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Statements to go to Ministers</MarginalNote><Label>50.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board shall send copies of the financial statements for the first, second and third quarters of the financial year, prepared in accordance with subsection 39(6), to the Minister and the appropriate provincial Ministers within 45 days after the end of the three-month period to which they relate.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Statements to be made public</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Within seven days after the financial statements are sent as required under subsection (1), the Board shall make the statements available to the public.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17.</Label><Text>Subsection 51(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report required</MarginalNote><Label>51.</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Board shall as soon as possible, but in any case within 60 days, after the end of each financial year provide the Minister and the appropriate provincial Ministers with an annual report on the operations of the Board in that year and the Board shall make copies of the report available to the public.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18.</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 56 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Duty of Board</MarginalNote><Label>56.</Label><Text>The Board shall pay into the Consolidated Revenue Fund, for credit to the Canada Pension Plan Account established under subsection 108(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, any amount required under subsection 108.1(2) or 113(1.1) of that Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 56 of the Act is renumbered as subsection 56(1) and is amended by adding the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Transfer of securities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Board shall transfer to the Minister any designated securities of a province or of Canada that the Minister requires under subsection 113(1.1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer of securities to the Board</MarginalNote><Label>19.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>On the first day of each month after the coming into force of this section, 1/36 of the right, title or interest of the Minister of Finance in each security that was purchased by the Minister under section 110 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>, and that is held by that Minister on the first day of the first month following the coming into force of this section, is transferred to the Canada Pension Plan Investment Board established under section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan Investment Board Act</XRefExternal> (“the Board”).</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Transfer of replacement securities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If a security referred to in subsection (1) is replaced within the 36-month period beginning on the first day of the first month following the coming into force of this section,</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>the Board is deemed to have acquired a right, title or interest in the replacement security in the same proportion as the right, title or interest it had acquired in the security being replaced; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>on the first day of each month after the day on which the replacement security is purchased, for each month then remaining in the 36-month period, an equal portion of the right, title or interest of the Minister of Finance in the replacement security is transferred to the Board, so that the replacement security is fully transferred to the Board on the same day as the security that it replaced would have been fully transferred.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Rights extinguished</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>If a security referred to in subsection (1) is redeemed during the 36-month period referred to in subsection (2) and is not replaced, any right, title or interest of the Board in the security is extinguished.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" type="transitional"><TitleText>COMING INTO FORCE</TitleText></Heading><Section type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>20.</Label><Subsection type="transitional"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (2), the provisions of this Act, and the provisions of any Act as enacted by this Act, come into force in accordance with subsection 114(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal> on a day or days to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Subsection><Subsection type="transitional"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Despite subsection 114(4) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Pension Plan</XRefExternal>,</Text><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">a</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>subsections 4(1) and (3), 5(3), (5), (7) and (10) and 9(1) and (3), sections 10 and 11, subsection 12(2), section 14 and subsection 18(2) come into force on the day that is three years after the day on which section 19 comes into force; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph type="transitional"><Label>(<Emphasis style="italic">b</Emphasis>)</Label><Text>section 8 comes into force on the day that is four years after the day on which section 19 comes into force.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>